-a

pas/imp. suffix.

-ali

(perhaps a var. of ani.)

-aʻi

nonproductive transitive suffix. see huaʻi, luaʻi, lumaʻi.

-ea

pejorative suffix.

-hana

nominalizing suffix.

-hi

a rare transitivizer.

-hia₁

how many? How much? (Follows ʻa-, ʻe-, or pā-.)

-hia₂

pas/imp.

-hiki₁

hoʻohiki₂. to vow, swear, take an oath, promise; to administer an oath; vow, oath, promise, pledge.

-hiki₂

to peel, pry off.

-hine

female, feminine.

-hune

cf. nē hoʻohune, to wheedle...

-hūnōai

father- or mother-in-law, usually after makua and followed by kāne or wahine for specific designation of sex. These terms apply also to uncle and aunt by marriage.

-i

transitivizer suffix.

-ia

pas/imp.

-iele

pejorative suffix.

-ihoiho

cf. hoʻopiʻipiʻi.

-kai

swollen, bloated.

-kana

nominalizer noted in pale, to ward off, and palekana, safety; pili, to cling, and pilikana, relative.

-kanaoʻe

hoʻokanahē

-kaʻi

perhaps a transitivizer.

-kaʻu

hesitation, fear.

-ki

transitivizer.

-kia

pas/imp. similar to ʻia.

-kou

indicator of plurality in the plural pronouns and possessives only (kākou, mākou, ʻoukou, lākou).

-kē

here and there.

-kī

intensifying suffix. see:   auwalakī₁,₂, entangled, snarled... destitute (wala to fall backwards...)   halakī. to go off course, miss the way. (hala to pass by, miss...)   hilikī, to hit carelessly, at random (hili₃ to whip, smite, thrash, switch, bat...)   kūpakakī, intensive of kūpaka, kick, thrash...   makakī, to look at with hatred. (maka eye, face...)   mōkākī, scattered, littered, mess... (moka offal, waste matter, refuse, filth...)   pakakī₁. to talk irrationally, loudly, or contentiously... (paka₂ to criticize constructively, to look for flaws...)   pūkalakī, rough, boisterous, as wind; ruffled, mussed... (pukakala rough, coarse... )   walawalakī, to fall back; to plummet to the ground... (wala to fall backwards...)

-kīkē

back and forth.

-lana₂

nominalizing suffix.

-laʻi

transitivizer, as in kaulaʻi, kulaʻi, lualaʻi.

-lele kī

flying tī

-lia

pas/imp. suffix corresponding to ʻia.

-lua₂

dual number in pronouns and possessives, as ʻolua, kāua, māua.

-mia

pas/imp. suffix.

-mā

see koʻi hoʻomā, chisel...

-naʻi

a rare transitivizer. cf. hili, to wander, and hilinaʻi, to believe; pī, to sprinkle, and pīnaʻi, to fill a crack;

-na₁

common nominalizing suffix, sometimes with shortening of a long vowel in the base.

-na₂

rare pas/imp.; suffix.

-na₃

his, her (in poss. kāna, kona).

-nia

pas/imp. suffix.

-noʻu

see

-piʻi

complain, accuse, claim...

-poni

suddenly, without warning, as death.

-puʻukie

to ensnare, entrap.

-u

second person singular poss. suffix in kāu and kou, your.

-ua

indicator of the dual number in first and third persons of pronouns and poss. only (kāua, māua, lāua).

-walu

many. (Eight being a sacred number may have led to this extension of the meaning.)

-wā hoʻowā

to retch.

-ā-

simulative ligature in the sequence 'verb + noun' compounds; particle for forming verb compounds; like, similar to. usu. verb + ā + noun:     ʻaiāmanō eat like a shark, have a prodigious appetite     ʻaiāpuaʻa eat like a pig     hanuāpuaʻa breathe like a pig, gasp for breath     heleāiʻa (= holoāiʻa) swim like a fish     heleāwai flow like water     hikiāloa long-range, long-term     holoāiʻa swim like a fish     huliāmahi turn like a strong (cock); cooperation, strength     kaheāwai flowing like water     kaʻiālupe lit. to lead like a kite (support a person between two others)     kūākanaka turn into a man, look like a man     kūākiʻi stand with hands on hips... like a statue...     kūāmaʻi very sick     mokuāhana dividing into factions     mokuāhua grief, pity, disappointment     mokuāwai burst as floodwaters, rush as a crowd     paiālewa tossed here and there (lit., lift into space)     paʻiāumi beat one's chest (as in lamentation)     pukaāmaka to appear to the eyes (seal a relationship of two families by marriage)    ʻumiāpuaʻa strangled like pigs also verb + ā + verb:     uhaiāholo chase like running     uluāhewa mania, delusion; grow wild and lush

-ā₁

pejorative suffix, often written wā after o or u. see ʻaiā, haiā, hainā, huā (huwā), kauā (kauwā), lonoā, (lonowā), mākoeā, naʻauʻauā (naʻauʻauwā), poluā (poluwā)

-ā₂

personal article occurring only after the preposition i, written ia.

-ʻi

transitivizer suffix.

-ʻu

first person singular poss. suffix in kaʻu, koʻu, and kuʻu, mine, my.

-ʻulaʻula lehelehe

mea ʻulaʻula lehelehe lipstick...

-ʻulaʻula papālina

mea ʻulaʻula papālina rouge...

a kai

by the sea.

aea

to rise up; to raise the head; to come up from under water.

aeae₁

• a prolonged sound,   • wail;   • to prolong,   • stretch.

aeae₂

andante.

aeāea

a small green fish resembling the hīnālea, used as pani (food or drink taken to finish a medical treatment) for certain diseases of children of the ʻea type.

aeʻo₁

stilts.

aeʻo₂

Hawaiian stilt bird (Himantopus mexicanus knudseni), an endemic subspecies of stilt, formerly common on the main Hawaiian Islands, endangered.

Ahiahi Kalikimaka

Christmas Eve, Christmas night.

Ahiahi Makahiki Hou

New Year's Eve.

Aholehia

stroke in lua fighting.

ahaaha

to pant, to breathe hard with heat, as a dog.

ahahana₁

syllables repeated in chants, usually at ends of verses, similar to ēhē; also ahana and ahana kōkō lele, both meaningless.

ahahana₂

a taunting singsong teasing phrase, used especially by children, meaning "Oh! Oh! Aha! Shame on you! You are going to catch it!"; as a verb, to tease.

ahaʻina

short for aha ʻia ana.

ahe

breeze; to blow or breathe gently. waft; softly blowing.

aheahe₁

soft, gentle in sound.

aheahe₂

weak.

ahi koli

to pass fire from one candlenut to the next on a chain (koli) or candlenut torch. lit., to fire the torch.

ahi lele

fire fountain, firebrands thrown over cliffs at Kamaile, Kauaʻi. see ahi and chant, Kauahae.

ahi pōkaʻuwili

pinwheel (fireworks).

ahi ʻai honua

volcano, volcanic fire. lit., fire destroying land.

ahia

faded.

ahikao

fireworks (perhaps from Eng. scow [kao], as fireworks were first displayed from ships of explorers).

ahikao lele

skyrocket, rocket.

ahikoe

match. lit., scratching fire.

ahimakani

gasoline. lit., wind fire.

ahio

lazy, indolent; to shirk work, loiter.

ahipele

match.

aho loa

long line, as with several hooks for deep-sea fishing or for sounding.

aho pueo

lashing on the pueo main purlin.

aho ʻōwili

lashing fastening kaupaku roof to kua ʻiole, upper ridgepole.

aholoa

lit., long-breath.

ahona

better, well, well-being, fortunate, improved; to need (aho₃ + -na).

ahonui

• patience; patient,   • enduring,   • long suffering;   • to tolerate.   • lit., great breath.   see ex., lawe₂, makua.

aho₁

line, cord, lashing, fishing line, thong, kite string.

aho₂

breath; to breathe.

aho₃

it is better or preferable (used after e, sometimes in comparisons).

ahu

• heap, pile, collection, mound, mass;   • altar, shrine, cairn;   • a traplike stone enclosure made by fishermen for fish to enter;   • laid, as the earth oven.

ahu lāʻi

ti-leaf raincoat or cape.

ahu waiwai

storehouse, heap of goods.

ahu ʻai

to overeat, waste food, squander.

ahu ʻawa

kava dregs.

ahuahu

healthy, vigorous; strength and vigor, as of animal or plant; to grow rapidly, thrive.

ahue

to make two thicknesses by folding; to double up, fold, as paper or tapa.

ahukū

to stone to death; slaughter by burying the victim under a pile of stones. Hākau, half brother of ʻUmi, was killed in this fashion (FS 141), and this method was used unsuccessfully against the hero Kawelo (FS 107).

ahulau

• pestilence, epidemic,   • heaped up, as dead bodies.

ahuliʻu

overheated, as over stones; white-hot.

ahulu

overdone, overcooked; overcultivated, as soil.

ahuna

pile, heap.

ahunāliʻi

a land division.

ahup

abbreviation for ahupuaʻa₁, land division usually extending from the uplands to the sea...

ahupuaʻa₁

land division usually extending from the uplands to the sea, so called because the boundary was marked by a heap (ahu) of stones surmounted by an image of a pig (puaʻa), or because a pig or other tribute was laid on the altar as tax to the chief. The landlord or owner of an ahupuaʻa might be a konohiki.

ahupuaʻa₂

the altar on which the pig was laid as payment to the chief for use of the ahupuaʻaland.

ahuwale

exposed, conspicuous, prominent, obvious, in plain view; heaped up.

ai hea

Where? also: aia i hea.

ai laila

there, to be there.

ai lalo

down there.

ai loa

away off in the distance.

ai luna

up there.

aia hoʻi

behold! see there! look! suddenly.

aia i laila

there, to be there.

aia i lalo

down there.

aia i luna

up there.

aia kā

There now! So it's there after all!

aia lā

There! I told you so! There it is!

aia naʻe

but, furthermore.

aia₂

depending on, only if, only when, whatever, whenever.

aihuawaʻa

vagabond; to wander, roam.

aikahaʻula

cf. (FS 251).

aikāne

friend; friendly; to become a friend.

aina

sexual intercourse.

aiāhua

same as ʻaiā, ungodly; godless; irreligious, unbelieving, careless of observance of taboos; wicked, wickedness.

aiʻa

Here! Here it is!

ai₁

coition; to have sexual relations, cohabit (frequently pronounced ei).

Ak

abbreviation of ʻākau, north.

Akeomilu

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the liver of Milu

Akua kahikolu

Holy Trinity.

Akua₂

God (Christian).

Akua₄

name of the 14th night of the full moon.

aka kiʻi

negative of a photograph.

aka-

carefully, slowly. cf:       akaʻai to eat slowly, carefully (ʻai, to eat...)       akahai modest, gentle...       akahana to work carefully or slowly (hana, to work...)       akahao to pick up carefully, as food (hao, to pick up...)       akahele slow or moderate, cautious... (hele, to go...)       akahoe to paddle carefully, silently (hoe, to paddle...)       akaholo to sail or run cautiously (holo, to sail, run...)       akakuʻu lessened, diminished... (kuʻu, to diminish, as stream water...)       akalewa to sway the hips daintily... (lewa, to float, swing...)       akaluli to move slowly, carefully (luli, to shake, sway...)       akanahe careful, gentle in behavior and speech (nahe, soft, sweet...)       akanoho to sit quietly, live cautiously (noho, to sit, reside...)       akaʻōlelo to speak cautiously, deliberately, in moderation (ʻōlelo, to speak...)

akaaka ʻole

not clear, vague, indistinct.

akaakalani

afterglow.

akaaka₁

clear, luminous, transparent, visible, manifest, plain, intelligible; thin, as cloth; shining, bright, distinct.

akaaka₂

a white and very thin tapa.

akaaka₃

a downy, thorny branching plant (Solanum aculeatissimum), 30 to 90 cm high, from tropical America. It bears round scarlet fruits 2.6 em in diameter, which are strung for leis.

akahai

modest, gentle, unassuming, unpretentious, unobtrusive, docile, decorous, meek, suave; meekness, modesty.

akahana

to work carefully or slowly.

akahao

to pick up carefully, as food.

akahiʻu

base of caudal fin.

akahoe

to paddle carefully, silently.

akaholo

to sail or run cautiously.

akakole

destitution, poverty; poor.

akakuʻu

lessened, diminished, mitigated; to cease, abate, grow calm, stop, as wind, surf, rain, anger, grief, pain; settled, calmed, quieted, appeased.

akakū ānuenue

the phenomenon known as the Specter of the Brocken, seen at Haleakalā Crater. lit., rainbow apparition.

akakū₁

• vision, trance; to see a vision.   • reflection, as in a mirror;   • hallucination;

akalau

the ghost or spirit of a living person seen by others, a sign of calamity. lit., many shadows.

akalei

string of multicolored glass beads. lit., bead reflections.

akalewa

to sway the hips daintily, deliberately, and gracefully.

akaluli

to move slowly, carefully.

akanahe

careful, gentle in behavior and speech.

akanoho

to sit quietly, live cautiously.

akaoʻo

stingy, miserly, hard.

akauahelo

to go here and there, vagabond; vagabond.

akaʻai

to eat slowly, carefully, cf. Easter ʻaka kai, eat more.

akaʻakaʻawa

an endemic begonia (Hillebrandia sandwicensis), a succulent herb with oblique, rounded lobed leaves 10 to 20 cm in diameter and with sprays of small pink or white flowers, found only in shaded, damp ravines. Kauaʻi.

akaʻawa

a tall endemic climber (Smilax sandwicensis) with tendrils and shiny, leathery, heart-shaped leaves; used for tying rafters.

akaʻaʻamo

a type of fine white tapa.

akaʻula

red sunset, looked upon as a sign that rain will clear. lit., red shadow.

akaʻōlelo

to speak cautiously, deliberately, in moderation.

aka₁

shadow. cf. hoaka₄.

aka₂

• reflection,   • image, likeness (Nah. 12.8) ;   • faint glimmer preceding the rising of the moon; to appear, of moonlight.   • essence of an offering rather than the flesh; Many words compounded with aka express clarity, brightness, related to this meaning.

aka₃

embryo at the moment of conception.

aka₄

newly hatched fish in the stage in which its body is still transparent.

aka₅

knuckles, as of hands or ankles; joints of the backbone; node and stalk of kava; kava slip for planting.

ake maka

edible raw liver.

akeakamai

a lover of wisdom, seeker after knowledge, philosopher, scientist, scholar; philosophy, science; scientific. lit., to desire wisdom.

akeake

quick, ready, as to do a kindly, deed, helpful.

akeloa

spleen. lit., long liver.

akemakani

lung. lit., wind liver.

akemāmā

lung. lit., light liver.

akena

to boast, brag, admire, praise.

akenīʻau

spleen. lit., coconut-midrib liver.

akepahaola

lung.

akepau

tuberculosis, consumption. lit., finished liver.

akepaʻa

liver (more specific than ake). lit., firm liver.

akepāhola

lung.

ake₁

liver.

ake₂

to desire, wish, be eager, yearn [the emotions and intelligence were thought to be centered within the body].

ako

thatching; to thatch.

aku nei

a while ago, last.

akua hana

a god to whom one appealed with offerings for help, as in fishing, farming, or killing an enemy. lit.. work god.

akua hoʻounauna

god sent on errands of destruction.

akua hulu

feather image.

akua hānai₁

spirits, as of a recently dead kinsman, who were fed (hānai) offerings (such as food) and sent out to destroy an enemy.

akua hānai₂

the kauila, nīoi₂, and ʻohe "poison" woods of Molokaʻi, which were kept by sorcerers in their houses, wrapped in tapa, and to which food offerings were made daily; scraps of these woods were used as poison, and poison itself was sometimes called akua hānai.

akua kahukahu

a god to whom offerings and sacrifices were made.

akua kiʻi

image representing a god.

akua kumu haka

similar to akua hānai₁,spirits sent out to destroy an enemy...; akua hānai₂, scraps of woods used as poison...; sent out in the shape of fireballs to kill, or inserted in a victim's food, water, or tobacco.

akua kāʻai

stick image (general name); image wrapped in tapa; image consisting of a carved staff, with a tuft of feathers at the top, bound to its bearer by a sash (kāʻai₁) (Malo 80) and carried into battle; staff with a carved figure at the head, used in ceremonies to procure offspring.

akua lapu

ghost, specter, apparition, evil spirit.

akua lele

flying god, usually a poison god sent to destroy, sometimes in the form of fireballs (pōpō ahi).

akua loa

a tall image, especially an image of Lono carried on a circuit of the island during the makahiki, harvest festival; it was called loa, long, because of its "long" travels. The image consisted of a staff about two fathoms long. Pieces of pala fern, feather leis, and skins of the kaʻupu bird were fastened to a crosspiece tied near the top of the staff, in the center of which was a tiny carved head. A long and white tapa banner was attached to the crosspiece. ((Malo 143–5), but see (Malo text, chapter 36, sections 22–4)) Tribute was collected. also Lono Makua.

akua malihini

foreign god, epithet often applied to Pele because she had come from a foreign land.

akua noho

a spirit that takes possession of people and speaks through them as a medium.

akua pahulu

the god of nightmares; a god who carried persons to distant places in their sleep, especially if they had eaten certain fish, as the weke.

akua panauea

last and slow-moving image in a procession during kauila nui ceremonies.

akua poko

similar to akua loa (a tall image, especially an image of Lono carried on a circuit of the island during the makahiki), except that it was taken to a poko₃ (a small division of a district, sometimes the personal lands of a chief)

akua pāʻani

image representing the god of sports that accompanied the akua loa on its circuit, to preside at the sport festivals.

akua ulu

a god that inspires or possesses people.

akua wahine

goddess.

akua ʻai hamu

spirit eater of scraps, designation of a god sent on errands of destruction by sorcerers.

akua ʻai kahu

a spirit that destroys its keeper; a god sent on an evil errand who returns to destroy his keeper rather than the victim; any evil practice, as excessive drinking, gossiping.

akua ʻai pilau

spirit eater of filth. same as akua ʻai hamu.

akua ʻaumakua

supernatural with dual roles as akua to unrelated persons and ʻaumakua to relatives, as formerly the four major gods to high ranking chiefs, and later only as Pele, Hiʻiaka, and Laka to mortals.

akua₃

"it" in a game of tag or hide-and-seek.

akula

aku + demon. lā.

akule

big-eyed or goggle-eyed scad fish (Trachurops crumenophthalmus), Stages of growth are pāʻāʻā, halalū or hahalalū, and akule.

akuʻe

club-footed; deformity of the feet.

Ala hou

name of a Molokaʻi wind.

Alakea₁

name of a star, probably used in navigation.

Alakea₂

name of a downtown Honolulu street. lit., white road.

Alakeka

Alaska.

Alapiʻiakaʻōpae

lua fighting stroke. lit., stairway of the shrimp.

Alaʻeli

a wind of Mānoa Valley, Honolulu.

Alaʻoli

name of a Kauaʻi wind, said to bring good weather. lit., happy path.

Aliʻiokonaikalewa

same as Kealiʻiokonaikalewa.

ala hele wāwae

pedestrian's road, sidewalk.

ala holo papa

wooden bridge.

ala honua

to wake up early for no reason

ala hou

resurrection; to rise again, resurect.

ala kai

sea course, path where one must swim past a projecting cliff.

ala kāpae

detour.

ala maika

bowling alley

ala muku

cut off or unfinished road, dead-end road. fig., an incomplete rainbow, rainbow fragment

ala pō

night awakening.

ala pōʻai

orbit of the stars, circular road.

ala waele

road, highway. lit., cleared road.

ala waʻa

canoe course.

ala ʻoki

road cut, short cut.

ala ʻūlili

sheer trail as for climbing a cliff.

ala-

fast, quickly. cf.     alaheo, gone, departed   (heo depart in haste)     alamimo, quick, fast   (mimo deft...)     alapine₁, quick, fast   (pinepine often)     alawiki, to hurry; quick, fast   (wiki quick)

alahaka

• plank bridge,   • rough road over ravines or chasms,   • trestle,   • ladder.

alahakaonuʻalolo

type of braid used in the pāpale ʻie.

alahaki

mountain ladder or steps cut into a cliff.

alahao

railway, railroad track. lit., iron road.

alaheo

gone, departed.

alaheʻe

a large native shrub or small tree (Canthium odoratum; synonym Plectronia odorata) with shiny leaves and small, fragrant, white flowers. The wood is hard and was formerly used in making the ʻōʻō digging stick; also used medically.

alaheʻe haole

mock orange (Murraya paniculata), an ornamental hedge plant with shiny, dark-green leaves, small fragrant white flowers, and red berries.

alahiʻi

hem or finished border of a plaited mat or hat.

alahukimoku

marine railway. lit., road to pull ships.

alahula

• a frequented and well-known path; to frequent such;   • to tread or trample, as on a taboo being broken. And.

alaia

small thin surfboard, as of breadfruit or koa wood, and heavier than the olo board.

alakaʻina

leadership, guidance.

alakuʻukuʻu

place for climbing a cliff, usually with ropes.

alakō₁

to drag, pull along.

alakō₂

bird-catching pole.

alamimo

quick, fast.

alana

awakening, rising.

alani kuahiwi

all species of Pelea.

alani wai

a low native shrub (Pelea waialealae), found only on high, wet parts of Kauaʻi.

alania

smooth, even, not rough.

alaniho

long tattoo stripe. lit., tooth path.

alani₁

brown seaweeds (Dictyota spp.), regularly divided into narrow segments. They are so bitter that they will taint other seaweeds put with them and can be eaten but little and by some are considered poisonous. Medical kahunas used them in small quantities to treat asthma. This name is sometimes qualified by the terms kai and ʻula. Also maka and false līpoa.

alani₂

an Oʻahu tree (Pelea sandwicensis or P. oahuensis), with oblong, fragrant leaves (like the mokihana of Kauaʻi), which were used for scenting tapa. The bark was used for medicine. Also other species of Pelea.

alani₃

an upland moss.

alanui hele ʻaoʻao

sidewalk.

alanui ākea

avenue, boulevard, wide street.

alanuionāhōkūhoʻokele

pathway of the navigator stars; star course followed by navigators. Probably also hōkū ʻai ʻāina.

alapao

tunnel.

alapiko

belly of a fish, considered choice.

alapine₁

quick, fast.

alapine₂

frequent, often.

alapiʻi

stairs, steps, ladder, stile, doorstep, ascent, scale (musical).

alapiʻi kū

steep road or path.

alapiʻi lawe ʻōhua

escalator, moving stairs.

alapiʻi mele

musical scale.

alapoho

to gulp, swallow whole.

alapoki

shipwrecked.

alapuka

body sores; to have such sores; affected with dry rot, as taro.

alau

dividing, branching, as of winds and lineages.

alaula

light of early dawn, sunset glow. lit., flaming road.

alawai

channel, canal.

alawela

dark lines on stomach of a pregnant woman, converging near the navel. lit., burned path.

alawiki

to hurry; quick, fast.

alawī₁

to shriek; shrill.

alawī₂

upland bird, reported to be the young of the ʻanianiau, and on Kauaʻi, the ʻamakihi.

alaō₁

to swallow whole, as a fish or shrimp.

alaō₂

Heiau or temple that had no lele altar.

alaʻalai₂

type of taro patch built on artificial mounds, known near Hiloas kipi; mucky claylike soil, as in this type of patch.

alaʻau

river ford; place on a trail where one swims or wades across a stream.

alaʻololī

narrow path, lane, alley.

alaʻula

red dust in a road, red dust.

alaʻume

to draw, pull, attract, as a magnet.

ala₃

to rise up, arise, get up, come forward.

ala₅

there (same as the more frequent lā and -la). cf. e lākou ala, e lauala, e (verb) ala.

aleale

wounded, pierced; wound, sore. Less common than pōaleale.

alea₂

a fish, said to be short for hīnālea, or a kind of hīnālea.

alelo pala

coated tongue.

alelo pelu

tongue-tied, paralyzed tongue.

alelo puʻu

paralysis of the tongue, believed sometimes caused by a kahuna. Also alelo pehu, alelo pelu, lelo puʻu

aleloahi

a kind of introduced flower (no data).

alelo₁

tongue, language. Also elelo.

alelo₂

meat of the sea egg or sea urchin (wana), so called because of resemblance to a tongue.

alelo₃

concave curve of the lower portion of the lei palaoa, whale-tooth pendant, suggestive of a tongue.

alelo₄

point at the tip of a paddle.

alena

a lowland perennial weed (Boerhaavia repens), with long, thin, prostrate branches, bearing small leaves and flowers. The swollen roots were used medicinally, acting as a diuretic. Anena on Niʻihau.

ale₁

to swallow, engulf, gulp, absorb.

ale₂

hollow or cavern on the sea floor.

ale₃

an endemic mountain plant (Plantago princeps), 60 cm to 2 m high, rarely branching, stem woody, with long narrow leaves at top; related to the laukahi.

alia

to wait, stop; before; usually as a command: Stop! Wait a minute!

aliali

crystal clear, white; clarity, whiteness.

aliʻi hoʻomalu

presiding officer, ruling officer; chairman, viceroy.

aliʻi koa

military officer, officer of army or navy.

aliʻi koa i komikina ʻia

commissioned officer.

aliʻi koa uku

warrant officer.

aliʻi kuʻi

power behind the throne. lit., supplementary king.

aliʻi kāne

male chief, king; husband (polite, not said of one's own husband or to him).

aliʻi kūʻokoʻa

independent chief, aristocrat.

aliʻi maoli

true chief, commissioned officer (old term).

aliʻi palapala hoʻokohu ʻole

non-commissioned officer, petty officer (old term).

aliʻi papa

offspring of a high chiefess and commoner (or lesser chief) father.

aliʻi poʻe kauā

lesser chiefs who served other chiefs.

aliʻi pūʻō lani

an exalted chief (probably from pūʻoʻa, tower).

aliʻi wahine

chiefess, queen; wife (polite, not said of one's own wife or to her).

aliʻi waʻapā

boatswain.

aliʻi ʻai moku

chief who rules a moku (district).

aliʻi ʻānela

Archangel.

aliʻipoe

the ornamental cannas (Canna indica, forms and hybrids), large tropical American herbs, with large oval or narrow leaves and large red or red and yellow flowers. The round black seeds are worn in leis and are also placed in fruit shells of the laʻamia for hula rattles. Cannas are both cultivated and wild in Hawaiʻi.

aloaliʻi

in the presence of chiefs; royal court.

aloalo₂

squilla (Pseudosquilla ciliata, Lysiosquilla maculata), highly desired as food. Also Squilla sp.

aloalo₃

loved and served by many persons, as a chief or favorite child; esteemed.

aloalo₄

tapa made from māmaki mixed with wauke.

aloha hoahānau

brotherhood.

aloha kakahiaka

good morning...

aloha ʻoe

may you be loved or greeted, greetings (to one person).

aloha ʻole

pitiless, merciless, ungrateful, without love or affection.

aloha ʻāina

love of the land or of one's country, patriotism; the name of a Hawaiian-language newspaper published 1893–1920; aloha ʻāina is a very old concept, to judge from the many sayings (perhaps thousands) illustrating deep love of the land. (Aloha ʻāina) in (PN 268–9) cf. the song Kaulana nā Pua (EM 62–4).

alohalua

name given to the kāmole plant used in hana aloha sorcery. lit., mutual love.

alohaʻi

Bible spelling of aloha ai.

alohiki

families united by marriage, in-laws.

alokahi

single weft in plaiting; mat of a single thickness, with only one shiny side. lit., single side.

alokele₁

attractive, of fine appearance.

alokele₂

a red bird reported by Kepelino (no data).

alolua₁

two-sided, two-faced; facing one another, as cliffs on opposite sides of a valley.

alolua₂

double weft in plaiting; plaiting with a reversible side, with two thicknesses.

alopihe

persons shouting, as in mourning.

alopiko

belly of a fish, choice to Hawaiians.

alu

combined, acting together; to cooperate, act together.

alu like

work together...

alualu

• to follow, pursue, chase;   • to run, as for political office.

alāiki

appropriation of property by force, as practiced by some chiefs on their travels; to do so

Amu₃

name of a Kauaʻi wind.

ama

outrigger float; port hull of a double canoe, so called because it replaces the float.

amo

to carry a burden on the shoulders, to lift weights; a burden. fig., responsibility.

amo kau

a stick for carrying burdens on the shoulder.

amoamo

to raise or mount high, as waves; high, raised.

amu₁

to curse, revile.

amu₂

to eat.

Anianiikalani

name of a star said to be in the Milky Way.

ana hola

hourglass.

ana honua

surveying, to measure the surface of the earth.

ana hoʻohālike

model, pattern.

ana kaumaha

to weigh; weight.

ana loa

measurement of length.

ana manawa

tempo marker in music; Maelzel's metronome marker.

ana mekela

metric weight and measure.

ana paona

scales, balance; to weigh. lit., pound (Eng.) measure.

ana piha

measurement of capacity.

ana piwa

thermometer, for taking temperatures; to take temperature. lit., fever (Eng.) measure.

ana puka

underground passage, tunnel.

ana ua

rain gauge; to measure rainfall.

ana wai

water meter.

ana waina

liquid measure.

ana wela

thermometer, measurement of heat; to measure heat.

ana ʻole

without equal, unsurpassed, immeasureable, incomparable (in this sense, similar, to launa ʻole and lua ʻole), limitless, unlimited, never satisfied.

ana ʻāina

land surveying; to survey.

ana ʻōlaʻi

seismograph. lit. machine to measure earthquakes.

anaanapau

to move briskly.

anahonua

geometry.

anahuinakolu

trigonometry. lit. triangular measurement.

anahulu₁

period of ten days; for ten days; to pass ten days.

anahulu₂

large moana, a fish from 30 to 80 cm long.

anahā

reflection of light.

anaina

congregation, audience, assembly, gathering, crowd; to assemble.

anaina hoʻolewa

funeral wake or gathering.

anaina hoʻomana

congregation for worship.

anainaʻike aliʻi

royal reception or audience.

anakahi

unit of measurement.

analio₁

tail feathers.

analipo

distance, faraway space, beyond the horizon.

anana

fathom: formerly the distance between tips of longest fingers of a man, measured with arms extended on each side; Catholic writers equated anana with one meter; to count by this measurement or by fathoms.

ananea

leafless, bare.

ananū

turnip.

ananū pilau

daikon. lit., bad-smelling turnip.

anapaʻa

cubic measure.

anapuni

boundary, circumference, perimeter; to encircle, go around.

anawaena

diameter. lit., middle measure.

anaʻuku

mealybug (Coccidae) and scale insects.

anaʻē

to save for future use.

ana₂

to have enough or too much, satisfied, satiated, surfeited.

ana₃

cave, grotto, cavern.

ana₄

larynx.

ana₅

after e (verb). see e (verb) ana.

ana₆

following verbs indicating a single event, whether a command or a statement, whether completed or incompleted.

aneane

faint, feeble, exhausted; nauseous dizziness.

anena

Niʻihau.

ane₁

• a dermestid beetle that destroys feathers in feather-work;   • mites, as in chickens;   • ringworm;   • insect-eaten, gnawed.

ane₂

the breath of life, passing of a breeze.

ane₃

pimple, scabies.

ani

• to beckon, wave; beckoning.   • to blow softly, as a breeze;   • to draw a net over the surface of water;   • to pass over the surface, as a hand

ani peʻahi

to wave or beckon, as with the hand, fan.

aniani hoʻonui ʻike

magnifying glass, microscope, telescope. lit., glass to enlarge vision.

aniani ipu kukui

lamp chimney.

aniani kilohi

mirror, looking glass.

aniani kukui uila

electric-light bulb. lit., electric light glass.

aniani kū

standing mirror.

aniani nānā

mirror, looking glass.

aniani paʻa lima

hand mirror.

aniani₁

• mirror,   • glass;   • clear, transparent,   • obvious.   Several types of aniani are listed below.

aniani₂

• cool, refreshing; to blow softly, gently.   • fig., to travel swiftly.

ania₁

breezy.

ania₂

smooth.

anoa₁

dry, parched, barren.

anohale

individual presiding over the ʻume game.

ano₁

• awe, reverence, peacefulness, sacredness, holiness;   • feeling of awe, fear, or oppression;   • weird solitude, oppressive quiet;   • awestruck, lost in thought.

ano₂

time (in songs, and usually before ahiahi, rarely before kakahiaka).

anuhea

cool, soft fragrance, as of upland forests; sweetness; to be cool, fragrant, and sweet.

anu₂

cold, influenza; to have a cold.

Aohōkū

name of a star, possibly Jupiter, lit., star light.

ao akua

godly cloud. fig., rainbow.

ao kuewa

realm of homeless spirits.

ao loa

long cloud; high or distant cloud; stratus cloud along the horizon. fig., a distinguished person.

ao ʻōnohi

cloud with rainbow (ʻōnohi) colors.

aoaoa

a small seaside shrub (Wikstroemia sp.). The root bark is used externally for sores, and stems and bark of branches for coughs. Branches and leaves are mixed with rasped seeds of Barringtonia asiatica (syn. B. speciosa) to stupefy fish.

aokanaka

to think or behave reasonably; human enlightment, civilization; rational.

aokū

rain cloud, mist.

aouli₁

firmament, sky, blue vault of heaven.

ao₂

any kind of a cloud, including ʻōpua, but specifically, high clouds that when wind-blown scud along (kaʻa). cf:   aokū, rain cloud, mist   ao loa, long cloud; high or distant cloud...   ao ʻōnohi, cloud with rainbow (ʻōnohi) colors.   aouli, firmament, sky, blue vault of heaven.   ʻōpua, puffy clouds, as banked up near the horizon   pālāmoa, pāpalamoa, thick, dense, as clouds   puapuaʻa, plural of puaʻa₃, bank of clouds...

ao₃

world, earth, realm.

ao₄

to be careful, beware, watch out.

ao₆

the exact image of (preceded by a ʻe).

ao₇

a kind of fine mat.

ao₈

a kind of fish (no data).

Ap

abbreviation for ʻāpana, land parcel, used in surveying.

apo hele

orbit, as of stars and planets.

apo kula

gold bracelet; formerly a gold ring.

apo pepeiao

hoop earring.

apo pāpale

hatband.

apo ʻāʻī ʻīlio

dog collar.

apoapo

hill, as of sweet potatoes; bunch, as of taro; to hill up plants.

apohao

iron hoop or band, named for the king's guard under the monarchy.

apowaena

parentheses.

apoālewa

highest heavens or space.

apo₁

• circle, circuit, hoop, loop, band,   • bracelet, hoop-shaped earring, ring,   • girdle, belt,   • to span, reach around,   • embrace, put an arm around, clasp. Many compounds with apo are listed below.

apo₂

union of the molar or cheekbone with the temporal bone.

apuapu ʻānai makau

file or polisher for fishhook.

apuapu₂

file, rasp; to smooth or sharpen with a file.

apuapu₃

beard of a fishhook.

apuhihi

a shellfish resembling the hīhīwai, found in brackish water.

apu₁

• to snap or snatch with the teeth; snatching.   • fig., to destroy, ravage, ruin.

Auhaele

name of a star, companion to Hōkūʻula and Paikauhale. Perhaps the three are Sigma, Antares, and Tau Scorpii.

Auhaku

name of a star (no data).

Aukele

short for ʻAukelenuiaiku, a hero.

Aukoaʻeuamālie

name of a stroke in lua fighting. lit.., tropic bird hastens, it is calm.

au kō malalo

undertow.

au nele

hard times, depression, recession.

au wale

pass...

au ʻawa

bitter gall. fig.., ingratitude.

aua

to look, observe.

auahi

this word is related to uahi, smoke. One source says it refers to lowly or humble persons. (Malo 109) says it may refer to a distant relationship.

auakeʻe

dishonest.

auakua

ghost-ridden; haunted or unfriendly land. lit., ghost bile. cf. (Isa. 13.9) .

aualaliha

a variety of ʻoʻopu goby fish found in both brackish and fresh water.

aualaloʻi

terraced taro patches.

aualiʻi

royal, chiefly.

auaneʻi₁

soon, by-and-by, presently, shortly, just. cf. auaneʻi₂

auaneʻi₂

• probably,   • merely,   • probably not,   • possibly,   • doubtful.

auau₁

same as au₁, period of time, era...; to walk lightly and swiftly.

auau₅

to walk lightly and swiftly.

auaʻina

an unknown herb, the bark and leaves of which were used as medicine.

auhele

to go looking from place to place without any definite course, to drift or sail aimlessly, drifting.

auhili

to turn off the course, wander, deviate.

auhonua

ancient age, era, epoch.

auhuli

to overturn, overthrow, upset; to till.

auhā₁

molting, of a chicken.

auhā₂

outhouse, as for storing canoes; shed, shelter.

auka

weary, exhausted.

aukaha

desolate, dreary, nonproductive.

aukahi₁

• even,   • smooth,   • clear.   • fig., suave and pleasant in speech and manner.

aukahi₂

united, flowing together.

aukaka

deep coral bed with overlapping ledges where fishes hide.

aukana

short for au kanaiʻi.

aukanaka

inhabited place, settlement; inhabited.

aukukui

apprentice canoe maker.

aukukū

crowded, close.

aukūkū

agitated; agitation.

aukū₁

to pitch and toss; to raise, lift.

aukū₂

uphill path.

aukū₃

shallow.

aulau

to gather leaves to wrap fish in for cooking, as leaves of pōhuehue, mānewanewa, lauaʻe, ti; to frighten fish into a net with leaves.

aulele

to fly, as a frightened flock of birds.

aulike₁

even, smooth, as timber.

aulike₂

to treat kindly.

auloli

mildew.

aulā

stunted, sun-baked.

aumaiewa

large-mouthed net placed at the wings of the papa hului net to receive fish; used in deep water.

aumiha

• to float off in the air, as miasma;   • evil spirits thought to attend graves.

aumihi

to grieve, regret, be sorry.

aumiki₁

outgoing current.

aumiki₂

fresh water mixed with noni juice, drunk after kava.

aumoa

to care for; protected.

auolo

shelter or shed, as for canoes; outhouse, temporary house; tabernacle.

aupaka₁

some representatives of an endemic genus (Isodendrion), members of the violet family. They are small shrubs beating greenish-white or reddish flowers, which have equal petals and none spurred.

aupaka₂

Niʻihau name for naupaka kahakai.

aupoʻipū

according to (Kep) and (Kam), a relationship extending back 24 generations.

aupula

fishing with a pula stick or pūlale to drive fish into a net.

auwaea

distant, remote, deep.

auwalakī₁

entangled, snarled, as fishline.

auwalakī₂

destitute, especially of the rich who lose ever everything.

auwaʻalālua

paper nautilus (Argonauta argo). lit., fleet of canoes with two sails.

auwehekika

name recorded for kauā, outcasts.

auālipo

overcome by intense emotion, as love, grief.

auēuē

a calling, crying, humming, buzzing.

auī

ouch!

auʻāpaʻapaʻa

passing of much time on a piece of land, as an old family.

au₁₀

to rub, massage, polish.

au₁₁

to set, as a net or fish trap.

au₁₃

Hedyotis acuminata, a native shrub (coffee family), with small green flowers, and unpleasant-smelling, ovate or narrower leaves.

au₂

current; to flow, as a current.

au₃

• movement, motion; to move, stir;   • eddy,   • tide,   • drift, float,   • walk,   • hurry,   • succession or train, as of thought, trend.

au₄

gall, bile (Oihk. 3.4) ; gall bladder.

au₅

weather.

au₆

small sweet potatoes of poor quality that grow from the vine.

au₇

pumice.

au₈

grain of wood.

au₉

to weed.

awa kalamoho

a large awa, milkfish.

awa kū moku

ship harbor or anchorage, port.

awa lau

many channels

awa ʻaua

a herring-like fish, sometimes called tenpounder or tarpon (Elops hawaiensis); according to some, a medium-sized awa fish.

awaikū

good spirits, as the messengers of Kāne, who guarded people from evil ghosts and managed the rain, winds, and weather.

awaiāulu

to bind securely, fasten, as of the marriage tie.

awaloa

place where bones of chiefs were hidden, as in a cave, lit., eternal harbor.

awa₁

port, harbor, cove; channel or passage, as through a reef.

awa₂

milkfish (Chanos chanos). Stages of growth are pua awa (puawa), young; awa ʻaua, medium size; awa, commercial size; awa kalamoho, very large.

aweawe poi

drip of poi; an insult to the chiefs of Hawaiʻi, playing on the name of their chiefs, Keawe, with implication that poi is excreted in a sticky chain.

aweawe₁

• tenacious,   • sticky, adhesive; glueyness,   • threadlike, threads.

aweawe₂

wake, as of a ship.

awe₁

• strand, thread;   • thin,   • soft.

awe₂

wake of a ship.

awāwa

valley, gulch, ravine.

aī

of surprise.

Aʻe Loa

name for the trade wind. see ex., kiʻekiʻe.

Aʻe₂

northeast tradewind.

aʻa koko

vein, blood vessel.

aʻa kolo

a root running horizontally that produces roots below and above; a rhizome, creeping root.

aʻa kūkūkū

varicose veins. lit., raised veins.

aʻa moku

broken blood vessel.

aʻa puʻupuʻu₁

capsular ligament.

aʻa puʻupuʻu₂

knots in a fish net.

aʻa pūhaka

girdle, belt. lit., loin belt.

aʻaahi

scion or shoot of sandalwood.

aʻahuʻi

aching veins, varicose veins.

aʻalele

pulse. lit., leaping vein.

aʻalolo

nerve. lit., brain vein.

aʻapau

valve of a vein.

aʻaʻa

network of veins.

aʻa₁

• small root, rootlet,   • vein, artery, nerve, tendon, muscle.   • fig., womb, offspring.

aʻa₂

• to send greetings or love;   • joyous hospitality;   • joy at greeting a loved one.

aʻe nei

just now, lately; nearby, not far; ordinary, insignificant.

aʻeaʻe₁

mixing of a dark or brilliant color with a lighter one, as feathers in a lei; of dark hair of a young person with streaks of gray; to mix, as drinks.

aʻeaʻe₂

a kind of banana with green and white striped leaves and fruits.

aʻeaʻe₃

a fish (no data).

aʻela

directional part. aʻe + demon. lā.

aʻe₁

several native trees, the soapberry (Sapindus saponaria f. inaequalis), and all species of Zanthoxylum (also known as Fagara, Zanthoxylum having yellowish wood formerly used for digging sticks and spears); seeds of all (largest in the soapberry) are black, round, and used for leis.

aʻe₃

blight.

aʻe₅

replacement of e in songs (commonly written a e, but a glottal stop is pronounced before ʻe).

aʻe₆

Maui name for maua₂, trees.

aʻiaʻi₁

• bright as moonlight; brightness,   • fair,   • white,   • clear, clearness   • pure,   • brilliant, shining;

aʻiaʻi₂

a native tree or shrub (Streblus sandwicensis [Pseudomorus sandwicensis and P. brunoniana are synonyms]), with narrow-ovate leaves, and milky sap; a member of the fig family.

aʻi₂

replacing i often in songs; usually written a i.

aʻo hele

to teach while traveling; to act as itinerant teacher, preacher, missionary.

aʻo heluhelu

reader, primer; to learn or teach to read.

aʻo hōkū

astronomy, astronomer; to teach or learn astronomy.

aʻo kepela

spelling book; to learn or teach spelling.

aʻo kiko

manual of punctuation; to learn or teach punctuation.

aʻo loko

innermost teaching, inspiration.

aʻo palapala

instruction, education; to teach or learn writing.

aʻo piliʻōlelo

grammar, instruction in grammar; to teach or learn grammar.

aʻoaʻo

• stratagem, plot,   • advice, counsel.

aʻo₂

replacing o, of, and ʻo, subject marker, in songs.

aʻu kū

broadbill swordfish (Xiphias gladius).

aʻu lepe

sailfish (Istiophorus orientalis).

aʻu papaʻohe

a variety of aʻu fish.

aʻuaʻu

small aʻu fish.

aʻukī

a fish, perhaps a marlin.

aʻu₁

swordfish, sailfish, marlin, spearfish (Istiophoridae). See sayings, laʻa₂, ʻoloʻolo₃.

aʻu₃

my, mine (a-form, zero-class).

A₂

abbreviation of ʻākau, north, as in surveying reports.

e (verb) ai

particles indicating imperative/intentive mood and accompanying subordinate verbs (ai in this case is the anaphoric ai).

e (verb) nei

particles indicating imperfect aspect and future tense and accompanying subordinate verbs. The nei indicates action here or now. See (Gram. 5.2).

e lākou ala

similar to e lākou nei, you there (usually affectionate), but persons addressed are farther away.

e lākou nei

you (pl.), you there (usually affectionate). (Shortened vocative e + pronoun lākou + zero demon.)

e ue

(this is sometimes said today as a chant ending, but is probably an innovation.)

eaea₁

air, breath, air current. Some confusion exists in the uses of eaea, ʻeaʻea, and ʻeʻaʻeʻa.

eaea₂

to rise; high waves.

eaea₃

a smell, as of seaweed; to smell.

eamāmā

gas. lit., light air.

eaolamāmā

oxygen. lit., light life breath.

eaʻaʻā

gas. lit., burning air.

ea₁

• sovereignty,   • rule, independence.   [Lā Hoʻihoʻi Ea, literally the day sovereignty was restored, a holiday celebrated in the Kingdom of Hawaiʻi. Set on July 31, modern observations of this day include ceremonies taking place at different sites around Hawaiʻi, including a key commemoration at Thomas Square in Honolulu.]

ea₂

• life, spirit (Isa. 42.5) .   • air, breeze,   • breath, respiration,   • vapor, gas; fumes, as of tobacco; This ea, as well as ea₁,₃,₄, is sometimes pronounced or sung ʻea.

ea₃

to rise, go up, raise, become erect.

ea₄

to smell. Also ʻea.

Ehoʻikauʻiomānoauaahiahi

name of a lua stroke. lit., let the hero of Mānoa return, [it's] evening. (E- is sometimes omitted.)

ehaha

to breathe hard, pant.

ehehe

song refrain. (EM 67)

ehehene₁

to laugh merrily, giggle in glee; laughter.

ehehene₂

syllables repeated for musical effect at end of verses, similar to ēhē.

ehehoʻopiʻi

carved parallel or undulating lines on a tapa beater and on tapa.

eheʻula

name recorded for adult stage of hāpuʻu fish.

ehuehu₁

• animation varying from fury and storm to power and majesty, animated, animation.   • violent; violence   • anger, fury; furious   • powerful   • majesty.

ehuehu₂

healthy, vigorous. Less used than ahuahu.

ehuehu₃

a kind of rock, used for adzes.

ehu₁

same as:   • ʻehu₁ spray, foam, mist...;   • ʻehu₂ dust, dusty...;   • ʻehu₃ pollen...;   • ʻehu₄ faint, difficult to see...

ehu₃

water or water mixed with fragrant herbs used in sprinkling or gently rubbing a patient to revive him from fainting.

ehu₄

var. name for ʻōlapa₂, Cheirodendron trees.

ei neʻi

here, here it is.

eia (nō) naʻe

but, furthermore, however.

eia aku

approaching, nearby, soon.

eia ala

here, here it is; you over there, you.

eia aʻe

here close by, here approaching.

eia hou hoʻi

and again, furthermore.

eia hoʻi

and, finally, behold.

eia iho

wait a moment.

eia kekahi

but withal, moreover, furthermore.

eia kā

so at last, then.

eia₂

this place.

eina

scorched.

ei₁

var. of eia, especially before words beginning with a-.

ei₃

rather frequent variation of the anaphoric ai (ai₃) in fast speech, but seldom if ever found so in printed form.

ekele

plant listed (no data).

ekikilau

a stench that draws flies; bad-smelling.

ekoeko

redup. of eko; extremely bad-smelling.

elehu

slate or ash-colored pumice.

elelo lua

double-tongued, deceitful; trickster.

eluehe

a Molokaʻi name for ʻūlei, a shrub.

emi hope

to return, go backward, withdraw, back up.

emi kua

to go backward with stooped back, as from the presence of a chief.

emi pū

to lose weight rapidly, as due to sickness.

emi₂

cheap, inexpensive.

emi₃

flat (in music).

emowai

an addition of water, as for mixing poi. Kauaʻi.

emu₁

to shoo away.

emu₂

to rid plants of weeds.

ene

• first attempts of an infant to move;   • to draw up knees and push elbows,   • to crawl, creep.

enene₂

to dilate, as nostrils.

eo

• to lose, be defeated, beaten (if followed immediately by an animate subject and then by i-iā marking agent);   • to win, beat; winning, victory (in other environments).

epaepa

part of a fish's tail above and below the cleft.

epaepa huila

propeller blade.

eu

spelling occasionally found for e, part. + u, plural prefix (see (For. 5:507)).

Ewe

Eve.

ewa

• unstable,   • swaying,   • wandering;   • strayed.

eō₁

yes, I am here (in answer to a call by name, or to a name chant in one's honor).

eō₂

call; to call, answer

eʻe kuahiwi

to climb mountains; mountain climber.

eʻe moku

to board a ship; ship passenger; immigrant.

eʻea

to rise up frequently, as in water; to bob up and down.

eʻe₁

• to climb on, mount, get on,   • go aboard, board,   • embark;   • one who climbs, mounts, boards;   • step.   cf. eʻe kuahiwi, eʻe moku, hikieʻe.

e₂

by, by means of (follows a pas/imp.).

Haehaekamanuokānealoha

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the birds of Kānealoha tear to bits.

Haika Paka

Hyde Park.

Haiki

Haiti, Haitian.

Hakakāamoa₂

type of lua fighting in which the contestants did not use their hands, but fought with feet, legs, shoulders, head.

Hakalauʻai

name of a star associated with Hanakauluna, considered a sign of pestilence or calamity; also the name of a legendary place.

Hakamoa

name of a constellation. lit., chicken roost.

Hakaʻano₂

wind associated with Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

Hakuhiva

Fatu Hiva.

Hakuhiwa

Fatu Hiva.

Hakuohawaiʻi

Prince Albert, only son of Kamehameha IV and Queen Emma who died at the age of four in 1862, "leaving his father and mother heartbroken and the native community in desolation". lit., lord of Hawaiʻi. See chant, kiakahi.

Hakupōkano

name of a star. lit., lord of dark night.

Halakepoka

Hartford.

Hale ʻAhaʻōlelo Aliʻi

House of Nobles.

Halekuʻi o Papela

Tower of Babel.

Halemano

a romantic Oʻahu anti-hero who wooed, sometimes with success, the beautiful but fickle Puna princess, Kamalālāwalu. The account of the kilu (quoits) match contains some of the most beautiful of Hawaiian poetry. At the end of the tale the lovers apparently tire of one another. see ʻAikanaka₃. lit., many houses.

Halemauʻu

name of a Hāna wind. lit., grass house.

Halulu₂

a legendary man-eating bird.

Halāliʻi₁

name of a pleasure-loving chief of Niʻihau in ancient times. His name became synonymous with fun-making.

Hana-

bay, valley (only in place names, as Hanalei, Hanapēpē. Also Hono-, as in Honolulu).

Hanakahi

an ancient chief of Hilo whose name was used in poetry to designate the Hilo district.

Hanakalauʻai

name of a star associated with Hanakauluna, and the name of a legendary place. lit., Hana, the abundant food.

Hanakauluna₁

name of a star associated with Hanakalauʻai, and Hakalauʻai; all were omens of pestilence or calamity.

Hanakauluna₂

name of a death stroke in lua fighting.

Hanakaʻiluna

name of a lua stroke.

Hanalei₁

name of a large valley on Kauaʻi. lit., lei valley. see saying kaupoku₁.

Hanale₁

Henry.[word play: Henry / hungry]

Hanowa

Hanover.

Hanowela

Hanover.

Hanuipiʻi

a stroke in lua fighting. lit., rising breath.

Hapa Pele

Harper's Ferry.

Hauaʻiliki₂

name of a handsome surfer of Kauaʻi who vainly wooed Lāʻieikawai (SH 214-15); also a place name on Kauaʻi.

Haukomo

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the blow enters...

Haulani

a personal name. lit., ruling royal chief (this meaning is based solely on historical evidence: see hau-₂).

Haumea

an earth-mother goddess equated with Papa, Laʻilaʻi₃, and Kāmehaʻikana, the 'great source of female fertility' (HM 185) who bore children in successive generations. She is also called '[Haumea] … of mysterious forms, Haumea of eightfold forms, Haumea of four-hundred-thousand-fold forms...' (KL. 232). She married Wākea and later married Hāloa, her husband's son by his own daughter Hoʻohokukalani. Haumea had many other husbands. She is considered the mother of Pele and of Pele's many siblings who were born from her mouth or armpits. She presided over childbirth. Beckwith has summarized the many tales about her (HM 276-290). see Kaulu; Punaʻaikoaʻe; Kāmehaʻikana. lit., red ruler.

Haunakelekele

name of a star in the Milky Way.

Haunaʻīloli

wind name.

Haunone

name of a cold wind.

Hauomāʻihi

name of a wind associated with Kailua quadrangle, Hawaiʻi. lit., cool [wind] of Māʻihi (a wind goddess whose full name was Māʻihiʻalakapualono, fragrant sacred Māʻihi [child] of Lono).

Haupalemo

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the drowned blow...

Hawaiʻi piha

full-blooded Hawaiian.

Hawaiʻiloa₁

name of a legendary figure believed by some to have discovered Hawaiʻi, but see Barrère-1969; place name. lit. distant Hawaiʻi.

Hawaka

Harvard.

Haʻi manawa₂

The Times (name of a publication).

Haʻilono₂

name of a star.

Haʻinakolo₁

a forest-dwelling goddess of tapa makers and bird catchers, sometimes referred to in chants as Haʻiwahine or Haʻi.

Haʻinakolo₂

a legendary woman who had many adventures. She was deserted by her husband and ran away crazed at Waipiʻo, Hawaiʻi. lit., grumbling answer.

Haʻiwahine

variant name for Haʻinakolo₁, a forest-dwelling goddess of tapa makers and bird catchers...

Haʻi₈

var. spelling of Haʻinakolo₁ a forest-dwelling goddess...

Haʻo₃

name of a star.

hae Hawaiʻi₁

hibiscus. lit., Hawaiian flag, from having red petals striped with white.

hae Hawaiʻi₂

carnation (Dianthus caryophyllus), petals red with white stripes, formerly a great favorite with Hawaiians.

hae Hawaiʻi₃

a variety of plumeria.

haehae₁

to tear to bits, tease;

haehae₃

a native variety of taro in the piko group, characterized by having the two basal lobes of the leaf blade separated up to the piko (point of joining with the leaf stem); a hardy taro often grown commercially for poi, formerly common at Kaʻanapali, Maui, where strong winds tore the leaves (hence haehae).

haekoko

bloodthirsty.

haele

to go, come (dual or plural).

haena

-na₁ form with hae₁,₂,₃; wildness; barking; tearing.

haeola

murderous.

hae₁

wild, fierce, vicious, furious, savage, ferocious; fury, rage; to rage.

hae₂

to bark (Isa. 56.10) , growl, snap, as a dog; to chirp noisily or scold, as a mynah bird.

hae₃

to tear.

hae₄

flag, banner (perhaps so called because a piece of torn [hae] tapa was used as a banner).

hae₅

flowers. see hae Hawaiʻi₁,₂,₃

haha kāʻupena

net spacer or mesh stick, gauge used in making meshes in nets, made of wood, turtle shell, bone, bamboo, whale rib, coconut shell, or metal.

hahae₂

small sweet potatoes removed in thinning a hill. Kaʻū.

hahai manu

bird hunter, fowler; to hunt birds.

hahalu

empty, void; somewhat deflated, as a balloon; half rotten, as wood, taro. fig., hungry.

hahana

heat, warmth; warm, sultry, hot.

hahano

enema.

hahao

to insert, put in.

hahape

Kauaʻi.

hahau kākua

to hurl a blow by swinging from the shoulders.

hahau₁

• to strike, hit, whip, beat, switch, smite, wield, thrash; whip, lash, stroke; a blow.   • to throw down, as a playing card with force; to play, as a card or kōnane pebble;   • to trump;   • to insert;   • to bat, as a ball;

hahau₂

• to offer a prayer or sacrifice;   • to lay before.

hahau₃

to build, as by laying bricks.

hahaʻi lua

to break in two. fig., bad luck.

hahaʻi malū

to follow secretly, "tail", stalk.

hahaʻi₁

to break into pieces; to break off, as to thin sweet potato vines.

hahaʻi₃

painful swelling, as in the groin.

haha₂

proud, haughty.

hahei₂

plump, fleshy.

hahei₃

to be bound fast.

hahili

a kind of fish.

haho

lacking in flesh, thin; to fail, of an invalid.

hahu₁

(see ex., mānewanewa₂).

hahu₂

to clear, smooth; to purge, as the bowels.

hai ao

day sacrifice; to sacrifice by daylight.

hai pō

night religious service, sacrifice.

hai ʻai

food offering; to offer vegetable food.

hai-₁

simulative prefix similar to haʻa-, similar in meaning to the causative/simulative hoʻo-... see     haikea, same as hākea₁, pale... (kea₁, white, clear...)     hailawe, to exchange, barter... (lawe₁, to take, transport, carry, bring, haul...)     hailepo, ash-gray pallor; to have this pallor... (lepo₁, dirt, earth, ground, filth...)     hailuku, to stone. fig., to hurt the feelings... (luku, to massacre, destroy, slaughter...)     haipule, religious, devout, pious, reverent... (pule₁, to pray, worship, say grace...)     haiʻula, same as hāʻula, reddish... (ʻula₁, red, scarlet...)     haiwā, to plant far apart, as taro, coconut... (wa₄, space, interval...)

haialo

lit., follow the presence.

haiamū

• to gather, crowd, flock;   • in great numbers, as ripening fruit.

haihaiā₁

wicked person; wicked, unholy.

haihaiā₂

to prevent the gods from hearing a rival's curses by acting insane (eating poison, going naked), thus diverting the god's curses to himself and freeing the victim; with his superior mana he turns the curses away from himself and on to the rival sorcerer (Kam. 64:140–1); to prevent gods from hearing by offering herbs and medicine (And).

haikaika

• to make faces;   • a grimace of defiance and contempt; the corners of the mouth were drawn back tightly, the teeth separated, chin and lower teeth twisting from side to side;   • perhaps the figure-eight mouthed images were inspired by this violent fighting expression.

haikala muku

cramps, less severe than haikala.

haikala₁

severe cramps, said to have often proved fatal.

haikala₂

asthma.

haika₂

to gasp.

haikea₂

a type of tapa (no data).

haikina

hyacinth.

hailawe

to exchange, barter.

hailepo₁

ash-gray pallor; to have this pallor.

hailepo₂

an ancient pestilence.

hailepo₃

one of the sting rays, perhaps hīhīmanu.

haili aka

shadowy form of a ghost.

haili moe

recollected dream, vision.

hailimoa

a shellfish resembling the wana, but with short spines, possibly Tripneustes or Echinometra.

hailiopua

a small native fern (Schizaea robusta) found in high mountain wet areas believed to be the plant form of the sorcery goddess Pua; sometimes used as a psychological remedy to ward off the evil influence of Pua. lit., Pua's memory. Hawaiʻi.

haili₂

spirit, ghost; dim, indistinct.

haili₃

yellow band, as on the tail of ono, the fish.

hailona

• divination, casting lots, throwing dice;   • to test   • (also used interchangeably with hōʻailona).

hailuku

to stone. fig., to hurt the feelings.

hailōkeaka

the card game high-low-jack-and-the-game.

haina

offering, sacrifice.

hainaki₁

prayer removing the taboo on land after the taxes had been collected (an example of a pule hainaki is in (Malo 146–7)).

hainaki₂

quarter of a roasted pig reserved for priests at the laukini service (Malo 174); to offer such.

hainakā

handkerchief, napkin (rare).

hainakā lei

neckerchief.

hainakā pakeke

pocket handkerchief.

hainakā paʻeke

pocket handkerchief.

hainakā pepa

paper handkerchief, cleaning tissue.

hainakā ʻāʻī

neckerchief.

hainā

cruel, unmerciful, heartless; to abuse, treat cruelly.

haipule

religious, devout, pious, reverent; piety, a pious person; to worship; to hold prayers or service, as to consecrate a heiau; church service.

haiwā

to plant far apart, as taro, coconut.

haiā kāne

male retainer of a chief.

haiā wahine₁

female retainer of a chief.

haiā wahine₂

wicked woman, concubine

haiā₁

retainer or follower of a chief.

haiʻeʻa

a variety of ʻaʻawa lelo, a fish.

hai₁

offering, sacrifice; to offer, sacrifice. cf:   haina, offering, sacrifice   hai ʻai, food offering; to offer vegetable food   haialo, lit. follow the presence. same as haiā₁, retainer or follower of a chief...   haiau, var. of heiau   haipule, religious, devout, pious; to worship; to hold prayers or service, as to consecrate a heiau...   heiau pre-Christian place of worship, shrine...

hai₃

to hire, employ.

haka ipu

shelf for calabashes; frame from which calabashes were hung.

haka kau

perch, shelf.

haka kaulaʻi

drying frame or rack.

haka lele

altar platform, especially where human sacrifices were laid.

haka lāʻau₁

wooden trough, flume.

haka pono

to observe carefully, stare.

haka ʻula a Kāne

poetic name for the rainbow. lit., red perch of Kāne.

haka ʻōlelo

medium or one possessed, who speaks; one who reports to a chief, especially the misdeeds of others.

haka ʻūlili

ladder, trestle.

hakahaka leo

ghostly voice, spirit voice.

hakahakaea

rainbow with much green color.

hakahaka₁

• vacant space, vacancy, room;   • blanks, as in a questionnaire;   • gap;   • thin, emaciated, especially of one with hollow chest or sunken features.

hakai

container, bag, named for Haggai (Hagai 1.6) , who carried a bag with holes [spoken humorously].

hakaka

myrtle.

hakakai

bloated, swollen.

hakakau

to straddle. fig., a tall thin person.

hakakauluna

same as lona, canoe rest.

hakakaupili

to stand intently watching, as a thief [said to be the name of a legendary rat thief]; to stand precariously, as at the edge of a cliff.

hakakaʻe

frail, weak; thin, as tapa or a dress.

hakakā pahi kaua

duel with swords.

hakakā pūpanapana

pistol duel.

hakakāamoa₁

cockfight.

hakakē₁

crowded, overlapping, entangled.

hakakē₂

to stand on stilts, as a spider.

hakakī

plump.

hakakū

frame, platform, as for drying fish.

hakalina

showy, pompous, vain, as of one's attire.

hakalī

high.

hakanea

same as kanea.

hakanele

to be worthless, useless; uselessness.

hakanū

silent, sullen; struck dumb, as in amazement.

hakapō

darkness.

hakaʻano₁

breach, as in mist.

haka₁

• shelf, perch, platform;   • roost, as for chickens;   • fish spear rack;   • rack for suspending water gourds and other household objects;   • rack attached to booms of double canoe to hold spears and other objects;   • ladder

haka₂

recipient; medium, oracle, one possessed.

haka₃

crested feather helmet, so called because the crest perches on the helmet.

haka₄

hole, breach, open space, vacancy; empty, vacant, full of holes or spaces.

haka₅

to stare, gaze.

haka₆

to place wood in a ground oven, to lay an oven fire.

haka₇

heart, hearts, in a deck of cards.

hakia koko

bloody stools.

hakina

• broken piece, remnant, scrap, fragment;   • portion,   • balance,   • section,   • fraction, as in arithmetic.

hakina kūpaʻewa

improper fraction.

hakina kūpono

proper fraction.

hakina maoli

common fraction.

hakina pili

mixed number.

hakina pānaʻi

reciprocal number.

hakina pāʻumi

decimal fraction.

hakina ʻai

food fragment, scrap, morsel.

hakina ʻōlelo

portion of a word, syllable.

hakiʻopa

to limp, hobble, amble.

hako

dignified, noble, honorable.

haku hale

landlord, house owner, host, hostess.

haku hana

overseer, superintendent, employer, boss.

haku hulu

to plait, as feathers; featherworker.

haku mele

poet, composer; to compose song or chant; those that speak in proverbs. cf. haku o ke mele, owner of the chant, the one for whom a chant was composed rather than the composer.

haku moʻolelo

author, story writer.

haku nui

manager, as of a plantation or firm.

haku puke

author.

haku wahine

wife of a chief, lady, woman of high rank; female employer or supervisor.

haku waiū

hard core in a breast.

haku wale

to make up, invent, fabricate, improvise; fabricator.

haku ʻōhiʻa

ʻŌhiʻa log to be carved into a canoe (also malu ʻōhiʻa, (Kam. 76:136)); main ʻōhiʻa image in a heiau.

haku ʻōlelo

author, writer, reporter; to compose, as narrative or story; to slander, fabricate.

haku ʻōnohi

eyeball.

hakualo

belly, lower abdomen; belly fin and flesh of fish.

hakuhaku₁

lumpy, as poi.

hakuhaku₂

to fold, as tapa; to arrange, put in order.

hakukele

wet, lumpy, as poi.

hakukole

to defame, ridicule, as in figurative language and chant; defamer.

hakukoʻi

• disturbed, agitated, excited;   • to surge, excite, rush.

hakuone₁

small land division, as cultivated for a chief.

hakuone₂

inland pond.

hakupapa

to sew feathers to a band, as for a hat.

hakupaʻa

new taro patch. lit., hard core.

hakupehe

hesitating, slow; to walk or speak with hesitation; to stalk.

hakupeʻoʻi

to limp.

hakuʻepa

• to deceive, fabricate;   • liar; deceitful.   • malicious gossip;

hakuʻāina

landowner; landlord.

haku₃

• core,   • lump, as of poi;   • stone,   • coconut sponge.

hakē

packed full, protruding, bulging, cramfull, swollen.

hakū

rising, bulging; bulge; to rise, as the moon.

hala Polapola

a kind of pandanus. lit., Borabora [Tahitian] hala.

hala hua₁

a female pandanus bearing fruit, contrasting with hala hīnano.

hala hua₂

nut in a pandanus key.

hala hīnano

a male pandanus bearing the hīnano blossom.

hala iwi nui

hard pandanus key, not suitable for leis. fig., hard-appearing, dissatisfied.

hala iʻa

sin of eating a forbidden fish or meat; failure to offer essence of fish or flesh to the gods before consuming it; to commit such offenses.

hala kahiki

the pineapple (Ananas comosus), probably originating in Brazil, of great commercial importance. lit., foreign hala. see hala kea and hala ʻula for what some Hawaiians call native varieties, still said to be growing wild in the forests at Puna, Hawaiʻi. called hala on Niʻihau.

hala kapa

sin of breaking clothing taboos; to sin thus.

hala kea

said by some Hawaiians to be a native variety of pineapple; plant spreading vinelike; leaves with thorny edges; fruit plain green when unripe, yellow when ripe, small, fragrant, good-tasting; pieces of the skin were used for hat leis. lit., white hala.

hala lihilihi ʻula

variety of hala with keys bright yellow at base, grading to bright orange-red at top, and smaller than hala ʻīkoi. lit., red-edged hala.

hala loa

gone a long distance or time; far.

hala melemele

a common form of pandanus with bright yellow keys.

hala mōʻī wahine

a variety of pineapple. lit., queen pineapple.

hala pepe

native trees (Dracaena [Pleomele] spp) in the lily family, with narrow leaves in tufts at branch ends and with clustered round yellow fruits. (Neal 205–6). This was one of the five standard plants used in the hula altar to Laka. see more under palai (Neal 12).

hala pia

an indigenous variety of pandanus, with keys 4 cm long, canary-yellow and small; head small, about 15 by 12 cm., used in medical prescription and for exorcising evil spirits. It was much prized for leis.

hala ʻiʻo

pandanus key that is ripe and soft, suitable for leis.

hala ʻula₁

pandanus with fruit sections entirely orange-red; same size as hala ʻīkoi.

hala ʻula₂

a variety of pineapple similar to hala kea, but leaves and unripe fruit red-tinged.

hala ʻīkoi

a variety of hala with keys 7 cm long, lemon-colored at base, changing abruptly to bright-orange in upper half; when cut for leis, a rim of orange is left at top of each key used.

halahalawai

watery, wet, tearful, weeping.

halahala₁

correction, criticism, complaint, reproach.

halahala₂

young stage of kāhala fish.

halahala₃

bitter, soul, brackish.

halahiʻa

to fail to hit, miss.

halahula

consideration of grievances, disputes; councils for such consideration.

halahī

to buzz, whiz by, as in missing a mark.

halahū

to fail, err, miss.

halakau₁

to perch high, as a bird.

halakau₂

large, as a pregnant woman.

halakea₁

fair, light.

halakea₂

a yellowish tapa dyed with coconut oil.

halakeʻa

temporary support or prop in the middle of the house ridgepole.

halakī

to go off course, miss the way.

halalani

high heavens, atmosphere.

halaloa

a fish (no data).

halalē

to slurp, as soup; to eat noisily; to swish, as the sea; to spill or slop over; fat; not clear, as speech.

halalī

far away and small.

halalū₁

young of the akule, a fish, about 14 or 15 cm long.

halalū₂

weak, in poor health.

halalū₃

• to rumble;   • to strum, as an ʻukulele.

halawi

to scrutinize.

halaʻai₁

older name for hala kahiki, pineapple. lit., edible hala.

halaʻai₂

sin of eating forbidden vegetable or fruit; failure to offer essence of such food to the gods before consuming it; to commit such offense.

halaʻoʻa

• to project, extend;   • to appear dimly, as in a vision;   • to see dimly.   • fig., presumptuous.

halaʻuhaloa

probably the same as the weed ʻuhaloa, a plant form of the pig god Kamapuaʻa, mentioned repeatedly in an 1851 version of the legend of Kamapuaʻa.

hala₁

• sin, vice, to sin (Kanl. 9.21) ,   • offense,   • fault,   • error; err.

hala₃

the pandanus or screw pine (Pandanus odoratissimus), native from southern Asia east to Hawaiʻi, growing at low altitudes, both cultivated and wild. It is a tree with many branches, which are tipped with spiral tufts of long narrow, spine-edged leaves; its base is supported by a clump of slanting aerial roots. The pineapple-shaped fruits are borne on female trees whereas the spikes of fragrant, pollenbearing flowers are borne separately on male trees. Many uses: leaves (lau hala) for mats, baskets, hats; the yellow to red fruit sections for leis, brushes; male flowers to scent tapa, their leaflike bracts to plait mats (see hīnano). (Neal 51) The aerial root (uleule) tip is a good source of vitamin B and cooked in ti leaves was used medicinally, although unpleasant tasting. The tree is called pū hala. The hala lei is much liked today but formerly was not worn on important ventures because hala also means failure. For the same reason some persons will not compose songs about hala. Types of hala are listed below.

hale ahuwaiwai

warehouse.

hale aikāne

a close family friend, house with friends.

hale aliʻi

chief's house, royal residence, palace.

hale aupuni

capitol building, government building.

hale hana

workshop, factory.

hale hana hao

ironworks.

hale hana pia

brewery.

hale hana uila

powerhouse. lit., electricity-making house.

hale hana ʻili

tannery.

hale hau₁

house built with posts and thatch sticks of hau wood and thatch tied with hau cord; said to be used for healing the sick.

hale hau₂

icehouse.

hale heiau

house for keeping images and for worship; house in a heiau.

hale holoholona

barn.

hale hoʻokamakama

house of prostitution, brothel.

hale hoʻokipa

guest house, lodging house, inn.

hale hoʻokolokolo

court house.

hale hoʻokomo kini

cannery.

hale hoʻolako kaua

armory.

hale hoʻolewa

funeral parlor, undertaker's establishment.

hale hoʻoluhi

house of bondage.

hale hoʻolulu

railway depot or terminal, waiting station.

hale hoʻolulu kaʻa

bus station or terminal.

hale hoʻolulu kaʻaahi

train station or terminal.

hale hoʻolulu mokulele

airport.

hale hoʻoluʻu

dyehouse.

hale hoʻoluʻu ʻili

tannery.

hale hoʻomaha

resthouse.

hale hoʻomalu

quarantine house or station.

hale hoʻonā

building where land claims were adjudicated by the Board of Commissioners to Quiet Land Titles.

hale hoʻoponopono

administrative building.

hale hoʻoulu mea kanu

greenhouse, conservatory.

hale hoʻāhu

warehouse, storehouse, shed.

hale hoʻāhu puke

library.

hale hālāwai

meetinghouse, synagogue.

hale hōʻaiʻē

pawnshop.

hale hōʻaiʻē kālā

credit union. lit., house for loaning money.

hale hōʻikeʻike iʻa

aquarium.

hale imu

shelter for the ground oven; cookhouse.

hale inu kope

coffeehouse.

hale inu kī

teahouse, teashop. lit., tea- (Eng.) drinking house.

hale inu lama

saloon, tavern, bar. lit., rumdrinking house.

hale inu pia

beer parlor.

hale ipukukui

lighthouse.

hale kahu₁

house of a pastor.

hale kaua

fort, fortification; tower.

hale kaʻa₂

carriage, chariot. (Puk. 14.7) .

hale keaka

theater.

hale kia

portico; veranda with pillars; porch of pillars.

hale kiaʻi

watchtower, tower.

hale kilo

observatory.

hale kilo hōkū

star observatory.

hale kinai ahi

fire station.

hale kipa₁

guesthouse, lodginghouse, inn (Puk. 4.24) , house of hospitality.

hale kipa₂

hospitable friend.

hale koa

armory, barracks.

hale kua₁

log cabin.

hale kua₂

house where tapa was made.

hale kuke

customhouse, cookhouse.

hale kuku

house for beating tapa.

hale kupapaʻu

tomb, sepulcher (1-Nal. 13.22) , grave; undertaking parlor. lit., corpse house.

hale kuʻi hao

blacksmith shop.

hale kāhiko kaua

armory.

hale kāhumu

cookhouse.

hale kāmala

temporary shed, booth, shelter.

hale kāpiʻo

lean-to shelter; house without walls. This name may be qualified by the terms ʻalaneo, auolo, hālau, kāmala, kele, kōlea, Oʻahu a Lua.

hale kāpiʻo ʻili lāʻau

rude hut made of bent branches or uprights covered with bark.

hale kāwili lāʻau

pharmacy, drug store.

hale kūʻai lole

clothing store, dry goods store.

hale kūʻai lāʻau

drugstore, pharmacy.

hale kūʻai mea ʻai

grocery store.

hale kūʻai palaoa

bakery.

hale kūʻai puke

bookstore.

hale lama

house built of lama wood, completed during daylight (lama) hours and used for treating sick chiefs and for convalescence.

hale lana

floating house, ark, houseboat.

hale lanalana

house built on a double canoe, as for chiefs.

hale lapaʻau

hospital.

hale lau hau

taboo sleeping house for chief and chiefess.

hale lau₁

house thatched with leaves rather than with pili grass.

hale lau₂

same as hale lama; taboo house for training kahuna hāhā.

hale laʻa

temple, house dedicated to God.

hale lepo

mud house, adobe house; dirty house.

hale lio

stable, barn. lit., horse house.

hale liʻiliʻi

outhouse. lit., small house.

hale lole

cloth house, tent.

hale lole holoholona

slaughterhouse. lit., house for skinning animals.

hale lua

cave house; house or vault over a grave; grave (1-Sam. 2.6) ; outhouse. lit., pit house.

hale lua liʻiliʻi

outhouse. lit., house with little pit.

hale lālā lāʻau

house made of branches, booth (Oihk. 23.42) , shanty. lit., tree-branch house.

hale lāʻau

wooden or frame building.

hale malu

shaded house, shed.

hale malumalu

shaded house, shed

hale mana

largest house in a luakini temple.

hale mana hoʻokō

administrative building.

hale manawa

house belonging to the high chief where he held secret conferences with the kālaimoku. lit., temporary house.

hale manu

birdhouse, aviary.

hale maʻi

hospital.

hale moa

chicken house. chicken coop.

hale moe

sleeping house, dormitory.

hale mōneka

monastery. lit., monk (Eng.). house.

hale nauā

a place where genealogy was scanned to see whether applicants were related to the high chief and therefore eligible to become members of the royal household...

hale noa

house without taboo, where the family mingled and slept.

hale noho

dwelling house, residence.

hale o Lono

house where prayers to Lono were offered, as for rain and good crops; on all the islands heiau were so named. see (PN 38).

hale o Papa

house of the goddess Papa, i.e., house where religious services were held for women, said to be outside the heiau walls.

hale olo papa

sawmill.

hale pahu

drum house, especially in a heiau where prayers were uttered (Malo 162); a place of refuge in time of war (AP).

hale pale hau

snowshed.

hale papaʻa

storehouse (Kin. 41.56) . lit., secure house.

hale papaʻi

apartment building.

hale paʻahana

workshop, tool house.

hale paʻahao

jail, prison.

hale paʻi

publishing house, print shop, printing establishment.

hale pele

belfry. lit., bell (Eng.) house.

hale pepehi holoholona

slaughterhouse. lit., house for killing animals.

hale peʻa₂

menstrual house.

hale pili

house thatched with pili grass.

hale pipipi

house for convalescence; small, low house.

hale piʻo

type of ancient house, probably same as hale kāpiʻo.

hale poki

shrine where bones of dead chiefs were kept, as the Hale-o-Keawe at Kona, Hawaiʻi.

hale poʻo ʻoihana aupuni

capitol. lit., head house for government business.

hale pua niu

house where offerings of bananas, coconuts, and kava were kept, said to be offered in ceremonies deifying a deceased person or making him into a lizard god. lit., coconut-blossom house.

hale puhi kō

sugar mill; boiling of a sugar mill. lit., cane cooking house.

hale puhi palaoa

bakery.

hale puna

house built of limestone or coral.

hale pupupu

makeshift or temporary house, shed, shelter, lodge.

hale puʻuone

temporary booth, as in a luakini temple enclosure (Malo 163), probably used for divinations.

hale pākuʻi

• tower (Kin. 11.4) ,   • fortified house;   • addition to a house, annex.

hale pōhue

storehouse for gourds.

hale pūkaua

fort, tower, castle.

hale ukana

warehouse, storehouse.

hale umu

oven house, cookhouse.

hale wai

prison, jail. lit., house [for] retention.

hale weuweu

grass house.

hale wili

mill. lit., turning house.

hale wili kō

sugar mill.

hale wili palaoa

flour mill.

hale wili papa

planing mill.

hale ʻahaʻaina

restaurant.

hale ʻauamo

palanquin.

hale ʻauhau

house where taxes are paid; tax building.

hale ʻauʻau

bathhouse.

hale ʻopeʻope

house for keeping chief's clothes and possessions; house for keeping bones of chiefs. lit., bundle house.

hale ʻuʻuku

small house, cottage, cabin.

hale ʻāmala

blacksmith shop.

hale ʻāpulu

shack.

haleakaiʻa

same as pōniu and ʻinalua, the balloon vine. lit., house of the fish, so called because the vine was used in making small fish basket traps. Niʻihau.

halehaka

hollyhock (Althaea rosea), introduced.

halehale

• high, towering, as a housetop, cliff, or waves;   • cavernous.   • fig., emptiness, hunger.

halekoko

house where the hoa aliʻi, chief's companions, slept; house where prisoners were held until sacrificed. lit., blood house.

halekuʻi

building with many stories, tower. lit., added house.

halelewa

tent, portable house, tabernacle.

haleloke

a kind of lavender or purplish-red chrysanthemum. Probably lit., rose house, and named for someone called Rose, or whose house was called Hale Loke.

haleluia

hallelujah.

halelū

psalm, in the Bible; to sing psalms.

halepā

cupboard, safe. lit., dish house.

haleʻoihana

shop, workshop.

haleʻuwī waiū

dairy.

hale₂

host, hospitable person.

hale₃

name listed by Brigham for a pāwehe mat pattern; there is a central large lozenge with an enclosed rectangular figure internally enhanced with red on alternate weft crossings.

hale₄

hare.

hali

to carry, fetch, bear (Nah. 10.17) .

hali hele

to carry from place to place.

hali ukana

to carry baggage; porter.

halihali

to transport, transmit.

haliʻa

• sudden remembrance, memory, especially of a loved one;   • fond recollection; to recall, recollect fondly.   • premonition;

haloke

loose-fitting, not tight.

halolani

to move quietly, as a soaring bird.

halo₁

fins between gill plate and ventral fin.

halo₂

• motion of the fins or hands in swimming;   • motion of rubbing;   • to rub, polish.

halo₃

harrow.

haluhalu₂

to breathe heavily.

haluku₁

• to clatter, bang, thud, rattle, plop;   • to strike the side of the canoe with the paddle

haluku₂

• to wallow, as a hog;   • to render turbid [obscure, muddied].

haluku₃

to crowd, rush; crowded.

halulu₁

to roar, thunder; roar explosion, loud noise, racket.

halāliʻi₂

a variety of sugar cane, vigorous, large, of the Lahaina type, perhaps named for Halāliʻi, Niʻihau, where a famous sugar cane once grew in the sand dunes. This cane was used in ceremonies for remission of sins (uku hala, wehe hala). Also pakaiea. See saying, kō₁.

hamakuʻu

to tie the hair in a topknot.

hamapaka

humbug; to humbug.

hame₁

the two native species of Antidesma, medium-sized trees with hard wood, in the euphorbia family; leaves more or less ovate, fruits in grapelike clusters, purple, one-seeded. Formerly the wood was used for anvils for preparing olonā fiber, the fruit to color tapa red.

hame₂

ham.

hamo puna

whitewash, plaster; to plaster; one who plasters, bricklayer.

hamoʻula

ribbed tapa; to stain or dye with red, as tapa.

hamo₁

• anointed, smeared; to anoint, stain, rub, as with oil; to besmear, plaster, to spread, as butter;   • stroke gently, pet, fondle, caress;   • to struggle, as a drowning man;   • to put on, as gloves (Kel. 134);   • to plane smooth.   • fig., to flatter;   • compassion.

hamo₂

to thrust through or split asunder, as with a spear.

hamo₃

a variety of sweet potato.

hamumu

to whisper, murmur, hum; whispering.

hamuʻili

personal attendant of a chief, as a taster. lit., rind consumer.

hamu₁

• to eat voraciously, devour, eat scraps;   • fragments, scraps.

hamu₂

to destroy; to consume, as by fire.

hana aloha

love magic; to practice love magic. There follows a pule hana aloha, prayer to evoke love:

hana hemo

to loosen, let go.

hana hewa

to do wrong, err.

hana hou

to do again, repeat, renew, repair, mend; encore.

hana hoʻohala manawa

hobby, pastime.

hana hoʻohanohano

ceremony, ritual.

hana hoʻohiwahiwa

celebration to honor someone or something.

hana hoʻonanea

pleasant pastime, hobby, avocation.

hana ikaika

hard or strenuous labor or activity; to do such.

hana kalakalai

trifling, inconsequential action, as a casual love affair. lit., carving act.

hana kamaliʻi

childishness; childish; so easy that a child can do it.

hana keaka

to act in the theater; show business; a play...

hana kolohe

mischief, trick; to do mischief, misbehave.

hana kuli

noise, hubbub, cacophony; noisy

hana kīwila

civil service.

hana lepo

• dirty work; to do dirty work;   • excrement; to excrete.

hana lima

handmade, manual; manual labor; to work with the hands. crafting (HE).

hana luhi

tiresome activity or work, bother, toil.

hana make

thing of destruction, as a weapon of sorcery; to kill, destroy; deathly.

hana mana

miracle, supernatural deed, witchcraft.

hana mau

customary activity; to work constantly, diligent.

hana maʻa

customary or usual activity.

hana maʻi

sexual intercourse; to perform such. lit., genital activity.

hana mua ʻia

second hand, done before.

hana noʻeau

art.

hana nui

difficult, hard, laborious.

hana paʻa₁

to make secure, fasten, shut up.

hana paʻa₂

steady employment.

hana pipi

to work with cattle, especially as a cowboy; such work.

hana punahele

favorite pastime, hobby.

hana walea

to do with ease, as of long custom.

hana wale₁

to work aimlessly, gratuitously, to no avail, uselessly.

hana wale₂

to tease, annoy needlessly.

hana ʻili

tanner; to tan.

hana ʻoi

• to sharpen;   • cutlery.

hanaea

willful, disobedient.

hanahanai

edge of a precipice or slope, brow of a hill.

hanahana₁

hot, warm, vehement.

hanahana₂

sour, stinking.

hanahihi

rank-growing, wild, branchy. fig., untamed, uncivil, crude.

hanaina

feeding.

hanakapahu

smallpox (perhaps short for hana i ka pahu, build the coffin).

hanalei₂

hurled forth.

hanale₂

hungry, hunger.

hanana

occasion, event, occurrence, incident, time.

hananuʻu

short, plump.

hanapēpē

to bruise, crush.

hanauna

• generation;   • relative whose relationship was established several generations previously;   • ancestry, birth.

hanawai₁

irrigation; to irrigate, water.

hanawai₂

menstruation; to menstruate.

hanawai₃

urine; to urinate.

hanaʻiʻo

• serious about what one does;   • to consummate, as a love affair.   lit., to do truly.

hana₂

• worthless;   • provoked.

hana₄

same as hahana, warm. cf:   hahana, heat, warmth; warm, sultry, hot   hoʻohahana, to create heat; to rouse to fury   mahana, warmth, heat, warm...   hoʻomahana, to warm, create warmth, heat   pumahana, var. of pumehana, warmth, affection...   hoʻopumahana, var. of hoʻopumehana   hanahana, hot, warm, vehement   māhanahana, lukewarm...   hoʻomāhanahana, to make warm, heat...   kōhanahana, warm, hot   mehana, var. of mahana, warmth...   ola mehana, mesolithic, mid-temperature loving...   kukui hoʻomehana, heating lamp   pumehana, warm, warm-hearted; warmth, affection   kapuahi hoʻopumehana, fireplace   koʻehana, warmth, heat; warm   imu hau hana, oven in which hau wood was heated

hana₅

notch, as in a tree.

haneoʻo

strong blow, as of the fist.

hane₁

ghostly, soft, and indistinct sounding. cf. ʻuhane.

hane₂

to give life and spirit.

hanile

to prepare for or receive company.

hanina₂

yellow sarong, as dyed with turmeric.

hanini

• to overflow, spill, pour out, slop over;   • to pour down, as rain;   • to disappear.

hani₁

• to step or move lightly or softly;   • to graze, touch;   • soft, light.   • fig., to hint, suggest, act coy or flirtatious.

hani₃

to know well.

hano hāweo

distinguished, honored...

hano paka

tobacco box or container.

hanoa

fermented.

hanoalewa

temporary altar where offerings were made to the gods.

hanona₂

to determine by lot the virtue or value of a thing.

hanopilo

hoarse, wheezy, weak-voiced.

hano₂

hoarse; humming sound of chanting.

hano₃

nose flute.

hano₄

enema, syringe; to inject, use as a syringe.

hano₅

fish net, as for mālolo fish or ʻiao; bag net.

hano₆

container, as for water or tobacco.

hanu

• to breathe, breath, respiration, transpiration,   • smell, sniff, inhale;   • last breath of life;   • vanity. (Bib.)

hanu nui

deep breath.

hanu pau

last breath or gasp; to give the last breath, as of one dying.

hanu paʻa

a head cold; stifled breathing; to have such.

hanu pilo

bad breath, halitosis; to have such.

hanu pī

to sniffle.

hanunu

steep, bent-over, stooped, round-shouldered; stooping.

hanupaoa

lit., fragrant breath.

hanupau

a disease, perhaps pneumonia.

hanuāpuaʻa

to breathe like a pig; to gasp for breath, as a strangled pig.

hanuʻu₁

to flow in spurts, ebb, fluctuate; fluctuation, ebb.

hanuʻu₂

short, stunted, thick.

hao hakahaka

grate, grill.

hao hou puka

metal punch.

hao hoʻopaʻa wahie

andiron. lit., iron for holding fuel.

hao hoʻpaʻa lima

manacle. lit., hand-binding iron.

hao kaula waha

bit of a bridle.

hao keʻehi

stirrups.

hao kuni

branding iron.

hao kuʻe

piston.

hao manamana

grate, grill, gridiron, lit., branched iron.

hao mākēneki

magnet.

hao waha

bit of a bridle. lit., mouth iron.

hao wili

wrench.

haoa puhi

gorge used for catching eels: when the eel took the baited stick it was pulled by a string, and lodged in the throat of the eel.

haoa₂

scorching, bitter; heartburn, sour stomach.

haoa₃

Also laoa, laʻoa.

haohana

scooping; handful. (Probably hao₃ + -hana, nominalizer.)

haohao₂

soft meat that can be scooped from young coconuts.

haokanu

seedbed; to prepare a seedbed.

haokea

a rather common native variety of taro; the leaves are narrow, the piko, leaf attachment, light, and petioles light green. This taro supplies some gray commercial poi and lūʻau greens. It was formerly used both medicinally and in religious ceremonies, as for dedicating new fish nets. According to (HP 17), it is a domesticated form of wild ʻāweu. The name may be qualified by the colors hāʻulaʻula and keʻokeʻo. Var. names reported include ʻahakea, haʻakea, and hāʻawikea.

haokila

to be sturdy as steel. lit., iron steel (Eng.).

haoma

name of a fish (no data).

haona

handful, scoopful; receptacle, as a dipper for kava.

haoʻa

• rocky, as of broken lava or coral rubble;   • scraggly, uneven;   • choppy, as the sea.

hao₁

• iron,   • general name for metal tools,   • a bit;   • brand, as on a horse.   • See sayings, wela₁.

hao₂

all native species of a genus of small trees (Rauvolfia) related to the maile and the hōlei, four or five narrow branches are borne together at joints of branches; many small, yellowish flowers develop, and then small, black, flattened, twinned, inverted, heart-shaped fruits.

hao₄

• to come with force, as wind or rain;   • to do with force and energy.

hao₆

horn, as of a goat.

hao₈

• pillage, plunder, loot;   • robber

hapa Kepanī

one of part Japanese ancestry.

hapa haole

part-white person; of part-white blood; part white and part Hawaiian, as an individual or phenomenon.

hapa loa

a small portion, very few.

hapa makahiki

semiannual.

hapahaneli₁

hundredth part, percentage.

hapahaneli₂

a copper penny issued by Kamehameha III in 1847.

hapahapai

• to toss up, as a child;   • to heave or breathe heavily;   • to glorify, praise.

hapahiku

one seventh.

hapahā kini

five-dollar gold piece. lit., guinea (Eng.) quarter.

hapaina

carrying, lifting, carrier; pregnancy.

hapaipū

heavy breathing, as of one with asthma; to breathe heavily.

hapakolu

third; one third.

hapakuʻe

crooked, deformed, crippled, defective; speech impediment; to speak with an impediment, as one who has had a stroke; crippling, defection.

hapalima

fifth; one fifth.

hapalua kini

ten-dollar gold piece. lit., guinea (Eng.) half.

hapaono

one sixth.

hapapū

partly finished, incomplete, as work.

hapapūlima

signature, handwriting, autograph.

hapawai

a shellfish, Theodoxus vespertinus.

hapawalu

one eighth; eighth part; a coin worth twelve and a half cents; a piece of silver money (Luka 15.8) .

hapaʻumi

tenth part, tithe; five cents, nickel.

hapaʻuʻuku

minority, small portion; less.

hapa₂

of mixed blood, person of mixed blood, as hapa Hawaiʻi, part Hawaiian.

hapa₃

A-minor in music.

hapenūia

Happy New Year!

hape₁

incorrect, faulty, inaccurate; to break, transgress (Kep. 49).

hapuee

a kind of fish.

hau heheʻe

slush.

hau hele wai

a kind of hau hele shrub.

hau hele ʻula

an endemic genus of small trees (Kokia, four species), in the hibiscus family. The leaves are leathery, round, with three to seven shallow lobes. The flowers are large and red, and have three broad bracts at the base.

hau hele₂

a shrub or herb (Abutilon grandifolium). Niʻihau. lit. traveling hau.

hau kaʻekaʻe

a kind of hau tree.

hau kea

white snow, snow.

hau koʻiʻi

a kind of hard hau tree.

hau kuahiwi

five species of a native genus (Hibiscadelphus) of medium-sized trees, related to the hau; rare plants, with heart-shaped leaves and curved, red, yellow, and green flowers.

hau oheohe

a rare variety of hau, a tree, with a straight trunk.

hau pūehuehu

snowflake.

hau ʻō mālolo

hau-stick handle of mālolo (flying fish) net.

hau ʻō ʻiao

hau wood handle attached to net used for ʻiao fish.

hau-₁

dirty, unpleasant. cf.:     hauʻeka, defiled, filthy, smutty...     haukaʻe, stained, smeared, smudged, defaced, sordid...     haumanumanu, irregular, dull; ugly.     haumia, uncleanliness, filth, defilement, abomination... pollution     hauna, unpleasant odor, as of spoiling fish or meat, or volcanic sulphur...

hau-₂

ruler (nonproductive, mostly in proper names, such as in the common names Haulani and Haunani).

hauaʻiliki₁

bitter, cold.

haua₁

a blow, stripe; to whip.

hauene

calcareous earth resembling chalk or plaster.

hauhalakī

tangled, snarled; untidy, confused.

hauhana

lashing, as of adze to handle; to lash. (hau₃ + -hana, nominalizer)

hauhauhali

to carry to and from, as gossip.

hauhaukoʻi

swelling of the groin.

hauhau₂

cool, as food.

hauhilikī

to snarl, entangle.

hauhoa

• to tie, lash, bind;   • to saddle, as a horse.

hauhole

slang term for haole, perhaps related to hole, to fidget, squirm; it might also be said of a drunk, over-persistent lover, or mischievous child.

haui

a word known only in the chant called Haui ka lani, (For. 6:368–410); according to Andrews (For. 6:368), an ancient, poetical name for hāʻule which he translates "fallen" but more probably hau, to strike + -i, transitivizer. A more accurate translation of the chant's title is "the chief is struck down." A less plausible interpretation is hau i ka lani, offer to the royal chief.

hauka

out (said in gambling).

haukalalī

to strut.

haukalima

ice cream. lit., creamed (Eng.) ice.

haukalī

dressed in one's best.

haukapila

hospital.

haukau

choppy, as the sea.

haukawewe

same as kawewe,   • to clatter, as dishes;   • to roar, as a sudden downpour...

haukaʻe

• stained, smeared, smudged,   • to besmirch, stain, smear;   • defaced,   • sordid;   • defiled, as taboo food cooked with common food;   • babbler (Oih. 17.18) .

haukoi

floater, as on a fish net.

haukī

pudding made of arrowroot starch and juice extracted from baked ti root.

haukō

a pudding made of arrowroot starch, coconut cream, and sugar-cane juice.

haukōhi₁

icecap, as at the Arctic. lit., checked ice.

haulalapa

to blaze, scorch, sear.

haulana

iceberg, floating ice.

haulani

• to surge, as the sea;   • to plunge, as a canoe;   • to ply back and forth;   • restless, constantly on the move.   • to repeatedly travel speedily, as a boat or train...   • fig., to dissipate.

hauli

this word is used idiomatically with lele and hoʻolele, and may be related to mauli.

hauloliʻi

descendant, offspring.

haumakaʻiole

blurred eyes of a rat, said of very old persons; an aged person.

haumalu

quiet.

haumekū

a kind of stone used for adzes.

haumia

uncleanliness, filth, defilement, abomination; defiled, indecent, obscene, vile, lewd, unclean (Oihk. 15.2) , contaminated, sordid. (hau-₁ + -mia, pas/imp)

hauna

• unpleasant odor, as of spoiling fish or meat, or volcanic sulphur;   • stench; tainted.

haunaele

panic, riot, roughhouse, brawl, tumult, commotion, confusion, hubbub.

haunama

a slightly offensive odor.

hauone

soft limestone.

haupa

to eat heartily or voraciously.

haupeʻepeʻe

to play hide-and-seek; hide-and-seek.

haupoa

to soften the earth, as for planting.

hauwalaoʻa

a confused, excited din; to sound thus. (The following words are confused at times: uluaoʻa, walaʻau, wanaoʻa.)

hauwalaʻau

• to gabble,   • gossip,   • chatter, babble,   • hubbub,   • fuss.

hauwawā

medley of simultaneous talking.

hauwene

to cry, tease, nag, fret.

hauʻeka

defiled, filthy, smutty.

hauʻeli

glauber salts, sulphate of soda.

hauʻina

tapa sarong dyed with ʻōlena.

hauʻoki₁

• chilled to the bone, stiff with cold;   • frost, ice, cold;   • icy wind.

hauʻoki₂

a medicine made of hau bark for women in labor.

hau₁

a lowland tree (Hibiscus tiliaceus), found in many warm countries, some spreading horizontally over the ground forming impenetrable thickets, and some trained on trellises. The leaves are rounded and heart-shaped, the flowers cup-shaped, with five large petals that change through the day from yellow to dull-red. Formerly the light, tough wood served for outriggers of canoes, the bast for rope, the sap and flowers for medicine. (Neal 559–60). Of the two varieties of hau, a rare erect one (hau oheohe) was grown for its bast and a creeping one (hau) was planted for wind-breaks. (HP 196)

hau₃

to hit, smite, beat, tap.

hau₄

to lay before; to offer, as a sacrifice or prayer.

hau₅

a soft porous stone, as used for polishing calabashes.

hau₆

mother-of-pearl shell.

hawa

defiled, unclean, filthy, daubed with excrement.

hawahawa

a taunt in a children's game.

hawaiʻiloa₂

name of a line for ulua fishing in 17 or more fathoms of water.

hawewe₁

to rumble, clatter, patter, as rain; rumbling.

hawewe₂

to pour down, as the sun; to vibrate, as heat.

haīnana

to talk with animation.

haʻa-

• a prefix similar in meaning to the causative/simulative hoʻo-.   • before short vowels and glottal stop the form is usually hā-, as hāinu, to give to drink, and hāʻawe, to carry.   • before consonants, both haʻa- and hā- occur, as haʻalele and hākuʻi.   • before glottal stop plus a long vowel, ha- occurs, as haʻāpuka.   • for a few bases, derivatives with both haʻa- and hoʻo occur, as haʻakoʻo and hoʻokoʻo, which have the same meanings; with a few bases, meanings differ, as haʻalele and hoʻolele.   • a few bases with haʻa- may form another derivative with hoʻo-, as inu, hāinu, and hoʻohāinu; heo, haʻaheo, hoʻohaʻaheo.   • before colors the meaning is "-ish, somewhat," as hākea, haʻakea, hāʻeleʻele, hāuliuli.   • for clear understanding, delete haʻa- and look up the base.

haʻahui

united.

haʻaiwi

bachelor.

haʻakea₁

whitish, pale; pallor.

haʻakei

• proud, haughty, snobbish, snooty, vain;   • rude,   • to scorn, scoff.

haʻakoaʻe

like the tropic bird.

haʻakoi₁

egotistic; egotism; proud; to brag, boast, show off.

haʻakoi₂

to force, urge, insist.

haʻakoi₃

to practice onanism.

haʻakokōhi₂

to bring out the natural grain of wood, as by careful use of oil.

haʻakoni

female kāhili-bearer for a chief.

haʻakoʻa

short, as a bantam.

haʻakualiki

an officer who preceded a chief and his train and announced his rank and the object of his approach.

haʻakualiʻi

a class of dwarfish people of great strength and valor.

haʻakua₁

to struggle to right oneself, as a turtle turned over.

haʻakua₂

male kāhili-bearer for a chiefess.

haʻakuʻe₁

to shift or ripple; to and fro, back and forth.

haʻakuʻe₂

a kāhili-bearer for a chief or chiefess of the same sex.

haʻakūlipo

same as hoʻokūlipo, dark.

haʻakūlou

same as hoʻokūlou, to bow.

haʻalau

to produce leaves.

haʻalele loa₁

to abandon permanently or completely.

haʻalele loa₂

extremely, exceedingly.

haʻalele noho aliʻi

to abdicate a throne.

haʻalele wale₁

to abandon for no reason.

haʻalelea₂

man sacrificed when cutting an ʻōhiʻa tree for an image.

haʻaliki

to brag, boast; braggart.

haʻalilio

tight, taut.

haʻalilo

far off, distant.

haʻalipo

• to be darkened;   • to bow the head, as in grief.

haʻaloku

same as hoʻoloku; downpour; emotion.

haʻaloʻu

to bend over, as a heavy branch; to droop, as in sorrow.

haʻalulu

• to shake, quake, totter, tremble, quiver.   • nervous (NKE12)

haʻanapu

to sway, as in a dance.

haʻanepu

same as hoʻonepu, plump.

haʻanoanoa

var. of hoʻonoanoa, to free from taboo.

haʻanopu

to swell, surge, as the sea.

haʻanoʻu

to exaggerate, gush, boast, speak forcefully; to chant with emphasis and force on stressed syllables.

haʻanui

to boast, brag, exaggerate, gloat. (see nui and (2 Sam. 1.20) )

haʻapapaʻa

firm, tight.

haʻapuʻu₁

var. of hoʻopuʻu,   • to heap up, collect in heaps;   • to frown; resentment...

haʻawale

See pākiʻi haʻawale, a flatfish.

haʻawina hoʻi hope

review lesson. lit., lesson going backward.

haʻawina hoʻomau

life pension.

haʻawina hōʻike

examination, test. lit. showing lesson.

haʻawina ʻike

the gift of second sight, a gift or knowledge.

haʻaʻwina hoʻohanohano

honorarium.

haʻa₁

• low;   • dwarf;   • man or animal of short stature.

haʻa₂

• a dance with bent knees;   • dancing (1 Sam. 18.6) ;   • called hula after mid 1800s.

haʻa₃

a short variety of banana.

haʻe

yearning, longing; to yearn. rare.

haʻi aʻo

sermon, lecture, instructive discourse; to give advice.

haʻi kūpuna

to tell of ancestors; a chant concerning ancestors, genealogy.

haʻi liki

to boast.

haʻi manawa₁

to tell of the times.

haʻi manaʻo

to state an opinion, testify.

haʻi ola

to preach salvation or eternal life; one who so preaches.

haʻi pōkole

to speak or report briefly.

haʻi waha

word-of-mouth, verbal, oral; to tell verbally.

haʻi wale₁

easily broken, brittle.

haʻi wale₂

to tell without reason.

haʻi wale₃

to flirt readily, with little reason.

haʻi ʻale

to break, of billows. fig., to surge, of emotion.

haʻi ʻano

to describe, tell the nature of.

haʻi ʻeuanelio

to preach the gospel; evangelist.

haʻi ʻole

unbreakable, inflexible, stubborn.

haʻi ʻōuli

to tell omens, prognosticate, as by observing clouds; soothsayer.

haʻialiʻi

name of a hard rock used for making adzes.

haʻihana

verb (old name).

haʻihaʻi iwi

by holding the shoulders, to make a person's bones crack audibly; a form of chiropractic; to do so; to break bones.

haʻihaʻi₁

redup. of haʻi₁, to break or snap, as a stick; broken; fracture, joint, break...   • brittle;   • limbering exercises, as for the hula;   • massage in chiropractic;   • quavering;   • breaking, rising and falling of the voice;   • a style of singing with a breaking voice;   • to break, as a law.

haʻiinoa

noun. lit., name telling.

haʻiinoa laulā

common noun.

haʻiinoa pili kahi

proper noun. lit., noun referring to someone or place.

haʻikūumauma

a call to lift a canoe or to rally together in any work.

haʻikū₁

the kāhili flower (Grevillea banksii), so named because first planted near the town of Haʻikū, Maui. Also kāhili, and ʻoka pua ʻulaʻula on Niʻihau.

haʻikū₂

haughty, conceited.

haʻileʻa

to tell clearly.

haʻilima

distance from the elbow to the end of the fingers.

haʻiloaʻa

answer to a problem, solution, key.

haʻilono₁

to tell the news, to spread a report.

haʻimanawa

a thin, delicate white tapa.

haʻimoeipo

fascination, interest.

haʻina kekeʻe

irregular verb.

haʻina kuhikuhi

directional adverbs, as mai, iho, aku, aʻe. lit., pointing adverbs.

haʻina kōkua

helping or auxiliary verb.

haʻina nalu

breaking wave.

haʻina pili

transitive verb, active verb.

haʻina pili haʻiinoa

verbal adjective.

haʻina pili iā haʻi

transitive active verb. lit., verb referring to another person.

haʻina pili ʻia mai

transitive passive verb.

haʻina pili ʻole aku

intransitive verb.

haʻina pule

recitation of prayers.

haʻina ʻokoʻa

neuter or intransitive verb.

haʻinaleʻa

adverb. lit., clarifying verb.

haʻinau

to bend the head forward.

haʻina₂

a breaking, as of a stick or law; a break.

haʻina₃

verb.

haʻinole

to incite, encourage, stimulate.

haʻiwale

all native species of Cyrtandra, slender soft-wooded forest shrubs with white tubular flowers. Sometimes called kanawao keʻokeʻo.

haʻiʻano

adjective.

haʻiʻōlelo

speech, address, lecture, sermon; to orate, preach, make a speech; speaker.

haʻiʻōlelo hoʻoleʻa

eulogistic speech.

haʻi₁

to break or snap, as a stick; broken; fracture, joint, break. (cf. haki, moku, nahā, wāhi.)

haʻi₃

edge, border (not used with the articles).

haʻi₄

coquettish, flirtatious; to flirt.

haʻi₅

to sway, bend.

haʻi₆

house. Kauaʻi.

haʻi₇

• someone else, another person;   • another place, elsewhere (rare).   (Not used with articles)

haʻohaʻo

strange, puzzling, astonishing; astonished, puzzled, surprised; to wonder, marvel.

haʻohaʻona

astonishment, wonder.

haʻo₂

to long for, desire; to miss, whether desirable or not.

haʻu

• to snort (Ier. 8.16) , bray, puff;   • to chatter, as the teeth;   • to choke with sobs.

haʻuhaʻuuwē

to sob.

haʻuhaʻu₂

a refrain in dance songs, usually fast, and perhaps related to haʻu.

haʻukeke

to quiver, shiver

haʻulena

a falling, dropping.

haʻulili

to shiver.

haʻupā

to open and shut, as scissors, jaws.

haʻuōwī

Niʻihau.

Hehipuahala

rain name associated with Poʻo-kū, Kauaʻi. lit., stepping upon pandanus flowers.

Heleekela

the planet Uranus, formerly called Hershel for its discoverer, Sir William Hershel, in 1781.

Helene

Greek, Grecian, Greece.

Helepoka

Hereford.

Helepona

Hebron.

Hem

abbreviation used in surveying for hema, south.

Hepela

Hebrew.

Heʻenehu

name of a misty rain observed off the coast of Hilo when nehu fish are running.

Heʻepālaha

a stroke in lua fighting.

he aha sananā

of scorn. What does it amount to? It's of no value. (Perhaps nanā is from he ʻahi kananā, a phrase describing a fierce fighter; cf. nanā.)

hea inoa

to give a name; to chant a name chant; to call a name in hospitable welcome; to call the roll; roll call; name chant.

heahea₁

• to call frequently and hospitably;   • to welcome;   • friendly, hospitable, genial.

heahea₂

warm, tepid, insipid.

heana kanaka

human carcass, human sacrifice, an insulting name for kauwā, outcasts.

heana₁

corpse, especially of one slain in battle; victim, human sacrifice; carcass (Mat. 24.28) , remains.

heana₂

calling, as in greeting.

heau₁

place where fishermen set a basket fish trap, as for hīnālea.

heau₂

Exocarpus spp., native shrubs and small trees (sandalwood family), with more or less leafless, jointed branches.

heaʻe

Kauaʻi name for kāwaʻu, a kind of Zanthoxylum.

hea₁

to call, name; to sing or recite a name chant; to give a name to.

hea₂

misty, clouded, smoky, obscure.

hea₃

bank, as of a river.

heehe

to bleat.

heepālaha

each of two posts at the back wall of the ancient house, visible at the door.

heha

lazy, indolent, drowsy; weariness following sexual gratification.

hehe

a kind of bird (no data).

hehehewa

a mistake by many.

hehei₂

type of pāʻū, woman's skirt, sarong. (no data).

hehelo

reddish, bright, showy.

hehena

• insane, raving mad, crazy, possessed;   • insanity, madness;   • lunatic, maniac.

heheo

a swaggering or swishing walk; swishing, as of a skirt; to whirl, swish, strut.

heheʻe₁

• to slide,   • sag,   • fade;   • landslide, avalanche;   • soft, watery, melting.

heheʻe₂

discharge, as of pus; fluid.

hehi

to stamp, tread, trample, pedal, step on; trampling. fig., to repudiate, deny, desecrate, loathe, break (as taboo).

hehi hewa

misstep; to make a misstep.

hehi palaoa

to thresh wheat; threshing. lit., tread flour (Eng.).

hehi ʻino

to step firmly, stamp; to make a misstep and come down hard.

hehihehi

hiking (HE).

hehikū

• to break rules or taboos,   • disregard the rights of others, trample on their rights,   • trespass; trespassing,   • willful   • violation.

hehina

footrest; any place on which to step or tread; a stepping, treading.

hehu₁

• to uproot, dig up,   • put to flight, drive away, shoo,   • evict.

hehu₂

young seedlings or plants, as for transplanting; sucker.

hehu₃

a purge, as of water and juice of gourd stems used as an enema; to purge.

hehu₄

ceremony to drive away evil influence.

hehu₅

pile, as of rocks.

hehē

burst of laughter, guffaw; to guffaw.

hei kapu

a sacred place, as one where a priest stayed in seclusion to await a message from the gods, usually a small house on the heiau. (UL 74.)

heiau

pre-Christian place of worship, shrine; some heiau were elaborately constructed stone platforms, others simple earth terraces. Many are preserved today. Several types are listed below. In (Isa. 15.2) , heiau is a high place of worship.

heiau hoʻoulu iʻa

heiau where fish were offered to insure good fishing.

heiau hoʻoulu ua

heiau where offerings were made to insure rain.

heiau hoʻoulu ʻai

heiau where first fruits were offered to insure further growth. lit., heiau for the increase of food crops.

heiau hoʻōla

heiau for treating sick.

heiau kālua ua

heiau for stopping rain, or (less frequently) for bringing rain. One such heiau named Imukālua-ua (rain-baking oven) was in the Kaunakakai quadrangle, Molokaʻi; a land section in Puna, Hawaiʻi, also has this name. Rain in leaf packages is said to have been baked in an oven.

heiau maʻo

small temporary heiau covered with tapa stained green (maʻo), used for the hoʻoulu ʻai ceremony to bring food.

heiau poʻo kanaka

heiau where human sacrifices were offered.

heiau waikaua

a heiau used for services to bring success in war.

heia₂

piece of hair, tooth, fingernail, small bone, or the like of a deceased beloved, kept and offered food in order to please the spirit of the deceased.

heihei kūkini

footrace.

heihei₂

redup. of hei₁, net, snare, stratagem, ruse...; hei₂, string figure, cat's cradle...; hei₃, motion of hands and fingers, especially of the dying...; to festoon, drape.

heihei₃

to enthrall, enchant.

heiē

helper or apprentice to a priest.

hei₁

• net, snare, to ensnare, entangle, catch in a net;   • stratagem, ruse;   • to festoon with leis. see kāhei₁,₂; (Luka 5.4) .

hei₂

string figure, cat's cradle; to make such. Many kinds are listed by (Dickey).

hei₃

motion of hands and fingers, especially of the dying, (Some persons did not make string figures, hei, at night because of the association of the figures with the motions of death.)

hei₄

• adept, deft;   • to absorb, as knowledge or skill.

hei₆

water oozing from a cliff and trickling down.

heka

red, sore, inflamed, bleary.

hekau₁

• anchor, stone anchor, to anchor, anchored   • towline, tow   • line for fastening boats; make fast   • warp   • taut, stretched

hekau₂

to come upon, happen, befall, strike.

hekeheke

plump.

hekekē

plump.

heke₁

best, greatest, foremost.

heke₂

top gourd in a hula gourd drum.

heke₃

feathered top of an ʻulīʻulī, hula rattle.

heke₄

nail, pin, rack, as for hanging objects in a house.

heke₅

triangular sail, topsail.

heke₆

shy, sensitive.

hekili pāmalō

thunder without rain.

hekili₁

thunder; to thunder. fig., passion, rage.

hekili₂

a variety of taro.

hekili₃

a variety of sweet potato.

helahela₂

widespread.

hela₁

redness of the eyelids; rawness, as of scraped skin; to be red or raw.

hela₂

to spread, as the arms.

hela₃

Hula step: one foot is placed at about a 45-degree angle to the front and side, with the weight on the opposite hip and with that knee bent; the foot is then returned to the original position and the step is repeated with the other foot; to dance thus.

hele au

to go drifting along.

hele hewa

to go wrong, take the wrong path, go astray, err.

hele honua₁

to go suddenly, early, or for no apparent reason.

hele honua₂

to tie or bind beforehand, as in preparation for a journey.

hele hope

younger brother or sister; descendant of a younger brother or sister; to go behind.

hele kauhale

to go from house to house, gad.

hele kikī

to go quickly, fast.

hele kūkū

to go by fits and starts, jerk.

hele loa

to go or come far; to go with no hope of returning.

hele lua

to travel together, of two.

hele malihini

to go to a place for the first time or as a stranger.

hele mauna

to travel in the mountains; mountain climber.

hele mua₁

to go ahead.

hele mua₂

da capo (musical term).

hele mua₃

older sibling, descendant of an older sibling, senior.

hele pēlā

get out! Go away!

hele pū

to go with, accompany.

hele wale

to go naked; to go without fixed purpose or far and wide; to go empty-handed; to go without recompense.

hele wiki

quick step, quick time; to go fast.

hele wāwae

to walk, go on foot, hike; pedestrian. (Hawaiian pidgin ‘walk feet’ is probably a loan translation.)

helehele

to cut up, divide; divided; filled with ruts, as a road.

helehelei

redup. and intensifier of helei₁,₂.

helei₁

to straddle.

helei₂

• stretched sideways, as the mouth;   • pulled down, as an eyelid with a finger (these were signs of contempt);   • inflammatory disease of the eye with a drawing down of the lower lid.   See saying, maka helei.

helekika

heretic.

helekū

to walk upright, wade.

helela

herald.

helelei

quick-bearing kind of sweet potato.

heleleʻi

• falling;   • scattered, as rain, tears, grain;   • crumbling, as the earth;   • dilapidated;   • to shed, as a dog's hair.

helemauna

a rare native variety of dry-land taro, with dark purplish petioles and white corms; grown on Hawaiʻi.

helena₁

going.

heleuma

stone anchor, anchor.

heleāwai

to flow like water.

hele₂

• to become ___, get ___;   • like, in a state of, similar   (frequently followed by ā).

hele₃

• when,   • by the time that   (usually followed by ā).

hele₄

following other bases, imparting idea of   • everywhere,   • here and there,   • continuously.

hele₅

a relationship term.

hele₆

• to tie, bind, lash,   • make fast;   • noose, snare.

hele₇

• to divide,   • cut apart.

heliokalope

introduced, sweet-scented heliotrope (Heliotropium arborescens syn. H. corymbosum).

helohelo

rosy, as cheeks.

helo₁

to move back and forth rapidly; jerky pushing or sawing motion.

helo₂

ramrod.

helo₃

red, as ʻōhelo berries; rosy.

helu hanaʻia

composite number.

helu hou

to recount; recount.

helu hoʻolawe

subtrahend.

helu hoʻonui

multiplier.

helu hoʻonui ʻia

multiplicand.

helu hōʻike

abacus.

helu kamaliʻi

children's arithmetic.

helu kanaka

census; to take a census.

helu kaulike

even number.

helu komo

divisor.

helu komoʻia

multiple.

helu kuala

rate of interest.

helu kumu

prime number.

helu lua

double number; dual number, as in grammar.

helu naʻau

mental arithmetic.

helu nui

large number; plural number.

helu nui kaʻawale

exclusive plural, as in Hawaiian grammar.

helu nui pili

inclusive plural, as in Hawaiian grammar.

helu papa

to count or recite in order or consecutively.

helu paʻewa

odd number.

helu poʻokela

perfect number.

helu puka

quotient, in division.

helu pā-

to count by, as helu pālua, to count by twos; helu pākolu, to count by threes; helu pāʻumi, to count by tens.

helu pāloka

to count ballots; election teller.

helu pāʻani

counting game with chants; to play this game.

helu pō

list of the nights of the moon in the old Hawaiian calendar; to count the nights.

helu waiwai

inventory.

helu ʻai

scorekeeper; to keep score.

helu ʻano hui

uneven totals, as ten bushels and three pecks.

helu ʻano like

even numbers and totals, without fractions.

helu ʻokoʻa

whole number.

heluhana

factor, as in arithmetic.

heluhana kumu

prime factor.

heluhelu hoʻoponopono

to proofread.

heluhelu kaʻahele

to take turns reading, read in turn.

heluhelu₂

to scratch.

heluna

number, count, total sum, amount; grade or mark (evaluation).

heluna papa

grade or mark, as in school; number of a grade (class), enumeration.

heluʻekahi

best, "number one."

heluʻekalekia

church census.

helu₂

arithmetic, score, reckoning, account; serial; volume (in a series); numbered.

helu₃

a few.

helu₄

to scratch the earth, as a hen; to dig with the fingers; to paw the earth, as an angry bull.

helu₅

to grumble, list offenses or complaints, especially about lack of gratitude or appreciation.

helē

priest's helper.

hemahema₂

want, need, necessity; lacking, destitute (Oihk. 22.23) , needy.

hemohemo

separation, loosening.

hemolele₁

perfect, faultless, flawless, holy, immaculate, saintly, pure in heart; complete; perfection, virtue, goodness, holiness; angel, person without fault.

hemolele₂

without restraint.

hemoʻē

faint, scanty, feeble, hungry, gasping, as of one near death.

hemuwā

to sound indistinctly, as a voice.

hemū

shoo, be off, scat (perhaps from Eng. move).

hena

buttocks; mons pubis; hollow of the thigh; nakedness.

hene ʻūhā

inner side of the thighs where they join the body on either side of the genitals; groins.

henehene₁

to laugh at, ridicule, mock, tease, snicker, giggle; mockery, laughter.

hene₁

mons pubis.

hene₂

slope, as of a hill.

hene₃

to snicker.

henoheno

lovable, sweet.

heoheo

same as heo₁ and pōheoheo, knob.

heo₁

knob of any kind, as of a door; end of the penis, prepuce.

heo₂

to depart in haste.

heo₃

proud, haughty (less common than haʻaheo).

hepa

• idiot, moron, imbecile; feebleminded, moronic.   • partial paralysis of the vocal organs causing indistinct articulation;

hepekoma

week; seven years.

heu aniani

fine bits of broken or ground glass; mercury on glass made into a mirror.

heumiki

beautiful, comely, attractive.

heu₁

• down or fine hair, fuzz, fuzzy, downy;   • loose fibers on certain fruits or leaves, hairlike growths or spines on sugar cane stalks or cactus;   • quicksilver or mercury on back of a mirror,   • to begin to grow, as a youth's beard or pubic hair;   • to sprout, of seedlings.

hewahewa₁

a great many, very, vast, in great quantities.

hewahewa₂

crazy, demented, wild, aimless.

hewahewa₃

to fail to recognize.

hewa₂

Is it wrong to? Then why not?

hewa₃

offended, annoyed.

hewa₄

to the point of satiety; to be in great quantities; to do excessively.

heʻa

stained red, inflamed, reddened; flattened and destroyed, as by lava; blood red; a blood sacrifice, as hog or man.

heʻaheʻa

to imprint with spots, stains; smeared, as with red earth.

heʻe hōlua

• to ride a hōlua sled; the hōlua course;   • fig.., an expression of pride in descent from certain chiefly families at Waipiʻo, Hawaiʻi, who were famous for their skill with the hōlua sled.

heʻe koko

flow of blood, hemorrhage, menstrual flow.

heʻe mākoko

a variety of large red octopus (Octopus ornatus); it was rarely eaten because of its bitter taste, but was sometimes used as medicine.

heʻe mākole

squid beginning to decompose, with a pinkish color and a bad odor, liked by some.

heʻe nehu

season when nehu fish run; to run in schools, of nehu.

heʻe pali

tiny, young octopus that clings to rocks along sea pools, especially in certain seasons.

heʻe pulu

octopus slightly decomposed.

heʻe puʻewai

to surf toward the mouth of a stream or up the stream.

heʻe pālaha

an octopus settled on the ocean floor with tentacles spread out.

heʻe pū loa

a long-headed, long-tentacled octopus (Octopus ornatus), very tough, tenderized only by much pounding; now called the night octopus. lit., long-headed octopus.

heʻe umauma

body surfing; to body surf.

heʻeheʻe₁

avalanche.

heʻeheʻe₂

breast disease, with caking and great pain during nursing.

heʻewale

miscarriage; to have a miscarriage.

heʻe₂

see also. heʻe₆ 'to flee'   • to slide, slip,   • surf,

heʻe₃

• to melt, soften;   • flow,   • drip,   • to skim, as milk.

heʻe₄

to hang down, as fruit; to sag; to bear breadfruit.

heʻe₅

line that supports the mast, stay.

heʻe₆

flee.

heʻupueo₁

a reedlike grass, a bent grass (Agrostis avenacea, synonyms A. retrofracta and Calamagrostis forsteri), originally found in Australia, and now found through Polynesia; Panicum heupueo on Niʻihau. lit., owl hoot.

heʻupueo₂

probable Hawaiian name for pili uka, a grass.

heʻu₁

hoot, as of an owl; to croak, hoot.

heʻu₂

deep-throated sounds made in Hawaiian chants and prayers; to chant thus.

Hik

abbreviation for hikina, east.

Hikaua

name of an unknown person, used something like so-and-so, usually followed by mā.

Hikauhi

name of the wife of the famous legendary navigator, Pākaʻa and of the coastal area, Molokaʻi, where she lived. She was lost during labor pains and her husband searched vainly for her, hence the saying applied to fruitless endeavors, Hikauhi i Kaumanamana, Hikauhi is at Kaumanamana [another place on Molokaʻi]. [cf slightly different explanation at (ON 1162)]

Hikianalia

name of a star, described as medium-bright and near the equator; visible from April to September; used as a guide to mariner and fisherman.

Hikikauelia

name of a star; according to some, Sirius.

Hikikauelono

name of a star.

Hikikaulonomeha

the star Sirius.

Hikiliimakaounulau

star name, perhaps morning star.

Hikina

Orient.

Hikina₂

Orient.

Hikipua₂

wind name associated with Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

Hikiʻaumoana

Kauaʻi name for the star Hikianalia.

Hiku₂

generally known as Hiku, this hero was the son of Kū-ʻōhiʻa-laka and the goddess Hina. lit., Hiku in the forest.

Hilina Ehu

name of a star and of a Hawaiian month (same as Māhoe Mua: see month).

Hilina Mā

name of the eleventh month (Molokaʻi) eighth (Kauaʻi), or tenth (Alexander).

Hilo₂

first night of the new moon. See (Malo 35).

Hilo₃

name of a famous Polynesian navigator for whom the city and district may have been named. see sayings, Hilo (Eng.-Hawaiian)

Himela

Himalayas. See song, hene₂.

Hinaiaʻeleʻele

a Hawaiian star and month name.

Hinaikamalama

vague accounts (HM 214) mention this goddess as being born in the undersea land Kahikihonuakele (wet land Kahiki), and as floating on the sea and becoming a gourd bailer—Hinaikekā (Hina in the bailer) (KL. 235). In some stories she makes tapa in the moon (HM 220). She was also called Hinahanaakamalama (Hina foster-child of the moon), the name of Queen Emma's home in Nuʻu-anu Valley, Honolulu. lit., Hina in the moon. see ʻAikanaka₃; Hema.

Hinaikekā

goddess of canoe bailers, sometimes called the sister of Hina who was the mother of Māui (HM 219), or equated with the mother of corals, Hinaʻōpūhalakoʻa. Most commonly she took the form of a gourd canoe bailer (kā); Wākea found her floating and took her into his canoe. lit., Hina (in) the bailer. see Hinaikamalama; Pīmoe.

Hinalani

name of a star.

Hinaliʻi₁

name of a chief in whose time occurred a famous deluge called kai a ka Hinaliʻi; the Biblical flood (Kin. 6.17) . See saying ʻiliki₁.

Hinaliʻi₂

name of a star that appears in the month of Hilinehu and follows in its course the star Polowehilani [Polo-Wehi-Lani].

Hinamālailena

name of a star, said to be the tutelary star of Hāna, Maui.

Hinapukuʻai

goddess of food plants (HM 69), also known as Hinahele, and sister of Hinapukuiʻa. She assumed the form of Lea, and as an ʻelepaio flycatcher alighted on trees that canoe makers wanted to cut; if she pecked a tree, canoe makers knew that it was insect ridden and not suitable for a canoe. The spot where she landed on a felled tree was to be the prow; she then ran toward the stern. lit., Hina gathering vegetable food.

Hinaʻaikamalama₂

name of a legendary goddess.

Hinaʻōpūhalakoʻa

goddess of corals and spiny creatures of the sea, appearing as a woman and as a coral reef. From her shells Māui made his famous hook for drawing the islands together. lit., Hina stomach passing coral.

Hina₁₀

a goddess associated with Kū (upright), with whom she had incestuous relations. Hina in this instance means 'prostrate.' When gathering medicine with their left hands, people prayed to Hina for success. See Hikuikanahele, Kū.

Hina₆

a goddess... Probably the most widely known goddess or demigoddess of Polynesia, frequently connected with the moon. Four well-known Hawaiian Hinas follow.

Hina₇

wife of Akalana and mother of Māui. see Kaʻalaenuiahina and (HM 220).

Hina₈

mother of Kamapuaʻa by Kahikiʻula and referred to in chants by her mother, Kamaunuaniho, in order to save Kamapuaʻa in time of peril (FS 196-203). When she failed to recognize her pig son, Kamapuaʻa, in human form, she exposed herself in humiliation (FS 242-249).

Hina₉

a wife of Wākea and the mother of the island of Molokaʻi, celebrated in the song Molokaʻi Nui a Hina, Great Molokaʻi Child of Hina.

Hinekū

Hindu.

Hipakāne

the star Aries.

Hiʻiakaikapoliopele

Pele's favorite younger sister born from the mouth of Haumea rather than from the bosom, as were the many other Hiʻiaka sisters ((Westervelt p. 69), says there may have been forty sisters). Born as an egg, she was carried under Pele's bosom until she became a young beauty. She is the heroine of the epic concerning her trip from Kīlauea Volcano to Kauaʻi to find and fetch Pele's dream lover, Lohi'au; on her long and dangerous journey she transformed many evil moʻo into stones which are still visible (see PH). One of her forms was the palaʻā lace fern used to treat diseases and one of the first plants to grow on new lava. As the physician of the Pele family, she resuscitated Lohiʻau. She instituted the eating of fish from head to tail. She was worshiped by hula dancers. lit., Hiʻiaka in the bosom of Pele.

Hiʻiaka₁

first part of the names of the twelve younger sisters of the goddess Pele; the youngest and most famous was Hiʻiakaikapoliopele. see (PH).

Hiʻikua₃

name of a star said to rise on the night of Hoaka and to vanish on the night of Muku in the month of Welehu.

Hiʻilawe₂

name of the highest waterfall in Hawaiʻi, and one of the highest in the world, with a vertical drop of about 300 m, at Waipiʻo Valley, Hawaiʻi. see (EM 49), for a famous song.

Hiʻilei

name of a star that rises and vanishes at the same times as Hiʻikua.

hia

desire, delight.

hiaala

same as the more common hiaʻā, indisposed to sleep, wakeful, sleepless...

hiahia₁

faded, gray, hazy.

hialaʻai₂

to eat heartily.

hialele

restless, furtive.

hialoa

well trained, skilled.

hiamoe iki

a little sleep, nap; to take a nap.

hiamoe loa

to oversleep, sleep deeply; death, eternal sleep.

hiamoe paʻa loa

fast asleep; deep sleep.

hiana

depression or hole, as under water.

hiapaʻiʻole

foremost, expert.

hiaʻai

pleased with, delighted with; delightful, pleasing.

hiaʻaiʻono

• greatly pleased or delighted, most delightful;   • appetite for delicious food.

hiaʻā

indisposed to sleep, wakeful, sleepless; insomnia.

hie

attractive, distinguished, dignified, noble, becoming.

hiehie

redup. of hie, attractive, distinguished, dignified, noble, becoming...; superb.

hiena₁

kind of soft porous stone used to smooth and polish utensils; it is harder than the ʻana stone, which is used on wood.

hiena₂

hyena.

hiena₃

speckled bird of prey. (And. Ier 12:9).

hihi manō

net made of strong cord used for shark fishing.

hihi pūnāwele

spider web, cobweb.

hihia kalaima

criminal case.

hihia waiwai

civil case.

hihialou

a plant with small yellow flowers.

hihiawai

the swamp fern (Ceratopteris thalictroides), an edible, somewhat succulent fern, distributed through the tropics. It grows in mud or water, as around taro patches, in tufts about 30 cm high. The fronds are triangular and are finely divided into long, narrow parts. Young fronds are eaten with fresh-water shrimps.

hihia₁

• entangled, interwoven, involved, rank, snarled, snarl, entanglement, kink,   • perplexed, hampered, obscure and difficult to understand (Kep. 167);   • thicket,   • difficulty, problem, trouble.

hihia₂

lawsuit or case before the court, trial.

hihihiki

to come or go, of many people.

hihihina

redup. and intensifier of hina, to fall.

hihikolo₂

name of a legendary koa tree on Kauaʻi that was said to have no trunk.

hihina₂

entanglement, spreading.

hihio

soft whistling sound, gust or draft of wind; to whistle.

hihipeʻa

• jungle, tangled thicket;   • entangled.   • fig., bewilderment, grief.

hihiu₁

wild, untamed.

hihiu₂

rare, uncommon.

hihiʻo

• a dream or vision (Kin. 15–1) , as while dozing; to dream while dozing;   • to whistle or sough, as wind.

hihi₁

• to entangle, intertwine, intermingle; entanglement,   • creep,   • spread,   • web,   • snare.

hihi₂

a large-meshed fish net.

hikaʻa

to tilt back, as the head.

hiki kū

portion of the sky immediately above the horizon.

hiki mua

to come ahead or beforehand.

hiki nō

all right, O.K., certainly, surely, it can be done.

hiki wale

to come accidentally, alone, or without any particular purpose or reason.

hiki ʻole

impossible, unable, can't or unable to do; inability, regrets.

hiki-

names of cardinal directions, stars, and portions of the sky, perhaps because of movement (hiki₃) of the sun. see below.

hikia

to aim carefully, as with stone, spear, or gun.

hikialoalo

zenith.

hikianakopili

spittle passed from a dying master, according to the belief that his knowledge was thereby handed on.

hikieʻe

large Hawaiian couch. lit., possible to mount.

hikihiki₁

to come repeatedly, as voices.

hikihiki₂

to fetch repeatedly or a little at a time.

hikikiʻi₁

to lean back, relax.

hikikiʻi₂

to spread, as mist; to rain, especially a slanting rain.

hikilele

to jump or start from shock, to gasp; shock, perturbation.

hikimoe

west. lit., come to rest.

hikimua

progress, advance; to progress.

hikina hema

southeast.

hikina ʻākau

northeast.

hikina₃

coming, advent.

hikipua₁

to force one's way, as through a crowd or undergrowth.

hikiwale

easy.

hikiwawe

quickly, speedily, suddenly, prompt, quickly done; possible to do quickly; doubletime (military command).

hikiʻalamea

probably the same as ikiʻalamea, a disease.

hiki₄

next.

hiki₅

to fetch, carry back and forth (less used than lawe).

hikoni

tattoo brand on the forehead of a kauā outcast, or on the forehead of the caught seducer of a high chief's wife. (see (Malo 70, figure 1))

hikua

to throw aimlessly, carelessly.

hikuhiku₁

many.

hikuhiku₂

confusion of sounds.

hilala

to reel, lean or tilt sideways.

hilaʻi

to exalt, praise.

hila₂

heel.

hila₃

hill.

hili hewa

tangled, confused; entanglement, confusion; to become entangled; to trip or fall.

hili hā

four-strand braid; to braid thus.

hili kolu

a three-strand braid; to braid such.

hili pāhā

four-strand braid; to braid such.

hili pākolu

three-strand braid; to braid such.

hili pō

to wander or grope aimlessly in the dark.

hiliau

in devious ways; to ramble; be indirect.

hilihili₂

dark red or brown (less dark than hili₄).

hilihua

to grope here and there.

hilikau

mixed, snarled, entangled; to mix, snarl.

hilikua

to lash against, whip.

hilikī

to hit carelessly, at random.

hilinaʻi

• to believe, trust; trust, confidence.   • to lean on, rely on;

hiliu

sound or call of a wind instrument, as the conch shell.

hiliʻōʻū₁

square braid of eight or sixteen strands.

hiliʻōʻū₂

ailment of the bowels or stomach, accompanied by gas pains.

hili₁

to braid or plait, as a lei or candlenuts; a braid, plaiting, string.

hili₂

to turn aside, deviate, miss the way, wander, stray.

hili₃

to whip, smite, thrash, switch, bat; batter, as in baseball; stroke, as in fighting.

hili₄

bark used in dyeing, as hili kukui, hili kōlea, hili noni; the dark-brown dye made from this bark; a tapa dyed with hili; to dye with hili.

hilohilo₁

to lengthen a speech or story by inserting new matter; to embroider or spin out a tale.

hilohilo₂

sweet juice of ti root.

hilo₁

to twist, braid, spin; twisted, braided; threadlike; faint streak of light.

hilo₅

gonorrhea; a running sore.

hilo₆

a variety of sweet potato.

hiluhilu

elegant, beautiful.

hilu₁

various species of reef fishes of the genus Coris. The name hilu may be qualified by the terms ʻeleʻele, lauwili, melemele, moelola, pano (probably same as uli), pāniʻo, pilikoʻa (Paracirrhites forsteri, hawkfish), ʻula, uli. See saying, noʻenoʻe₂.

hilu₂

quiet, reserved, well-behaved, decorous, unobtrusive, easygoing; such a person (a child born to a woman who craved hilu fish during her pregnancy was thought to be of this desirable type).

hilu₃

strange.

hina leʻa

to blow favorably, as wind.

hina moe

to lie down to sleep; to lie low, as of smoke; to drop dead.

hina pū

to fall together, of several; to topple.

hina ulu

to begin to gray, of hair.

hinahina kahakai

a native Hawaiian plant of the water-leaf family (Nama sandwicensis). Niʻihau. cf. (Neal 712).

hinahina kula

an unidentified plant.

hinahina kū loa

an unidentified plant.

hinahina ʻaʻala

dusty miller (Artemisia stelleriana), a perennial herb in the daisy family, from northeastern Asia and eastern North America. The leaves and stems have a white, velvety covering and are aromatic.

hinahina₁

the silversword (Argyroxiphium sandwicense).

hinahina₂

florida moss (Tillandsia usneoides), an air plant, growing on tree branches and hanging baskets, forming masses of gray, thread-like stems and leaves. It is often substituted for the heliotrope (below) as the flower of Kahoʻolawe, and so called. Also ʻāhinahina and ʻumiʻumi o Dole, Dole's Whiskers.

hinahina₃

native heliotrope (Heliotropium anomalum var. argenteum), a low, spreading beach plant, with narrow, clustered, silvery leaves and small, white, fragrant flowers. As designated by the Territorial legislature in 1923, it represents Kahoʻolawe in the leis of the islands; it is used for tea and medicine. Called nohonoho puʻuone on Niʻihau.

hinahina₄

native geraniums (Geranium cuneatum var. tridens and other native silvery geraniums), shrubs or small trees of the high mountains, with ovate, toothed leaves and red or white flowers.

hinahina₅

native artemisia (Artemisia australis).

hinahina₇

a variety of sugar cane, gray-green with a rosy flush, the whole covered with a wax bloom; pith dark brown; looks like lahi₂.

hinakea

type of stone laid near the coral pile (umu) to attract fish; it was flat on one side and rounded on the other, and was believed to attract manini and young of other fish which resembled it in color. lit., white gray.

hinakā

handkerchief.

hinakā paʻeke

pocket handkerchief. Niʻihau.

hinakā ʻāʻī

neckerchief. Niʻihau.

hinana

young of ʻoʻopu, a fish, formerly caught in nets and greatly relished. See saying, pā ʻili.

hinao

type of pāʻū (no data).

hinapē

too weak to stand alone.

hinapū₁

a rare native variety of upland taro, with green leaves, reddish leaf juncture (piko), dark-green petioles, and white corm. Perhaps same as lauloa uliuli.

hinapū₂

a variety of sweet potato.

hinaʻula

a kind of seaweed.

hina₂

italics, probably so called because italics slant.

hina₃

to blow in a straight course, of wind.

hina₄

gray- or white-haired; gray.

hina₅

hin (a Hebrew measure).

hine

gaudy, showy, splendid.

hinehineʻula

a moss listed by (Rock).

hini

weak, feeble, delicate.

hinihini konouli

a land shell (Succinea casta orophila).

hinihini kua mauna

a land shell (Succinea casta).

hinihini ʻula

air upland moss (no data).

hinihini₁

indistinct, faint, as a voice.

hinihini₂

a variety of land shell. see hinihini konouli, hinihini kua mauna.

hinihini₃

cooked greens, as of ʻāheahea, pōpolo, pakai.

hinu

• oil, grease, ointment;   • oily, greasy;   • smooth and polished, lustrous, slick.

hinuhinu₁

intensification of hinu, smooth and polished, lustrous, slick   • bright, shining, lustrous,   • glossy,   • glittering, as of polished stones or shells;   • splendid; splendor.

hinupuaʻa₁

same as maiʻa ʻeleʻele or ʻeleʻele, a mountain banana with shiny black trunk.

hinupuaʻa₂

a native variety of upland taro.

hiohio haole

to jibber jabber in the white man's language, so called because English seemed full of whistling (hiohio), sibilant sounds.

hiohio₁

to whistle softly; to blow softly, draw in the breath, as of one eating hot food.

hiohio₂

gibberish; to jabber.

hiohio₃

lure for trolling, said to be named for its whistling sound tripping over the water.

hiolo

• to tumble down,   • collapse;   • falling.   • landslide,   • overthrown,   • defeated;

hiona

leaning, slanting.

hio₁

a sweep or gust of wind; to blow in gusts.

hio₂

inside corners of a house, said to be so named because ghosts came whistling in at the corners.

hio₃

to break wind silently.

hipa keiki

lamb.

hipa kāne

ram. lit., male sheep.

hipahipa₂

hip, hip, hurrah! Cheers! (Eng., hip.)

hipa₂

sheep.

hipopokamu

hippopotamus.

hipū

resting place, as in the shelter of a tree or cave.

hiua₁

a game something like checkers, played on a board with five squares.

hiua₂

menstrual.

hiuhiu

• redup. of hiu₁, to throw or fling violently...;   • redup. of hiu₂, to elevate, hoist, as by block and tackle...;   • to pelt repeatedly;   • to tug, lift again and again...

hiu₁

• to throw or fling violently;   • to haul energetically with ropes;   • to get into action, as play or sport;   • to pursue with energy, as love-making.

hiu₂

to elevate, hoist, as by block and tackle.

hiu₃

stones used in games of kōnane, kinipeki, and āneo, usually polished and flat.

hiwa lani

esteemed chief; beloved child or favorite; royal favorite.

hiwa paʻa

coal-black, entirely black, solid-black. (A puaʻa hiwa might have a few white hairs, but none at all were on a puaʻa hiwa paʻa.)

hiwahiwa

precious, beloved, esteemed, petted, darling, indulged; favorite.

hiwakea

an all-black pig with white hoofs and white tips of tail, ears, and nose.

hiwa₁

entirely black, as of pigs offered to the gods, a desirable blackness contrasting with uli and ʻeleʻele, which have pejorative connotations. see polohiwa and its associations with the god Kāne₂.

hiwa₂

choice.

hiwa₃

a term qualifying coconuts and kava.

hiwihiwi

redup. and intensifier of hiwi₁.

hiwi₁

skinny, bony, thin, angular.

hiwi₂

sharp ridge of a mountain. cf. more common kuahiwi.

hiō

to fall sideways, lean, slant, slope, incline, leaning, oblique, diagonal.

hiōhiō

to lean every which way.

hiʻa kā ʻupena

shuttle or needle for making a fish net, sometimes of bone.

hiʻali₁

food offering to the gods.

hiʻali₂

to stir, as a fire; to signal with the hands.

hiʻaloa₁

bald temple.

hiʻanakiʻu

stems by which tubers are attached to vines.

hiʻa₁

to make fire with the fire-plow; the act of making fire thus.

hiʻa₂

shuttle or needle for making nets; to knot or fasten the meshes of a net; to form a network; to bind, as house rafters.

hiʻi kala

hook used for kala, a fish, and baited with kala, a seaweed.

hiʻiaka₂

a rare variety of taro with bronze-red leaf and stem, used in medicine.

hiʻialo₁

carried in the arms, as a beloved child.

hiʻialo₂

nearby, in front.

hiʻikua₁

carried on the shoulders, as a beloved child.

hiʻikua₂

in back, far.

hiʻilani

to nurse or care for, as an infant; to admire, exalt, praise, extol in poetry; praise.

hiʻilawe₁

to lift, carry.

hiʻilei

to carry, tend, and cherish a beloved child (lei ).

hiʻimoʻopuna

to bear a grandchild in the arms; to be a grandparent (a term of pride and affection).

hiʻipaka

to care for a child; to instruct a child.

hiʻipoi

to tend, feed, cherish, as a child.

hiʻi₁

• to hold or carry in the arms, as a child;   • to bear;   • to nurse or tend a child (Hawaiians did not carry children unrelated to them, and commoners did not touch a chief's child; carrying a child symbolized love, kinship, and affection). cf:     Hiʻiaka, first part of the names of the twelve younger sisters of the goddess Pele...     hiʻialo, carried in the arms, as a beloved child...     hiʻikua, carried on the shoulders, as a beloved child...     hiʻilani, to nurse or care for, as an infant...     hiʻilei, to carry, tend, and cherish a beloved child...     hiʻimoʻopuna, to bear a grandchild in the arms...     hiʻipaka, to care for a child...     hiʻipoi, to tend, feed, cherish, as a child...

hiʻi₃

tall, as cliff or mountain.

hiʻohiʻo

ruddy, bright red.

hiʻohiʻolani

to level off, as a flower bed.

hiʻohiʻona₁

• features, as of a face or landscape;   • sight, aspect.

hiʻolani

to sleep, lie at ease, lounge, relax (this word sometimes replaces moe in poetry because moe suggests the sleep of death).

hiʻona

general appearance, as of a person; impression.

hiʻu kahi

a single fishtail. fig., limited knowledge.

hiʻu waʻa

canoe stern. fig., a straight tree suitable for a canoe.

hiʻuhiʻu

last bits of odds and ends; remnants of matting strips that must be cut off after plaiting is finished; ends of knots in plaiting; wispy end of a braid.

hiʻuiʻa

fishtail fern (Nephrolepis biserrata cv. furcans), a kind of sword fern, with forked divisions (pinnae). In Kaʻū, leis are made by combining pinnae of this fern (or whole frond) with flower sprays of wāpine (lemon verbena).

hiʻukole

a fresh-water ʻoʻopu fish with a pinkish tail (hiʻu kole). It is taboo to some because it is believed related to the moʻo lizard gods.

hiʻukā

whole fish used as bait for trolling.

hiʻuwai₁

water purification festivities on the second night of the month of Welehu (near the end of the year). The people bathed and frolicked in the sea or stream after midnight, then put on their finest tapa and ornaments for feasting and games.

hiʻuwai₂

water-tailed," said of one allegedly descended from a shark.

hiʻuwīwī

a kind of ʻahi, a tuna fish. lit., thin tail.

hiʻu₁

hind part or tail section of a fish, considered less delicious than the head or front section. See saying, pau₁.

hiʻu₂

caudal fin.

hiʻu₃

to break wind.

hiʻu₄

to motion with the hands in a way destructive to the addressee.

Hoaka₂

second day of the month.

Hokenekoka

Hottentot.

Hoku

night of the full moon. When this moon set before daylight it was called Hoku Palemo, Hoku that slips away. When it set after daylight it was called Hoku Ili grounded Hoku.

Holoholopīnaʻau

name of a star, perhaps Mars.

Holoholoʻā

star name (no data).

Holoikahiki

name of a legendary star (Kep. 77) that guided Hawaiʻinui on his return to Kahikihonuakele after discovering Hawaiʻi.

Holopoʻopoʻo

wind famous at Waipiʻo, Hawaiʻi. lit., running in the hollows.

Holu₂

name of a star.

Holu₃

name of a fish god.

Home Rula Republalika

semi-weekly newspaper in Hawaiian and Eng. published 1901–02.

Hono-

bay, gulch, valley (as a part of place names such as Honolulu, Honokōhau, Honoliʻi, Honomanu; also in the poetic phrase nā Honō a Piʻilani, the bays beginning with Hono- of Piʻilani [a chief who ruled the bays on Maui, Molokaʻi, and Lānaʻi that were visible from Lahaina]. Hana- occurs similarly as in Hanalei and Hanauma.

Honokaona

Hong Kong.

Honokaʻa₂

town name, Hāmākua, Hawaiʻi.

Honolulu

name of the capital city in the Hawaiian Islands lit., sheltered bay.

Hoʻoheu₂

name of a strong wind threatening to be a gale

Hoʻohokuikalani

the daughter of Wākea and Papa, the ancestors of the Hawaiians. Wākea instituted taboo nights so that he might sleep with Hoʻohoku. The root -hoku may be cognate with Tahitian hotu, to produce fruit, and Tongan fotu, to appear; if so, the translation would be 'to bear fruit in the heavens'.

Hoʻolapa₂

wind famous at Kaʻū.

Hoʻoleia₁

name of a star

Hoʻolua₃

name of a strong, north wind associated with Makaiwa, Kauaʻi; Hāna, Maui; and Hālawa, Molokaʻi. At Hālawa the name may be qualified by Iho, Kaʻi, Kele, Pehu, Wahakole

Hoʻomālama₂

star name

Hoʻāo₂

night of the day called Huna₃, eleventh night of the month, when the hoʻāo nuptials took place.

ho-

marker of the caus/sim.; same as hoʻo-, but commonly found before words beginning with a glottal stop followed by a long vowel, as ʻāpuka, hoʻāpuka.

hoa aliʻi

companion of a chief, fellow chief, chief descended from the god Kāne. fig., the gods.

hoa hana

fellow worker, colleague, partner, accomplice.

hoa hanauna

relative of one's own generation.

hoa haumana

schoolmate.

hoa hele

traveling companion, fellow traveler. (In (Ios. 14.8) "kou hoa hele" seems to be the Hawaiian translation of "my brethren.")

hoa holomoku

shipmate.

hoa kamaliʻi

childhood playmate.

hoa kanaka

fellow man.

hoa kaua

• fellow soldier,   • enemy.

hoa kua

companion of a god, godly companion.

hoa kākau

coauthor, writing associate.

hoa kākoʻo

ally, supporter.

hoa kāunu

lover, delightful companion.

hoa kūkā

consultant, counselor, adviser, one with whom one confers and deliberates.

hoa lawe pū

sharer, partner.

hoa lawehana

fellow laborer or worker, helper.

hoa like₁

companion or contemporary of equal status.

hoa liʻi

same as hoa aliʻi, companion of a chief, fellow chief, chief descended from the god Kāne...

hoa loaʻa

fellow sharer, receiver, partaker.

hoa luhi

fellow worker, especially one helping to rear a child.

hoa lumi

roommate.

hoa makaʻāinana

fellow citizen.

hoa moe

sleeping companion, bedfellow.

hoa paio

opponent, antagonist, adversary, enemy, rival.

hoa paʻahana

fellow worker.

hoa pili

close, intimate, or personal friend.

hoa pāonioni

enemy, contestant, rival.

hoa pāʻani

playmate.

hoa una

one accompanying a messenger.

hoa waʻa₁

canoe companion, mate.

hoa waʻa₂

canoe rigging, tackle.

hoa ʻai

eating or dinner companion.

hoa ʻinau

sweetheart, mate, spouse.

hoa ʻōlelo

companion with whom one converses or consults.

hoahoa

a rounded tapa beater (also called hohoa, pepehi); rapid beating, striking, as of tapa or pandanus leaves; a stick beater for washing clothes. fig., bad-tempered.

hoahoaka₂

comb of a rooster.

hoahui

associate.

hoai

joining, suture, joint. cf. hoa₂, and below.

hoai kala

lambdoidal suture.

hoai kaupaku

sagital suture.

hoai maha

temporal suture.

hoai manawa

coronal suture.

hoaka kākala

a disease (ruptured appendix?).

hoaka ʻīpuka hale

ruptured appendix, appendicitis (not certain).

hoakakala₁

bracelet of tusks of hog or dog.

hoakakeʻa

arch over a door, lintel.

hoaka₁

• crescent;   • arch, as over door of ancient house (Kep. 101);   • crescent-shaped design at base of temple drum;   • crest, as on a helmet.

hoaka₃

• brightness; shining, glittering, to glitter, shine,   • splendid;   • flash as lightning,   • become daylight;   • to flame.   • fig., glory.

hoaka₄

• to cast a shadow;   • to brandish, as a spear (2-Sam. 23.18) ,   • to drive away, ward off, frighten.

hoaka₅

to open, as the mouth.

hoaka₆

spirit, apparition, ghost.

hoaka₇

disease of the abdomen, perhaps appendicitis, rupture (followed by a qualifier). see hoaka ʻīpuka hale, hoaka kākala. Other qualifiers reported are hāwele, kū, kū kahi, kū lua.

hoalauna

neighbor, close associate or friend.

hoana kaʻa

grindstone, rolling grindstone.

hoana₁

hone, whetstone, grindstone; to rub, grind.

hoana₂

to brandish, as a whip; to threaten.

hoana₃

joining, joint, binding.

hoaʻāina

tenant, caretaker, as on a kuleana.

hoa₂

• to tie, bind,   • secure,   • rig; rigging,   • lashing.

hoa₃

to strike with a stick or club; to club; a club.

hoe kala

a paddle with a blade narrower than the hoe nanue. lit., pointed paddle.

hoe nenue

a type of paddle named for nenue fish, with broad and round blade.

hoe uli

steering paddle or oar, rudder, helm.

hoea

let's get started, go ahead.

hoeamāui

probably same as ʻēkaha ʻula fern, but according to some it is Elaphoglossum pellucidum, a smaller Elaphoglossum than the ʻēkaha ʻula. lit., Māui's paddle.

hoehaʻa

• same as ʻoehaʻa     • crooked, distorted, deformed;     • to walk in an ungainly manner, swaying the shoulders;     • to waddle.     • fig., deceitful; trick.   • fig., unreliable, unstable.

hoehoene₂

to pierce the ear lobes with acid.

hoehoene₃

poor, destitute, sick.

hoehoepākea

a name for a Niʻihau pāwehe design in plaiting.

hoehoe₁

paddling back and forth.

hoehoe₂

a plaintive prolonged sound, as of the nose flute.

hoehoe₃

shoulder blade (used after iwi).

hoelo

to stir, poke, as a fire.

hoena

paddling.

hoene₁

a soft sweet sound, as of song; to sound softly, rustle, sough, as the wind

hoene₃

to use a douche or enema; enema, medicine, injection, abortion.

hoe₂

to draw in the breath and expel it with a whistling sound, as when tired.

hoe₃

a bird reported by (Kep) as being the size of the ʻōʻō and black and gray.

hohiu

a native fern (Dryopteris glabra) with rather finely divided fronds.

hohoiea

wheezy. cf. (For. 4:169).

hohola

to spread out, unfold, unfurl, as tapa, mats, clouds, wings; to extend, stretch, diffuse.

hohonu

deep, profound; depth, soundings.

hohopa

tall, thin.

hohō

to snore, snort, bray, heehaw, splash, gurgle, breathe hard, draw in mucus.

hoi kuahiwi

a native vine (Smilax sandwicensis), growing wild in the mountains; the leaves are heart-shaped, shiny, with longitudinal veins, much like the hoi but bearing tendrils; the roots are tuberous and not palatable.

hoiʻa

Niʻihau name of a sea tern.

hoi₁

bitter yam (Dioscorea bulbifera, synonym D. sativa), a vine with cylindrical stem, heart-shaped leaves, small tuberous root, round aerial tubers. The tubers, used only in times of famine, need long washing to make them fit to eat. Called piʻoi on Kauaʻi. (HP 167), (Neal 230).

hokahokai₂

to mix, as ingredients.

hokaʻawa

to strain kava; a kava strainer.

hoka₂

to squeeze, strain, as kava or liquids through fibers.

hoki₁

mule, ass.

hoki₂

barren, of a woman. (modern).

hoko₁

fat, fleshy, as thighs, buttocks, or calf.

hoko₂

to strike, threaten.

hokua₁

• nape of the neck, shoulders (Puk. 12.34) ;   • main stem of a vine (Kep. 157).

hokua₂

tip of high waves, crest.

hokua₃

to lift up.

hola₂

to drug fish with ʻauhuhu (a small legume with pods used for poisoning fish). Niʻihau.

hola₃

groin (rare, in chants, (Kam. 64.124))

hole iʻe

to groove or carve figures in the iʻe tapa beater.

hole ʻie

to strip aerial roots of the ʻieʻie vine for baskets or plaiting.

holehole iwi

to strip flesh from the bones, as formerly done with the dead, fig., to tell evil of one's relatives or reveal confidences.

holehole₂

to mix different feathers in a lei ; mingling, as feathers.

holelola

Holy Roller [disparaging and offensive term for a member of a Pentacostal sect].

hole₁

• to skin,   • peel,   • file, rasp,   • make a groove;   • to strip, as sugar-cane leaves from the stalk;   • furrow.

hole₂

to squirm, twist, turn, fidget; to caress passionately.

holili₁

weak, spindly, puny.

holili₂

rippled surface of the sea, as caused by fish; undulation or vibration ...

holina

immature and inferior, as breadfruit falling prematurely.

holi₁

to sprout, as plants or a youth's beard.

holi₂

to ask indirectly, seek to open conversation, search.

holo ahi

steam-driven.

holo hele

to run to and fro; bustle.

holo hōlua

course for hōlua, sledding.

holo i mua

to progress, advance, surpass, go ahead; progress, advancement; successful.

holo kaʻa

to ride in a car or carriage.

holo kūkū

to trot, as a horse; to jounce.

holo leʻa

to succeed, fare well; successful.

holo lio

to ride horseback; horseman, rider.

holo lua

• to run, sail, move in two ways.   • fig., hypocrite; deceitful.

holo manaʻo

to decide, determine.

holo paheʻe

to skate, skid.

holo pono

to pass off successfully, succeed, accomplish; successful; success.

holo puni

to sail or travel around, circumnavigate; everywhere.

holo pupule

reckless, mad running; to tear madly, as a frightened horse; to speed recklessly, as an auto.

holo pāʻū

to ride horseback while wearing the sarong known as pāʻū; a pāʻū rider.

holo ʻai

food bundle, especially ti-leaf bundle of hard poi.

holo ʻino

to speed recklessly.

holo ʻāʻā

to run about in a panic...

holoaʻa₂

sheath covering coconut flowers; spathe.

holohau

to ice skate, ski. lit., ice run.

holohiʻa

to dart this way and that, as children at play; to veer at an angle, miss.

holoholo kaʻa

to go for a drive or ride. see song in (EM 53–4).

holoholo lio

to go horseback riding.

holoholokake

blown, as by wind.

holoholomoku

ocean trip, cruise.

holoholona hiamoe

sloth, sleeping animal.

holoholona lele

insect, flying creature.

holoholona ʻai weuweu

herbivorous animal.

holoholona ʻai ʻiʻo

carnivorous animal.

holoholona₂

a trip, excursion, ride.

holoholoʻōlelo

to gossip, slander, bear tales, tattle; tattler, talebearer, spreader of gossip.

holoholo₂

basting; to baste, sew.

holoholo₃

a net into which fish run (holoholo) after being frightened; to fish with this net.

holoholo₄

an old Hawaiian game of kicking a ball to which feathers were attached; to play this game.

holohuʻa

to glance off, fly off obliquely, miss, fail to hit the mark. lit., run edge.

holoi lauoho

shampoo.

holokahiki

sailor; to sail to foreign lands.

holokai

seaman, seafarer; to sail on the sea; sea voyage or cruise.

holokake

not secure, loose, not tight.

holokia

to dart, as a bird.

holokikī

to run or sail swiftly; headlong.

holokuku

upper edge of an ʻōpelu fish net.

holokē

to run here and there; helter-skelter.

holokū kua poepoe

a round-yoked holokū.

holokū₁

a loose, seamed dress with a yoke and usually with a train, patterned after the Mother Hubbards of the missionaries. cf. the muʻumuʻu, which formerly was not yoked and has no train or seam. Both garments are frequently made of gaily patterned material.

holokū₂

cloak (Isa. 59.17) , mantle (Hal. 109.29) .

holokū₃

evenly plump, stout and symmetrical.

hololani

mission.

hololeka

to correspond.

holomakani

breezy, airy. lit., wind running.

holomoku₁

sailor, passenger, anyone who sails; to sail, take a sail or ocean trip.

holomoku₂

rush or torrent, as of water; to rush, break forth, overflow. fig., overwhelming.

holomua

improvement, progress.

holomū

a long fitted dress, a combination of holokū and muʻumuʻu, a name probably coined after World War II.

holona₁

a running, sailing, traveling; performance.

holona₂

a double bar to show the end of a piece of music.

holopani

a pain that nearly shuts off (pani) the breath.

holopapa₁

• shelf, ledge, rack,   • frame on which tapa and other articles were laid;   • flooring.

holopapa₂

to spread, overrun, prevail, overcome, control, defeat; everywhere, completely.

holopeki

to trot. lit., pace (Eng.) run.

holouka

draft, air current, as in the mountains.

holowai

water ditch or course; to run in such courses; watery.

holowaʻa lepo

form or mold, as for making adobe bricks.

holowaʻaʻōwili

powder horn.

holowaʻa₁

trough, especially vessel in which kava was mixed; oblong box, coffin, chest, cradle; furrow, as for planting sugar cane.

holowaʻa₂

sheath covering coconut flowers.

holowaʻa₃

shuttle into which the bobbin of a sewing machine is slipped after it is filled with thread.

holowaʻa₄

a kind of fish net.

holowā₂

thrust through a cleft.

holowā₃

war engine.

holowī

long, thin.

holoāiʻa

• to swim like a fish;   • to get the bends; the bends, caisson disease.   • to drown,   • to sink;   •

holoāwai

to flow like water.

holoʻanai

to gallop.

holoʻokoʻa

• whole, entire, complete,   • total, all,   • absolute, altogether;   • entirely;   • paramount, supreme;   • entity.

holo₁₀

hall.

holo₂

decided, determined, agreed upon, settled, approved, passed, enacted.

holo₃

noose.

holo₄

running hula step to the side; similar to kāholo except that the feet are not necessarily brought together

holo₅

a long bundle, as of hard poi.

holo₆

to sew, as a break in a gourd calabash.

holo₇

holes in edge of a canoe, through which lashings were passed to hold a canoe cover in place.

holo₈

diagonal pole or strut attached to the inner side of the roof framework and extending obliquely from the upper end of a rafter at one corner to the lower end of the rafter at the other corner; diagonal brace. see illus. 1, illus. 4

holo₉

loss of a pebble in the kōnane game.

holu nape

to sway, wave; swaying.

holua₂

prayer for luakini dedication.

holuholu

flexible.

holulu

to oppress.

holu₁

• springy, pliable, resilient, as a mattress;   • to sway, as palm fronds;   • to ripple, as waves;   • to play back and forth;   • bumpy, as an airplane ride.

holāholā

to blossom, as a flower or adolescent growing into maturity. Kaʻū.

homa₁

disappointed.

homa₂

thin, flabby; hollow, as cheeks.

homa₃

to hold a canoe to its course in a rough sea.

homa₄

beat of paddle on canoe side, as in rhythmic paddling while fish are driven into a net.

home hoʻokūʻonoʻono

homestead.

home hoʻopaʻa

detention home.

home lula

home rule; the name of the political party composed of native Hawaiians formed in the early years of Hawaiʻi as a territory. This party ended in 1912 after Kuhiō was elected delegate to Congress.

homeka

sand lizard (RSV), snail (KJV).

homeopakika

homeopathic.

hona₂

a variety of taro.

honehone

melodious.

honekakala

honeysuckle, a low, twining shrub (Lonicera japonica), from East Asia, with shortstemmed, oval leaves and fragrant tubular flowers that open white and turn yellow.

honekoa

saucy, impudent.

hone₁

• sweet and soft, as music; to sound softly;   • sweetly appealing, as perfume or a memory of love;   • to tease, play pranks;   • mischievous.

hone₂

honey.

hone₃

tenon of a wall post.

honi lima

to throw a kiss; such a kiss.

honi pāhaʻohaʻo

a "puzzling" smell: said if the smell is out of place, as that of gardenias in a canoe at sea, interpreted as a warning of danger.

honihoni

to kiss or smell repeatedly, sniff.

honikā

a loud kiss; to kiss loudly.

honina₂

name of a tapa dyed with turmeric and worn as a sarong.

honi₂

to smell, sniff, scent; a scent.

honi₃

to touch, as a match to a combustible.

hono makani

windbreak.

honohina

wild spiderflower (Gynandropsis gynandra), a cosmopolitan tropical hairy annual weed, native to Africa, in the caper family, 30 to 90 cm high, leaves five-parted; flowers spider-like, white with a purple tinge; fruit narrow, cylindrical capsule with many seeds.

honohono kukui

the basket grass (Oplismenus hirtellus), a creeping grass that originated in America, called kukui because it is often found under kukui trees.

honohono kū mau

a variety of honohono₂ [wandering Jew, dayflower]

honohono ʻula

wandering Jew or zebrina, an ornamental, now naturalized, native to Mexico (Zebrina pendula).

honohono₂

the wandering Jew or dayflower (Commelina diffusa), known in many temperate and tropical countries, a creeping weed, rooting at the joints, and bearing grasslike, ovate leaves and small bright-blue flowers. Also honohono wai, and mākolokolo.

honohono₃

a very rare native mint (Haplostachys haplostachya), a downy erect herb with oblong or narrower leaves and white flowers.

honohono₆

a children's game; the child locked fingers of two hands and thrust them into the sand, letting the sand out through a small opening.

honokaʻa₁

cavern, sea cave.

honokoī

a hard lump beside the mons pubis.

honole

mischievous, teasing; to tease.

honopū

mob, angry crowd.

honoā

same as kūkae, excrement, and an insulting epithet for commoners.

hono₁

• to stitch, sew,   • mend, patch;   • a joining, as of mountains.

hono₂

• back of the neck,   • brow of a cliff.

hono₃

bad smelling (less common than hohono).

hono₄

rite at the end of kapu loulu rituals during which chiefs sat without shifting positions while a kahuna prayed for as long as an hour.

honu kahiki

a tortoise, perhaps the introduced land tortoise of the genus Gopherus. lit., foreign turtle.

honu māeaea

a variety of turtle.

honu peʻekue₁

a variety of thick-shelled turtle. lit., coarse turtle.

honu peʻekue₂

crowded, thick.

honu poʻo kea

a variety of turtle. lit., white-headed turtle.

honu ʻea

hawksbill turtle (Chelonia); the shell of this turtle was used as medicine for the disease called ʻea and was used for combs and fans.

honua nalu

base of a breaker.

honuaʻula

a variety of sugar cane, a dark brown-red mutant of manulele, with purple leaf sheaths and leaves. (HP 221, 225). It was formerly used in medicine, and is one of the best canes for eating raw.

honua₃

suddenly, abruptly and without reason.

honua₄

middle section of a canoe; central section of a canoe fleet, as fishing iheihe fish; main section, as of an army.

honuhonu₁

a game in which player and opponent sat with legs crossed and tried to unseat each other; to play this game.

honuhonu₂

a game in which one boy sat astride the back of another who was down on all fours; to play this game.

honuhonu₃

a tapa pattern said to have its surface raised in ridges like corduroy.

honu₂

name of a design for Niʻihau mats.

hooleaʻi

old spelling for hōʻole + ai.

hope haʻina

object of a sentence.

hope kiaʻāina

Lieutenant governor.

hope kumu

substitute or assistant teacher.

hope pelekikena

vice-president.

hope poʻo

acting or deputy head, director, leader.

hope puʻukū

assistant or deputy treasurer.

hope waiwai

assignee (term in will 303, 1875, State Archives).

hopena alahao

railroad terminus.

hopena₁

result, conclusion, sequel, ending, destiny, fate, consequence, effect, last.

hopeʻaʻei

part of an ʻōpelu net.

hopeʻeha

lit., pain-inflicting rear.

hopeʻō

wasp, yellow jacket, hornet.

hope₂

• result, consequence,   • conclusion, end,   • purpose,   • sequel, supplement.

hope₃

deputy, substitute, assistant, adjutant, representative, surety, successor, proxy, acting officer, supporter, vice-, agent, factor.

hope₄

posterior, buttocks. tail (of a plane) (HE)

hope₅

second brew of kava.

hopilole

to eat slowly, as an invalid.

hopohopo

• anxiety, anxious,   • uncertainty, uncertain, doubt, in doubt,   • fright; fearful,   • perturbed, alarmed, uneasy.

hopoʻi

transitive form of hopo.

hopuna ʻōlelo₁

pronunciation, enunciation.

hopuna ʻōlelo₂

paragraph.

hopuna ʻōlelo₃

syllable.

hopuna₁

grasping, seizing, taking; arrest.

hopuna₂

pronunciation, accent.

hopu₁

to seize, grasp, take, catch, capture, arrest; seizure, taking, arrest.

hopūʻali

to gird, compress; grooved

hou kui

injection needle...

hou pahi

to stab with a knife.

hou puka

to drill a hole, bore or pierce through.

houhewa

to turn this way and that, as in panic.

houhou

redup of hou₃, to push, thrust, pierce...; fig., to make cutting or cruel remarks.

houpo

• diaphragm,   • chest,   • solar plexus.

houpo lewalewa

• sagging chest;   • hunger.

houpo ʻume pau

strong pulsation in solar plexis, heart attack.

hou₃

• to push, thrust, poke, shove,   • stab, pierce, prick,   • plunge, ram, jab,   • drill, bore,   • inject.

hou₄

perspiration, sweat; to perspire, sweat.

hou₅

varieties of wrasse (Thalassoma) shallow-water fish, as T. purpureum. The following names have been recorded for the young stages of the hou: ʻāwela, kanaloa, ʻōlali, ʻōlani, pāhouhou, pakaiele, pakaueloa, palaeʻa, pāʻouʻou.

hoāluka

to bring together, collect. caus/sim of ʻāluka, crowd, heap; mixed, crowded, heaped...

hoʻ-

marker of the caus/sim.; same as hoʻo-, but commonly found before words beginning with a- or e- (or sometimes i-), with lengthening of the first vowel of the word, as ano, hoʻāno; emi, hoʻēmi; inu, hoʻīnu, or before words beginning with a long vowel, as ō, hoʻō.

hoʻaikāne

to be a friend, make friends, befriend

hoʻalo

caus/sim of alo, front, face, presence; upper surface, as of a bowl; leeward...

hoʻanapa

caus/sim of ʻanapa, to shine, gleam, glitter, flash, sparkle; brightness, gleam...

hoʻanuanu

caus/sim of anuanu, redup. of anu, cold; chilly...

hoʻaʻā

to kindle, light

hoʻeaea

to approach.

hoʻi hope

to go back, return, retreat, revert, backslide, deteriorate morally. (In (Ier. 3.22) hoʻi hope seems to be the translation of "faithless" and "faithlessness" and in (Ier. 6.28) the translation of "revolter.")

hoʻi hou₁

to go or come back, return.

hoʻi hou₂

repeat sign in music.

hoʻi loa

to go or come with no thought of returning; to go permanently.

hoʻihoʻi ea

restoration, as of sovereignty; to restore sovereignty.

hoʻikau

very, great (often written as two words).

hoʻina₁

returning, coming back; return.

hoʻina₂

farewell gift, as to a parting guest after a feast.

hoʻioʻiole

caus/sim of ʻioʻiole, mousy, like a rat...

hoʻiʻimo

to blink rapidly; to twinkle, to cause a twinkling

hoʻi₂

to enter, as an institution or last resting place.

hoʻi₃

a parting chant to which hula dancers dance as they leave the audience.

hoʻi₄

marriage of a chief with the daughter of a brother or sister; to do so (a means of increasing the rank of the offspring).

hoʻi₅

intensifying preceding base.

hoʻi₆

also, too, besides.

hoʻi₇

expressing doubt, uncertainty.

hoʻmāhū

to behave like a homosexual or hermaphrodite

hoʻo-

a very active former of caus/sim. derivatives. hoʻo- is treated as a prefix because it occurs only before bases; unlike prefixes, however, it takes the stress of a word, as does the following base; thus hoʻouna, to send, bears stress on the u and on the first o. hoʻo- usually precedes stems beginning with the vowels i- and u- and all the consonants except the glottal stop. important meanings follow...

hoʻo-₁

causation and transitivization, as pono, correct; hoʻoponopono, to correct.

hoʻo-₂

pretense, as kuli, deaf; hoʻokuli, to feign deafness.

hoʻo-₃

similarity, as kamaliʻi, children; hoʻoka maliʻi, childish.

hoʻo-₄

no meaning, as kāholoholo, to hurry; hoʻokāholoholo, to hurry. The meanings of some hoʻo- derivatives are quite different from the meanings of the stems, as maikaʻi, good; hoʻomaikaʻi, to congratulate.

hoʻoahiahi

same as hoʻāhiahi: to become evening; to spend an evening; to detain until evening; to darken, obscure.

hoʻoaka

to cast a shadow

hoʻoala

same as hoʻāla, to awaken someone

hoʻoalo

caus/sim of alo, front, face, presence; upper surface, as of a bowl; leeward...

hoʻoana

to make measurements, rearrange, put in order. also hoʻāna.

hoʻoaʻa

to cause a plant or slip to take root; to take root.

hoʻoehu

caus/sim of ehu₂, same as ehuehu₂ thriving...

hoʻoeke

var. of hoʻoweke, to open. (weke₁, crack, narrow opening... )

hoʻohaehae

caus/sim of haehae₂, redup. of hae₁ wild...   • to drive into a fury;   • to decoy uhu fish by tying an uhu to a line;   • to tease.

hoʻohae₁

to make wild or savage; to provoke, tease, exasperate, stir up wrath

hoʻohae₂

to cause to bark, growl, scold

hoʻohahai

to cause to follow, entice; to pretend to follow

hoʻohahana

to create heat; to rouse to fury

hoʻohahauhia

to be struck.

hoʻohaha₁

to parade, strut

hoʻohaha₂

overcast, calm

hoʻohahu

to smooth, level off; to give a purge; cathartic purge.

hoʻohaikaika

a less violent grimace than haikaika; to make faces, cause to make faces

hoʻohaili₁

to cause, produce a recollection or premonition; to challenge.

hoʻohaili₂

to assume a ghostly form; dim

hoʻohaka

to make openings holes, spaces; to create space; full of holes. fig., hungry.

hoʻohakahaka

full of openings and spaces; to make open spaces, holes

hoʻohakakā

to provoke a fight

hoʻohakanū

to cause silence; silent.

hoʻohaku

to act as haku, dominate; to treat as a haku; to rule others, sometimes without authority; bossy

hoʻohakē

to pack full, cram, push; to break, as a boil.

hoʻohakū

caus/sim of hakū, rising, bulging; bulge; to rise, as the moon...

hoʻohala manawa

to pass the time, agreeably or otherwise; to loaf; pastime

hoʻohalahala

• to criticize, complain, find fault, complaint; critical.   • correct, correction,   • negotiate (rare),   • suggest;

hoʻohala₁

• to cause to sin, lead astray;   • to fail to do

hoʻohala₂

• to cause to miss; to dodge, turn aside;   • to pass, as time

hoʻohale

to lodge in a house; to receive in a house

hoʻohale kipa

to entertain, as a guest or friend; hospitable

hoʻohale papaʻa

to convert into a storehouse; to store in a house; to serve as a storehouse

hoʻohalehale

caus/sim of halehale, high, towering, as a housetop, cliff, or waves; cavernous. fig., emptiness, hunger...

hoʻohali

to cause to carry

hoʻohaliʻa

to evoke reminiscence or recollection; remembrance; to remind

hoʻohalu

caus/sim of halu, same as puhalu, uhalu, soft, flabby, loose, sagging, sunken...

hoʻohalulu

same as halulu₁; to produce a roaring noise.

hoʻohamo

caus/sim of hamo₁, anointed, smeared; to anoint, stain, rub, as with oil; to besmear, plaster, stroke gently, pet, fondle, caress...

hoʻohamohamo

caus/sim of hamohamo, redup. of hamo₁, to pat...

hoʻohana₁

to use, employ, cause to work, carry out, administer, manage, encourage; use, employment, management, administration.

hoʻohana₂

to tease, provoke, nag, plague; one who teases or provokes

hoʻohani

• to touch,   • graze,   • hint.

hoʻohanini

to overflow, etc.; to cause an overflow

hoʻohano

same as hoʻohanohano, to honor, exalt, glorify; to conduct oneself with distinction.

hoʻohanohano

to honor, exalt, glorify; to conduct oneself with distinction.

hoʻohanu

to cause to breathe, resuscitate, administer an inhalant

hoʻohanuhanu

redup. of hoʻohanu to cause to breathe, resuscitate, administer an inhalant.

hoʻohao

caus/sim of hao₄, to come with force, as wind or rain; to do with force and energy...

hoʻohaoa

caus/sim of haoa₃, same as haoa puhi, gorge used for catching eels...

hoʻohaole

to act like a white person, to ape the white people, or assume airs of superiority

hoʻohapa

to lessen, diminish

hoʻohape

caus/sim of hape₁, incorrect, faulty, inaccurate; to break, transgress...

hoʻohauhau

same as hauhau₁ redup. of hau₃, to hit...

hoʻohauhili

to cause confusion, as in speech. caus/sim of hauhili₁, same as hilikau mixed, snarled, entangled...

hoʻohaukaʻe

to spoil, as a ballot. fig., to defile a reputation. caus/sim of haukaʻe, stained, smeared, smudged, defaced, sordid; to besmirch, stain, smear...

hoʻohaumia

to pollute, defile, befoul, besmirch, contaminate...

hoʻohaumāna

to act as a pupil, become a pupil; to make pupils of

hoʻohauna

to cause an offensive odor; to use strong-smelling bait to attract fish; to smell such an odor

hoʻohaunaele

to provoke panic, riot; agitator.

hoʻohaunuʻu

proud

hoʻohauwawā

provocative of loud noise. caus/sim of hauwawā, medley of simultaneous talking...

hoʻohauwene

to tease others. caus/sim of hauwene, to cry, tease, nag, fret...

hoʻohauʻoli

to cause happiness, entertain, gaiety, joy; have fun, do fun things. (NKE)

hoʻohawaiʻi

to act as a Hawaiian; to ape or imitate Hawaiians

hoʻohaʻa

to lower; humble. see the more common hoʻohaʻahaʻa

hoʻohaʻahaʻa

to lower, debase, humiliate, humble (Kanl. 8.2), disgrace, underrate, belittle; humble, lowly, modest.

hoʻohaʻaheo

to act haughty. caus/sim of haʻaheo, proud, haughty; to strut; to cherish with pride; pride, vanity, haughtiness...

hoʻohaʻalele

to pretend to quit or leave; to cause to quit

hoʻohaʻalulu

caus/sim of haʻalulu, to shake, quake, totter, tremble, quiver...

hoʻohaʻanui

caus/sim of haʻanui, to boast, brag, exaggerate, gloat...

hoʻohaʻihaʻi

to break, as waves. caus/sim of haʻihaʻi₁, brittle; limbering exercises, as for the hula; massage in chiropractic; quavering; breaking, rising and falling of the voice; a style of singing with a breaking voice; to break, as a law...

hoʻohaʻilua

to flirt; loose jointed. see -haʻilua.

hoʻohaʻi₁

to cause a break

hoʻohaʻi₂

caus/sim of haʻi₄, coquettish, flirtatious; to flirt...

hoʻohaʻohaʻo

to arouse wonder, surprise, puzzlement.

hoʻohehelo₁

caus/sim of hehelo, reddish, bright, showy...

hoʻohehelo₂

proud, especially of one's appearance or dress

hoʻohehena

caus/sim of hehena, insane, raving mad, crazy, possessed; insanity, madness; lunatic, maniac...

hoʻoheheo

to swish, swirl; to swish up and down on the foot, as a child, toss up. caus/sim of heheo, a swaggering or swishing walk; swishing, as of a skirt; to whirl, swish, strut...

hoʻoheheʻe

• to melt, liquefy,   • cast,   • dissolve,   • soften;   • to slide, especially to slide by jerks, as on a hōlua, sled, or ti-leaf slide.

hoʻohei

• to snare, tangle, rope, lasso;   • to beset with difficulties;   • to infatuate, be enraptured

hoʻoheihei₁

to run swiftly, take part in a race, pretend to race, cause to race

hoʻoheihei₂

• to ensnare, entrap;   • to mend, as a net or wire fence

hoʻoheihei₃

to fascinate, flirt; to ward off possible sorcery by imitating the gestures of the kahuna. caus/sim of heihei₃, to enthrall, enchant...

hoʻoheihei₄

to beat, as a heiau drum; sound of heiau drum.

hoʻohekili

to cause thunder; threatening thunder storm

hoʻohelehele

to help someone walk, as a child; to take walking, as a dog

hoʻohelehele ʻōlelo

to lead up to a subject in a roundabout way, hint, suggest

hoʻohelei₁

caus/sim of helei₁, to straddle...

hoʻohelei₂

to pull down, as the eyelid; to stretch, as the mouth

hoʻoheleleʻi

to scatter, sow; to fall, as rain.

hoʻohele₁

to cause to move, set in motion; to start, as a clock; to manage; to walk someone else or force oneself to walk

hoʻohele₂

to imitate, pretend; imitative, pretending

hoʻohelu

numerator, in fractions; a telling, explanation. caus/sim of helu₁, to count, number, compute...

hoʻohemahema

to neglect, not care for; careless, negligent, defective, deficient, ignorant

hoʻohemo

to loosen, undo, unfasten, disconnect, take off, set at liberty, liberate, free, abort.

hoʻohemohemo

to take off. caus/sim of hemohemo, separation, loosening...

hoʻohemolele

to make holy; to feign holiness

hoʻohemū

to drive off, scare away, as hens

hoʻohena

to see, feel, or handle the hena, mons pubis; to take off one's clothing and expose the hena

hoʻohenehene

to tease, laugh at, jeer, banter, ridicule.

hoʻohenoheno

lovable. caus/sim of henoheno, lovable, sweet...

hoʻoheno₁

to cherish, love, caress; affectionate, demonstrative of affection; expression of affection, as a song

hoʻoheno₂

decorative plaiting on mat, fan; to decorate thus

hoʻoheo

proud, vaunting, vain; to show off, boast

hoʻohepa

misconstrue. caus/sim of hepa, idiot, moron, imbecile; partial paralysis of the vocal organs causing indistinct articulation; feebleminded, moronic...

hoʻohepahepa

caus/sim of hepahepa, redup. of hepa, idiot, moron, imbecile...

hoʻoheu₁

to bleach

hoʻoheu₃

to grow, sprout, germinate; pubescence. caus/sim of heu, down or fine hair, fuzz, loose fibers on certain fruits or leaves, quicksilver or mercury on back of a mirror, hairlike growths or spines on sugar cane stalks or cactus; fuzzy, downy; to begin to grow...

hoʻohewa

to cause one to do wrong, cause or feign a mistake; to blame, condemn (cf. the more common hoʻāhewa, to condemn)

hoʻohewahewa₁

mat mesh, twill plaiting

hoʻohewahewa₂

to fail to recognize

hoʻoheʻeheʻe

redup. of hoʻoheʻe; slide (by jerks), slip.

hoʻoheʻe₁

• to cause to slip, slide, flee;   • to put to flight, rout.

hoʻohia

caus/sim of hia, desire, delight...

hoʻohiahia

caus/sim of hiahia₂, var. of hiehie, redup. of hie, attractive, distinguished...; superb...

hoʻohialaʻai

caus/sim of hialaʻai₁, same as hiaʻai, pleased with, delighted with; delightful, pleasing...

hoʻohiamoe

to put to sleep, lull to sleep, to pretend to sleep; soporific.

hoʻohiapo

to have the privileges of a first-born; to act as a first-born; to treat as a first-born

hoʻohiaʻai

to delight, enchant, entrance

hoʻohiaʻā

to cause sleeplessness

hoʻohie

to make or cause to appear distinguished; distinguished, stately, regal; delightful.

hoʻohiehie

to beautify, make distinctive, beautiful, elegant; distinguished in manner or appearance

hoʻohihia

to get into difficulties, entangle, perplex, beset with trouble (Mat. 26.31) , complicate.

hoʻohihina

to cause to fall; to sway to and fro.

hoʻohihiu

to cause fear, frighten

hoʻohihi₁

to cause entanglement; to entwine, entangle

hoʻohihi₂

to take a fancy to, admire greatly, be enraptured with

hoʻohikihiki₁

caus/sim of hikihiki₁, to come repeatedly, as voices...

hoʻohikihiki₂

caus/sim of hikihiki₂, to fetch repeatedly or a little at a time...

hoʻohikilele

to startle, shock

hoʻohikiwawe

to accelerate, hurry, hasten

hoʻohiki₁

to cause to come, arrive, appear

hoʻohiki₂

to vow, swear, take an oath, promise; to administer an oath; vow, oath, promise, pledge. see ʻōlelo hoʻohiki

hoʻohila

caus/sim of hila₁, same as hilahila₁, bashful, shy, ashamed...

hoʻohilahila

to make ashamed or embarrassed; to disgrace, humiliate; shameful, bashful, timid.

hoʻohilala

to cause to swing back and forth; to lean over, tilt. caus/sim of hilala, to reel, lean or tilt sideways.

hoʻohilihili₁

redup. of hoʻohili

hoʻohilihili₂

to dye

hoʻohilikau

caus/sim of hilikau, mixed, snarled, entangled; to mix, snarl. See saying makau...

hoʻohiliu

to blow a conch or wind instrument

hoʻohili₁

to lead astray. caus/sim of hili₂, to turn aside, deviate, miss the way, wander, stray...

hoʻohili₂

to pretend to whip, to whip gently. caus/sim of hili₃, to whip, smite, thrash, switch, bat; batter, as in baseball; stroke, as in fighting...

hoʻohilo

caus/sim of hilo₁, to twist, braid, spin; twisted, braided; threadlike; faint streak of light...

hoʻohiluhilu

to beautify, bedeck, decorate

hoʻohilu₁

to decorate, beautify

hoʻohilu₂

to praise, exalt, dignify. see hilu₂, quiet, reserved, well-behaved, decorous...

hoʻohina

to throw, cause to fall, knock down; to lean over.

hoʻohinuhinu₁

to shine, polish; to show off

hoʻohinuhinu₂

var. of hoʻohiluhilu, to beautify, bedeck, decorate... .

hoʻohiohiolo

to hang or drape festively. caus/sim of hiohiolo, redup. of hiolo, to tumble down, collapse...

hoʻohiolo

to overthrow, demolish, raze

hoʻohiolohia

caus/sim of hiolohia, pas/imp. of hiolo, to tumble down, collapse...

hoʻohiu₁

caus/sim of hiu₁, to throw or fling violently; to haul energetically with ropes; to get into action, as play or sport; to pursue with energy, as love-making...

hoʻohiu₂

caus/sim of hiu₂, to elevate, hoist, as by block and tackle...

hoʻohiwahiwa

• to honor,   • adorn, decorate;   • to display, as the flag;   • to treat as a favorite;   • festive...

hoʻohiwi

to be downright skin and bones

hoʻohiō

caus/sim of hiō, to fall sideways, lean, slant, slope, incline, leaning, oblique, diagonal...

hoʻohiōhiō

redup. of hoʻohiō

hoʻohiʻi

caus/sim of hiʻi₁, to hold or carry in the arms, as a child; to bear; to nurse or tend a child...

hoʻohoahoa

caus/sim of hoahoa, a rounded tapa beater (also called hohoa, pepehi); rapid beating, striking, as of tapa or pandanus leaves; a stick beater for washing clothes. fig., bad-tempered...

hoʻohoaloha

to make friends, be friendly, befriend

hoʻohoa₁

to challenge, dare, provoke; daring, defiant.

hoʻohoa₂

to make friends.

hoʻohoe

to have a canoe paddled. caus/sim of hoe₁, paddle, oar; to paddle, row...

hoʻohohoka

caus/sim of hohoka, redup. of hoka₁, disappointed, thwarted, baffled; disappointment, frustration, hoka₂, to squeeze, strain...

hoʻohoholo

caus/sim of hoholo, redup. of holo, to run, sail...

hoʻohohono

to cause or produce such an odor.

hoʻohohonu

to deepen

hoʻohohō

to cause a snort. caus/sim of hohō, to snore, snort, bray, heehaw, splash, gurgle, breathe hard, draw in mucus...

hoʻohoihoi

to entertain, amuse, charm, delight, encourage, please

hoʻohoka

to cause disappointment, chagrin; to frustrate, thwart, put to shame.

hoʻohokahoka

caus/sim of hokahoka, redup. of hoka₁, disappointed, thwarted, baffled; disappointment, frustration, hoka₂, to squeeze, strain...

hoʻoholo i mua

to promote, cause progress; advancement, success

hoʻoholo kaʻa

to drive a car or carriage

hoʻoholo lio

same as holo lio horseman (Puk. 14.9) ; to make a horse run

hoʻoholo manaʻo

caus/sim of holo manaʻo, to decide, determine...

hoʻoholoholo kaʻa

to take someone for a drive or ride

hoʻoholoholoʻōlelo

caus/sim of holoholoʻōlelo, to gossip, slander, bear tales, tattle; tattler, talebearer, spreader of gossip...

hoʻoholoholo₁

to take someone out for a drive or excursion; to escort; to help walk, as a child or invalid

hoʻoholoholo₂

to make large running stitches. caus/sim of holoholo₂, basting; to baste, sew...

hoʻoholoi

to have washed, cleaned; to pretend to wash

hoʻoholomoku

to sail (as a ship).

hoʻoholopau

to finish, complete

hoʻoholoāiʻa

caus/sim of holoāiʻa, to swim like a fish; to get the bends; to drown, sink; the bends, caisson disease...

hoʻoholoʻōlelo

caus/sim of holoʻōlelo, same as holoholoʻōlelo, to gossip, slander, bear tales, tattle; tattler, talebearer, spreader of gossip...

hoʻoholo₁

• to sail, run;   • to cause to run, sail, run free, as a horse;   • to ride, as a horse;   • to add water, as to poi;   • to flush, as a toilet;   • to drive, as a carriage...

hoʻoholo₂

• to decide, determine, conclude; decision, judgment...   • enact, pass,   • resolve, settle,   • enforce,   • appraise,   • to manage, as a business;   cf. ʻōlelo hoʻoholo

hoʻoholo₃

grooved piece above the door frame, in which the door slides...

hoʻoholu

to bend, move up and down, sway. caus/sim of holu₁, springy, pliable, resilient, as a mattress; to sway, as palm fronds; to ripple, as waves; to play back and forth; bumpy, as an airplane ride...

hoʻoholuholu

caus/sim of holuholu, flexible...

hoʻohone

caus/sim of hone₁, sweet and soft, as music; sweetly appealing, as perfume or a memory of love; to sound softly; to tease, play pranks; mischievous...

hoʻohoni₁

to cause or pretend to kiss

hoʻohoni₂

caus/sim of honi₂, to smell, sniff, scent; a scent...

hoʻohonu

to deepen.

hoʻohonua

to establish land, act as land; to scoop out earth, as for a fireplace; firmly established. fig. rich (rare)

hoʻohopohopo

to evoke or produce doubt, fear, anxiety

hoʻohua kama

to sire a child

hoʻohuahua

to make the huahua gesture

hoʻohuahualau

to cross-examine, to ask indirectly, to obtain information by roundabout methods, to question indirectly, quiz. caus/sim of huahualau, interrogation to incriminate, ensnare, or obtain information by roundabout methods, to question or quiz indirectly...

hoʻohuakawowo

to induce pregnancy

hoʻohuaka₁

to cause a gleam of light, flash, glimmer

hoʻohuaka₂

to cast a shadow or reflection

hoʻohuakeʻeo

hurt, angry, displeased, resentful... (see -huakeʻeo)

hoʻohuali

to polish. caus/sim of huali, bright, polished, clean, pure, white, glittering, gleaming; morally pure...

hoʻohua₁

• to bear fruit, reproduce, produce, yield;   • to sire or give birth;   • to swell high, as a wave.

hoʻohua₂

to have as a result, because of, ever since (followed by nō)

hoʻohuelo

to lengthen, continue, make a tail; to stream down, as water over a cliff

hoʻohuhuki

to pull, cause to pull. fig., headstrong

hoʻohuhū

to provoke anger, pretend anger

hoʻohuihui

mixed; to mix individually identifiable things together (NKE12). caus/sim of huihui₁, mixed, mingled, united, joined; to pool together, as to buy cooperatively...

hoʻohuikau

to mix, confuse, complicate, perplex, scramble. caus/sim of huikau, mixed, confused, haphazard, blurred; mix-up, confusion, jumble; to mix...

hoʻohuini

to carve or sharpen into a point

hoʻohui₁

to form a society

hoʻohui₂

to join, as two words; to add a prefix or suffix; to add on, annex, append, unite; to introduce one person to another; meeting of persons; binder

hoʻohukihuki

caus/sim of hukihuki₂, to disagree, quarrel; disagreement; not cooperative, headstrong, obstinate...

hoʻohuki₁

to pull gently. caus/sim of huki₁, to pull or tug, as on a rope; to draw, stretch, reach; to support, as a political party...

hoʻohuki₂

willful, headstrong

hoʻohuku

to project, protrude

hoʻohula

to cause someone to dance; to pretend to hula

hoʻohulali

caus/sim of hulali₁, shining, glittering, glossy, slippery; to shine, glitter, sparkle, reflect light...

hoʻohulei

to trot, cause to trot, move back and forth. caus/sim of hulei, to lift, raise, draw up, as a skirt; to pull, pry; to pitch and toss, as a ship on the waves; to move along, as a ship; to flap wings; to trot, as a horse...

hoʻohuli manaʻo

to induce change of opinion, influence, convert

hoʻohulihuli

to convert; proselyte. caus/sim of hulihuli, redup. of huli₁ to turn, reverse; to curl over, as a breaker; to change, as an opinion or manner of living...

hoʻohulili

caus/sim of hulili, dazzling light, vibration, undulation; to blaze, sparkle, dazzle, glare, vibrate, swell...

hoʻohuli₁

to turn, change, affect, overturn, convert, reform

hoʻohuli₂

caus/sim of huli₂, to look for, search, explore, seek, study; search, investigation; scholarship...

hoʻohulu

to esteem, prize

hoʻohulā

caus/sim of hulā, to prod, pry, uproot, pierce and penetrate, expel, reject...

hoʻohulō

caus/sim of hulō, hurrah, cheers...

hoʻohume

to put a loincloth on another

hoʻohumu

to make someone sew

hoʻohune₁

to cause poverty, impoverish

hoʻohune₂

to persist, nag, tease; to do with avidity and persistence

hoʻohunāhunā

caus/sim of hunāhunā, to hide frequently or be hidden by many persons; secretly...

hoʻohuoi

to suspect, surmise distrust; suspicion.

hoʻohuā

to provoke anger or jealousy

hoʻohuʻa

to insist, persist.

hoʻohuʻahuʻa

caus/sim of huʻahuʻa₁, foam, froth, lather, bubbling, frothing...

hoʻohuʻihuʻi

to make cold, chill, as by refrigeration

hoʻohāhā

to beat, pound, as tapa; to harden.

hoʻohāhāpaʻakai

to gather salt

hoʻohāiki

to contract, shrink, restrict, curtail, narrow.

hoʻohāinu

same as hāinu, to give drink.

hoʻohākoʻi

caus/sim of hākoʻi, same as hakukoʻi agitated; paraphimosis...

hoʻohākuʻi

caus/sim of hākuʻi, to beat, pound, pummel; to echo, reverberate; to flutter, palpitate, thump; to puff, as smoke...

hoʻohākuʻikuʻi

caus/sim of hākuʻikuʻi, redup. of hākuʻi to beat, pound, pummel...

hoʻohākā moa

cockfighting. caus/sim of hākā moa, cockfight...

hoʻohākālia

to delay, slow down; slow, dilatory; hesitation.

hoʻohālana

caus/sim of hālana₁, to overflow, flood...

hoʻohālau

to make numerous

hoʻohālike

• to compare, contrast,   • make alike,   • resemble,   • copy;   • artificial.   • example (Wight)

hoʻohālikelike

comparison, resemblance, similarity, impersonation; to equalize, match, impersonate...

hoʻohāliu

caus/sim of hāliu, to turn, look, hearken, incline, have regard...

hoʻohāliʻaliʻa

remind, reminiscent. caus/sim of hāliʻaliʻa, redup. of hāliʻa. sudden remembrance, memory...

hoʻohālua

same as hālua₂,   • to ambush, lie in wait, waylay,   • spy,   • provoke trouble...

hoʻohālāwai

to arrange a meeting

hoʻohāmama

to open, expose; to pretend to open, yawn

hoʻohāmau

to silence, hush

hoʻohānau

to act as midwife, deliver a baby; to reproduce

hoʻohānau hou

to cause a rebirth, baptize

hoʻohāneʻe

to cause an avalanche, slide; to flatten

hoʻohāpai₁

caus/sim of hāpai₁, to carry, bear, lift, elevate, raise, hoist, hold up; to support, as another's testimony...

hoʻohāpai₂

to cause conception; to perform ceremonies or take treatment to induce conception

hoʻohāpala

to besmear, etc

hoʻohāuliuli

to darken

hoʻohāʻawe

to have something carried on the back; to load on the back

hoʻohāʻule

to drop, cause to fall

hoʻohāʻupu

to cause to recollect, recall

hoʻohē

same as hōhē, cowardly...

hoʻohī

to purge (of bowels). caus/sim of hī₂, dysentery, diarrhea; to flow, hiss; to purge...

hoʻohīpuʻu

to tie, bind

hoʻohōkai

to cause confusion, mix up, bother; to blot out the memory

hoʻohūleilei

to toss, as a child on one's foot. caus/sim of hūleilei, redup. of hulei, to lift, raise, draw up, as a skirt; to pull, pry; to pitch and toss, as a ship on the waves; to move along, as a ship; to flap wings; to trot, as a horse...

hoʻohūnā

to hide deliberately.

hoʻohū₁

• to cause someone to deviate from the path;   • to shoo, drive away,   • rout

hoʻohū₂

• to leaven, cause to rise,   • inflate,   • swell,   • overflow;   • yeast,   • baking powder

hoʻoihoiho

in quilting, to make running stitches towards the sewer

hoʻoihona

descent, slope; to descend, go south

hoʻoiho₁

caus/sim of iho₁,   • to go down, descend; descent...   • downhill,   • towards the sea;   • to subside;   • go south or before the wind;

hoʻoiho₂

besides that, also, furthermore,

hoʻoikaika

to make a great effort, work hard, encourage, animate, strengthen, fortify, try, strive, strain; calisthenics

hoʻoiki

to lessen, diminish, make small

hoʻoilimoʻo

a service for luakini dedications.

hoʻoilina

heir, inheritance, legacy, estate, heritage, bequest; successor (so used in the official English version of the Constitution of 1852, Article 25)...

hoʻoili₁

• to land upon,   • load, as freight on a ship;   • to transfer, consign, transmit; see ili₂, inheritance.   • to set on shore... see ili₁, stranded   • to rush on, as in battle, to start a battle, attack.

hoʻoiloilo, hoīloilo

to predict disaster or misfortune

hoʻoilo₂

a strong, bitter purgative.

hoʻoilo₃

to cause germination or sprouting

hoʻoinaina₁

to stir up anger, rouse hate

hoʻoinaina₂

to sooth as by soft music

hoʻoioio

to cut grooves; to sew a quilt so that stitches settle in grooves

hoʻoipo

to make love, court, woo

hoʻoiwi akua

to impart mana to a human bone

hoʻokae₁

• to despise, detest, treat with contempt of scorn;   • destroy, devastate (Oihk. 26.31);   • to refrain from doing, as due to horror.

hoʻokahakaha₁

caus/sim of kahakaha₁, to mark frequently, to draw lines, scratch; to cut lengthwise or into strips; to scarify, engrave; striped, lined...

hoʻokahakaha₂

• to parade back and forth, make a display or exhibition; parade, celebration, exhibition, display;   • to show off, act the dandy; vanity, pomp;   • to drill, as a fire drill;   • superb, showy.   caus/sim of kahakaha₂, redup. of kaha₃ swoop...; pass by...; surf...

hoʻokaha₁

caus/sim of kaha₁,   • to scratch, mark, check, draw, sketch,   • cut, cut open or slice lengthwise, as fish or animals;   • to operate, as on the sick;   • to give a grade or mark to;   • to engrave;   • a line in mathematics;   • punctuation or other mark, as an accent mark...

hoʻokaha₂

caus/sim of kaha₃,   • to swoop, as a kite;   • to be poised,   • soar, as a bird (less used than kīkaha);   • to go by, pass by,   • to turn and go on;   • to surf, body surf...

hoʻokaha₃

to extort. caus/sim of kaha₄, to desolate, plunder, cheat...

hoʻokahe

to water or irrigate; to cause to flow, discharge, drain

hoʻokahe koko

to shed blood; bloodshed

hoʻokahekahe

redup. of hoʻokahe

hoʻokahekahe wai

irrigation, to irrigate, to water. also same as naʻinaʻi mimi contest in urinating by small boys. lit., urine striving.

hoʻokahiko

to think, act, speak in the old way; to speak of old times; to cling to old ways; old-fashioned; maturity

hoʻokahi₂

caus/sim of kahi₁, to cut longitudinally, shave, plane, comb, press, rub or stroke, as in a massage, with gentle pressure of the open palm of the hand; to scrape; to run the fingers along the side of a poi bowl so as to...

hoʻokahua

• to lay a foundation, establish, found;   • to camp or be stationed, as soldiers;   • to settle down and develop a place, as homesteaders

hoʻokahuli

caus/sim of kahuli, to overturn, overthrow, capsize, upset...

hoʻokahuna

to cause to be a kahuna or pretend to be one; to ordain or train as a kahuna

hoʻokahu₁

to act as a kahu; to appoint a kahu

hoʻokahu₂

to make a fire for cooking in the oven; to act as kahu

hoʻokaikaina

to claim a kaikaina relationship; to act as a kaikaina, to address and treat as kaikaina, as from affection

hoʻokaikuahine

to claim a kuahine relationship; to address and treat as a kaikuahine, as from affection

hoʻokaikuaʻana

to claim a kaikuaʻana relationship, to act as a kaikuaʻana, to address and treat as kaikuaʻana; to address a kaikaina as kaikuaʻana as a means of showing great respect...

hoʻokaikunāne

to claim a kaikunāne relationship, to act as a kaikunāne; to address and treat as kaikunāne, as from affection

hoʻokainuʻu

to take possession (referring to an action of a god)

hoʻokakahele

to parade, as Lahaina-Luna students

hoʻokakale

to make soft or watery; soft, flexible, saggy, soft, limp; to dilute

hoʻokakane

caus/sim of kakane, blight on plants; blighted...

hoʻokakani

to make noises

hoʻokakano

caus/sim of kakano, to persist, keep on...

hoʻokakaʻa

to cause to turn, roll, etc.; to turn somersaults or cartwheels

hoʻokakaʻawale

redup. of hoʻokaʻawale

hoʻokakaʻi

to lead, take along

hoʻokake₁

to speak kake; to speak unclearly

hoʻokake₂

to disturb. caus/sim of kake₂, to slip back and forth; to mix, shuffle...

hoʻokalakalai

caus/sim of kalakalai, to carve, cut, hew, hoe, etc., a little at a time; to whittle...

hoʻokalakupua

magic; to do wondrous acts; a magician, enchanter, witchcraft; extraordinary fisherman, elusive thief

hoʻokalalī

to hurry. caus/sim of kalalī, to go quickly, briskly, without noticing anyone; to walk or talk in a brisk, haughty way; proud; such activity...

hoʻokala₁

caus/sim of kala₁,   • to loosen, untie, free, release,   • remove, unburden, take off, undo;   • absolve, let go, acquit,   • to forgive, pardon, excuse;   • to proclaim, announce;   • to substitute for;   • counter-sorcery...

hoʻokala₂

to sharpen, grind (so called because things were formerly sharpened by rubbing against a rough surface); sharpener; to speak roughly or harshly

hoʻokale

to make liquid (less used than hoʻokakale)

hoʻokalekale

to make watery or thin; to lie, deceive; soft, spongy, sagging

hoʻokali

to cause to wait, delay; lingering, slow, as a disease

hoʻokama

to adopt a child or adult one loves, but for whom one might not have the exclusive care (An older adult of either sex might be adopted thus. A child so adopted, termed keiki hoʻokama, is somewhat comparable to a godchild. An adult so adopted might be called kaikuaʻana hoʻokama, kaikaina hoʻokama, kaikuahine hoʻokama, kaikunāne hoʻokama.)

hoʻokamahaʻo

to be or do something wonderful; to take a new and more splendid form.

hoʻokamakama

to prostitute; prostitute, prostitution, concubine. lit., to cause children.

hoʻokamalani

to make a favorite of a person, to treat with indulgence, to pamper, spoil, or lavish with favors; to put on finicky airs and mannerisms.

hoʻokamaliʻi

childish.

hoʻokamaniha

sullen, cross, resentful, hostile, uncivil.

hoʻokamani₁

to act the hypocrite (Mat. 15.7); to deal falsely (Oihk. 19.11), to disguise oneself (1-Nal. 14.2), to pretend, be insecure; hypocrite; sham.

hoʻokamaʻilio

to talk and lead up to the subject one wishes to discuss.

hoʻokamaʻāina

to become acquainted with

hoʻokanaaho

caus/sim of kanaaho, relieved after a struggle; feeling of ease or relief after surviving sickness or danger; joy over escape; rest after violent exertion or danger; breathless arrival; refuge; one convalescing or resting...

hoʻokanahaʻi

small, depressed, stunted, humble, cautious, moderate; to lessen.

hoʻokanahaʻu

caus/sim of kanahaʻu, rare var. of kanahaʻi diminish, lessen...

hoʻokanahua

to rise up, as a whale's back in the water; bent, humpbacked, disobedient; bend, crook.

hoʻokanahē

to drive or urge forward, accelerate, hurry, quicken.

hoʻokanaie

conceited, vain, overbearing.

hoʻokanaka makua

to act as an adult, to act mature.

hoʻokanaka₁

manly, human, courageous; to become a servant or helper; to assume human shape, as a child in the womb. see hoʻokanaka makua.

hoʻokanaleʻo

caus/sim of kanaleʻo, to deceive, mislead, feign, act the hypocrite; deceitful...

hoʻokananeʻo

to disregard, as instruction, warning, danger, careless of danger, indifference to discomfort or health.

hoʻokananuha

to cause sulkiness; dull of hearing.

hoʻokanaoʻe

same as hoʻokanahē to drive or urge forward, accelerate, hurry, quicken.

hoʻokanaʻoi

conceited, feeling that one is superior to everybody else.

hoʻokanaʻō

in doubt; to hesitate.

hoʻokanea

to cause loss of appetite.

hoʻokanikani

redup. of hoʻokani; also a diminutive:

hoʻokano₁

• to harden;   • to form a tuber, as of sweet potato.

hoʻokanu

to cause to plant or bury.

hoʻokaomi

to add or feign pressing, pressure.

hoʻokapalulu

to crackle, roar, etc.

hoʻokapeke

• to loosen, set askew;   • to tilt, as a canoe;   • to sit or loosen the clothing so as to cause indecent exposure.

hoʻokapu

to make taboo, prohibit, sanctify consecrate, forbid.

hoʻokapukapu

to impose a taboo, especially on something not previously taboo; to pretend a taboo that was not existent; to extol, praise, glorify.

hoʻokau

to put on, place on, lay on, as responsibility; to happen, come to pass.

hoʻokauaheahe

to hover; to fly softly, gently, continuously, at the same speed.

hoʻokauhihi

to entangle.

hoʻokauhua

• to cause pregnancy;   • gestation;   • pregnancy sickness;   • pregnancy craving

hoʻokaukau

to place, put, etc.

hoʻokaulana

• to make famous;   • to spread a report concerning a person or thing.

hoʻokaulike

to equalize, balance.

hoʻokauluwela

caus/sim of kauluwela₁, glowing, bright-colored, colorful...

hoʻokaumaha

to burden, load down, laden. fig., to oppress, cause sadness or grief; sorrowful, woeful, sorry, depressed, oppressive, burdensome.

hoʻokaunu

caus/sim of kaunu₁,   • to make love;   • to love;   • thrill of love, passion;   • to be fascinated, absorbed...

hoʻokaupale

to cause a separation, barrier; to disown, disinherit.

hoʻokaupalena

caus/sim of kaupalena, to limit, mark a border or boundary, restrict, moderate, set a deadline; limitation, deadline, ration...

hoʻokauā

• to burden with work,   • make a servant of,   • enslave;   • to act as servant or outcast.

hoʻokauō

to cause to be dragged; to prolong vowels in chanting.

hoʻokawowo

caus/sim of kawowo, seedling; thrifty young plant; sucker, shoot from a parent stalk; to multiply and thrive, as a plant or people. fig., progeny. See hoʻohua kawowo...

hoʻokaʻahea

to soothe

hoʻokaʻakaʻawili

redup. of hoʻokaʻawili to cause pain; to torture; to cause to twist or writhe; to fondle or pet in ardent love-making.

hoʻokaʻakaʻa₁

caus/sim of kaʻakaʻa₁, to open, as the eyes; open, watching...

hoʻokaʻakaʻa₂

to cause to roll repeatedly. also hoʻokakaʻa

hoʻokaʻalia

pas/imp. of hoʻokaʻa

hoʻokaʻana

to divide equally among, share

hoʻokaʻao

to tell tales; story telling

hoʻokaʻawale₁

to separate, distinguish (1 Nal. 3.9) ; to cause a division; to keep a distance or distinction; to establish as a separate entity; to set aside, appropriate, sort, segregate, reserve, discriminate, differentiate...

hoʻokaʻawili

• to cause pain (Ier. 4.19); to torture;   • to cause to twist or writhe;   • to fondle or pet in ardent love-making.

hoʻokaʻaʻokoʻa

to separate, set apart, refrain, abstain from

hoʻokaʻa₁

to cause a rolling, turning

hoʻokaʻa₂

to pay a debt, disburse, avenge

hoʻokaʻe

to daub, smudge, soil, smear. cf. haukaʻe. also hōkaʻe.

hoʻokaʻekaʻe

redup. of hoʻokaʻe to smudge, smear, blot. also hōkaʻekaʻe.

hoʻokaʻukaʻu

to cause delay, linger.

hoʻokaʻulua

to cause delay, etc.

hoʻokeha

to cause height, pride, boasting, etc. same as keha, height, pride, dignity; lofty, high, prominent; majestic, dignified; to brag, boast, praise; to rise to the top. fig., head...

hoʻokehakeha

to act proudly; to cause pride.

hoʻokeikei

caus/sim of keikei, redup. of kei, glory, take pride in...

hoʻokekeʻe

to crook, bend, twist out of shape, pervert.

hoʻokeku

caus/sim of keku, to repulse, shove away, nudge...

hoʻokekē₁

to scold, expose the teeth, etc. also. haʻakekē.

hoʻokekē₂

caus/sim of kekē₃, indecent exposure by a woman or girl; admonition to a female to sit properly...

hoʻokela

to outdo, surpass, excel, exceed; to show off, try to excel, show preference; higher, superior, vain.

hoʻokelakela

• to brag, show off, flaunt, display;   • disrespectful, overbearing, conceited.

hoʻokelekele₁

to make muddy; to sprinkle; soak material, as pandanus leaves, in water to make pliable for plaiting; to feed, fatten, especially with soft food or liquids.

hoʻokelekele₂

redup. of hoʻokele; to steer, navigate or sail frequently; to manage; to cast, as for fish.

hoʻokele₁

• to make muddy;   • to sprinkle;   • to soak material, as pandanus leaves, in water to make pliable for plaiting;   • to feed, fatten, especially with soft food or liquids...

hoʻokele₂

• steersman, helmsman, navigator;   • to sail or navigate, as the master of a ship;   • to steer;   • to drive, as a car,   • fig., to conduct any business...

hoʻokele₃

kind of stone found at craters, as Kīlauea, and used for adzes.

hoʻokena

to satisfy thirst.

hoʻokenākenā

to compel, order.

hoʻokeonimana

gentlemanly conduct or etiquette; to act as a gentleman.

hoʻokepa

to cut obliquely, snap, tear, rend.

hoʻokepania

to act like or mimic Spaniards or Spanish.

hoʻokepanī

to act like or mimic Japanese.

hoʻokeʻa

to cross, block, obstruct, hinder.

hoʻokeʻe

to make a turn, as in cutting paper or cloth; to turn, as in walking; to bend, form an angle.

hoʻokeʻekeʻe₁

redup. of hoʻokeʻe; zigzag, angular; zigzag lines, as in a mat motif.

hoʻokeʻekeʻe₂

redup. of hoʻokeʻe; cranky, surly.

hoʻokeʻemoa

to behave thus.

hoʻokeʻo

to whiten, bleach.

hoʻokeʻokeʻo

to whiten, to bleach.

hoʻokiawe

to stream (flow). caus/sim of kiawe₂, a streak; to stream gracefully, as rain in the wind; to sway, as branches...

hoʻokiaʻi

to post a watch.

hoʻokihi

to make a corner by overlapping, as in plaiting; to fold partially over; to turn aside, make a corner

hoʻokihikihi

to branch out, make corners, make irregular

hoʻokikilua

in the card game high-low-jack-and-the-game, to hide one's strength and then play a winning card

hoʻokikina

redup. of hoʻokina. goad, urge

hoʻokiko

to hatch

hoʻokikī

to cause to flow, pour, etc.

hoʻokili

to rain gently

hoʻokilihune

caus/sim of kilihune₁, fine, light rain, wind-blown spray, drizzle; to shower lightly...

hoʻokiloi

to feign throwing; to cause to throw; to attract someone's attention by throwing something at him, as a stone, leaf, flower

hoʻokilo₁

caus/sim of kilo₁, stargazer, reader of omens, seer, astrologer, necromancer; kind of looking glass (rare); to watch closely, spy, examine, look around, observe, forecast...

hoʻokilo₂

thin, wasted

hoʻokinakina

redup. of hoʻokina₁ to persist, do continually; incessant.

hoʻokina₁

to persist, do continually; incessant

hoʻokina₂

• to urge, compel,   • add one burden or command to another

hoʻokino

• to take shape,   • embody;   • to develop, as a puny infant;   • to take form, as a spirit

hoʻokino wailua

caus/sim of kino wailua, spirit of the dead; dead person, bodily remains, corpse...

hoʻokio₂

to spread out, project

hoʻokipi

to foment or act in revolt; rebellious

hoʻokiwi

to curve, bend; to stagger, etc

hoʻokiwikiwi

caus/sim of kiwikiwi, redup. of kiwi, horn of an animal; curved object; curved, bent; to pull obliquely; to reel and stagger...

hoʻokiʻe

caus/sim of kiʻe, same as kiʻekiʻe, height, tallness...

hoʻokiʻekiʻe

• to elevate; elevation,   • lift up;   • promote; promotion,   • proud, vain; conceit   • lording it over others, overbearing, disrespectful or disobedient to seniors

hoʻokiʻikiʻi

to cause to fetch, fetch, take hold of, seize, get

hoʻokiʻi₁

to send, have sent for; to take away

hoʻokiʻi₂

var. of hōkiʻi, thin, wasted

hoʻokiʻo

• to gather or settle, as water in a lake or pond;   • to cease flowing, of menstruation

hoʻokoa₁

brave; to cause bravery

hoʻokoa₂

to act as a soldier; to cause to be a soldier

hoʻokoene

to endeavor to walk in spite of weakness; mentally at rest after mental agitation, calmed. caus/sim of koene, to edge away, back away, creep, move cautiously and carefully, as a frightened or feeble person...

hoʻokoe₁

to save, reserve for later use, cause a remainder

hoʻokohana

to strip bare or naked

hoʻokohe

to fold pandanus matting to form a corner; to form a crease, groove, etc

hoʻokoho

to choose, elect, appoint

hoʻokohukohu

redup. of hoʻokohu; to pretend, impersonate, disguise, pose; affectation

hoʻokohu₁

• to assume a likeness to; pretense   • to presume to; presumption,   • to make advances, perhaps hypocritically;   • to take a fancy to; to have a crush on;

hoʻokohu₂

to appoint, commission, authorize

hoʻokoi

caus/sim of koi₁, to urge, implore, persuade, compel, require, insist on, ask insistently, demand, claim, pull; requirement...

hoʻokoko

to cause bloodshed; to blush (rare). fig., angry. cf. piʻi ka ʻula under piʻi.

hoʻokokoe

caus/sim of kokoe, redup. of koe₂ remain, exclude...

hoʻokokoke

to draw near, approach...

hoʻokokolo

caus/sim of kokolo, redup. of kolo, to creep...

hoʻokokonoiʻe

to rouse, encourage, incite

hoʻokokōhi₂

slow and stunted of growth.

hoʻokokōhi₃

black and threatening, as clouds before a storm.

hoʻokokōhi₄

forceful.

hoʻokola

to arouse sexual excitement, titillate

hoʻokolakola

caus/sim of kolakola, redup. of kola₁ hard, sexually excited...

hoʻokolekole

to cook rare; to skin, denude, bruise. caus/sim of kolekole₁, redup. of kole₁, rawness...

hoʻokolili

to flutter, wave

hoʻokolo

• to cause to creep, crawl;   • to follow a trail, track, clue;   • to trace to a source.   cf. hoʻokolokolo

hoʻokolohe

to do mischief, play pranks, etc.; to cause to be mischievous; to disturb, annoy; to do amusing things to create laughter; funny, humorous, comical, mischievous

hoʻokolokolo

to try in court, judge, investigate; judiciary; trial. cf. hale hoʻokolokolo court house.

hoʻokololio

caus/sim of kololio₁, same as kokololio, gust...

hoʻokololohe

to delay maliciously, to loiter sullenly, to dillydally in order to annoy; to not cooperate, sulk

hoʻokolono

to pretend not to hear, to feign deafness; indifferent

hoʻokolonuha

same as hoʻokananuha to cause sulkiness; dull of hearing.

hoʻokomokomo₁

to cause a spirit, usually evil, to possess; possession

hoʻokomokomo₂

to dress, as children

hoʻokomokomo₃

to file, put in

hoʻokomo₁

• to insert, put or let in,   • enter,   • pack,   • penetrate,   • import,   • sink into,   • deposit,   • install,   • admit.   see niho hoʻokomo, false tooth.

hoʻokomo₂

to dress another person

hoʻokoni

caus/sim of koni, to throb, pulsate, tingle, beat; to flutter, as the heart; to tug, as small fish on baited hook...

hoʻokono

to invite

hoʻokonokono

• to induce, entice, urge persistently, especially to urge someone to will him his property;   • to set dogs to fight.

hoʻokonā

caus/sim of konā, hard, unyielding, unfriendly, contemptuous, brusque, haughty...

hoʻokoʻakoʻa

caus/sim of koʻakoʻa₄, to stay or live in one place...

hoʻokoʻana

to settle, as dregs. fig., to put one's mind on a thing, concentrate upon

hoʻokoʻekoʻe

to make cold; to chill

hoʻokoʻele

caus/sim of koʻele, sound of tapping, as wood against wood; ticking, as of clock; thumping, trudging; rattling, as a window; crack of thunder; to tap, tick, thump, trudge, crackle, rattle; noisy, stormy...

hoʻokoʻi

same as hoʻokoʻikoʻi

hoʻokoʻikoʻi

to deepen the voice; to stress or emphasize in speech; to treat with severity, harshness, rigor; to burden, oppress

hoʻokoʻikoʻina

to stress; accent

hoʻokoʻo

prop with a pole, as a heavily laden banana plant, or a house to keep it from falling down; to pole, as a canoe

hoʻokoʻokoʻo

to push, brace, resist, lean back and brace oneself

hoʻokoʻū

caus/sim of koʻū, damp, moist. fig., thriving, prosperous...

hoʻokua

to persevere in work even when interest and pleasure have gone from it; burdensome

hoʻokua kapa₁

to make such an anvil

hoʻokua kapa₂

to form a boundary. lit., make stand border

hoʻokuakahi

to remove obstruction, interference; to clear the way, free

hoʻokuakaʻeo

var. of hoʻohuakeʻeo

hoʻokuakea

to bleach or whiten

hoʻokuakeʻeo

var. of hoʻohuakeʻeo hurt, angry, displeased, resentful...

hoʻokuakua

to heap up, as in banks; to make spaces between lines of stitching in quilting

hoʻokualana

to fail in strength. caus/sim of kualana₁, lazy, indolent, bored, fatigued; roving about without a chief to support one, as a "floater" (lana); to wander...

hoʻokuali

to whiten

hoʻokuanoʻo

to meditate, think deeply

hoʻokuanui

same as kuanui; to do a thing grudgingly...

hoʻokuapaʻa

to enslave, oppress, downtrodden, slaving

hoʻokuapuʻu

sit humped. caus/sim of kuapuʻu₁, hunchback; hunchbacked; hump, as of a camel...

hoʻokuapōlaʻo

to assemble tribute for a high chief

hoʻokuaʻiʻi

caus/sim of kuaʻiʻi, to flatter, cajole with flattery...

hoʻokuaʻāina

to act like one from the country; countrified, rustic

hoʻokuekuene

caus/sim of kuekuene, redup. of kuene, waiter; supervise...

hoʻokuene

caus/sim of all meanings of kuene:   • waiter, to wait on table;   • steward,   • treasurer;   • to supervise, put in order, arrange;   • to lay out, as measurements for a building.

hoʻokuewa

caus/sim of kuewa,   • vagabond,   • exile,   • wanderer; wandering,   • friendless,   • homeless,   • unstable...

hoʻokuhikuhi

rare caus/sim of kuhikuhi₁, to show, demonstrate, designate, prescribe, teach, give orders; to direct heiau ceremonies; one always giving orders; reference, direction, prescription, exponent; bossy...

hoʻokuhi₁

to teach the art of gesturing in the hula; to point, etc

hoʻokuhi₂

caus/sim of kuhi₂, to suppose, think, infer, presume, assume, expect, surmise, imagine...

hoʻokuke

to shoo, drive off, banish, expel, oust, evict, eject

hoʻokukule

caus/sim of kukule, inactive, listless, unresponsive, dejected...

hoʻokukuli

caus/sim of kukuli, knee; to kneel; to crouch or lie as an animal, with feet under the body...

hoʻokukuʻe

to imitate the walk of a clubfooted person

hoʻokula manu

to make into a bird place

hoʻokulana

to cause insecurity. caus/sim of kulana, to tilt, rock, reel, sway, toss and pitch; wobbly, shaky, unsteady. fig., insecure, hesitant...

hoʻokulaʻi

caus/sim of kulaʻi, to push over, knock down, overthrow, shove, push to one side; to brush off...

hoʻokuleana

to entitle, give or delegate right to possess; to give a responsibility; copyright (OO)

hoʻokuli

• deaf; to feign deafness.   • fig., to disobey; disobedient

hoʻokuloukulou

caus/sim of kuloukulou, redup. of kūlou, to bow the head, bend; to beckon with the head...

hoʻokulukulu

to cause to drip, distill. caus/sim of kulukulu₁, to drip, leak, drop: leaky...

hoʻokumakaia

caus/sim of kumakaia, traitor, turncoat; traitorous; to betray; to abuse one who has been kind to one...

hoʻokumu

to make a beginning, originate, create, commence, establish, inaugurate, initiate, institute, found, start...

hoʻokunu

to cause coughing; to pretend to cough

hoʻokuolo

caus/sim of kuolo₂, to tremble, as the voice; to shake, as with palsy; to vibrate, resonate, as a chanting voice...

hoʻokuoni

caus/sim of kuoni, to walk gently, slowly, softly; to lag behind...

hoʻokupa

to naturalize, make a citizen

hoʻokupaianaha

amaze. caus/sim of kupaianaha, surprising, strange, wonderful, amazing, extraordinary, unaccountable, marvelous; astonishing situation...

hoʻokupe

caus/sim of kupe₁, to stumble, twist the ankle. fig., to misstep, err in conduct...

hoʻokupuna

to take a person as a grandparent or grandaunt or granduncle because of affection; an adopted grandparent; to act as a grandparent

hoʻokupu₁

to cause growth, sprouting; to sprout

hoʻokupu₂

tribute, tax, ceremonial gift-giving to a chief as a sign of honor and respect; to pay such tribute; church offering

hoʻokuānea

to make lonely, barren. fig., to behave ignorantly; to cause boredom, dreariness; boring

hoʻokuʻakuʻai

to trade, buy and sell

hoʻokuʻekuʻe

to elbow, push with the elbows

hoʻokuʻekuʻemaka

to frown

hoʻokuʻemaka

to frown, scowl

hoʻokuʻia₂

checks and balances, as in government

hoʻokuʻikahi

to unite, reconcile, agree, make a peace treaty or armistice; armistice

hoʻokuʻikuʻi₁

redup. of hoʻokuʻi₃ to hit, pound, collide, crash, bump. fig., to hurt the felings...; to jostle.

hoʻokuʻina

same as kuʻina₂

hoʻokuʻi₁

• to join, connect, annex, weld, unite;   • to connect, as letters in forming a word;   • to spell;   • to dovetail, fit, splice;   • to add up, as numbers

hoʻokuʻi₂

zenith

hoʻokuʻi₃

to hit, pound, collide, crash, bump. fig., to hurt the felings

hoʻokuʻu kāua

let's stop

hoʻokuʻu maikaʻi

honorable discharge

hoʻokuʻu ʻia mai ka hopu ʻia ʻana

exemption from arrest

hoʻokuʻukuʻu₁

• lenient, permissive;   • to pay out, as a fishline.   caus/sim of kuʻukuʻu₁, to let down gradually, slack off a little at a time...

hoʻokuʻukuʻu₂

same as kuʻukuʻu₂

hoʻokā

to dash down, shatter, break, strike

hoʻokāhihi

to entrap, ensnare, entangle, etc

hoʻokāhiko

to dress someone in finery to adorn, decorate, deck, trim, array; to wear fine clothes

hoʻokāhikohiko

caus/sim of kāhikohiko₂, redup. of kāhiko, finery...

hoʻokāhili

to brush or fan gently. caus/sim of kāhili₁, feather standard, symbolic of royalty; segment of a rainbow standing like a shaft (also a sign of royalty); to brush, sweep, switch...

hoʻokāhinu

caus/sim of kāhinu, to rub with oil, grease, petroleum jelly; to anoint...

hoʻokāhiō

caus/sim of kāhiō, to lean to one side (kā-₂ + hinu). cf. the more common hiō...

hoʻokāholo

to cause to hurry; to speed, hurry

hoʻokāholoholo

redup. of hoʻokāholo, to exercise, as a horse; to practice racing; skittering in fishing

hoʻokāhuli

caus/sim of kāhuli₁, to change, alter...; pervert.

hoʻokāhāhā

surprising, astonishing; to cause astonishment

hoʻokākoʻo

caus/sim of kākoʻo, to uphold, support, favor, assist, prop up; to bind, as with a sash or belt; support, aid, recommendation, girdle...

hoʻokākāuha

• to stretch forth,   • to make rigid;   • to oppress;   • to flex muscles, as in desire to show off one's strength

hoʻokālai

• caus/sim of kālai, to carve, cut, hew, engrave, hoe; to divide, as land; to shape a canoe   • fig. an enterprise or intellectual policy; to plan, formulate, budget...

hoʻokālaʻe

to cause to clear; to become clear

hoʻokālele

to cause to support; stress. see hilinaʻi

hoʻokālilo

to cause death; to have the appearance of death

hoʻokālilolilo

caus/sim of kālilolilo, redup. of kālilo dying, at death's door; to lie hovering between life and death...

hoʻokāluhe

to pretend to droop, flirt, etc.; to cause drooping

hoʻokāluli

to cause to bend and sway

hoʻokāmaka

male homosexuality; to practice such.

hoʻokāmakamaka

to ask forgiveness, to seek restoration of friendship.

hoʻokāmau₁

caus/sim of kāmau₁, to keep on, continue, persevere, last, add a little more...

hoʻokāmau₂

to eat, as ʻinamona relish. caus/sim of kāmau₂, to drink, especially intoxicants, to eat (rare) to your health (something like prosit)...

hoʻokāmaʻa

to put on shoes, furnish shoes

hoʻokāmaʻe

caus/sim of kāmaʻe, to feign friendliness and good will when there may be hatred; insincere, hypocritical...

hoʻokāmoku

caus/sim of kāmoku, to break, cut, as land...

hoʻokānalua

to cause doubt.

hoʻokāne

• to behave as a male;   • masculine;   • to adopt a man as a platonic friend, said of a woman (the relationship cements friendship between the relatives of both participants);   • to offer to become husband or sweetheart.   cf. ho‘owahine.

hoʻokānāwai

to impose a law, especially to vow not to associate with certain persons or places until certain conditions are fulfilled.

hoʻokāoʻo

to strut.

hoʻokāpae

to cause to turn off, push aside, parry, thrust away, refute an argument.

hoʻokāpekepeke

caus/sim of kāpekepeke, to walk unsteadily, totter; insecure, unsteady. fig., doubtful, uncertain, vague, inconstant, fickle...

hoʻokāpili

caus/sim of kāpili, to build, put together, put on (as glasses), fit together, set (as precious stones), mend, fix, repair, shingle, join, plaster, unite, attach blame, shoe (as a horse)...

hoʻokāpuhi

same as kāpuhi;   • to feed an eel;   • to nurse or care for a child or person.   • fig., clever, smart.

hoʻokāpule

to ripen, fatten.

hoʻokāpōʻai

to rotate, revolve, as in a hula.

hoʻokāwala

to make sparse; to eat sparingly; to talk unintelligibly.

hoʻokāwele

to wipe, pretend to wipe.

hoʻokāwili

caus/sim of kāwili, to mix ingredients, blend; to ensnare birds, as with lime; entwined, interwoven, interlaced...

hoʻokāwōwō

to roar, as a wind or waterfall.

hoʻokāʻalo

to pass to and fro, to cause to pass

hoʻokāʻau

• witty, clever, funny, entertaining, humorous;   • to pass the time pleasantly; entertaining time

hoʻokāʻeuʻeu

to encourage and bestir to action. also hōkāʻeuʻeu

hoʻokāʻili

to tug and pull as though to snatch, but not with great force, as in playing with a kitten; to cause a snatching, etc.

hoʻokāʻoi

to progress, go ahead, improve, better; progressive.

hoʻokāʻokoʻa

• to separate from others,   • keep away,   • abstain.

hoʻokēkē

to crowd... redup. of hoʻokē₁, to crowd, elbow, push aside, jostle, struggle, oppress, shun, scorn, protest...

hoʻokēāmaka

selfish, ungracious, as one eating in the presence of others; partial; partiality.

hoʻokēʻē

to shun, slight, avoid.

hoʻokē₁

• to crowd, elbow, push aside, jostle,   • shun, scorn,   • oppress,   • struggle,   • protest.   • fig., to beset with difficulties.

hoʻokī

to cause to shoot; to sick on, as a dog; to make a cat spit; to snort; emitted. caus/sim of kī₃, to shoot or aim, as with a gun; to squirt water, as with a syringe; to blow from the mouth...

hoʻokīhā

caus/sim of kīhā₁, belch, burp; to belch or burp...

hoʻokīkeʻe

to go zigzag

hoʻokīkeʻekeʻe

caus/sim of kīkeʻekeʻe, zigzag...

hoʻokīkiʻi

caus/sim of kīkiʻi₁, to lean back; to tilt, heel, as a ship; to stretch out, extend...

hoʻokīkē

ready with a rude retort, answer.

hoʻokīkī

caus/sim of kīkī, redup. of kī, to shoot, as a gun; to incite or sick, as a dog; to spout...

hoʻokīlepa

caus/sim of kīlepa₁, to float in the wind, to flutter, flap, flip...

hoʻokīmō

caus/sim of kīmō, to pound, bruise, mash, as with stick or stone; to smash, break into bits; to dub out the inside of a canoe log with an adze, tamping and smoothing the surface; to crack, as nuts...

hoʻokīnohi₁

caus/sim of kīnohi, decorated, spotted, ornamented; decoration, ornamentation...

hoʻokīnohi₂

to adorn, add color

hoʻokīnā

to cause defect, disaster, etc

hoʻokīpehi

caus/sim of kīpehi, to pelt, throw at. fig., to assail with rough language, speak harshly...

hoʻokīpulu

to enrich or fertilize, as soil

hoʻokīpupū

caus/sim of kīpupū, to hinder, draw back; to jerk and start, as an automobile...

hoʻokō

• executive;   • to fulfill; to carry out, as a contract;   • to enforce, execute, confirm, construe, interpret, decree;   • to award, as land;   • to probate, perform, satisfy;   • to transact, accomplish;   • to cause a conception;   • confirmation, award...

hoʻokō kauoha

executor of an estate (o-class)

hoʻokōheo

caus/sim of kōheo₁, to show off, parade, strut...

hoʻokōhi

Cc

hoʻokōkē

caus/sim of kōkē, to strike, hit, punish...

hoʻokōkōliʻi

to rise, as a thick black cloud

hoʻokōwā

to separate by a space

hoʻokōʻehaʻeha

to cause heat. fig., to distress

hoʻokūamuamu

caus/sim of kūamuamu, to revile, blaspheme, curse, swear, damn, insult; to chant a curse or reviling song...

hoʻokūkū₁

• contest, game, match; to hold a contest, compete,   • compare;   • to place evenly, as canoes about to race (hoʻokūkū like i nā waʻa)

hoʻokūkū₂

to fit, as a garment; a fitting

hoʻokūkū₃

to cause to shake; to shake, bounce

hoʻokūkū₄

uncomfortably full, as after overeating

hoʻokūlanalana

caus/sim of kūlanalana, unsteady, tottering, unsettled, wavering, wobbly, undecided, uncertain, fluctuating...

hoʻokūlia

caus/sim of kūlia₂, to try, strive...

hoʻokūlike

to conform, make alike

hoʻokūlipo

caus/sim of kūlipo, dark, dank, deep, as a cave. fig. extremely, intense, much...

hoʻokūlou

to bow down, cause to bow, humiliate; to subdue, as an enemy

hoʻokūmene

flatten. caus/sim of kūmene, blunt, flat, of the nose...

hoʻokūmole

to smooth, make even, as stones in a wall

hoʻokūnaʻi

caus/sim of kūnaʻi, same as kūnaʻina, to conquer, push over; conquest...

hoʻokūnānā

caus/sim of kūnānā₁, puzzled, stumped, at wit's end, hesitating, undecided, bewildered; uncertain. lit., stand look...

hoʻokūoʻe

caus/sim of kūoʻe, to saunter, trudge...

hoʻokūpaoa

to emit fragrance; fragrant

hoʻokūpaʻa

• to remain loyal, firm, etc.; loyal, steady.   • to persist,   • perform,   • make fast,   • strengthen, fortify,   • establish;

hoʻokūpene

caus/sim of kūpene, permanent, stationary; to reside long in one place...

hoʻokūpikiʻō

caus/sim of kūpikiʻō, agitated, raging, turbulent, as wind or storm. fig., mentally disturbed...

hoʻokūpono

to behave uprightly; to conform to; to go straight toward, face toward, proceed correctly

hoʻokūpouli

anguish. caus/sim of kūpouli, befuddled, stupefied, mentally clouded, dazed, carried away with emotion, stricken...

hoʻokūpū

to thicken. caus/sim of kūpū, thick, as gravy, or moisture-laden lomi fish; to jell...

hoʻokūwaho

to stay or keep on the outside

hoʻokūwō

to pretend to howl. caus/sim of kūwō, see uwō, var. spelling of uō, bellow, roar...

hoʻokūāhua

caus/sim of kūāhua, heap, pile; heaped or piled up; rising up, as a whale's back above water. lit., back heap (āhua)...

hoʻokūākino

to change form; transubstantiation

hoʻokūāʻino

to influence one into bad behavior; evil

hoʻokūō

to pretend to howl. caus/sim of kūō, to cry loudly, as with joy or pain; to howl, as a dog; to roar, as a lion...

hoʻokūʻike

to show beforehand; to recognize at sight

hoʻokūʻiʻo

convinced; to prove, verify; to insist on the truth of a matter

hoʻokūʻoi

similar to ʻoi₂ best, superior, superb, main, prominent, exceeding...

hoʻokūʻokoʻa

to establish independence, make independent

hoʻokūʻono

to indent, form a bay, cranny, or corner

hoʻokūʻonoʻono

to prosper

hoʻokūʻoʻi

caus/sim of kūʻoʻi, same as kūpāʻoʻi, to limp...

hoʻokūʻē

to cause opposition, to stir up resistance; to oppose, clash

hoʻokūʻēʻē

to stir up opposition or disagreement

hoʻokū₁

to produce a resemblance, likeness

hoʻolae

to pretend to be wise; to act smart; pretentious

hoʻolaha

• to spread abroad, publish, advertise, broadcast,   • disseminate, distribute, circulate,   • make known, promulgate, increase, propagate;   • advertisement, propagation, publicity

hoʻolahi

to cause thinness, frailty; thin, frail (as cloth, paper)

hoʻolaholaho

same as laholaho; miserly; to hoard

hoʻolaka

to tame, domesticate; to treat with kindness, as a child or animal, so as to familiarize with one

hoʻolakalaka

redup. of hoʻolaka to tame

hoʻolaki

to bring luck; lucky...

hoʻolako

• to supply,   • equip,   • provide,   • furnish,   • enrich

hoʻolako kaua

to supply arms, arm, fortify

hoʻolakolako

redup. of hoʻolako to supply, equip, provide, furnish, enrich.

hoʻolala

to turn aside

hoʻolalahū

to cause to swell

hoʻolalau₁

• to deceive, as in actions to conceal what one is about;   • to divert, as a child from the matter he is crying about;   • roundabout.

hoʻolalau₂

• to cause to wander, lead astray;   • to procrastinate, dillydally, kill time;   • to digress or wander in speech, perhaps to avoid a subject...

hoʻolalawe

to produce thrills, itching

hoʻolalaʻō

to insist on accompanying

hoʻolale

• to hasten, hurry;   • to incite, provoke,   • to propose, to urge, suggest strongly, encourage

hoʻolalelale

redup. of hoʻolale; to inspire, incite, rouse

hoʻolali

to cause greasiness, glitter

hoʻolanakila

to cause to triumph; overbearing or impudent, as of a spoiled child unafraid of punishment, or of a most privileged, unassailable person

hoʻolanalana₁

redup. of hoʻolana

hoʻolanalana₂

to make lashings, to lash

hoʻolanamanaʻo

hopeful, encouraging. (Kel. 15) see hoʻolana under lana₁

hoʻolana₁

same as lana₃, to be aware of noises as one wakes...

hoʻolana₂

disobedient, willful

hoʻolana₃

• to cause to float, launch;   • to right a canoe.   • fig., to launch a project;

hoʻolana₄

• cheerful, unworrying, hopeful; to cheer up, encourage, be of good cheer;   • to lighten grief, as by taking a mourner on a trip and away from the grave of the one he mourns.   (Mat. 14.27)

hoʻolanilani₁

redup. of hoʻolani; to treat as a chief; to claim relationship to a chief, especially unwarranted

hoʻolanilani₂

to exalt, praise redup. of hoʻolani to exalt, praise.

hoʻolani₁

to treat as a chief; to render homage to a chief; to act as a chief; to enjoy the position and prestige of a high chief

hoʻolani₂

same as hoʻolanilani₂ to exalt, praise...

hoʻolaoa

to fish for eels with eel-catching stick.

hoʻolapalapa

to cause to blaze, boil, etc

hoʻolapa₁

• to rise up;   • to boil; to cook by boiling   • to swell, as a blister;   • to spread or blaze, as fire or volcanic eruption;   • to excite or flare, as with passion;   • to animate;

hoʻolapa₃

to form a ridge; ridge

hoʻolapu

to pretend to be a ghost, as children on Halloweʻen

hoʻolapulapu

caus/sim of lapulapu, to pick up, as sticks for fuel; to collect, gather; to handle, tie...

hoʻolau pala

to show signs of fading, of a leaf; to show signs of failing health; also same as lau pala

hoʻolauaʻe

to cherish, as a beloved memory

hoʻolaukanaka

to have many people about one; to dispel loneliness with people

hoʻolaukoa

same as above

hoʻolaukōnā

to treat cruelly, mercilessly; to oppress; to cause hatred

hoʻolaulaha

to spread, circulate, publicize, make known

hoʻolauleʻa₁

celebration, festival, gathering for a celebration, large party; satisfaction; to hold a celebration, to celebrate.

hoʻolauleʻa₂

to reconcile, restore peace or friendship, appease ((Kin. 32:20) ); to preserve friendship and good will; to be at peace with; to seek to please.

hoʻolaulima

to get to cooperate

hoʻolaumania

to smooth; to spread out smoothly and evenly; to free of bumps or lumps

hoʻolauna

to introduce one person to another; to be friendly...

hoʻolaunea

caus/sim of launea, bare, as of leaves...

hoʻolaupaʻi

to make an abundance, supply, cause an increase, reproduce

hoʻolauwili

to cause fickleness, change, twist

hoʻolau₁

to use a lau

hoʻolau₂

a bundle of grass or ferns set in water to attract shrimps or ʻoʻopu fish; a net was placed under this bundle, and the fish shaken into it.

hoʻolau₃

to grow leaves; to leaf out

hoʻolau₄

to make numerous; to assemble, as of numerous persons or animals; numerous

hoʻolawa

to supply, apportion sufficiently, equip

hoʻolawe

• to cause to take,   • pretend to take,   • deduct, deduction,   • subtract; subtraction,   • minus

hoʻolawehala

• accusation; to accuse;   • to grow worse, of a sickness, especially an insignificant one

hoʻolaʻa

to consecrate, dedicate, sanctify, bless, hallow

hoʻolaʻa hale

dedication of a house; to dedicate a house

hoʻolaʻa waʻa

blessing of a canoe launching; to dedicate a canoe

hoʻolaʻalaʻa

var. of hoʻolāʻau, insist, urge...

hoʻolaʻe

to clear up, brighten

hoʻolaʻi

• to cause to be still;   • to poise aloft, as a bird;   • to quiet, as a mob;   • to cease talking;   • calm; peaceful, quiet

hoʻolaʻilaʻi

caus/sim of laʻilaʻi₁, light-hearted...

hoʻolaʻo

to get something in the eye

hoʻolehelehe kiʻi

caus/sim of lehelehe kiʻi, indolent talker; to do nothing but talk. lit., image lips...

hoʻolehelehe nui

sullen, obstinate, sulky, pouting

hoʻolehu

to reduce to ashes, cremate

hoʻolehua

swift, expert, strong

hoʻolehulehu

to make a multitude; to increase into many

hoʻoleia₂

pas/imp. of hoʻolei to cast, throw, heave, toss, pitch; to put a lei on oneself or on someone else

hoʻoleilei

redup. of hoʻolei, to scatter, toss about, swing, dandle, as a baby; to juggle; juggling

hoʻoleina

place to throw things, as a trash heap

hoʻoleinamoa

couch (probably, from hoʻoleina moe, place to sleep)

hoʻoleinawao

a variety of wild taro. lit., thrown [into] wilderness

hoʻolei₁

• to cast, throw, heave, toss, pitch;   • to stretch,   • send

hoʻolele kī

A game played only at Malamakī, Puna, Hawaiʻi. A player would hold a ti leaf in his hand, chant ʻO kēlā kī, ʻo kēia kī, na Kamohoaliʻi kaʻu kī, lele!. That ti, this ti, my ti is for Kamohoaliʻi, fly! If the wind was right and the chant correctly rendered, the ti would fly off and return to the sender. lit., make the ti fly

hoʻolele lupe

to fly a kite. (-lele lupe)

hoʻoleleaka

to project, as magic lantern slides

hoʻolelekē

a game of tossing ti leaves into Malama Crater at Puna, Hawaiʻi, and dedicating them to Ka-moho-aliʻi

hoʻolelele

caus/sim of lelele, to beat swiftly, as the heart; to frisk, hop about, romp, caper; inconstant, promiscuous; at intervals, here and there...

hoʻolele₁

[Note: the hoʻolele entries are listed altogether under lele₁ in P&E.]   • to cause to fly;   • to fly, as a kite.

hoʻolele₂

to disembark.

hoʻolele₃

to embark, as on a project.

hoʻolele₄

to palpitate, as the heart

hoʻolele₅

to enlarge or project, as pictures.

hoʻolena

to stretch, pull back, as a bow

hoʻolepe

to cut, tear; to stir, as water

hoʻolepo

dirty, to soil. caus/sim of lepo₁, dirt, earth, ground, filth, rubbish, silt, soil, excrement; dirty, soiled...

hoʻolewalewa₁

same as lewalewa₁ to float, dangle, swing, hang, oscillate...; to cause to dangle

hoʻolewalewa₂

kind of fish net suspended from a canoe in the deep sea

hoʻolewa₁

to float, as a cloud; to lift up and carry, as on a stretcher; to suspend

hoʻolewa₂

to rotate the hips in dancing, sway. see song under Hōpoe₂.

hoʻolewa₃

funeral

hoʻoleʻa

to cause pleasure, joy; to praise, please, delight, extol; praising, eulogistic

hoʻoleʻoleʻo

agitated, stormy, tempestuous; rising and falling as waves; disturbing confusing; uneven, as a pavement or a wrinkled mat. also hōleʻoleʻo

hoʻolihi

to gird. caus/sim of lihi₂, small quantity, particle, a little bit, minutia; slight...

hoʻolikelike

redup. of hoʻolike, same as the more common hoʻohālike, to compare, contrast, make alike, resemble, copy...

hoʻolike₁

same as the more common hoʻohālike, to compare, contrast, make alike, resemble, copy...; to equalize, make alike, translate

hoʻolikiliki

to tighten

hoʻolilina

heir, inheritance, legacy, estate, heritage, bequest; successor (so used in the official English version of the Constitution of 1852, Article 25). also hoʻīlina.

hoʻoliliʻu

caus/sim of liliʻu₁, scorching, burning, smarting, as salt in a raw wound or pain in the eyes...

hoʻolili₁

to provoke jealousy; jealous

hoʻolili₂

rippled surface of the sea, as caused by fish; undulation or vibration of light in the hot sun; to ripple, vibrate, undulate; to close or blink the eyes in bright glare. also holili.

hoʻolilo₁

to transfer, assign, as in legal transactions; to export; change, reduction, as in fractions

hoʻolilo₂

expense, expenditure; to spend; to lose; to buy or sell

hoʻolina

to scar

hoʻoliuliu

to prepare

hoʻoliʻiliʻi

to decrease, lessen, make small

hoʻoliʻoʻliʻo

caus/sim of liʻoliʻo₁, bright, dazzling, dazzled...

hoʻoliʻuliʻu

to cause a delay, prolong, procrastinate

hoʻoloa

to stretch, extend, prolong, lengthen

hoʻoloaʻa

to obtain, find, get; product, answer, etc

hoʻolohelohe

caus/sim of lohelohe₁, to listen carefully, eavesdrop...

hoʻolohi

to delay, make slow, detain; to go slowly, procrastinate, dillydally lag

hoʻolohilohi

redup. of hoʻolohi, to delay, make slow, detain; to go slowly, procrastinate, dillydally lag...

hoʻoloio

• to ask the lawyer;   • to show off knowledge;   • to ask bewildering questions as a lawyer might

hoʻoloko

to insinuate, suggest, implant a thought, either good or bad

hoʻoloku

• to pour, as rain;   • to disturb;   • agitated

hoʻolokuloku

• downpour,   • to be angry.   redup. of hoʻoloku

hoʻolola

caus/sim of lola₁, drooping, hanging downward; droopy, sluggish, lazy, idle...

hoʻololalola

caus/sim of lolalola, redup. of lola₁, drooping...

hoʻolole

caus/sim of lole₂, to unfold, turn inside out, reverse; to strip or peel off, as bark; to skin, flay; to scalp; to handle, turn over with the hands...

hoʻololi

to change, convert, exchange, alter, transform, take a new form, amend; amendment, change...

hoʻololia

caus/sim of lolia,

hoʻololiloli

caus/sim of loliloli₁, changing, turning, changeable...

hoʻololoa

to lengthen

hoʻololohe₁

to listen carefully; to strain the ear to hear

hoʻololohe₂

caus/sim of lolohe₂, stubborn; hard to move, as a rock...

hoʻololohi

similar to hoʻolohi

hoʻololōiele

caus/sim of lolōiele, dull...

hoʻolono

• to listen, hear,   • obey; obedient,   • attentive...

hoʻolonolono

redup. of hoʻolono

hoʻolou

to hook, catch with a hook; to put on a hook, as bait

hoʻoloua

rare caus/sim of loua₁, pas/imp. of lou₁, hook...

hoʻoloʻihi

to lengthen, extend, prolong

hoʻoloʻu

to droop. caus/sim of loʻu, to overhang, as a cliff; to bend over, as with grief or laughter; bent over, as a laden branch...

hoʻoluahine

to act or dress like an old lady; to try to be like one

hoʻoluaiele

caus/sim of luaiele₂, swaying...

hoʻolualuaʻi

redup. of hoʻoluaʻi

hoʻoluana

caus/sim of luana, to be at leisure, enjoy pleasant sorroundings and associates, live in comfort and ease, enjoy oneself, relax, be content...

hoʻoluaʻi

• emetic; causing vomiting; to cause a vomiting,   • to feign vomiting;   • to gag;   • to drive out people

hoʻolua₁

to bake in the oven. cf. hoʻolua under lua₃ and kālua

hoʻolua₂

to do twice, repeat, do over and over; to bake twice, as food in the oven,

hoʻoluhe

caus/sim of luhe, to hang down, overhang, sag, droop, wilt, wither...

hoʻoluhi hewa

to oppress, harass, burden to no use

hoʻoluhiluhi

to make tired, disturbed, etc.; to wear one down with work. cf. hoʻoluhi

hoʻoluli

to rock, as a child; to shake, as a drink; to sway. cf. mōhai hoʻoluli

hoʻoluliluli

redup. of hoʻoluli, to rock, as a child...; to agitate

hoʻoluluhi

to make sleepy; drowsy

hoʻoluluʻu

same as hoʻoluʻuluʻu; to cause to bend down, to load heavily

hoʻolulu₁

• to lie quietly in calm water, as a ship in port;   • to be calm;   • to gather together, as objects,   • or to wait, as for transportation.

hoʻolulu₂

to chum, for fish; this type of fishing and fisherman

hoʻoluna

to appoint as foreman, officer, etc.; to act as officer

hoʻolupalupa

to cause to flourish; lush. see nupanupa

hoʻoluʻa₁

to bear many children

hoʻoluʻa₂

to lay an egg, as of a chicken

hoʻoluʻe₁

same as hoʻoluʻa. to loosen, let down, as hair; to unfurl, as a flag; to hang down

hoʻoluʻe₂

to shape a log for a canoe, as at bow and stern

hoʻoluʻua

pas/imp. of hoʻoluʻu to dip, immerse, dye

hoʻoluʻuluʻu₁

to cause sorrow, grief; to oppress, load down

hoʻoluʻuluʻu₂

redup. of hoʻoluʻu; to set a fish trap

hoʻoluʻu₁

to dip, immerse, dye

hoʻoluʻu₂

dip, immerse, dye

hoʻolāhui₁

to form a nation, race, etc

hoʻolāhui₂

to cause to be consecrated; to taboo

hoʻolālani

to place in rows

hoʻolālau

to cause to seize, etc.; to tackle

hoʻolālei

to gather together, as flowers

hoʻolālā₁

to cause to branch out, as by topping; to branch out,

hoʻolālā₂

• to lay out land areas;   • to mark with lines;   • to plan, make plans or projects.

hoʻolāpeʻe

caus/sim of lāpeʻe, bent, crooked, doubled up; curled up, like the tail of a pig; coiled, flexed...

hoʻolāpuʻu

caus/sim of lāpuʻu, bunched up, humped up, curled up; crooked, bent over, arched; head bent forward, as of a bucking horse...

hoʻolāʻau₁

to form mature wood, as of a shrub; to gather in trees, as birds

hoʻolāʻau₂

• to insist, urge persistently;   • continuously, persistently, endlessly

hoʻolā₁

parsimonious, miserly.

hoʻolā₂

gray tapa, tapa in general.

hoʻolā₃

to sun, put out in the sunlight ...

hoʻolīʻō

to frighten, cause to shy, leap

hoʻolōkahi

• to bring about unity;   • to make peace and unity;   • to be in agreement

hoʻolōlō

to pretend paralysis, stupidity; to pretend to be asleep

hoʻomae

to cause to wilt, fade; to fade

hoʻomahamaha

caus/sim of mahamaha₃, to show or feel pleasure, love, affection; affectionate...

hoʻomahana₁

vacation, rest

hoʻomahana₂

to warm, create warmth, heat

hoʻomahiki

to cause to leap, jump, etc

hoʻomahola

to unroll. caus/sim of mahola, to spread out; to smooth out, as a cloth to dry; to extend, expand.

hoʻomahu

to eat just a little to allay hunger, as while waiting for a feast

hoʻomahua

to mock (Hal. 2.4) ; to spy, watch, as a cat watching a mouse

hoʻomahuakala

to show disbelief, skepticism; to ridicule, mock, as beliefs, cynical, iconoclast, irreligious, skeptical

hoʻomahuka

• to chase,   • drive away,   • assist or help to escape

hoʻomahuʻi

caus/sim of mahuʻi, to guess, suppose, surmise, expect, suspect, assume, imagine; clue...

hoʻomahāha

to prepare soil for gardening, to make earth soft and fine

hoʻomailani

caus/sim of mailani,   • to extol, praise,   • treat as a chief or great favorite,   • indulge, spoil, favor...

hoʻomainaina

to cause anger; to anger

hoʻomaka hinu

to conceal annoyance or or anger by pretense of cheerfulness. caus/sim of maka hinu, bright face, cheerful look...

hoʻomaka hou

to begin again

hoʻomakahehi

caus/sim of makahehi, admiration, desire for, wonder; amazement; attractive, entrancing; to admire; be entangled...

hoʻomakakī

to look at with hatred; to plan revenge or evil

hoʻomakala

caus/sim of makala₁, to loosen, undo, untie, open a little, liberate or set at liberty; to remit, as a debt; to forgive; to free of defilement or uncleanness; to open or unfold, as a flower...

hoʻomakamaka

to befriend, be a friend to, make a friend, cause to be friends. cf. hoʻokāmakamaka

hoʻomakanahele

to let a garden grow wild; wild, untamed

hoʻomakapō

to cause blindness, to feign blindness, to blindfold

hoʻomakapū

to frown, look with disapproval

hoʻomakauliʻi₁

• to economize;   • thrifty, saving, economical, frugal;   • to desire, covet.

hoʻomakauliʻi₂

to seek every detail; to find out even the smallest things, scrutinize.

hoʻomakawela

to treat like a kauā makawela.

hoʻomakaʻauʻa

to hang moist, as undried tapa, over a line or drying rack (haka), so that the edges will correspond and that a fixed crease will form

hoʻomakaʻeo

to look at with anger, to avoid looking at because of anger; not to recognize because of anger

hoʻomakaʻu

to frighten, scare, terrify, make afraid; fear; to pretend to fear

hoʻomakaʻua

to frighten, scare. caus/sim of makaʻua, pas/imp. of makaʻu, fear; frightened, afraid...

hoʻomakaʻē

caus/sim of makaʻē, to look at with disfavor; to look askance...

hoʻomake

• to kill deliberately, execute;   • to pretend to be dead;   • to let die;   • to let diminish, grow faint.

hoʻomakekeʻeo

resent, resentful

hoʻomakemake

to cause or feign desire

hoʻomakeʻe

caus/sim of makeʻe, covetous, greedy, desirous to have; to prize, have affection for...

hoʻomakili₁

to open a crack; to crack

hoʻomakoa

to act bravely, brave

hoʻomakua kāne

• to act as or claim to be a makua kāne;   • to address or treat as a makua kāne

hoʻomakuahine

• to act as or claim to be a makuahine;   • to treat as a makuahine

hoʻomakua₁

• to grow into maturity, mature;   • to act the part of a parent;   • to foster, adopt, as a child;   • to call or treat as a parent;   • to address as parent, aunt, or uncle one related by affection rather than by blood or adoption

hoʻomakua₂

to become established or permanent

hoʻomakākiu

to spy, watch, reconnoiter

hoʻomala

to cause such aching

hoʻomalae

to feign friendship

hoʻomalamala

to leave so as to sour, as mashed sweet potato to be eaten as poi; to ferment

hoʻomalau

skeptical, unbelieving, irreverent

hoʻomalauea

caus/sim of malauea, lazy...

hoʻomale

to perform the marriage ceremony, to marry off; to force into marriage

hoʻomalele

to scatter, distribute

hoʻomalihia

pas/imp. of mali₂, to tie, as bait to a hook...

hoʻomalihini

to be or act as a stranger, guest; to reveal that guests are coming, as by omens

hoʻomaliko

to refuse respect, discredit

hoʻomalimali

to flatter (Hal. 78.36) , wheedle; to mollify with soft words or a gift; to soothe, quiet

hoʻomaliu

to cause to heed, heed

hoʻomalohi

sluggish; to act drowsy, sleepy; to cause drowsiness, sleepiness

hoʻomaloka

same as maloka, skeptical, unbelieving, impious

hoʻomalolo₁

to cease work for a time, recess; to adjourn temporarily. cf. lā hoʻomalolo

hoʻomalolo₂

caus/sim of malolo₂, low, of a tide...

hoʻomaloʻo₁

• to dry out, dehydrate, blot;   • to season, as lumber;

hoʻomaloʻo₂

tracing, as of genealogy.

hoʻomaluhi

same as hoʻomāluhiluhi

hoʻomaluhia

to cause or give peace, protect; to arbitrate between warring parties

hoʻomalule

• to make lax, limp, weak;   • to relax, weaken, enfeeble;   • to shed a hard shell, as of a crab;   • to change from a caterpillar into a butterfly;   • to metamorphose. cf. lāʻau hoʻomalule kino

hoʻomalumalu

to overshadow, cast a shadow; shade; darken, as by a cloud

hoʻomalu₁

• to bring under the care and protection of, to protect;   • to keep quiet, still, as during taboos or (modern) for peaceful meditation during hoʻoponopono family therapy;   • to restrict, confine, quarantine. lit., protected. cf. hale hoʻomalu, luna hoʻomalu.

hoʻomalu₂

• to judge,   • rule over, govern,   • to preside, as at a meeting; to call to order;   • make peace between warring parties;   • to suspend, as a license;   • probation. see malu₁ shade, shelter, protection, peace, control, strength (Kanl. 33.25) ; shaded, peaceful, quiet, safe; protected by taboo; reserved, held apart; taboo; the stillness and awe of taboo.

hoʻomamae

to weaken. caus/sim of mamae, sickly, listless; weakening or withering effect of pain; wan or pale, as after illness; crestfallen, as after enthusiasm is squelched...

hoʻomamao

to keep away, keep one's distance; to go far; to remove someone to a distance

hoʻomamau

to cause to get stuck, to stall

hoʻomanakiʻi

idolatrous; to worship images

hoʻomanakā

same as manakā; to cause boredom

hoʻomanamana

to impart mana, as to idols or objects; to deify; superstitious

hoʻomanana

to stretch out, extend; to loosen, as a grip

hoʻomanawaleʻa

caus/sim of manawaleʻa, a generous heart, charity, alms, donation; to give freely and willingly; gratis, free, benevolent, beneficent...

hoʻomanawanui

patience, steadfastness, fortitude; to have patience, fortitude; patient, steadfast, courageous and persevering; to try one's patience.

hoʻomanaʻo

to remember, recall, commemorate, reflect deeply on, meditate. see ʻōlelo hoʻomanaʻo.

hoʻomana₁

to place in authority, empower, authorize

hoʻomana₂

• to worship;   • religion, sect

hoʻomana₃

callus; callous. Kauaʻi

hoʻomanewa

same as hoʻomānewanewa to display violent grief...

hoʻomaneʻo

to cause to itch; to tickle, ticklish

hoʻomania₁

to cause sleepiness, drowsiness, drowsy, sleepy

hoʻomanoa

to increase

hoʻomanoninia

caus/sim of manoninia, pas/imp. of manoni mixed feelings as of joy and sorrow, unhappiness...

hoʻomano₁

• to increase;   • to do repeatedly or persistently

hoʻomano₂

a name given to the kāmanomano plant when used in hana aloha, love sorcery

hoʻomanuheʻu

caus/sim of manuheʻu, bruised, injured, damaged, dented; in bad condition, as an old building; to bruise, damage, injure, deface; to bite with the teeth and peel off, as bark...

hoʻomanunu

to break out, as with a skin eruption

hoʻomanō

to behave as a shark; to eat ravenously; to pursue women ardently

hoʻomaoe

• to ask indirectly;   • to hint or suggest, as in asking;   • to imply, allude

hoʻomaopopo

• to understand, cause to understand, pay attention in order to understand;   • make plain or clear, tell clearly, to certify, inform,   • remember, recollect, recall, remind,   • realize, ascertain, recognize, discover   • think about,   • believe in,   • take care of...   (Depending on context, many translations are possible; for substitution of maopopo for hoʻomaopopo see (Gram. 4.4))...

hoʻomauakala

var. of hoʻomahuakala.

hoʻomauhala

to bear a grudge, cherish revenge

hoʻomauhaʻalina

to oppress, burden

hoʻomauleho

to cause calluses; to oppress, overwork

hoʻomaumau

redup. of hoʻomau to continue, keep on, persist...

hoʻomauʻu

to give nothing of value (probably related to the fig. meaning of mauʻu Hilo, Hilo grass (Paspalum conjugatum), "...it's just Hilo grass."

hoʻomau₂

to make fast, as an anchor in sand; to snag; to cause to be retarded, grounded, wagered, stopped

hoʻomau₃

to mate for the purpose of having children

hoʻomau₄

a variety of sweet potato

hoʻomaʻa

to practice, gain experience or skill, become accustomed (less used than hoʻomaʻamaʻa)

hoʻomaʻalea

caus/sim of maʻalea, cunning, craft, trickery, deceit, guile; cunning, crafty, artful, deceitful, sly, shrewd; skillful; accustomed, skilled...

hoʻomaʻalili

• to cause to cool;   • appease, soothe, quiet,   • pacify, assuage anger or grief

hoʻomaʻamau

to become accustomed, familiar

hoʻomaʻau

• to persecute,   • offend,   • injure,   • bully, tease, torment.

hoʻomaʻawe

to make a tracing; footprint, track, slight path; to make small fibers or threads

hoʻomaʻewa

to reproach, sneer at, mimic, ridicule, desecrate, jeer, mock, scorn.

hoʻomaʻi

to cause or feign sickness

hoʻomaʻimaʻi

to pretend to be sickly

hoʻomaʻule

to cause fainting; to faint; to feign fainting

hoʻomaʻū

to dampen, moisten, irrigate, soak, saturate, baste; to shade, cool

hoʻomaʻūmaʻū

caus/sim of maʻūmaʻū, redup. of maʻū, moist...

hoʻomea

to talk in a roundabout way, as to obtain information or conceal the truth; to hint at, trifle, joke, allude, pretend, act

hoʻomeamea₁

• to bluff,   • pretend,   • disguise.  caus/sim of meamea₁, redup. of mea₄, to say...

hoʻomehameha

to cause silence, loneliness; to hush

hoʻomeheu

to make a track; to follow a track, trail, trace; to lead up to deviously, as in asking a favor

hoʻomele

to cause to sing or chant

hoʻomelemele

to color or paint yellow

hoʻomelomelo

to prepare this club; to use this club

hoʻomelu

to cause a decomposition, to leave (as fish) until decomposition begins

hoʻomene

to make dull; dull

hoʻomenemenee

caus/sim of menemene, to shrink from handling; hesitation. fig., to feel sorry, compassionate, pathetic; compassion; to fear for a loved one...

hoʻomihamiha

to decorate, dot

hoʻomikanele

to act as a missionary; to ape the missionaries; to be a goody-goody

hoʻomikioi

to do neatly; to work with skilled craftsmanship; to handle daintily

hoʻomiko

to season, salt

hoʻomikomiko

caus/sim of mikomiko, garnish; delicious; salted lightly; entertaining, instructive, as conversation...

hoʻomimi

to cause urination; to help to urinate, as a child

hoʻomimilo

to curl, twist

hoʻominoʻaka

to cause to smile; to smile a little

hoʻomiona₁

caus/sim of miona₁, swift disappearance or movement...

hoʻomiona₂

creased; to make a crease

hoʻomoamoa

• to accompany, as a cock with hens;   • to care for, protect, cherish

hoʻomoana₂

to spread down, as mats

hoʻomoekolohe

to lead into adultery

hoʻomoemoe

to cause to lie down; to hush or put to sleep; to arrange a match; to set a line or net; to pretend to sleep. cf. hoʻomoe

hoʻomoepū

to place artefacts with the dead. lit., put to sleep with

hoʻomoe₁

• to put to sleep, to lay down;   • to set, as a hen (Isa. 59.5)   • to set, as a fish net;   • to offer, as a sacrifice;   • to deposit, as in banks;   • to bring down, as a club (FS 241);   • to "drop" a matter;   • to defer, postpone, rest a while;   • to table, as a motion;   • to lay, as bricks or cement;   • to subscribe, as to a newspaper.   As an epithet for Kalākaua, moe probably refers to the kapu moe. cf. hoʻomoemoe

hoʻomoe₂

to arrange a match

hoʻomoe₃

caus/sim of moe₆, same as moea₂, to press onward, go straight toward...

hoʻomohala

• to open, unfold,   • spread,   • recover,   • develop, evolve; development, etc

hoʻomoho

to stalk; to lie in wait, as a cat ready to pounce; to trail or follow behind, sneak. Kaʻū

hoʻomokapu

to separate by imposing a taboo

hoʻomoko

to flood, fill with water

hoʻomokuāhana

to divide, alienate

hoʻomoku₁

to cut and divide; a cutting, division, separation

hoʻomoku₂

to place one over a moku, district

hoʻomolemole

to smooth

hoʻomole₁

to smooth

hoʻomole₂

to cause delay; to delay

hoʻomoloā

to feign laziness; to waste the time of others; lazy

hoʻomomoa

same as hoʻomoamoa

hoʻomomole

redup. of hoʻomole; to hesitate; reluctant

hoʻomomona₁

to fatten, fertilize

hoʻomomona₂

to sweeten; candy

hoʻomomoʻa

to cook

hoʻomoʻo

to follow a course, continue a procedure

hoʻomoʻolelo

caus/sim of moʻolelo, story, tale, myth, history, tradition, literature, legend, journal, log, yarn, fable, essay, chronicle, record, article...

hoʻomoʻomoʻo

to beat raw bast into moʻomoʻo

hoʻomoʻopuna,

to claim a moʻopuna relationship; to address and treat as a moʻopuna, as from affection

hoʻomua

to push forward, to do something first; to claim to be senior; to advance to seniority; to give the rights of seniority to a junior

hoʻomuamua

to push forward; to act as senior

hoʻomumuku

caus/sim of mumuku₁, amputated, mutilated, maimed; premature, as a baby...

hoʻomumule

caus/sim of mumule, speechless, silent, taciturn, mute, sullen, sulky...

hoʻomuʻe

to make bitter

hoʻomā

caus/sim of mā₁, faded, wilted, stained, discolored, blushing; defeated; passed away, perished; to have lost a former attractiveness; to fade...

hoʻomāhanahana₁

to make warm, heat

hoʻomāhanahana₂

to relax rigor of taboo during a long rigorous session

hoʻomāhanahana₃

to dedicate, as a temple (FS 117); to offer first fruits to the gods

hoʻomāhele₁

to have a division made, distribute, divide, etc

hoʻomāhele₁

to lead conversation towards a topic

hoʻomāhele₂

caus/sim of mahele₂, to translate, interpret...

hoʻomāhie

• delightful, charming;   • to cast shy glances, as of a coy child

hoʻomāhilu

to beautify, adorn, bedeck, cf. hiluhilu

hoʻomāhu

to create steam; to cook or soften food by steam; to steam

hoʻomāhua

to increase, expand, enlarge, multiply, grow

hoʻomāhuahua

to enlarge. caus/sim of māhuahua, to grow strong, as a ruler; to accrue, increase; productive, big...

hoʻomāhukahuka

caus/sim of māhukahuka, redup. of mahuka, to run away, flee, escape, elope; fugitive...

hoʻomāhuā

to bring bad luck, misfortune; to annoy, distress, harm; adversity

hoʻomāhuʻi

to mimic. caus/sim of māhuʻi, to imitate, ape, pattern after, do as, follow after...

hoʻomāhāhā

to place taro tops together until they begin to sprout and are ready for planting (perhaps a contraction of hoʻomaka hāhā, to start stems)

hoʻomāikaika

caus/sim of māikaika, same as hoʻoikaika to make a great effort, work hard, encourage, animate, strengthen..., but less common...

hoʻomāilo

to cause thinness

hoʻomāino

to treat cruelly, abuse, persecute; to cause misery and suffering

hoʻomāinoino

caus/sim of māinoino, redup. of māino   • cruelty, misery, harm; cruel, miserable, hurt...;   • to torture;   • atrocity.

hoʻomāio

to furrow, cut in ridges, cause thinness, waste away.

hoʻomākahakaha

to show signs of clearing

hoʻomākaʻi

to act as a policeman; to appoint or invest as a policeman

hoʻomākaʻikaʻi

to take others on a visit; to show the sights; to escort

hoʻomākaʻukaʻu

to scare, frighten; scared, frightened

hoʻomākeʻaka

witty, comic, funny, amusing; to cause laughter, exercise wit or humor

hoʻomākole₁

to cause redness or soreness of the eyes

hoʻomākole₂

to prepare octopus in this fashion

hoʻomākoli

to cut into small bits, to render small or fine

hoʻomākonā

to act mean, hard, etc

hoʻomākōmakō

large, billowy; to increase, enlarge

hoʻomākū

• to cause to harden, solidify, thicken, gel;   • to lower, as clouds.   • fig., to show off

hoʻomālailena

to cause sourness; to embitter

hoʻomālamalama

• to cause light,   • brighten,   • illuminate,   • enlighten,   • inform,   • civilize

hoʻomālama₁

caus/sm

hoʻomālana

to make buoyant, lighten

hoʻomālaʻe

• to clear, explain clearly;   • to calm, cheer, dispel gloom;   • to clear away, as brush or weeds

hoʻomālaʻea

pas/imp. of hoʻomālaʻe to clear, explain clearly; to calm, cheer...

hoʻomālaʻelaʻe

caus/sim of mālaʻelaʻe, redup. of mālaʻe clear, calm; clear of weeds...

hoʻomālie

to calm, quiet, hush, soothe, lull, ease pain

hoʻomālielie

to comfort one who is disturbed, to soothe; to slow down

hoʻomālili

caus/sim of mālili₂, ...

hoʻomāloʻeloʻe₁

caus/sim of māloʻeloʻe₁, tired, exhausted; stiff or aching, as from unaccustomed exercise...

hoʻomāloʻeloʻe₂

to stretch, make taut

hoʻomāluhiluhi

to cause fatigue, exhaust, tire; tiresome, exhausting, toilsome

hoʻomālō₁

to make straight, firm, as a cord or sail; to tighten

hoʻomāmalu

to protect; to make shady; to cast gloom

hoʻomāmā

• to lighten, as a load;   • to ease pain;   • to cheer

hoʻomānalonalo

caus/sim of mānalonalo₁, redup. of mānalo₁, sweet, potable, mānalo₂, appeased...

hoʻomānalo₁

to remove bitterness or saltiness, as of overly salty salmon

hoʻomānalo₂

to appease, assuage, or mollify, as a god; to neutralize, as a curse

hoʻomānaʻonaʻo

to cause a sensation of horror, grief

hoʻomānea

to harden, raise calluses; to strengthen, make steadfast

hoʻomānewanewa₁

to display violent grief; to free oneself from black magic and regain health by extravagant conduct, as going nude or eating of filth or drinking ʻauhuhu juice

hoʻomānewanewa₂

to treat unkindly

hoʻomāneʻoneʻo

to tickle, titillate. caus/sim of māneʻoneʻo₁, redup. of maneʻo itch; itchy; smarting...

hoʻomānoa

to thicken

hoʻomāpu

caus/sim of māpu, fragrance, especially, wind-blown fragrance; wafted; bubbling, splashing, as water; dipping, swooping. fig., surging, as emotion...

hoʻomāui

to bruise, sprain, beat down, as by heavy rain or sea; to crush, as a leaf for a poultice; to cause a sprain; to ripen bananas by burying in a leaf-lined pit

hoʻomāuiui

to ask over and over, mull over in the mind

hoʻomāuna

• to waste,   • spend carelessly,   • abuse;   • to help oneself lavishly, as to drinks

hoʻomāunauna

to waste, squander

hoʻomāwae

to make a crack, furrow

hoʻomāʻakaʻaka

same as hoʻomākeʻaka, to cause laughter

hoʻomāʻana

beginning

hoʻomāʻauea

to laugh at, ridicule, mock; to disregard

hoʻomāʻauē

to mimic speech in a nasty way, to mock, annoy thus

hoʻomāʻeha

same as hoʻoʻeha

hoʻomāʻele

caus/sim of māʻele, same as māʻeʻele numb, as a foot that has "gone to sleep"...

hoʻomāʻewaʻewa

• to purge oneself of the effects of black magic by performing a prescribed humiliating ceremony, as walking about naked;   • jeer.

hoʻomāʻeʻele

to cause numbness, shock, great love

hoʻomāʻike

to show (demonstrate)

hoʻomāʻikeʻike

to show, reveal, make known or comprehensible

hoʻomāʻinoʻino

to defame, slander, deface

hoʻomāʻiuʻiu

to keep at a distance, avoid

hoʻomāʻiʻo

caus/sim of māʻiʻo₁, to cut raggedly and unevenly, as cloth or hair; dented; chipped, as crockery...

hoʻomāʻoi

to act bold, impertinent

hoʻomāʻokiʻoki

to make streaks, cut grooves

hoʻomāʻona

to eat all one wants, to feed all that is wanted

hoʻomāʻopaʻopa

fatiguing, fatigue

hoʻomāʻē

short for hoʻomakaʻē

hoʻomāʻūʻū

to moisten, dampen, wet, as earth about plants

hoʻomō

short for hoʻomoku, to cut and divide; a cutting, division, separation...

hoʻomōakaaka

explanation, definition; to explain clearly, clarify, define

hoʻomōhalu

to slacken, relax; to cause relaxation, ease

hoʻomōkākī

to litter, scatter, cause disorder or untidiness, disarrange

hoʻomōʻali

to make an impression; scar, tracing, groove

hoʻomūkā

caus/sim of mūkā, sound of lips popped open; clicking sound, as in urging a horse to speed up; smack, as in eating...

hoʻomū₁

to sit in silence, to refuse to answer; speechless

hoʻomū₂

same as mū₃; multitude, crowd; to cause a gathering

hoʻonae

to cause shortness of breath

hoʻonaele

to soften, as earth for planting. caus/sim of naele₂, stretched out of shape; yielding, soft, miry, spongy; misshapen; swamp, mire, bog; to stretch...

hoʻonahoa

to challenge. caus/sim of nahoa₁, bold, defiant, daring...

hoʻonaholo

to chase, cause to run

hoʻonahu

to bite, cause a stomachache; to pretend to bite

hoʻonahā

to smash, shatter, crack, split; to take a purgative

hoʻonaikola

to show contempt, as by destruction

hoʻonakaka

caus/sim of nakaka, redup. of naka₂ crack open...

hoʻonakeke

to make a rattling or rustling noise

hoʻonakele

caus/sim of nakele, soft, boggy, slippery, yielding, sinking in; a shallow boggy area...

hoʻonaki

caus/sim of naki, same as nākiʻi, to tie...

hoʻonakoa

brave, daring

hoʻonaku

caus/sim of naku₁, to root, wallow, as a hog; to tread, trample, push, as through mud or grass; to struggle; to roil, as water; to delve, search.

hoʻonakuli

apathetic; lack of interest

hoʻonakulu

caus/sim of nakulu, dripping, as water; patter, clatter, rattle, echo; rumbling, as the stomach; grumbling; vibrating, as thunder; to spread or circulate, as rumor...

hoʻonalo

to cause to be lost; to conceal, secrete, put out of sight

hoʻonalonalo

• hidden;   • to cause to disappear,   • camouflage.   cf. manaʻo hoʻonalonalo, ʻōlelo hoʻonalonalo

hoʻonalu

to form waves

hoʻonalulu

to cause a pain in head or stomach

hoʻonamu

to pretend to speak in a foreign language, to mutter, mumble, speak gibberish

hoʻonanaka

caus/sim of nanaka, marked in sections, as a turtle's back or breadfruit skin...

hoʻonanana

caus/sim of nanana₁, to flutter, as wings...

hoʻonanauha

caus/sim of nanauha, same as kākāuha, rigid...

hoʻonane

to make riddles, speak in parables

hoʻonanea

to pass the time in ease, peace, and pleasure; to relax, lounge, repose; absorbed, contented...

hoʻonanenane

same as above; puzzling, riddling; figurative. see ʻōlelo hoʻonanenane

hoʻonani

• to beautify, adorn, trim, decorate, decorative,   • glorify, honor, exalt, praise, adore; glorifying...

hoʻonaninani

to beautify, adorn

hoʻonanā

• aggressive,   • looking for a fight,   • threatening;   • to antagonize

hoʻonapa

to cause delay

hoʻonape

caus/sim of nape₁, bending and swaying, as coconut fronds; surging, as the sea; to rise and fall, as the chest in breathing; yielding, springy...

hoʻonapele

same as above; to wound, to make soft; to digest, as food

hoʻonaue

• to cause to shake, revolve, sway, rock;   • to disturb

hoʻonauki

causing irritation; aggravating, annoying, exasperating, provoking

hoʻonaʻanaʻa

to protrude

hoʻonaʻauao

to educate, instruct; educational, instructive, civilized

hoʻonaʻaupō

to cause or feign ignorance; ignorant

hoʻoneko

to make dirty, soil

hoʻonele

to deprive, make destitute; to deny , impeach

hoʻonema

same as above

hoʻonemo

to polish, smooth

hoʻonene

caus/sim of nene₁, to stir, show animation, move, as a fledgling...

hoʻoneo

to lay waste, devastate, make destitute; desolation; turning to naught

hoʻoneoneo

redup. of hoʻoneo

hoʻonepu

to cause plumpness, swelling; plump

hoʻonewa

caus/sim of newa₂, to reel, stagger; dizziness, vertigo; dizzy...

hoʻoneʻe

• to cause to move,   • shift,   • hitch along,   • push ahead...

hoʻoneʻe hope

to back up, as a car

hoʻoneʻe mua

to cause progress

hoʻoneʻeneʻe

caus/sim of neʻeneʻe₁, redup. of neʻe, moving along little by little...

hoʻoneʻineʻi₁

caus/sim of neʻineʻi₁, same as neʻeneʻe₁, moving along little by little...

hoʻoneʻineʻi₂

caus/sim of neʻineʻi₂, short, small, as clothes; low-lying, squatting; crowded; to shrink, a small bit...

hoʻonia

to make smooth and even, as in carving; to remove all vestige of vegetation

hoʻoniania

caus/sim of niania, redup. of nia smooth...

hoʻonianiau

var. of hoʻoniniau

hoʻoniau

• following swiftly and silently;   • continuing;   • prolonging;   • copying, imitating

hoʻonihinihi

caus/sim of nihinihi, fastidious, overly strict, finicky, decorous, dainty. Also lihilihi...

hoʻoniho

to lay stones interlocking; to set stones, as in a fence

hoʻonihoniho

to make into a toothed, scalloped, notched design; to make teeth; to carve an irregular notched edge

hoʻoniku

to soil, make dirty

hoʻoniniau

redup. of hoʻoniau

hoʻoninihua

caus/sim of ninihua, resentment; resentful...

hoʻoniniu

• to cause dizziness;   • to spin, as a top

hoʻoniniʻo

caus/sim of niniʻo, same as ʻōniʻoniʻo, spotted, streaked...

hoʻonipo₁

to make love, court, woo, yearn for

hoʻonipo₂

to cause sleepiness, make drowsy

hoʻoniua

to cause to spin, whirl, stir

hoʻonoa

to cause to cease, as a taboo; to free from taboo; to repeal, revoke; to adjourn, as a meeting; to prostitute, as one's daughter

hoʻonoanoa

to free from taboo

hoʻonoenoe

redup. of hoʻonoe. cf. lāʻau hoʻonoenoe

hoʻonoho papa

to arrange, put in order

hoʻonoho paʻa

caus/sim of noho paʻa, to live permanently; to settle down; to be established...

hoʻonohonoho helu

to calculate, compute, figure

hoʻonohonoho₁

• to pretend to be possessed by a spirit;   • to arrange, classify, organize

hoʻonohonoho₂

a variety of yam (uhi) having tuber with white flesh and red skin; vine and its wings green, petiole red, veins of blade red and green

hoʻonoho₁

bone hooks lashed together

hoʻonoho₂

to summon a spirit to possess

hoʻonoho₃

• to take up residence;   • to install, establish, provide, seat, locate,   • arrange, pack, regulate,   • convey, carry,   • appoint; to place in authority;   • to set, as type ...

hoʻonohu₁

to scowl, frown

hoʻonohu₂

to reef, as the sails of a ship

hoʻonoi

caus/sim of noi, to ask for something, request, solicit, appeal, apply, make a motion, move, propose, plea; proposal, request, petition, motion (in documents of the 1860s, often preceded by the article ke)...

hoʻonoke

caus/sim of noke, to persist, continue, repeat, persevere, keep on; perseverance, persistence...

hoʻonole

awkward, without skill

hoʻonolu

caus/sim of nolu₁, springy, elastic, soft, yielding, boggy...

hoʻonolunolu

a name for the straight portion of a canoe rim

hoʻonome

to cause to munch, move along

hoʻonomenome

redup. of hoʻonome; to move the lips silently, as though speaking to oneself

hoʻonone

to work slowly and with disinterest; to be a slowpoke

hoʻononi

to create a disturbance, cause trouble, incite

hoʻononohuā

to nurse jealousy and ill will; to hate

hoʻononō

caus/sim of nonō, to snore, gurgle...

hoʻonou

to throw, pelt; to put forth physical effort; to strain; to pretend or cause to throw. cf. haʻanou

hoʻonoʻonoʻo

to cause to think, reflect; reminiscent, recalling to mind, remembering. cf. more common hoʻomanaʻo

hoʻonuha

to cause to sulk; to sulk

hoʻonuhanuha

redup. of hoʻonuha

hoʻonui

• to enlarge,   • increase,   • multiply,   • magnify,   • exaggerate,   • add to,   • dilate;   • multiplication;   • to increase in volume, of music;   • crescendo mark in music...

hoʻonuinui

to use threatening language, usually without carrying out the threat; to exaggerate, stretch the truth, talk verbosely.

hoʻonunu

a seaweed (Laurencia obtusa var. racemosa)

hoʻonupanupa

same as hoʻolupalupa to cause to flourish; lush

hoʻonuʻa

• to heap up;   • to give generously and continuously;   • to indulge, as a child;   • surging, rising in swells, as the sea

hoʻonuʻanuʻa

redup. of hoʻonuʻa

hoʻonuʻu

to eat heartily

hoʻonā

• to relieve pain, soothe, comfort,   • quiet, appease, lull, placate, make calm, pacify,   • console, find solace;   • to end, as a taboo;   • to settle a claim...

hoʻonāhili

to cause a blundering, wandering, as by misdirecting; to procrastinate, waste time through blundering

hoʻonākelekele

caus/sim of nākelekele, redup. of nakele, soft, boggy, slippery, yielding, sinking in...

hoʻonākuʻi

caus/sim of nākuʻi, to rumble, roar, thump; rumbling; beating, as the heart; thrilled (perhaps naku₁ + -ʻi, transitivizer)...

hoʻonākū

to suffer gas pains

hoʻonānahu

to turn into charcoal, as burnt wood

hoʻonānawaū

to cause to be weak and unhealthy

hoʻonānā₁

to cause to look, show

hoʻonāueue

to cause to sway back and forth

hoʻonāuki

caus/sim of nāuki, vexation, anger; to harass...

hoʻonāukiuki

redup. of hoʻonauki; to provoke, annoy

hoʻonāulu

to provoke to anger by taunting and teasing

hoʻonāwali

to cause weakness; to enfeeble; to feign weakness

hoʻonāwaliwali

caus/sim of nāwaliwali, redup. of nāwali, weak...

hoʻonāwele

same as nāwele

hoʻonē

• teasing,   • fretting,   • appealing

hoʻonīele

questioning, especially by leading up indirectly rather than directly; quizzing; curious; curiosity

hoʻonīnau

to ask a question; to have questions asked; to ask indirectly

hoʻonōʻā

to cause a burning

hoʻonū

to moan, groan, sigh, hum, roar, etc

hoʻonūkeʻe

to twist the face to one side

hoʻooloolo

to elongate. caus/sim of oloolo₂, long and narrow, as a head; elongated, oblong, oval...

hoʻopaepae₁

to build up a paepae (platform) or a taro embankment; to finish a space in quilting

hoʻopaepae₂

redup. of hoʻopae, bring ashore, cast ashore...

hoʻopae₁

bring ashore, cast ashore, to cause to land, reach shore.

hoʻopae₂

to build up an embankment, row, cluster

hoʻopahele

to cause to be ensnared; to ensnare, deceive

hoʻopahelo

var. of hoʻopakelo

hoʻopahemo₁

to cause to slip, slacken, loosen, etc

hoʻopaheʻe

to cause to slip, slide; to make smooth, slippery; to smooth with oil, as the hair; to lubricate. see ex., kū₁₃

hoʻopahilau

to tell lies

hoʻopahinu

to make shiny, etc

hoʻopahu

to cause to push, etc

hoʻopahulu₁

to have a nightmare; nightmare; to haunt; to bring bad luck; unlucky

hoʻopahulu₂

to exhaust the soil; to let the land rest and lie fallow

hoʻopahuʻa

to spoil, wreck

hoʻopahāha

to cause swollenness; to hoist the shoulders; to strut

hoʻopahū

to explode, set off, as dynamite or firecrackers; to blast, blow up

hoʻopahūpahū

redup. of hoʻopahū; to drum or stamp with force; to squeeze certain types of small fish so they burst

hoʻopai

to encourage, cause to rouse, etc

hoʻopaiho

to peel

hoʻopaikau

caus/sim of paikau, to march, drill, parade, pass to and fro; to practice firearms...

hoʻopailani

to make or treat as a favorite. caus/sim of pailani, similar to mailani, to praise, but often pejorative; to spoil...

hoʻopailua

to cause nausea, vomiting; nauseating, sickening, revolting, disgusting, loathsome

hoʻopaio

caus/sim of paio, to quarrel, argue, fight; combat, argument, conflict, strife, battle, struggle; to contend, as conflicting winds...

hoʻopaipai

redup. of hoʻopai, to encourage, cause to rouse, etc . ;   • to promote,   • cheer,   • lobby;   • promotion,   • agitator

hoʻopakakē

to talk thus

hoʻopakalaki

to cause bad luck

hoʻopakaneo

to bring destitution or poverty

hoʻopakauʻaʻaka

same as pakauʻaʻaka; provocative of crankiness

hoʻopakele

to rescue, save or deliver from danger, free; to protect; to help escape...

hoʻopakelo

caus/sim of pakelo₁, to slip out, as an animal from a trap or a fish from the hand; slippery, slick, slipping, sliding; to thrust, as a spear...

hoʻopakeʻo

to thrust out, slip out, etc

hoʻopakika

to make smooth, as by polishing; to make slippery, as by greasing; to cause to slip and slide

hoʻopakikī

caus/sim of pakikī, redup. of pakī splash...

hoʻopakipakika

redup. of hoʻopakika

hoʻopakē

to cause to be brittle, weak

hoʻopakī

to splash, spatter, etc.

hoʻopakīpakī

caus/sim of pakīpakī, redup. of pakī splash...

hoʻopakū

to burst, etc

hoʻopakūpakū

redup. of hoʻopakū, to pop, as a Portuguese man-of-war that is stepped upon on the beach

hoʻopalaha

to cause to fall, trip, push over; to fall

hoʻopalaheʻa

to stain, besmear

hoʻopalaheʻaheʻa

redup. of hoʻopalaheʻa

hoʻopalaheʻe

to cause to flee, chase

hoʻopalahuli

to cause to turn, fall

hoʻopalahō

to cause to rot, etc

hoʻopalai

• to have turned the face away,   • to cause to turn away;   • ashamed, confused, etc.

hoʻopalaka

• to feign indifference;   • indifferent, etc.

hoʻopalakaʻeo

peeved, resentful

hoʻopalakāhela

to curve, bend, stoop

hoʻopalaleha

to neglect. caus/sim of palaleha, indifferent, careless, slack, neglectful of duty...

hoʻopalalehe

var. of hoʻopalaleha

hoʻopalalē

caus/sim of palalē₁, to speak imperfectly, as of one with a foreign accent or speech defect; to work in a disorderly, slipshod way; confusion...

hoʻopalalū₁

to sound thus

hoʻopalalū₂

to cause nervousness, weakness

hoʻopalani

to cause to go sour, rancid

hoʻopalau

to betroth in marriage; engaged

hoʻopala₁

to ripen, turn yellow

hoʻopala₂

to daub, besmear

hoʻopale

• to fend or ward off;   • to separate, partition off;   • to defend in court;   • to disown

hoʻopalekana

to save, rescue

hoʻopalela

to cause laziness; same as above

hoʻopalemo

to drown, plunge into water, sink

hoʻopalena

to confine. caus/sim of palena₁, boundary, limit, border, margin, juncture, separation, partitioning; terms of a fraction...

hoʻopalipali

caus/sim of palipali, precipitous, full of cliffs and steep hills...

hoʻopalolo

to cause garrulousness; same as above

hoʻopalu

to cause to lick, to lick

hoʻopaluheʻe

var. of hoʻopaluhē

hoʻopaluhē

to make soft, pulpy; to reduce to pulp, cook until soft

hoʻopalupalu

to soften, weaken, mollify, make pliant or flexible; to feign softness

hoʻopalō₁

to feign ignorance. same as palō₁

hoʻopalō₂

to act the goody-goody. same as palō₂

hoʻopana

caus/sim of pana₁, to shoot, as marbles, arrows, bow; bow and arrows; to snap, as with fingers and thumb to punish a child; to flip...

hoʻopanapanau

redup. of hoʻopanau

hoʻopanau

to cause to seesaw, wander, etc. ; to make the vulgar gesture

hoʻopanaunau

redup. of hoʻopanau

hoʻopane

caus/sim of pane₁, answer, reply, response; to answer, speak...

hoʻopanepane

to cause controversy by arguing; same as above

hoʻopaneʻeneʻe

redup. of hoʻopaneʻe; to keep putting off, etc

hoʻopaneʻe₁

caus/sim of paneʻe₁, to move along, bring, push along a little; pushed forward...

hoʻopaneʻe₂

to postpone, delay, put off, defer, procrastinate

hoʻopani

to cause a closing, pretend to close

hoʻopaniniʻo

same as hoʻoniniʻo

hoʻopaniolo

to be like a cowboy or pretend to be a cowboy

hoʻopano

to cause darkness; to make mysterious, unknown, unfathomable; same as pano

hoʻopanoa

to cause barrenness. caus/sim of panoa, barren, arid, desert, dry, hot, parched...

hoʻopanopano

redup. of hoʻopano

hoʻopapailua

redup. of hoʻopailua; beginning to be nauseated, first symptoms of nausea; seasick

hoʻopapapau

redup. of hoʻopapau

hoʻopapau

• to devote oneself,   • to make an effort to finish up,   • to concentrate

hoʻopapaʻi

redup. of hoʻopaʻi; to move the stomach muscles, as in certain hula dances

hoʻopapa₁

• to place in rank or file;   • to put in order,   • to put in layers, overlay, overlap, as shingles;   • to make a shelf;   • to pack neatly

hoʻopapa₂

purification of woman after childbirth, involving medicinal herbs bound to the abdomen, and a taboo on sex relations

hoʻopau kaua

to make a truce or armistice

hoʻopau manawa

to waste time; not worth doing, undesirable, unnecessary, waste of effort

hoʻopau pilikia

to attend the calls of nature. lit., to put an end to trouble

hoʻopau ʻeka

to soil, make dirty

hoʻopauaho

to cause shortness of breath, panting, despair, etc. caus/sim of pauaho, out of breath, breathless, gasping for breath, panting, worn out. fig., discouraged, faint-hearted, despairing, desperate, weary, exhausted; to die...

hoʻopauhā

similar to hoʻopaumanawa, to waste time; not worth doing, undesirable, unnecessary, waste of effort...

hoʻopaulina

same as hoʻopaulinalina, to waste time on trivials, to take life easy, relax

hoʻopaulinalina

to waste time on trivials, to take life easy, relax

hoʻopaumākō

to cause great grief, lamentation; to pretend grief

hoʻopaumāʻele

to soil, make dirty, smear, pollute, befoul, defile

hoʻopauʻaka₁

to make grotesque, odd

hoʻopauʻaka₂

same as pauʻaka₃

hoʻopaʻa haʻawina

to study the lesson; studious.

hoʻopaʻa kuleana

copyright; to copyright

hoʻopaʻa manaʻo

to keep a memorandum, make a record of thoughts, memorize

hoʻopaʻa waiwai

to insure property; property insurance

hoʻopaʻahao

to make a prisoner, imprison, jail, prison

hoʻopaʻakikī

• same as paʻakikī;   • to cause hardness, obstinacy;   • to pretend to be hard, stubborn, unreasonable, unreceptive

hoʻopaʻakope

copyright; to copyright

hoʻopaʻakūkū

to cause to clot, congeal, etc

hoʻopaʻanaʻau

to memorize

hoʻopaʻaola

life insurance; to get life insurance

hoʻopaʻapaʻa

to argue, dispute; argument, quarrel

hoʻopaʻapaʻanā

to cause pain to be soothed; to entertain

hoʻopaʻapaʻaʻina

to make a crackling sound, etc

hoʻopaʻapū

to make crowded, covered with, stifling, etc

hoʻopaʻaua

to enslave, overwork, treat as a drudge, downtrodden

hoʻopaʻewa

to cause to be crooked, wrong, distort, etc

hoʻopaʻi ā paʻi

to make similar; to copy the clothing or manners of another, to ape, mimic, imitate

hoʻopaʻi₁

• to slap, hit,   • punish, punishment, chastise,   • fine, penalty   • pay back, seek revenge, revenge   • to judge, judgment (Bib.).

hoʻopaʻi₂

design with 12 to 18 ruled parallel lines on a tapa beater

hoʻopaʻuhia

to cause to fall into a deep sleep, as a drug

hoʻopaʻupaʻuhia

redup. of hoʻopaʻuhia

hoʻopaʻu₁

to soil, smudge, make sooty

hoʻopaʻu₂

to treat as a drudge, overwork, oppress with tedious labor

hoʻopaʻēpaʻē

to be noisy, as a distant sound; to talk loudly

hoʻopaʻū

to soak, moisten, dampen

hoʻopaʻūpaʻū

redup. of hoʻopaʻū

hoʻopehi

to cause to throw or pretend to throw

hoʻopehu

to swell, cause to swell, distend, brag, boast

hoʻopehupehu

redup. of hoʻopehu; to brag; braggadocio; swollen, billowy, as a cloud

hoʻopeki

caus/sim of peki₂, to back up, as a car...

hoʻopelapela

to befoul, make dirty or filthy, soil, pollute

hoʻopele

to knead

hoʻopeleki

caus/sim of peleki, brake; to apply brakes...

hoʻopeleleu

to cause to spread, extend; same as above

hoʻopelo

lie (falsify). caus/sim of pelo, to flatter, tell tall tales, lie...

hoʻopelopelo

caus/sim of pelopelo, redup. of pelo, to flatter, tell tall tales, lie...

hoʻopelu

to fold, turn, etc.

hoʻopenu

to cause to sop, dunk; to dunk

hoʻopenupenu

redup. of hoʻopenu

hoʻopepehi

to cause to beat, strike, kill; to pretend to beat

hoʻopepehu

redup. of hoʻopehu; to flex the muscles or make them bulge

hoʻopepeʻe

to bend, twist, etc.

hoʻopeu

to thrust up, etc

hoʻopeʻa

• to cross and tie;   • fig., to persecute

hoʻopeʻa kua

to cross the hands behind the back

hoʻopeʻahi

to beckon or wave, pretend to wave, etc.

hoʻopeʻapeʻahi

redup. of hoʻopeʻahi

hoʻopeʻe

to hide or pretend to hide

hoʻopeʻelulu

to create confusion; confusion; confusing

hoʻopeʻepeʻe

redup. of hoʻopeʻe; camouflage

hoʻopiha pono

to complete, make completely full, clear, intelligible

hoʻopihapiha ʻōlelo

to stir up dislike for another, to turn against another, as by telling tales or gossip

hoʻopihapiha₁

to fill, complete; to file, as cards; frame, questionnaire, any kind of form to be completed

hoʻopihapiha₂

to make a ruffle; ruffler, as on a sewing machine

hoʻopiholo

to sink, drown

hoʻopihō

caus/sim of pihō₂, var. of piholo, to swamp, as a canoe...

hoʻopiki

to shorten, shrink; to make, as a lei piki

hoʻopilapilau

to allow to spoil, as fish or meat. cf. hoʻomelu

hoʻopilau

to cause a stench

hoʻopili wale

caus/sim of pili wale, to cling, etc., for no reason or cause; often used in unfavorable sense of living off other people...

hoʻopilihua

to cause sorrow, astonishment, etc

hoʻopilikia

to cause trouble, bother, disturb, inconvenience; to lead into difficulty, get into trouble, meddle

hoʻopilimeaʻai₁

• to attach oneself for personal gain, as to a chief (often said disparagingly);   • to fawn;   • to support, especially one in the wrong.   (a derogatory remark alluding to people who seem to show up at mealtimes, but never when there's work to be done.)

hoʻopilimeaʻai₂

perjury; to commit perjury

hoʻopilipili aliʻi

to claim relationship to a chief, as of one only remotely related, or of one desirous of favors

hoʻopilipili ʻōlelo

word play, punning; to illustrate a point with parables, stories, anecdotes

hoʻopilipili₁

redup. of hoʻopili₁, to bring together, stick...;   • to court, woo, make advances (FS 155);   • to associate in close friendship;   • to claim relationship, especially if unwarranted

hoʻopili₂

caus/sim of pili₃, to refer, concern, relate, pertain, apply...

hoʻopili₃

to mimic, imitate; repeat (Aniani)

hoʻopilo

to cause a bad odor; to pollute.

hoʻopinana

to elevate, cause to climb

hoʻopiopio

to pipe on a flute-like instrument

hoʻopio₁

to conquer, subdue, defeat, make prisoner, capture, overcome

hoʻopio₂

to put out, extinguish, as a light or fire

hoʻopipika

caus/sim of pipika, to draw away, shrink away, as an octopus tentacle on a fire; to crinkle up, contract: to turn aside so as not to meet, avoid...

hoʻopipiki

to cause to shrink, clamp

hoʻopipili

same as hoʻopilipili; to paste, glue, stick

hoʻopipipi

to put close together; to squint

hoʻopipiʻi

same as hoʻopiʻipiʻi; to set a high price

hoʻopipī

to smoke, as ham. caus/sim of pipī, sputtering, smoldering, to snort, sniffle...; squinting; twinkling, as stars. fig., barely surviving.

hoʻopiʻi aliʻi

caus/sim of piʻi aliʻi, to claim chiefly blood, whether or not it exists...

hoʻopiʻina₁

same as piʻina

hoʻopiʻina₂

quilting in a direction away from the quilter. also hoʻopiʻipiʻi

hoʻopiʻipiʻi ʻōlelo

to cause controversy, words of anger, etc.

hoʻopiʻipiʻi₁

to sail, beat, or tack against the wind; to regurgitate

hoʻopiʻipiʻi₂

same as hoʻopiʻina₂

hoʻopiʻipiʻi₃

to stir up ill feelings, to rouse anger; jealousy

hoʻopiʻi₁

• to cause to rise, raise up,   • promote, promotion.   • mount,   • come up,   • bring forth,   • utter;   • to turn into the wind;

hoʻopiʻi₃

to cause to mount, as of male animals; to breed, impregnate

hoʻopiʻi₄

to sue, bring suit, bring a complaint to one in authority, accuse in court, prosecute, petition; appeal, lawsuit, court case, petition

hoʻopiʻo

to arch, bend, curve, crook

hoʻopiʻoloke

to cause confusion, consternation, vexation; harass

hoʻopiʻopiʻo

redup. of hoʻopiʻo; a form of imitative magic in which the practitioner, while concentrating, touched a part of his own body, thereby causing injury to his victim's body in the same place, as a chest pain or headache. If the intended victim saw the gestures, he might imitate them and thereby send the black magic back to the original practitioner. Both practices were hoʻopiʻopiʻo

hoʻopoe

to round; to form into a round shape, as a loaf of bread

hoʻopoehi

caus/sim of poehi, var. spelling of powehi dim, obscure, indistinct, vague, faint, unclear...

hoʻopoepoe

redup. of hoʻopoe

hoʻopohala₁

to revive, etc.

hoʻopohala₂

to clarify

hoʻopohala₃

to discredit, not believe, depreciate

hoʻopoheke

to squeeze out

hoʻopohihihi

to confuse, bewilder, puzzle, make mysterious

hoʻopoho

caus/sim of poho₂, mortar; to knead, as bread or poi...

hoʻopohole

to bruise, skin, peel, etc. cf. hole₁

hoʻopohopoho

caus/sim of pohopoho₃, to stick out the buttocks, as in bending over to pick up something, or as a sign of contempt...

hoʻopohu

to calm, quiet; to bring into a calm, as a ship

hoʻopohā

to cause to break, burst; to crack, as a whip

hoʻopohāpohā

redup. of hoʻopohā

hoʻopohō

to cause a loss, fail; to sell at a loss

hoʻopoina

to cause to forget; same as poina

hoʻopokakaʻa

to spin, roll, coil, revolve; to repeat the same story over and over

hoʻopoko

short for hoʻopōkole

hoʻopolapola

to cure, make get well; to fill out, as after sickness

hoʻopoloke

caus/sim of poloke, broken; broke, without funds (slang)...

hoʻopololei

• to straighten,   • correct,   • reform;   • to aim, as a gun;   • to be partial and treat with favoritism

hoʻoponi

to anoint, crown, ordain, consecrate, inaugurate

hoʻopono

righteous, respectable, correct, upright; to behave correctly

hoʻoponopono₂

to make ready, as canoemen preparing to catch a wave. cf. luna hoʻoponopono, mea hoʻoponopono

hoʻoponopono₃

mental cleansing: family conferences in which relationships were set right (hoʻoponopono) through prayer, discussion, confession, repentance, and mutual restitution and forgiveness

hoʻopopohe

caus/sim of popohe, round, shapely; neat and trim, as flowers; roundness, a round or clean-cut object...

hoʻopopololei

caus/sim of popololei, same as pololei₁ straight, upright, direct, correct, right, O.K., accurate...

hoʻopouli

to darken, make dark, blind, mislead; to pretend to be ignorant or not know

hoʻopoupou

to shorten, stoop

hoʻopowehi

caus/sim of powehi, dim, obscure, indistinct, vague, faint, unclear...

hoʻopoʻi

to cover

hoʻopoʻipoʻi

caus/sim of poʻipoʻi, to conceal, as property that one does not want to share with others, or as a secret; to cover up, as the truth; to smother, as a fire; to hush the wailing of a child...

hoʻopoʻopoʻo

redup. of hoʻopoʻo

hoʻopoʻo₁

to appoint a head or leader; to go ahead; to be brave

hoʻopoʻo₂

to dig, dub out

hoʻopua

caus/sim of pua₂,   • to issue, appear, come forth, emerge,   • said especially of smoke, wind, speech, and colors,   • hence to smoke, blow, speak, shine...

hoʻopuahi

caus/sim of puahi₂, same as puahia spry, quick...

hoʻopuakea

to appear bright, shine

hoʻopuananu

to rise as a wave

hoʻopuapua

redup. of hoʻopua; to appear again and again

hoʻopuaʻi

to cause to flow, show, etc.

hoʻopue

caus/sim of pue₁, to huddle or sit crouched, as with cold...

hoʻopuehu

• to scatter, disperse,   • rout,   • blow away, blown away,   • whisk,   • crumble;   • fluff;   • gone

hoʻopuhalu

to pulverize or loosen, as the soil. caus/sim of puhalu₁, soft, flabby, loose, sagging, sunken, deflated; to loosen, deflate, sink, sag. fig., unenthusiastic, relaxed, weak...

hoʻopuhemo

to loosen, release; listless (EH)

hoʻopuhi

to cause to blow, blow. fig., to steal

hoʻopukakū

to speak plainly, frankly, bluntly, crudely, without regard to feelings of others

hoʻopukalia

to bring forth

hoʻopukapuka₁

caus/sim of pukapuka₁, many holes, filled with holes, chinks, cracks; pock-marked, as due to small-pox; porous, as stone; cells, as in honeycomb...

hoʻopukapuka₂

to keep talking, issuing, etc

hoʻopukapuka₃

redup. of hoʻopuka; to invest, speculate, search for profit

hoʻopuka₁

to perforate, puncture, make a hole or opening

hoʻopuka₂

• to issue, as a permit;   • to acquit, as a defendant in court;   • a chant to which dancers issue

hoʻopuka₃

to graduate

hoʻopuka₄

to proclaim, speak, say, pronounce

hoʻopuka₅

to invest; to make a profit; profitable. cf. waiwai hoʻopuka

hoʻopukumoa

saving, miserly

hoʻopukupuku

same as pukupuku and transitive

hoʻopulakaumaka

to cherish

hoʻopulapula₁

• to start seedlings or cuttings;   • to multiply, procreate

hoʻopulapula₂

to rehabilitate; rehabilitation

hoʻopule

to cause to pray, to feign praying

hoʻopulelehua₁

to act the butterfly, to talk much but say little; frivolous

hoʻopulelehua₂

to blow

hoʻopuluea

to cause body odor; to sweat offensively

hoʻopulupulu₁

redup. of hoʻopulu₂; to make compost

hoʻopulupulu₂

to protest, deceive; hypocrite

hoʻopulu₁

to wet, soak, moisten, saturate

hoʻopulu₂

to mulch, fertilize with compost

hoʻopumahana

var. of hoʻopumehana

hoʻopumehana

to warm, heat

hoʻopuna

same as hoʻopunalua

hoʻopunahele

to treat as a favorite, make a favorite, indulge

hoʻopunahelu

to grow moldy, musty; to cause mildew

hoʻopunalua

to attain or have the punalua relationship, to pretend to be a punalua

hoʻopuni wale

to fool, deceive easily

hoʻopunihei

to fascinate, charm, captivate, ensnare, decoy, trap

hoʻopunipuni

• to lie, liar;   • to deceive, deceitful,   • false

hoʻopuni₁

• to surround, enclose,   • get control of,   • besiege

hoʻopuni₂

• to be charmed by,   • desire greatly

hoʻopuni₃

to deceive, fool, delude

hoʻopuoho

caus/sim of puoho, startled; to cry out in alarm; fright, shock; to explode, as a lava flow; to wake suddenly; sudden appearance, as a burst of fragrance...

hoʻopupuka

to make ugly, disfigure, deform

hoʻopupuku

scowl. same as hoʻopukupuku

hoʻopupule

to make insane; to drive crazy; to act crazy, pretend to be crazy

hoʻopupuni

caus/sim of pupuni, redup. of puni₁, surrounded, puni₂, fond of, puni₃, deceived, puni₄, completed...

hoʻopupū

• to stall; cause to get stuck (transitive);   • to balk, resist, hold back;   • bumpy, rough, as a road. Also , hōpupū, haʻapupū

hoʻopuīa

to perfume

hoʻopuʻeʻeke

caus/sim of puʻeʻeke, to shrink away from; to shorten, contract; to grimace...

hoʻopuʻipuʻi

to grow or increase in weight

hoʻopuʻu

• to heap up, collect in heaps;   • to frown; resentment. cf. hoʻopuʻukahua

hoʻopuʻua

to choke

hoʻopuʻukahua

same as huahua; to ridicule, belittle, taunt

hoʻopuʻupuʻu₁

to clench the fist, to shake the fist threateningly

hoʻopuʻupuʻu₂

a mound, to mound up.

hoʻopuʻō

caus/sim of puʻō, to blaze up, as fire; to bend, as coconut fronds in a wind; to lift up; to bloom...

hoʻopuʻōpuʻō

redup. of hoʻopuʻō

hoʻopā-

caus/sim. cf. hoʻopālima

hoʻopāhala

skeptical

hoʻopāhaʻohaʻo

• to mystify, bewilder,   • cause wonder,   • puzzle;   • transfigured

hoʻopāhemahema

same as pāhemahema; to cause awkwardness, to fake lack of skill

hoʻopāhemohemo

redup. of hoʻopahemo

hoʻopāhenehene

caus/sim of pāhenehene, to ridicule, laugh at, make fun of, mock, scoff...

hoʻopāheʻeheʻe

caus/sim of pāheʻeheʻe₁, redup. of paheʻe₁, slippery, smooth, as a surface...

hoʻopāhili

to cause such a wind; to blow, as such a wind, etc

hoʻopāhiwa

caus/sim of pāhiwa, dark, to darken (note that hiwa is a sacred, desirable black that contrasts with uli)...

hoʻopāhola

to cause to spread, have spread

hoʻopāhono

to have mended, etc

hoʻopāhonohono

redup. of hoʻopāhono

hoʻopāhuʻa

to move sideways; to sail to windward

hoʻopāhūhū

to cause to gush forth

hoʻopākaha

to cause to cheat

hoʻopākakaʻa

to mill around. caus/sim of pākakaʻa, to roll one at a time...

hoʻopākela

to cause to exceed

hoʻopākeu

to increase, exceed

hoʻopākikakika

redup. of hoʻopakika, to make smooth, as by polishing; to make slippery...

hoʻopākiko

caus/sim of pākiko, temperate, abstemious, frugal, economical, skimpy; temperance...

hoʻopākikokiko

caus/sim of pākikokiko₁, redup. of pākiko temperate, abstemious, frugal, economical, skimpy; temperance...

hoʻopākiʻi

to flatten out

hoʻopākiʻikiʻi

redup. of hoʻopākiʻi

hoʻopākole

var. of hoʻopōkole

hoʻopākuʻi

to beat, cause to beat

hoʻopākuʻikuʻi₁

redup. of hoʻopākuʻi

hoʻopākuʻikuʻi₂

caus/sim of pākuʻikuʻi₂, to argue, contradict...

hoʻopākākā

to shape into a low, wide door or bowl

hoʻopākē

to imitate or act like a Chinese

hoʻopākīkē

caus/sim of pākīkē, to answer saucily or rudely; rude, sarcastic, insolent, saucy, impudent; rudeness...

hoʻopākīkī

redup. of hoʻopākī.

hoʻopākī₁

to smash, etc.

hoʻopākī₂

to act as though one has plenty, to show off, as by spending in a flashy way

hoʻopākūwā

to do over and over, repeat; to render commonplace or trite, as a song

hoʻopākūā

to do over and over, repeat; to render commonplace or trite, as a song

hoʻopālahalaha

redup. of hoʻopālaha₁

hoʻopālaha₁

to spread, extend, flatten; leveling, flattening

hoʻopālaha₂

transitive of pālaha₂, to broil, of flattened-out flesh on coals...

hoʻopālama

To guard, protect, as a taboo princess in a pālama.

hoʻopālau

same as pālau₁; to cause to tell tall tales, exaggerate

hoʻopālaulau

caus/sim of pālaulau₁, broad, flat, extended; a wrapper, especially apron or skirt used as a conveyor; to carry in a wrapper...

hoʻopālima

to divide in fives; same as above

hoʻopālua₁

to divide in two parts; double; pair

hoʻopāluku

caus/sim of pāluku, to beat, pommel, hit hard, thrash, pound, destroy...

hoʻopānaʻi

to seek revenge, reward, etc

hoʻopāniʻo

same as hoʻoniʻo, streaked

hoʻopāoni

to cause quarrel, strife; to argue

hoʻopāono

caus/sim of pāono, by sixes, sixfold; to divide by sixes; to have six or distribute to six...

hoʻopāpaʻa

to make crisp, brittle; to burn, scorch

hoʻopāpā-

redup. of hoʻopā-

hoʻopāpālima

to touch hands as in making an agreement

hoʻopāpā₁

• To touch repeatedly;   • to feel one's way, as a blind person does;   • a contest in wit (as riddling) or strength; to hold such a contest;

hoʻopāpā₂

repartee, banter; to endeavor to find out something or obtain something by indirect methods, by feeling out the person indirectly; to debate, argue; contests in wit (as in riddling).

hoʻopāpā₃

a style of guitar playing in which one person strums, and the other touches the strings of the same guitar to produce certain effects; to play thus

hoʻopāweo

to cause to turn away, snub, etc.

hoʻopāʻani

to make sport, cause to play, joke, playful

hoʻopāʻele

to blacken, blot, etc

hoʻopāʻeli

to cause such digging

hoʻopāʻeliʻeli

redup. of hoʻopāʻeli

hoʻopāʻewaʻewa

redup. of hoʻopaʻewa

hoʻopāʻēʻē

to cause to go astray, mislead, misrepresent

hoʻopāʻū

to put on a pāʻū

hoʻopā₂

to procure barrenness, as by prayer or medication

hoʻopēheu

same as hoʻēheu, to flap the wings; to lift up or stretch the wings

hoʻopēheuheu

redup. of hoʻopēheu

hoʻopēkeu

same as hoʻopēheu

hoʻopēpē₁

redup. of hoʻopē; to flatten; humble. also hōpēpē

hoʻopēpē₂

to act like a baby; infantile.

hoʻopē₁

• to crush, break fine, mash, pulverize;   • to cringe, assume a humble or fearful attitude

hoʻopē₂

to drench, soak

hoʻopē₃

to perfume, anoint

hoʻopē₄

caus/sim of pē₄, to bribe...

hoʻopī

stingy, extremely economical, frugal; to skimp

hoʻopīhoihoi

to cause anxiety; to worry, excite, astonish

hoʻopīkele

to dole out in small quantities

hoʻopīpī

to cause to sprinkle, urinate

hoʻopīʻao

to make such a package

hoʻopīʻena

to cause anger; to cause to shy; to feign anger

hoʻopīʻōʻō

same as hoʻopiʻoloke

hoʻopō

to behave in an ignorant manner, perhaps purposely; to keep out of sight, to stay in the dark; ignorant

hoʻopōhae

to tear, as a hole in cloth

hoʻopōhaku₁

to harden, as lava; to petrify; hard. fig., stubborn

hoʻopōhaku₂

to remain long in one place; to stay at home

hoʻopōheoheo

to round, smooth, or shape into a knob (insulting: see pōheo)

hoʻopōkaʻakaʻa

same as hoʻopokakaʻa; to overwhelm, bewilder with a succession of tasks

hoʻopōkiʻi

to claim a pōkiʻi relationship; to behave as a pōkiʻi

hoʻopōkole

to shorten, cut short, abbreviate; contraction

hoʻopōlehulehu

beginning of dusk; to become dark

hoʻopōloli

to deprive of food, starve, cause hunger; to fast,

hoʻopōmaikaʻi

to cause good fortune; to bless, improve, ask grace; blessing

hoʻopōnalo

to cause blight

hoʻopōnalonalo

caus/sim of pōnalonalo, swarming with gnats...

hoʻopōnaʻanaʻa

to confuse, bewilder

hoʻopōneko

to soil, besmirch

hoʻopōniu

to revolve, spin

hoʻopōniuniu

caus/sim of pōniuniu, grief-stricken...

hoʻopōpilikia

to cause distress, harm, trouble; to afflict

hoʻopōpō

to shape or wad into a ball

hoʻopōuliuli

redup. of hoʻopouli; blackout

hoʻopōʻai

to encircle, surround, besiege, etc

hoʻopōʻino

to harm, injure, distress, devastate; to cause misfortune, distress, damage

hoʻopū paʻakai

to gather salt; salt gatherer

hoʻopūhalahio

to chase off, help escape

hoʻopūhalalū

to fill with air, inflate

hoʻopūhili₁

to blow in gusts from varying directions

hoʻopūhili₂

to confuse, thwart, frustrate

hoʻopūhiʻu

caus/sim of pūhiʻu₁, to break wind audibly (cf. hio₃), considered rude; to cause failure by audible flatulency; a term of contempt for show-offs...

hoʻopūhā

caus/sim of pūhā₃, to belch, burp, clear the throat, hawk up phlegm...

hoʻopūkuʻi₁

to collect, assemble

hoʻopūkuʻi₂

huddle. caus/sim of pūkuʻi₃, to sit doubled up, as for protection from the cold; to nestle together, as in embrace; to hug, huddle...

hoʻopūlale

to stir up to action, hurry

hoʻopūlehulehu

to collect, bring many things together

hoʻopūliki

to gird on

hoʻopūliko

to bud, form shoots

hoʻopūloʻu

to blindfold, veil

hoʻopūloʻuloʻu

to take a steam bath

hoʻopūnana

• to make a nest,   • to settle in a nest or over young;   • to sit on eggs, as a hen;   • to take shelter

hoʻopūnini₁

caus/sim of pūnini,   • to tack, as a ship;   • to float here and there,   • drift...

hoʻopūnini₂

• to demonstrate pleasure at seeing one, as a child or dog;   • to cling to as with delight, frisk about happily;   • to perform ritual with the object of pleasing the gods (rare).

hoʻopūnoni

to dye red with this dye

hoʻopūnono

to make attractive with bright or red colors, to dress or appear gorgeous

hoʻopūnonohu

caus/sim of pūnonohu, redup. of pūnohu₁ rise, as smoke, spread out...

hoʻopūpū

to arrange in bunches

hoʻopūʻiwa

to startle, astonish, etc

hoʻopūʻulu

caus/sim of pūʻulu, group, crowd, army, party, gang, retinue; to form a group, crowd; to crowd, throng, assemble...

hoʻopūʻāʻā

to put to flight, drive in confusion

hoʻopū₁

caus/sim of pū₈, to divide by lot: pebbles or seeds were placed under a tapa, and divided unseen into heaps, and the players drew to get the largest heaps...

hoʻopū₂

to crouch, sit dejected and silent

hoʻoua

to cause rain

hoʻouahi

to smoke, emit smoke, cure by smoking

hoʻouai

caus/sim of uai, to move, as an object; to push aside; to move from place to place, as a tethered animal; sliding, as a door; opening and shutting; to be dislocated, as a joint...

hoʻouaua

to toughen; tough, stubborn

hoʻouhi

caus/sim of uhi₁, covering, cover, veil, film, lid, solid tattooing, tent; to cover, spread over, engulf, conceal, overwhelm; to don, as a feather cloak. fig., to deceive, hide the truth...

hoʻouhiuhi

to prepare uhiuhi wood for house posts

hoʻouhuhī

to tease, annoy, vex, nag

hoʻouila

to flash, as lightning. also , hōʻuila

hoʻouiui

caus/sim of uiui, redup. of ui₁, ask, ui₂, stir up...

hoʻoui₁

to cause a question to be asked, to ask

hoʻoui₂

to bestir, hurry, surge

hoʻoukali

to cause, pretend, or try to follow, accompany, attend, etc

hoʻoukana

to bundle up, pack up, load, as freight

hoʻouka₁

• to load, as cargo or freight;   • to put on, as gear on a horse;   • to send, as a letter...

hoʻouka₂

to rush on, as in battle; to attack, raid

hoʻouki

same as hoʻoukiuki

hoʻoukiuki

to provoke, offend, displease, irritate

hoʻouku

to make someone pay; to levy a tax, fine, assess, charge

hoʻoule

to form a tenon or post for the crotch of a rafter

hoʻouli

to darken, to make blue, green, etc.; to make the skin black and blue; to bruise

hoʻouliuli

same as hoʻouli

hoʻoulu iʻa

to cause fish to be numerous, as by prayer

hoʻoulu kauō

to inspire canoe haulers by chant and prayer

hoʻoulu pono

to make grow well, thrive. caus/sim of ulu pono, to grow well; progressive, thriving, successful...

hoʻoulu ʻai

to grow food plants; a prayer to bless crops

hoʻouluhua

to annoy, weary, vex

hoʻoulukū

caus/sim of ulukū,   • disturbed, upset,   • nervous, agitated, perturbed; nervousness, agitation; to disturb...   • restless,   • depressed,

hoʻoulumāhiehie

• to adorn,   • decorate attractively

hoʻoulupuni

to cause passion, possession, etc

hoʻouluulu lei

hula altar where fresh leis were placed during hula instruction

hoʻouluulu₁

caus/sim of uluulu₂, Redup. of ulu₂ possessed by a god...

hoʻouluulu₂

to wrangle, snarl, snag, taunt, rouse to anger, excite

hoʻouluwehi

to bedeck with plants; to adorn, bedeck, decorate

hoʻouluwehiwehi

caus/sim of uluwehiwehi, redup. of uluwehi lush and beautiful verdure...

hoʻouluāoʻa

to create confusion, excitement; to incite, stir up bedlam, cause trouble

hoʻoulu₂

• to stir up, excite,   • inspire,   • taunt. also, hoʻūlu

hoʻoumu

to make an umu; to pile in a heap

hoʻounauna

redup. of hoʻouna, to send, transmit, send on an errand...; sorcery

hoʻoune

caus/sim of une, lever; lever on a sewing machine that raises or lowers the presser foot; to pry. fig., to urge, disturb, harass...

hoʻounuhi

to have something translated, withdrawn, etc

hoʻounu₁

to place stones; to pave, macadamize

hoʻounu₂

to massage with the palm of the hand and with quick movements rather than gentle pressure. caus/sim of ʻunu, to shorten, hoist, jerk upwards; to pull or draw together, as the hair...

hoʻounā

to cause weariness

hoʻouoi

caus/sim of uoi, to move along, of many; to slouch along together...

hoʻouweke

to open a little. caus/sim of ʻuweke, same as ʻuwehe₁, open...

hoʻouwā

caus/sim of ʻuwā, to shout, cry out, yell, sound loud, shout, racket...

hoʻouwī

caus/sim of ʻuwī₁, to squeak, squeal; to gnash, as teeth; such sounds...

hoʻouāniʻi

to stiffen

hoʻouē

to cause weeping, make someone cry

hoʻouēuē

to imitate wailing; a wailing dirge. caus/sim of uēuē, redup. of uē cry, weep...

hoʻouʻiuʻi

to beautify, make attractive

hoʻouʻi₃

to beautify, make beautiful

hoʻowae

to choose, pretend to choose; finicky

hoʻowahalehe

to stretch the mouth with fingers; to stretch out of shape, as the mouth

hoʻowaha₁

• to talk excessively;   • to make faces;   • to make an opening or furrow;   • to dub out a canoe, hew

hoʻowaha₂

caus/sim of waha₃,   • to carry on the back, as a child;   • a load so carried...

hoʻowahine

to behave like a woman, effeminate, feminine; to imitate the ways of a woman; to grow into womanhood; to have the manners and ways of a lady; to become a wife; to obtain a wife (rare); to take a wife

hoʻowahāwahā

caus/sim of wahāwahā,   • to treat with contempt, scorn, ridicule;   • despise, abhor,   • be disgusted,   • defy...

hoʻowaia

to disgrace, put to shame

hoʻowaianuhea

to cool, make fragrant and cool

hoʻowaiho

to leave, abandon, ignore, shun; to expose or leave naked

hoʻowaiwai

to enrich, bring prosperity

hoʻowalania

to cause pain, wound

hoʻowalaʻau

to cause talk, start talk or conversation

hoʻowale hau

unreliable, fickle, unstable; slippery and amusing, as in speech

hoʻowalea

caus/sim of walea₁, same as nanea:   • interesting, of absorbing interest; fascinating,   • to have a good time, enjoyable;   • repose, tranquility; leisure, at leisure,   • relaxed, at ease,   • amused,   • engaged with, busy with;

hoʻowalewale

• to tempt; entice; tempter, temptation   • decoy,   • lead astray,   • beguile,   • fool,   • take advantage of;

hoʻowali

• to make soft, smooth, as soil,   • to mix, as poi or dough; to mix fine particles with liquid to form a semi-liquid, as poi (NKE12).   • to digest;

hoʻowawā

caus/sim of wawā,   • tumultuous;   • racket, roar:   • loud talk,   • echo,   • sound of distant voices,   • rumored, talked about,   • resounding, repeating   (see hānau wawā)...

hoʻowaʻawaʻa

to act the fool

hoʻowaʻawaʻalia

caus/sim of waʻawaʻalia, same as waʻalia to dig a trench... cf. waʻa₂ trench, furrow...

hoʻowehe

to cause to open, undo, etc

hoʻowehi

to beautify, decorate, adorn

hoʻowehiwehi

decorate, festive. redup. of hoʻowehi

hoʻoweke, hōweke

to open

hoʻowela

• to beat,   • burn,   • arouse passion

hoʻoweli

to frighten, terrify, arouse fear

hoʻoweliweli

• to threaten;   • terrible,   • fierce...;   • to frighten.

hoʻoweuweu

fluff. caus/sim of weuweu, herbage, grass, greenery; bushy or fuzzy, as a beard; fluffy...

hoʻowiki

to hurry, hasten

hoʻowili

• to wind, coil, twine,   • drill,   • turn;   • to mill about, as a school of fish

hoʻowilimoʻo₁

same as wilimoʻo

hoʻowilimoʻo₂

ceremony during luakini or war temple dedication. for a pule hoʻowilimoʻo see (Malo 185)

hoʻowilimoʻo₃

quadrille dance

hoʻowiliwili

redup. of hoʻowili; to swirl, circle

hoʻowini

to sharpen, make a point

hoʻowiʻu₁

to cause to smart

hoʻowiʻu₂

to besmear, soil

hoʻowiʻu₃

to entangle.

hoʻowā

to make a sound, roar; to cause gossip, talk. see ex., haʻanou

hoʻowāhi

caus/sim of wāhi, to cleave, split, burst through, break through; to change, as money; to have sex relations with a virgin, deflower...

hoʻowīwī

to make thin, slenderize; to diet in order to lose weight; to reduce

hoʻoā

to cause to split, crack

hoʻoīkā

to put or throw ashore; to float, strike, drift

hoʻoū

to moisten, soak, wet. also , hōʻū₂.

hoʻoūpē

to crush, belittle, flatten, treat contemptuously

hoʻoʻieʻie

caus/sim of ʻieʻie₃, high, conceited...

hoʻoʻihaʻiha

bloated, uncomfortable

hoʻoʻino

to harm, injure, damage, abuse, insult, malign

hoʻoʻiʻika

to contort the features; to pucker, shrink, contract, wrinkle, scowl

hoʻoʻulua

to assemble

hoʻoʻumeke

to assume the shape of a bowl; to assume the shape of fruit, to bear fruit.

hoʻoʻumiki

to shape a gourd for a drum, as by tying. caus/sim of ʻumiki, same as ʻūmiʻi, clamp, clip... ...

hoʻoʻuʻuku

to make small, reduce, lessen

hoʻoʻū

to grunt and strain, as with physical exertion (Kep. 159); to mourn. also , hōʻū₁

hoʻoʻūmalu

to cast a shadow, overshadow, frown

hoʻuwīʻuwī

redup. of hōʻuwī

hoʻā ahi

to set on fire, to kindle fire.

hoʻāeae

a style of chanting with prolonged vowels and fairly short phrases, much used in love chants; to chant in this fashion; to read or recite Bible passages or multiplication tables

hoʻāhewa

• to find guilty, pronounce guilty, convict,   • blame, condemn,   • curse.

hoʻāhiahi

to become evening; to spend an evening; to detain until evening; to darken, obscure...

hoʻāho

a narrow escape; to escape by a slim margin; to have courage; to put forth great effort...

hoʻāhonui

caus/sim of ahonui, patience; patient, enduring, long suffering; to tolerate. lit., great breath...

hoʻāhu

• to pile, heap up; mound.   • collect; collection, gather, accumulate,   • to lay away, as goods for the future;   • fig., to resent, dislike

hoʻāhua

to pile up or heap up; embankment

hoʻāiki

• to make shine a little;   • to open the eyes a little to see;   • to peek

hoʻāiwaiwa

mystifying, causing wonder; to mystify

hoʻākaaka

to clarify, explain, render or make intelligible, provide clearly for, prescribe, describe; explanation, clarification...

hoʻākahele

precautionary; to take precautions. caus/sim of akahele, slow or moderate, cautious, careful, prudent...

hoʻākakū

caus/sim of akakū₁, vision, trance; reflection, as in a mirror; hallucination; to see a vision...

hoʻākakū ānuenue

caus/sim of akakū ānuenue, the phenomenon known as the Specter of the Brocken, seen at Haleakalā Crater. lit., rainbow apparition...

hoʻākamai

• to make wise or smart;   • to make a pretense of wisdom;   • to show off, display erudition;   • theorist

hoʻākaʻa

caus/sim of ʻākaʻa, to tear off, peel; to break open, as a seal; to fall off or down, as old thatching of a house; to break up, as the sides of a house; to uproot; ruffled, as feathers...

hoʻākea

• to widen, broaden, extend, enlarge, broadening, expansion; extension;   • make public;   • to escape (rare)

hoʻākoakoa

to assemble, congregate, muster, throng; to collect, gather...

hoʻākua

to deify, make a god of; godlike, supernatural, extraordinary, divine. cf. hoa kua.

hoʻākuleana

to give or delegate responsibility. caus/sim of ʻākuleana, to give property or a right to it; to delegate responsibility...

hoʻāla kuahua

chant said at the construction of a hula altar (kuahu hula), calling on the gods, especially Laka, to possess the altar

hoʻāla pō

a summons sent at night

hoʻālaala

cf. ʻoālaala.

hoʻālahia

to awaken; wakefulness, insomnia. caus/sim of alahia, rare pas/imp. of ala₂, to waken, stay awake, ala₃, to rise up, arise...

hoʻāla₁

• to arouse, stir up, incite,   • renew, restore, revive, to restore, as a building;   • raise;   • summons

hoʻālia

to stop, check, restrain, wait

hoʻāliali

to whiten, cause to shine.

hoʻālikiliki

caus/sim of ʻālikiliki, to tighten, tie tightly...

hoʻāliʻi

to make a chief, establish royalty in office; to imitate royalty; to treat as royalty; regal, royal, kingly; to be made an officer, be commissioned.

hoʻāli₁

• to signal, wave; signal,   • to stir, as coffee or a fire; stirring;   • wavy, undulating.

hoʻāli₂

To make an offering to the gods with signals and signs or prayers with gestures. cf. mōhai hoʻāli.

hoʻāloa loa

to keep at a distance

hoʻālohaloha

• to make love,   • express affection, gratitude or compassion;   • expression of love or affection (FS 93);   • to give thanks (I Kor. 11.24);   • friendly, loving, lovable

hoʻālualu

caus/sim of alualu,   • to follow, pursue, chase;   • to run, as for political office...

hoʻāmana₁

to give authority, authorization; to empower, authorize, commission. cf. kula hoʻāmana, charter school.

hoʻāna

to make measurements, rearrange, put in order. also hoʻoana.

hoʻānaʻē

to withhold for the future

hoʻāni

• to beckon, wave, signal;   • to let wind

hoʻāno

holy, devoted to sacred use, hallowed, solemn; to reverence, sanctify, attribute divine honor, hallow. [NB: hoʻāno, listed under ano in the 1986 edition of PE with the 1991 preface, is misspelled as hō.ano, and in the examples below as Hōano and hōano. In the 1986 edition with the 1984 preface, it is misspelled hō.ʻano, Hōʻano, hōʻano. It is respelled correctly here, as in the 1965 and earlier editions, and as in the Hawaiian Bible. The "Ē kō mākou..." of the Lord's Prayer example in the 1986 editions has been rewritten here as "E ko mākou...", the spelling of the earlier editions and the Hawaiian Bible.]

hoʻānu

to cool

hoʻānuʻunuʻu

• to vibrate, undulate,   • wave, wavy, as hair   • to jerk,   • make steps;

hoʻāo₁

to marry; marriage

hoʻāpipi

to join, couple.

hoʻāpono

• to approve, approved, approval, approbation.   • accept, justify, sanction,   • find not guilty in a trial;   • worthy;   see ʻāpono to approve, confirm, justify, ratify, recommend, commend, consent, accept, endorse, adopt; to pass, as a bill.

hoʻāpuka₁

caus/sim of ʻāpuka₁, to swindle, cheat, defraud; forgery, embezzlement; fraudulent...

hoʻāpuka₂

caus/sim of ʻāpuka₂, to emerge, come into light...

hoʻāuau₁

same as hoʻāu₃, to set, as a net or fish trap.

hoʻāuau₂

to hasten, hurry, rush, excite to action.

hoʻāuhuli

caus/sim of auhuli, to overturn, overthrow, upset; to till...

hoʻāuna

to flock, collect.

hoʻāu₁

to cause to float, as timber. caus/sim of au₃, movement, eddy, tide, motion; to move, drift, float, walk, hurry, stir; succession or train, as of thought, trend...

hoʻāu₂

to dedicate, set apart, as in a housewarming

hoʻāu₃

to set, as a net or fish trap; fishermen who set nets in kuʻu fishing.

hoʻāweʻaweʻa

caus/sim of ʻāweʻaweʻa₁, faint trace, spot, glimpse; faint, dim; streaked, faded...

hoʻāwāwa

to make a groove, furrow.

hoʻāʻiaʻi

• to whiten, whitewash, white,   • clear,   • shine, shining.   • remove rust or dirt;     fig., to clarify, brighten, as a tarnished reputation

hoʻāʻīpuʻupuʻu

to appoint or make one a steward; to act as one, as by waiting on the table; to issue provisions

hoʻā₁

• to set on fire, burn, ignite; to light, as a lamp.   • fig., to incite, arouse.

hoʻā₂

caus/sim of ʻā₇, to drive, as fish or cattle...

hoʻā₃

to talk a lot, jabber

hoʻēheu

to flap the wings; to lift up or stretch the wings; to undulate the arms in a hula imitating a bird in flight; to flap the arms, shrug the shoulders; to pull up shoulders proudly, hence to be proud

hoʻēhu

to drive or shoo away; to stir, as a fire. see -ēhu.

hoʻēmi

to reduce, diminish (Puk. 21.10) , lessen, draw back, curtail, discount. see emi₁ to diminish, reduce, depreciate, grow smaller, subside...; lower the price, cheapen; cheap see emi₂, cheap...

hoʻēmi hope

caus/sim of emi hope, to return, go backward, withdraw, back up...

hoʻēmiemi

• to retreat,   • lag, hesitate;   • to lower a price,   • to bargain   caus/sim of emiemi, lowering, decreasing, diminishing, dwindling, lagging slowly; backward... redup. of emi₁, to diminish, reduce, depreciate..., emi₂, cheap...

hoʻēmu

caus/sim of emu₂, to rid plants of weeds...

hoʻēwe

caus/sim of ēwe₁, sprout, rootlet; lineage, kin; birthplace; family trait; to sprout...

hoʻēʻe₁

to rise or swell, as surf; to mount, as a surfer mounts a wave

hoʻēʻē₂

to keep away from, avoid

hoʻīho

See iho, to go down, and -iho.

hoʻīlewa

pain of hunger. cf. houpo lewalewa.

hoʻīli kaua

to attack in war

hoʻīlina

heir, inheritance, legacy, estate, heritage, bequest; successor...

hoʻīli₁

to land upon, load, as freight on a ship; to transfer, consign, transmit; to set on shore.

hoʻīli₂

to bequeath or leave in a will; to lay aside, save.

hoʻīloli

• to feel the discomforts of pregnancy;   • to suffer emotional disturbance;   • to yearn for an absent lover;   • to be imbued with (often used favorably)

hoʻīlo₂

land term of unknown meaning used in the 1840s, perhaps a winter-time plot.

hoʻīnana

to animate, give life to

hoʻīnea

to cause hardship, distress

hoʻīnu

to give to drink. also hoʻoinu.

hoʻōeoe

to stretch out, as the neck; to reach high; to prolong, as a sound; to toll; to yodel

hoʻōheke

to cause shyness, to be modest

hoʻōhelohelo

to color pink

hoʻōhemo

to cause weakness; to pretend weakness

hoʻōhewa

to bring on drunkenness; drunk, incoherent

hoʻōhewahewa

redup. of hoʻōhewa drunk, incoherent.

hoʻōho

to exclaim, cheer, shout, halloo. cf. hoʻōhooho below and kiko hoʻōho.

hoʻōhooho

redup. of hoʻōho

hoʻōhule₁

to cause baldness; to shear the hair completely

hoʻōhule₂

complete defeat, as in card games, whitewash (keep opponent scoreless, slang)

hoʻōiwi

to pass oneself off as a native son; like a native son

hoʻōkaoka

to pulverize, cut into little pieces.

hoʻōki

to put an end to, terminate, conclude, annul, finish, stop; end.

hoʻōkohe

to cause a scab to form, etc.

hoʻōkohekohe

redup. of hoʻōkohe

hoʻōkomo

caus/sim of ʻōkomo, to insert, include; to calk, as a ship; to inlay...

hoʻōkomokomo

redup. of hoʻōkomo caus/sim of ʻōkomo

hoʻōkupe

to trip someone; to stumble or pretend to stumble

hoʻōkuʻu

to cause to squat, crouch, perch; to crouch, perch

hoʻōla hou

to restore to life, revive, resurrect

hoʻōla pānaʻi

to redeem, ransom; redeemer

hoʻōla₁

to save, heal, cure, spare; salvation; healer; savior...

hoʻōla₂

small piece of tapa; tapa in general (Kauaʻi).

hoʻōlepe

to cause to turn, shut, etc

hoʻōlepelepe

redup. of hoʻōlepe

hoʻōlohe

caus/sim of ʻōlohe₁, bare, naked, barren; hairless, as a dog; bald; destitute, needy...

hoʻōlohelohe

to denude. caus/sim of ʻōlohelohe, redup. of ʻōlohe₁ bare, naked, barren; hairless..

hoʻōluheluhe

to cause limpness, etc

hoʻōmalu

to cast a heavy shade; overcast

hoʻōmalumalu

redup. of hoʻōmalu, to cast a heavy shade...

hoʻōmamaka

caus/sim of ōmamaka, same as ʻōmakamaka redup. of ʻōmaka₁; to leaf out or bud afresh...

hoʻōmaʻomaʻo

to make green, paint green

hoʻōmo

to draw in, as a wave. caus/sim of omo₁, to suck, absorb; suckling; to gasp...

hoʻōmou

to cause to pin, to pin, to pretend to pin

hoʻōnaha

to cause to be stooped, bent, bowlegged; to imitate the walk of a bowlegged person

hoʻōnaona

to impart fragrance; attractive, sweet, alluring

hoʻōne

pumice; to rub and polish with sand

hoʻōnea

to cause desolation; to desolate

hoʻōneanea

redup. of hoʻōnea

hoʻōniu

to spin, as a top; to cause to whirl

hoʻōniʻo

to spot or print with colors, as tapa

hoʻōniʻoniʻo

caus/sim of ʻōniʻoniʻo, embroidered (Biblical); mottled...

hoʻōnoʻonou

caus/sim of ʻōnoʻonou, to force upon...

hoʻōnēnē

caus/sim of ʻōnēnē₁, fretful, fussy...

hoʻōnū

to cause to swell, expand

hoʻōpaha

to make lopsided; misshapen

hoʻōpahapaha

redup. of hoʻōpaha

hoʻōpaka

to cut in ʻōpaka fashion

hoʻōpala

to litter, make rubbish, strew, soil, make untidy

hoʻōpeʻa

• treacherous,   • overturning;   • to cause to twist, cross, etc

hoʻōpili

to cause a cramp, numbness, etc

hoʻōpio

to make young, freshen, refresh, rejuvenate; to act young

hoʻōpiopio

redup. of hoʻōpio

hoʻōpulepule

caus/sim of ʻōpulepule₁, moronic, somewhat crazy, psychotic. see pule and ex., ʻōhewahewa...

hoʻōʻā

to mix

hoʻō₁

to cause to enter, put or dip in, thrust in, insert; to reach in

hoʻō₂

to provide food for a journey

hoʻūlala

to behave as one crazy; to cause craziness

hoʻūlili

to act like the tattler bird

hoʻūlu

to stir up, inspire, excite, taunt. also hoʻoulu

hoʻūouo

caus/sim of uōuō, redup. of uō bellow, roar...

Huana Pelenana

Juan Fernandez.

Hua₇

name of the thirteenth night of the lunar month.

Hua₈

name of a star

Huehu₁

name of a strong northwesterly wind of the winter months. Also Kiu Inu Wai and Mālua Kiʻi Wai.

Huhui₂

Pleiades.

Hui Heihei Moku Pākīpika

Pacific Yacht Club. lit., Pacific ship racing club.

Hui Keʻa ʻUlaʻula

Red Cross.

Hui Moku Holo Piliʻāina

Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company.

Hui Mokulele Piliʻāina

Inter-Island Airways Company.

Huia₂

name of a surfing wave.

Huihuikōkōamakaliʻikauiluna

a name for Pleiades. lit., Makaliʻi's net hanging above.

Huihui₄

Pleiades.

Hukekona

Hudson, as the river or bay.

Hukuenoka

Huguenot.

Hulialopali

name of a wind at Lahaina, Maui. lit., turn to the face of the cliff.

Hulona

Huron.

Humumā

name for the cluster of three stars in a row in the constellation Aquila. lit., Humu and companions.

Humuʻula₂

name of a place on the slopes of Mauna Kea.

Humu₃

the star Altair, in Aquila, said to have been used for navigation from Hawaiʻi to Tahiti. Also Hoʻohumu.

Hunakalia

Hungary; Hungarian.

Huna₃

eleventh night of the month.

Hunekali

Hungarian, Hungary.

Huo

name of an unidentified star.

hua alakaʻi

a leading note in music, the major seventh of any scale, a semitone below the tonic.

hua aniani

glass bead.

hua hapa

half note, as in music.

hua hapahā

quarter note, as in music.

hua helu₂

a few, little.

hua hoʻoneʻe

combination, as of a safe. lit., number to make move.

hua hoʻonoho

type.

hua hāule wale

also said of a sweet potato produced from the extended vine as distinguished from the product in the hill.

hua hāʻule

fallen fruit or seed. fig., friendless, uncared for by parents or chief; bastard, illegitimate child (modern); foetus lost through miscarriage.

hua hōʻailona

abbreviation.

hua iki

small letter, small fruit.

hua kahi

an only child or offspring.

hua kai

scrambled eggs.

hua kalakala

bur.

hua kani

tone in music.

hua kanu

seed, as of mango; bulb.

hua kineko

jacinth.

hua kukaima

mandrake.

hua kukui

Kukui (candlenut) nuts.

hua kumu

alphabet. lit., basic letters.

hua kēpau

printer's type.

hua kōkua

grace note in music.

hua lani

offspring of a chief.

hua lewa

ʻōhiʻa or ʻōhiʻa ʻai fruit uses as medicine (Kam. 64:103, 141); perhaps also a kind of wood.

hua lili

blasted fruit.

hua liʻiliʻi₁

berry.

hua liʻiliʻi₂

grace note in music.

hua liʻi₁

small or inferior fruit; runt; small, puny.

hua liʻi₂

small letter.

hua loaʻa

product, answer, as in arithmetic.

hua mele

notes in music; words of a song.

hua mua₁

offering to a Congregational church of the first earnings in a new job or undertaking; offerings in gratitude for a particular success, as a big fish catch. lit., first fruit.

hua mua₂

initial letter, first word.

hua māhoe

a two-note chord.

hua nanai

name of the hinahina root when used in hana aloha, love sorcery.

hua nui₁

large fruit; to be fruitful, productive.

hua nui₂

capital letter.

hua palaoaʻeleʻele

rye (Secale cereale).

hua palapala hiō

italics.

hua palapala leo hui

consonant. lit., letter joined in pronunciation.

hua palapala leo kahi

vowel. lit., letter pronounced separately.

hua palapala nui

capital letter.

hua pale

barley (Hordeum vulgare).

hua pākā

scrambled eggs, omelet.

hua pāma

date. lit., fruit of pāma, date palm.

hua pōpolo

pōpolo berry.

hua waina

grape, grapes (Vitis spp.). lit., wine (Eng.) fruit.

hua waina maloʻo

raisins. lit., dry grapes.

hua ʻai

edible fruit or seed. cherries (HE)

hua ʻalo

missing letter.

hua ʻaluʻalu

egg with a very soft shell.

hua ʻokoʻa

whole note in music.

hua ʻole

fruitless, unproductive, worthless, sterile, unrewarding.

hua ʻē

child born out of wedlock, that is accepted by the husband or wife of the parent and treated as his own. lit., strange fruit. Kaʻū.

hua ʻōlelo₂

an affront to a family ʻaumakua god.

huaale

pill, tablet. lit., seed to swallow.

huaale hoʻomoe

sleeping tablet.

huahekili uka

a small native naupaka (Scaevola kilaueae) found only on dry lava near Kīlauea Volcano. It does not exceed a height of 80 cm, has narrow, thick leaves, dull-yellow flowers, and small black fruits that were used to dye tapa.

huahekili₁

hail. lit., thunder fruit.

huahekili₂

rare name for the beach naupaka (Scaevola) plant.

huahualau

interrogation to incriminate, ensnare, or obtain information by roundabout methods, to question or quiz indirectly.

huahuaʻi

• to boil up, as water in a spring;   • to gush forth, effervesce;   • culmination of sexual passion.

huahua₁

fruitful, productive, prolific; to bear many fruits; to lay many eggs.

huahua₂

testicles. see insult, loaʻa … kāu.

huahua₃

a vulgar gesture of contempt made by thrusting the thumb between index and middle fingers with the fist clenched, or the fist held up to the face and the eyelid drawn down. With the gesture one sometimes said, "Eia kāu ʻo ka huahua," "Here's your huahua gesture."

huakaʻi

• trip, voyage, journey, travel,   • procession, parade;   • mission, quest (NKE12), adventure (Hopita).

huakaʻi hele

travels, a long trip; to keep traveling.

huakaʻi hoʻohanohano

honor escort.

huakaʻi kaʻahele

tour; to make a tour.

huakaʻi pō

night procession or parade, especially the night procession of ghosts that is sometimes called ʻoiʻo.

huaka₁

clear as crystal, bright, dazzling, white, shining, flashing.

huaka₂

shadow, reflection.

huakē

full and plump, as a healthy person; well proportioned, as a properly built canoe.

hualala

curved, warped, oval, twisted.

hualani

a variety of sweet potato.

hualau

a variety of banana. lit., many fruits.

hualele₁

seeds of the laulele plant.

hualele₂

hernia. lit., flying testicles.

huali

bright, polished, clean, pure, white, glittering, gleaming; morally pure.

hualūkini

musk, as used in making perfume.

huamailani

lit., fruit from heaven.

huamakani

tiny, yolkless egg. lit., wind egg.

huamoa₁

round-ended bone entering the hip socket.

huamoa₂

type of house with thatch purlins separated by a width of three fingers.

huamoa₄

a variety of sweet potato.

huana

gushing forth, overflow.

huapalaoa

wheat. lit., flour (Eng.) grain.

huapala₁

orange trumpet or sweetheart vine (Pyrostegia venusta syn. Bignonia venusta, B. ignea), an ornamental climber from Brazil, bearing early in the year many deep-orange flowers, hence chestnut-colored or light brown. lit. ripe fruit.

huapala₂

• sweetheart, lover;   • pretty, handsome.

huapala₃

chestnut brown.

huapoʻo

bones of the side of the head; side of the head.

huawaimaka

collection of dew or rain water, pool.

huaʻala

nutmeg, spice. lit., fragrant fruit.

huaʻina

boiling up, opening, uncovering: to gush forth, as lava.

huaʻi₁

• to disclose, reveal, uncover, as an oven;   • to disinter, dig up, (hu₁ + -aʻi, transitivizer).

huaʻi₂

pour forth, break forth;

huaʻi₃

to churn water, as a ship propeller

huaʻono

a variety of sweet potato.

huaʻulaʻula

the red sandalwood tree (Adenanthera pavonina), from parts of tropical Asia and Malaysia, of moderate height and with rather widespreading branches. The tree is planted in parks, and its round, lens-shaped, red seeds are used for leis, and their long, yellow-lined pods for decorative arrangements.

huaʻā

very sour, of poi.

huaʻōlelo hoʻohuiʻia

compound word.

hua₂

round object, as pill or bead.

hua₃

• result, effect;   • credit, as for a university course.

hua₄

testicles.

hua₆

• word, letter, figure,   • watchword, rallying cry,   • note in music;   • winning word in the Chinese gambling game of chee-fah;   • type;   • to speak.

hua₉

the bulging of the broadest part of a paddle blade.

hue mānalo

an edible sweet gourd.

hue nuku pueo

a variety of gourd with a short beak.

hue wai

gourd water container, water bottle.

hue wai pueo

water gourd shaped like an hourglass. lit., owl water gourd.

hue wai pūʻali

gourd water container with constriction about the middle.

hue wai ʻihi

long-necked water container.

hue ʻawaʻawa

type of bitter gourd, as used for utensils.

hue ʻili

container or bag for liquids made of animal skin.

huehue haole

a wild passionflower (Passiflora suberosa) with small greenish-yellow flowers, small three-lobed or undivided leaves, and blackish fruits 1.3 cm in diameter. lit., introduced huehue.

huehuelo

tail end, as of a strip of pandanus plaiting.

huehue₁

pimples, acne; to have pimples.

huehue₂

a native climber (Cocculus ferrandianus), with oval leaves and bluish one-seeded fruits. The stems were used for twine and for funnel-mouthed fish traps. (Neal 354.) Also hue ʻie.

huehu₂

chilled, benumbed, as of one shivering in this wind.

huelo māewa

tail end, especially of a junior line of a lineage.

hueloelo

tail-like, having tails.

huelopoki

whaleboat.

huelopōpoki

Australian bluegrass, Andropogon sericeus. lit., cat tail. Niʻihau.

hueloʻawa

sting, as of a scorpion, lit., bitter tail.

hueloʻīlio

a small shrub (Buddleja asiatica), native of southeastern Asia to Java, growing wild in Hawaiʻi, related to the summer lilac. It has narrow leaves and small white flowers growing in long narrow clusters. lit., dog tail.

huelo₁

tail, as of dog, cat, or pig; train of a dress; tail-end, last. fig., inferior.

huelo₂

a hop vine.

huene

a wheezing sound, as of asthmatic persons; a prolonged shrill cry.

hueʻie₂

demijohn.

hue₁

gourd, water calabash, any narrow-necked vessel for holding water, flask.

hue₂

• quick, as in stealing or deception;   • light-fingered;   • to steal, filch,   • move fast;   • to work the rope fast in skipping rope;   • theft (rare).

hue₃

a type of hula dancing, usually at the end of a program, a kind of ʻai ʻami with a revolving of the hips as fast as the drummer can beat time, to see who can dance longest; to dance thus.

hue₄

a way of connecting net sections by, interlocking meshes.

huhue

possibly a redup. of hue₂, fast.

huhuhu

insect-eaten, rotten, worm-eaten, wormy.

huhuhue

to filch repeatedly, to steal in company.

huhuhui

to meet as equals, as two beautiful persons.

huhuhula

Hawaiian hula by many persons; to hula, of many.

huhuhulei

lifting, tossing about, trotting, sporting, leaping, twisting.

huhuhuli

to turn, seek frequently.

huhuhune

redup. of hunehune and hune₁,₂; fine, dainty; stripped of all property.

huhui helu

logarithm. lit., number collection.

huhui palaoa

ears of grain.

huhui waina

cluster of grapes.

huhui₁

cluster, collection, swarm, bunch.

huhuki

to pull hard or frequently.

huhula

hula dance by many; to dance the hula, of many.

huhuli

to seek, turn, of many and repeatedly.

huhulu

bristling, tousled, as feathers, fur, body hair.

huhulu kū

to rise, as fur of an angry dog.

huhuna

particles, fragments.

huhune₂

skin eruption on animals, as hog, dog; to have such.

huhupaolāʻau

a wood borer. fig., slanderer, defamer. lit., borer that digs wood.

huhuʻailāʻau

wood-eating borer.

huhuʻe

probably a redup. of huʻe; to cease, quit.

huhu₁

• a wood-boring insect, termite;   • worm-eaten, rotten.

huhu₂

to pet, cherish, as animal pets.

huhū wale

short-tempered, peevish, cantankerous, angry without cause.

hui hali ukana

express company.

hui hoʻopaʻa

insurance company.

hui hōʻaiʻē kālā

credit union. lit., society [for] loaning money.

hui kahi₁

united in one; in accord and agreement.

hui kahi₂

girded in malo or pāʻū tightly fastened with a single hitch.

hui kinai ahi

fire department.

hui kālepa

trading company, mercantile firm.

hui malū

any secret society or fraternity, as the Masons; Masonic; to meet secretly.

hui o Papa

Chorus of Papa, a prayer for the purification of women uttered in the early morning at the Hale o Papa, house of Papa, a temple reserved for women.

hui puhi ʻohe

band (musical).

hui pū

to mix, unite, blend, assemble, combine, mingle. see ʻAmelika Hui Pū ʻIa.

hui ʻia

incorporated, united, joined.

hui ʻuwī waiū

dairy.

huihui maka liʻi

a kind of seaweed.

huihui ā kōlea

to gather together like a flock of kōlea birds. fig., to gather together to help one another in time of trouble.

huihui₁

mixed, mingled, united, joined; to pool together, as to buy cooperatively.

huihui₂

cluster, collection, bunch.

huihui₃

constellation.

huika

wheat.

huikala

• to absolve entirely, absolution;   • forgive all faults, excuse, pardon,   • atonement,   • cleanse and purify morally; ceremonial cleansing.   cf. (Malo 199).

huikau

mixed, confused, haphazard, blurred; mix-up, confusion, jumble; to mix.

huikaʻi

to mix or jumble, make disagreeing statements, put several stories into one. (hui₂ + -kaʻi, transitivizer).

huila kaulike

disc wheel of a sewing machine.

huila makani

pinwheel. lit., wind wheel.

huila nihoniho

stitch regulator of a sewing machine.

huila nui

large wheel; flywheel, as of a sewing machine.

huila wai

water wheel, windmill.

huilapalala

wheelbarrow.

huila₂

wheel.

huina alanui

crossroads, street corner.

huina helu₁

sum of several numbers, total.

huina helu₂

general arithmetic.

huina koho

purchase price, as at an auction.

huina kūpono

right angle.

huina loaʻa

gross profit.

huina peleleu

obtuse angle.

huina pū kuni ahi

battery (artillery).

huina waina

cluster of grapes.

huina ʻoi

acute angle.

huina-

geometric figure. See huinahā, huinakolu, and others.

huinahiku

heptagon.

huinahā

quadrangle, quadrilateral.

huinahā hiō

figure with four equal sides but oblique angles, rhombus.

huinahā hiō lōʻihi

oblique parallelogram.

huinahā kaulike

square.

huinahā like

square. lit., equal square.

huinahā like ʻole

quadrangle with unequal sides.

huinahā loa

rectangle.

huinahā lua like

quadrangle with only two sides parallel, trapezoid.

huinahā pāʻani

children's blocks.

huinakolu

triangle.

huinakolu kūpono

right-angle triangle.

huinakolu like

equilateral triangle.

huinakolu peleleu

obtuse triangle.

huinakolu ʻaoʻao like ʻole

irregular triangle.

huinakolu ʻelua ʻaoʻao like

isosceles triangle.

huinakolu ʻoi

acute triangle.

huinalima₁

pentagon.

huinalima₂

joining of two hands, especially in hand wrestling (uma).

huinalāʻaulana

raft. lit., collection of floating logs.

huinaono

hexagon.

huinapapalana

raft. lit., collection of floating boards.

huinawai

pool, meeting place of two or more streams.

huinawalu

octagon.

huina₁

sum, total, amount.

huina₂

unit, cluster; military detail or detachment.

huina₃

angle; corner, as of a house or street; crossroads, intersection, junction, juncture.

huina₄

tie or slur (music).

huini₁

needle-pointed, sharp-pointed.

huini₂

sharp, shrill sounds; to make such shrill cries.

huini₃

wooden peg used in mending bowls.

huipaʻa

syntax.

huipa₁

kind of hard, black stone used for maika stones.

huipa₂

whip; to whip.

huipuʻu

type of pāʻū (no data).

huipū

conjunction (the part of speech).

huiʻapa

a kind of stone, as used for making maika stones.

hui₁₀

a prayer on the morning after ʻanāʻanā sorcery. (Pronunciation uncertain: perhaps huʻi.)

hui₂

to join, unite, combine, mix, come together with; combination. See hui pū and saying, nāwao₁.

hui₃

a plus sign.

hui₄

cluster, as of grapes or coconuts; bunch, as of bananas.

hui₅

chorus of a song.

hui₆

flippers of a turtle.

hui₈

small uniting stick in a thatched roof, supporting rod for purlins.

hui₉

to disperse, as a meeting.

huka pihi

buttonhook; to hook a button.

hukahūkai

somewhat insipid, brackish.

hukailoloa

one who has long served a chief.

huka₁

hook, as on a door, shoes, clothes; to hook.

huka₂

advice, information.

huka₃

a balm.

huki leo paʻa

stroke that impedes speech.

huki like

to pull or work together, cooperate.

huki wai

to draw water; one who draws water.

huki ʻino

to jerk, pull hard or suddenly.

hukiheʻe₁

smooth.

hukiheʻe₂

fine-meshed net used for fish fry.

hukihuki₁

• to pull or draw frequently, or by many persons;   • to pull by jerks or continuously, as in the tug-of-war game (see hukihuki₃);   • to gather, as taro;   • friction, dissension. (see hukihuki₂)

hukihuki₂

to disagree, quarrel; disagreement; not cooperative, headstrong, obstinate.

hukihuki₃

tug-of-war game; to play the game.

hukikū₁

snobbish, haughty.

hukikū₂

uncooperative.

hukilau

a seine; to fish with the seine. lit., pull ropes (lau).

hukina

a pulling.

huki₂

• a fit of any kind, convulsion, stroke, spasm, epileptic fit;   • twitching, cramp, as in the leg;   • to have a fit or cramp.

huki₃

a hula step: one foot steps to the side, the other foot is pulled toward it so that the heels almost touch, and then is taken to the opposite side.

huki₄

soft, tender, as cooked meat that pulls apart when picked up.

huki₅

twisted, drawn at the mouth, as a result of illness.

hukopa

hyssop.

huku

protuberance, lump, projection, elevation, jutting out, heap; to protrude, jut.

huku liʻi

small protuberance; small, little.

hula Pahua

a kind of fast hula that increases to a frenzy, said to have been named originally for a mele maʻi named Pahua [pahua₁] (shoved). Emerson (UL 183–5) calls it a stick dance and gives an example. To perform this dance.

hula Palani paʻi umauma

name of chest-slapping hulas performed for Kalākaua's coronation.

hula Pele

sacred dance in honor of the goddess Pele.

hula honu

Hula in which the dancer imitates the motions of a turtle.

hula hoʻonānā

any hula for amusement.

hula kiʻi₁

dance of the images in which the dancers postured stiffly like images; to dance thus. Kauaʻi.

hula kiʻi₂

a dance with marionettes.

hula kolili

a dance with love forfeits, similar to those in the kilu and ʻume games.

hula kuahu

altar hula, any hula taught with ceremonies and an altar, contrasting with hula ʻauana.

hula kuhi lima

sitting dance with gestures of hands and swaying of torso

hula kuolo

sitting chant dance; the performer beats the gourd drum (ipu) and chants.

hula kuʻi

any interpretive hula, so called since the days of Kalākaua; lit., joined hula, i.e., old and new steps were joined together .

hula kuʻi Molokaʻi

the punch (kuʻi) hula of Molokaʻi, an ancient, fast dance with stamping, heel twisting, thigh slapping, dipping of knees, doubling of fists as in boxing, vigorous gestures imitative of such pursuits as dragging fish nets, and unaccompanied by instruments. This dance originated on Molokaʻi, an island famous for sports. Many of the songs contain taunts, as a laʻa kō kū i ke aʻu, now you are jabbed by the swordfish. cf. hula kuʻi under kuʻi, joined.

hula kōlea

a kneeling hula imitative of the kōlea, plover.

hula lāʻau pili

name of hulas performed for the coronation of Kalākaua, probably stick hulas.

hula manō

sitting dance imitative of sharks.

hula muʻumuʻu

a sitting dance...

hula mānai

dance with a thin flexible stick which the squatting dancer beats time as by striking the floor.

hula nemanema

name of hulas performed for Kalākaua's coronation.

hula noho

any sitting hula; to perform such.

hula pahu

dance to drum beat, perhaps formerly called ʻai haʻa (UL 103)

hula papa hehi

dance in which the dancers use the papa hehi, treadle boards; this dance is said to have originated on Niʻihau.

hula peʻepeʻemakawalu

a spider dance with stiff legs, dancers hopped, right foot forward and left in reverse; then opposite, keeping time with a boisterous chant and with hands fluttering vigorously.

hula puaʻa

a hula dance in which the hips sway from side to side in imitation of a fat hog's waddling. Also ʻami puaʻa.

hula ʻauana

informal hula without ceremony or offering, contrasted with the hula kuahu; modern hula.

hula ʻiliʻili

Hula in which smooth water-worn stones are used as clappers or castanets; the pebble hula.

hula ʻulīʻulī

hula with ʻulīʻulī, gourds.

hula ʻīlio

a hula imitative of the movements of a dog.

hula ʻōlepelepe

name of hulas performed for Kalākaua's coronation.

hulahula₁

ballrom dancing with partners, American dancing, ball; massed hula dancing; to dance.

hulahula₂

twitching, fluttering.

hulahula₃

ceremonial killing of a pig and offering it to the gods during the long ceremonies dedicating a luakini temple.

hulahē

to jump for joy, cavort with happiness.

hulali₁

• shining, to shine,   • glittering, glitter, sparkle,   • glossy,   • reflect light.   • slippery;

hulali₂

a kind of loli, sea cucumber.

hulaʻa

same as hulā,   • to prod, pry,   • uproot,   • pierce and penetrate,   • expel,   • reject...

hulaʻana

place where it is necessary to swim past a cliff that blocks passage along a beach or coast; sheer cliff where the sea beats.

hula₂

song or chant used for the hula; to sing or chant for a hula.

hula₃

to twitch, as a muscle or eyelid; to palpitate, throb.

hulehulei

repeated motions or lifting; to seesaw.

hulei

• to lift, raise, draw up, as a skirt;   • to pull, pry;   • to pitch and toss, as a ship on the waves;   • to move along, as a ship;   • to flap wings;   • to trot, as a horse.

huleilua

intensifier of hulei; to toss and pitch, trot, swing.

huleʻia

a kind of soft pumice stone.

huli alo

to turn toward; to face one another.

huli hana

diligent in work; to seek work.

huli hele

to search here and there.

huli honua

profound study of earth, geology; to do such. cf. (RC 433).

huli hope

• to turn back;   • inverse, as in math.

huli kanaka

profound studies of any kind, moral philosophy, social science, anthropology; to do such.

huli kua₁

to turn one's back, refuse to help, ignore; one who does so, as one who is offended.

huli kua₂

back section, as back house wall.

huli lua

to turn in two directions or twice; to shift, as the wind; unstable, shifting.

huli manaʻo

to seek an opinion; to change an opinion.

huli mio

taro stalk with spent strength.

huli pau

to overturn completely; to search everywhere; said sometimes as equivalent to modern "bottoms up", toast, instead of the vulgar "ōkole maluna".

huli pewa

• twists of the tail;   • fig., passing of time.   See pawa₁ and pewa₁.

huli pū

to overturn, turn upside down, overthrow.

hulialana

to remove the bitterness, especially to pour off the bitter liquid and add fresh water to the preparation of arrowroot (pia).

huliau₁

turning point, time of change.

huliau₂

to think of the past, recall the past.

hulihia

pas/imp. of     • huli₁, to turn, reverse; to curl over, as a breaker; to change, as an opinion or manner of living;     • huli₂, to look for, search, explore, seek, study; search, investigation; scholarship   • overturned;   • a complete change,   • overthrow;   • turned upside down.   Chants about Pele with verses beginning with the word "hulihia" are referred to as hulihia. See prayer, kualakai₂.

hulihuli₁

;

hulihuli₂

;

hulikoʻa

to seek into the depths of a matter, to describe fully; description.

hulikua

ornamental comb decorated with feathers, with ornaments turned towards the back.

hulilau₁

• a variety of large gourd or calabash, used as receptacle for tapa or garments, or for food offerings.   • fig., a woman, mother, wife.

hulilau₂

border, boundary.

hulilawa

to find enough material goods, as food.

hulili

• dazzling light,   • vibration, undulation;   • to blaze, sparkle, dazzle, glare,   • vibrate,   • swell.

hulilī

to shiver.

hulimaiʻa

name of a reddish-brown honey-sucking bird (no data). lit., banana seeker.

hulimoku

• to turn and rush;   • to pour forth, as a cloudburst;   • to stampede.

hulina alo

facing, face to face, opposite.

hulina₁

• turning, turning place,   • overturning,   • reversing,   • frontage.

hulina₂

a searching, seeking; search.

hulina₃

soft and sticky, glutinous, gluey.

hulinuʻu

highest rank or grade.

hulipahu

second mate of a vessel. lit., binnacle turner.

hulipeua

greedy; a greedy person.

hulipoepoe

globe. lit., revolving sphere.

hulipūloa

a variety of taro.

huliāmahi₁

to join together in great numbers to cooperate; to act with unanimity, as a political party.

huliāmahi₂

strong, as the sea. [see (Gram. 8.7.2): huli-ā-mahi 'turn like a strong (cock)'; i.e., cooperation, strength. see mahi₂: strong, energetic, as a worker. moa mahi, fighting cock.]

huliʻaoʻao

to lean over to one side, tilt, turn to the side.

huli₃

section, as of a town, place, or house.

huli₄

taro top, as used for planting; shoot, as of wauke (see ʻae₇).

huli₅

trump or winning card.

hulu aliʻi

royal favorite and loved one; royal feather.

hulu hipa₁

sheep wool, fleece; woolen cloth.

hulu koʻo

long tail feathers, as of a rooster.

hulu kupu

pinfeathers, new-grown fur.

hulu kupuna

the precious few living blood relatives of the grandparent's generation (a term of affection and pride).

hulu kuʻemaka

eyebrow.

hulu kākau

a pen, quill for writing.

hulu makua

precious parent or relative of the parent's generation.

hulu manu₁

bird feathers.

hulu manu₂

green seaweeds (Caulerpa spp.), growing like land plants, with roots, prostrate stems, and leaflike divided fronds; not edible.

hulu manu₃

court favorites of Kamehameha III.

hulu pena

paintbrush.

hulu piʻi

body hair, animal hair, or feathers standing on end.

hulu puaʻa

a small, matted, red seaweed (Spyridia spinella), its many branches covered with short bristles. It is rather common in shallow water near shore. It is eaten in South Hawaiʻi, but not generally elsewhere.

hulu weuweu

downy feathers or beard, fuzz.

hulu ʻaina ʻole

an esteemed, beloved person well cared for. lit., choice one not rejected.

hulu ʻiʻi

a kind of seaweed.

hulu ʻāʻīlio

horse's mane.

hulu ʻīlio₁

a fine, red seaweed (Centroceras clavulatum), forming short, dense, regularly branching tufts, with tiny forked tips; not edible. lit., dog fur.

hulu ʻīlio₂

fine, branching, edible brown seaweeds (Ectocarpus spp.), forming short, olive-brown clumps.

hulu ʻīlio₃

a fine, branching, green seaweed (Cladophora nitida), forming flexible, long, bright-green tufts; said to be edible.

hulu ʻīlio₄

a fine, feathery, green, fresh-water alga (Stigeoclonium amoenum), found in streams and ditches; said to be edible.

hulu ʻīlio₅

a fine, unbranched, green seaweed (Chaetomorpha antennina), looking much like hulu ʻīlio₃.

hulu ʻīlio₆

a fine, nonedible, brown seaweed (Sphacelaria tribuloides), densely tufted, shorter and darker brown than Ectocarpus.

hulu ʻīlio₇

some kinds of Polysiphonia seaweeds.

huluhulu waena

an irregularly branching, dark-red seaweed (Grateloupia falicina) with many narrow segments. It is commonly eaten and is sold in some markets.

huluhulu weo

bristling, glowing.

huluhuluaʻīlio

a green, velvety, carpet-like mountain moss. The spore cases rise above the plants. lit., fur like a dog's.

huluhulu₁

body hair, hair of eyelashes, fleece (Lunk. 6.37) , wool, fur; hairy.

huluhulu₂

frayed, splintered, rough, not smooth, shaggy, bristling, feathery.

huluhulu₃

blanket.

huluhulu₄

feathers.

huluhulu₅

down or fuzz on plant stems, rootlet.

huluhulu₈

kinds of seaweeds and mosses.

huluhulu₉

flannel.

hului₁

a kind of bag fish net; to drag such a net.

hului₂

to take or grab, as winnings.

hulukoa

bird crest.

hulukoaʻe

a kind of grass.

hululua

hook with two barbs.

hulumanu

tick used for mattresses and pillow covers, so called because they were stuffed with bird feathers.

hulumoa

the Hawaiian mistletoes (Korthalsella spp. formerly called Viscum), small plants perching on trees and extracting part of their food from them. They have flat or cylindrical jointed green stems. lit., chicken feathers.

huluokaʻauhelemoa

a moss said to grow only in Pālolo Valley, Honolulu, named for Kaʻauhelemoa, a legendary cock defeated in battle by a hen. She pulled out his feathers, which fell and became this moss. It is used in leis.

hulupala

light brown, bay, as a horse.

hulupuaʻa

beard hanging from the breast of mature turkey males. lit., hog hair.

huluʻiwi

a pig that is reddish-colored about the hams. lit., ʻiwi bird feather.

huluʻānai₁

scrubbing or painting brush, formerly made of a coconut husk.

huluʻānai₂

a variety of sea urchin.

hulu₂

esteemed, choice, precious; esteemed older relative, as of parents or grandparents' generations. (This meaning may be connected with the value attached to featherwork.)

hulu₃

fur, wool, fleece, human body hair (contrasting with lauoho, head hair).

hulu₄

kind, nature, color.

hulu₅

hackle; fishhook with barb on the outside.

hulu₆

brush.

hulu₇

muscle attaching a bivalve to rocks.

hulu₈

seal, named for its valuable fur.

hulu₉

cloth.

hulā

• to prod, pry,   • uproot,   • pierce and penetrate,   • expel,   • reject

hulō

hurrah, cheers.

hume

• to bind about the loins, as a malo;   • to put on a malo;   • to wear a sanitary napkin.

humena

a girding on of a loincloth; part of the loins covered by the malo.

humu hoʻi

back stitching; to sew with back stiching.

humu hoʻoholoholo

running stitch, basting.

humu kaulahao

chain stitch; to make chain stitches.

humu lala

to sew in a diagonal line.

humu peʻa

sail-making; to sew sails.

humu puka pihi

buttonhole stitch.

humuhumu hiʻu kole

pinktail durgon (Melichthys vidua). lit., red-tailed triggerfish.

humuhumu lei

lei triggerfish (Sufflamen bursa).

humuhumu mimi

bridled triggerfish (Sufflamen fraenatus). lit., urine triggerfish, so called because of its odor.

humuhumu puke

bookbinding.

humuhumu puke ʻili lole

cloth bookbinding.

humuhumu puke ʻili pepa

paper bookbinding.

humuhumu ulana

to darn, as socks.

humuhumu umauma lei

a variety of humuhumu fish (Balistes bursa). lit., humuhumu with leis on its chest.

humuhumu ʻeleʻele

black triggerfish (Melichthys niger), used as fuel when fuel was scarce.

humuhumunukunukuāpuaʻa

varieties of humuhumu (Rhinecanthus aculeatus, R. rectangulus). lit., humuhumu with a snout like a pig. [In l984, the reef triggerfish (Rhinecanthus rectangulus) was selected as the official State Fish of Hawai‘i after a popular vote and the approval of the State Legislature. The State Fish’s official term of office lasted five years, and there was no re-election campaign. In May of 2006 Governor Linda Lingle signed a bill that permanently established the humuhumunukunukuāpua‘a as the State Fish of Hawai’i.]

humuhumu₁

to sew, of many or continuously.

humuhumu₂

trigger fish. The name humuhumu is qualified by the following terms (in addition to those listed separately as identified): kapa or kapu, lei , māneʻoneʻo (said to be irritating to the mouth), ʻuwīʻuwī (thought by some to be the young of the māneʻoneʻo).

humuhumu₃

a variety of taro with coloring like that of the humuhumu (fish); the leaf stem is pink at base, dark-purple midway and green above.

humuhumu₄

a dark-colored birthmark, believed to be the result of the pregnant mother's eating humuhumu (fish).

humuhumu₅

to destroy, ravage.

humuhumu₆

seam.

humukā

cross-stitching; to do cross-stitching.

humulau

to embroider.

humuna

sewing, seam.

humuniki

pattern in pāwehe plaiting, said to consist of a continuous row of red lozenges with their lateral angles touching.

humupapa

to sew to a backing, as feather leis.

humupaʻa

lock stitch, a stitch that does not loosen easily; to sew thus.

humuwili

overcasting stitch; to hem.

humuʻula₁

red jasper stone, as used for adzes.

humuʻōmou

stitch used in tacking.

humu₁

• to sew, stitch; seam, stich;   • to bind together parts of a fishhook;   • to bind, as a book.

humu₂

hole by which parts of a hook were bound together.

huna kai

sea spray, sea foam.

huna kaua

a battle unit, either a single individual or a group of men; host of an army.

huna lepo

dust particle.

huna olonā

waste and refuse of olonā after the fiber is cleaned.

huna pakēpakē

a species of Hypnea, a seaweed. lit., brittle huna.

huna wai

drop of water, spray, mist.

huna wailele

spray from a waterfall.

hunaahi

fire spark, live cinder.

hunahuna

fragments, particles, crumbs, scraps.

hunahuna ʻōlelo

a particle, as ua, e, i in Hawaiian.

hunakai₁

white-flowered beach morning-glory (Ipomea stolonifera; synonym, I. acetosaefolia), distributed in tropical regions, with oblong to lyre-shaped leaves, and white flowers with yellow centers.

hunakai₂

sanderling (Calidris alba), a small winter migrant to Hawaiʻi, cinnamon brown with dark markings. lit., sea foam, so called from the bird's habit of following close behind receding waves.

hunakānaʻi

a kind of tapa with white and yellow dots.

hunalewa

van of an army, front ranks.

hunapaʻa

rear guard of an army.

huna₁

minute particle, grain, crumb, gram, speck, tiny bit, scrap, minutia; small, little, powdery. (This word is similar to hune₂.)

huna₂

hidden secret; hidden. cf. huna₁, a stative usually following nouns, and the transitive verb hūnā.

huna₄

common, fine, red seaweeds (Hypnea spp.), irregularly and more or less densely branching, thorny looking; eaten cooked, furnishes a good colloid when boiled.

hune kai

sea spray, sea foam.

hune one

fine-grained sand, sand particles.

hunehune₁

redup. and intensification of hune₂, very fine, delicate.

hunehune₂

bits, as of news, gossip; minutia.

hune₁

poor, destitute; a poor person.

hune₂

fine, tiny.

hunāhunā

to hide frequently or be hidden by many persons; secretly.

huoi

suspicion.

hupa

hoop.

hupau

to draw together.

hupilo

a kind of pilo₃. (Coprosma).

hupu

collection; catch, as of fish. (This rare word is not clear.)

huā

envy, jealousy; envious, jealous; to stir up trouble due to envy.

huāelo

Var. spelling of hua āelo.

huʻa kai₁

foam.

huʻa kai₂

sponge

huʻa kapa

pile of tapas.

huʻa kapu

taboo borders, as of a taboo place, or of the taboo enclosure where hula was taught.

huʻa kopa

soap bubble.

huʻa lole

trimmings or borders of a garment; hem of a dress.

huʻa moena

pile of mats.

huʻahuʻa kai₁

sponge.

huʻahuʻa kai₂

sea foam; crest of a wave breaking into foam.

huʻahuʻa kai₃

a variety of seaweed.

huʻahuʻa kopa

soapsuds.

huʻahuʻa lana

floating froth. fig., an ignoramus.

huʻahuʻakō

a coarse, weedy native dock (Rumex albescens) in the buckwheat family.

huʻahuʻa₁

foam, froth, lather, bubbling, frothing.

huʻahuʻa₂

jelly.

huʻalepo

to scatter dust, especially a method of fighting with a club or spear in which the opponent was blinded by stirring up dust; to hit an underhanded blow.

huʻa₁

foam, froth, bubble, suds, scum.

huʻa₂

• rim, border, edge, side, hem;   • ruffles and tucks at the bottom of a dress;   • tucks in a mat;   • train of a gown.   See mānele huʻa hoʻohiwahiwa.

huʻa₃

• suburb,   • boundary.

huʻa₄

pile, as of mats or tapa.

huʻe

• to remove, lift off, uncover, expose;   • to reveal.   • to unload, as a ship;   • to open, as an oven;   • to exhume,   • push, force, prod;   • to wash out, as flood waters;

huʻehuʻe₁

redup. of huʻe   • to keep removing;   • to take out and put in again, as furniture;   • to overflow repeatedly.

huʻelepo₂

small hula graduating exercises held at noon outside in the dust (lepo).

huʻena

opening, unloading, flowing, pushing.

huʻi lele

darting pain.

huʻi₁

ache, pain; aching.

huʻi₂

a prayer.

Hākau₃

oppressive older brother of ʻUmi... see ʻUmi₃.

Hālala₂

name of Kalākaua's genital. see (EM 67).

Hālaulani

a star, said to be observed in the month of Hilinehu.

Hāloa₂

a son of Wākea.

Hāloa₄

star name.

Hāmākuaikapaiaʻalaikahala

name of a lua fighting stroke. lit., Hāmākua of the bowers fragrant with pandanus.

Hānaiakamalama₁

the Southern Cross.

Hānaiakamalama₂

name of a benevolent goddess.

Hānaiakamalama₃

name of Queen Emma's residence in Nuʻu-anu Valley.

Hāna₂

name of a district and town, East Maui.

Hāwaʻe₄

name of a famous evil sorcerer. See lauhue₁, for figurative meaning.

Hāʻao₂

name of a rain at ʻAuʻaulele, Kaʻū and at Nuʻuanu, Oʻahu, so called because its showers follow one another like members of a chief's retinue.

Hāʻena₂

place names on Hawaiʻi, Kauaʻi, and Oʻahu.

hā niu

heavy end of a coconut frond.

hā wai

water trough or pipe, aqueduct, flume. rain gutter (HE)

hā wai laweʻino

sewerage pipes, sewage system.

hāehu

to grow well.

hāhoʻoili

hereditary stalk; established people with inherited land.

hāhā hele

to grope here and there, feel.

hāhā lua

a native tree lobelia (Cyanea leptostegia), found only on Kauaʻi. The trunk is slender, unbranched, to 12 m high, and bears a crown of narrow leaves that are up to 60 cm long. The many flowers are purplish-red, the fruits yellow berries.

hāhā nui

a native shrubby lobelia (Cyanea horrida), from Maui, with thorny branches and rough, lobed leaves.

hāhālua

manta ray, sea devil, family Mobulidae (Manta alfredi). lit., two mouths (two flap-like appendages extend forward on each side of the mouth).

hāhāmau

to catch fish with the hands, as in crevices.

hāhāpaʻakai

salt bed or pool; to gather salt.

hāhāʻaiakamanu

a native lobelia (Clermontia clermontioides), found only in high mountains of Kauaʻi, a shrub or small tree with many branches; oblong and narrow leaves; greenish-purple, curved flowers; and sweet, edible yellow berries. lit., hāhā, food of the birds, so called because the thick sap was used for catching birds.

hāhā₁

to grope, feel, as with the hands.

hāhā₃

trap made of twigs and small branches, for fresh-water fish.

kāʻei poʻo

diadem, turban.

kāʻei pāpale

hatband.

kāʻekeʻeke

bamboo pipes, varying in length from .3 to about 1 m; usually with one end open. A player held one vertically in each hand tapping down on a mat or on the ground. The tone varied according, to the size of the tube. Several musicians might play at once. (UL 143–4), (Roberts 53) Barrèrre suggests (Barrère 1980:11) that kāʻekeʻeke as the name for bamboo pipes seems to have originated with Emerson. She quotes Andrews (who refers to (Laie)) as saying the name applied to coconut-tree drums. It is also used as a verb. Also ʻohe kāʻekeʻeke or pahūpahū.

kāʻeko

peeved, offended.

kāʻekā

entangled, confused, twisted; to interweave.

kāʻeleloi

roll, ruffle, as of a drum.

kāʻele₁

darkened; cf. ʻele, black.

kāʻele₂

numerous.

kāʻele₃

slow, delaying.

kāʻele₄

a seaweed.

kāʻeo₁

full, as a food calabash. fig., full of knowledge.

kāʻeo₂

strong, zealous.

kāʻeo₃

hair gathered in a topknot on the head, as by priests in ceremonies.

kāʻeuʻeu

helpful, cooperative; joyous, active larger, bigger.

kāʻeʻaʻeʻa

expert, hero, fighter.

kāʻeʻe₁

a sea bean (Mucuna gigantea), native from southeast Asia, east into Polynesia, a high-growing vine, bearing greenish flowers and large pods, each pod containing two to four round and flattened seeds, black-spotted or brown. In Hawaiʻi, the seeds, known as pēkaʻa, are found on the beaches, and are used medicinally for their strong purgative effect and are also strung for leis.

kāʻeʻe₂

• hand net hanging on an ellipsoidal wooden frame with one end pointed, used for ʻōhua and other inshore fish;   • to use this net or a skirt of a dress in this type of fishing;   • to strain, as through a strainer.

kāʻiewe

group of relatives who faithfully serve and care for a chief during illness; perhaps related to ʻiewe, placenta.

kāʻihi₁

dizzy, dizziness.

kāʻihi₂

• to refuse to pay losses or   • forfeit, as in a game;   • to use another's property without permission;   • to usurp.

kāʻihi₃

a fine meshed fish net, similar to kāʻili.

kāʻili wale

to plunder, rob, seize, usually without premeditation.

kāʻilikū

to plunder, rob, seize, as in premeditated violence.

kāʻiliponi

to die suddenly, as by stroke or accident.

kāʻiliʻili₁

• snatching,   • pulling, especially of a newly carved canoe hauled from the mountains to the sea.

kāʻili₁

to snatch, grab, take by force, seize, abduct, usurp. (see song, (EM 58–9))

kāʻili₂

to cast for fish.

kāʻili₃

fine net as used for ʻōpelu fishing.

kāʻili₄

to gasp, labor for breath

kāʻioʻio

to bear a second crop of sweet potatoes.

kāʻiʻiwi

a climber (Strongylodon ruber, misidentified locally as S. lucidus), in the bean family, endemic in Hawaiʻi, with three-parted leaves and large seeds. The flowers are clustered, red, and shaped like narrow beaks.

kāʻiʻī

hard, rigid; stingy, close-fisted, hard-hearted, harsh; to refuse help; to deny a request; to strut pompously; persistent.

kāʻokoʻa

• whole, entire;   • separated,   • independent,   • neutral,   • standing apart,   • definite.   cf. ʻokoʻa, different, kūʻokoʻa, and holoʻokoʻa, entire.

kāʻope

yellowish mother-of-pearl shell.

kāʻēʻē

joyful, glad, hospitable, friendly.

kāʻēʻēʻe

very joyful, glad, etc.

kā₁

• to hit, strike, throw, smite, hack, thrust, toss, fling, hurl, dash, especially with a quick hard stroke;   • to bail water, as from a canoe (kā₂);   • to clean, as weeds or mud from a pond;   • to fling the arms or swing them while walking;   • to make net meshes;   • to tie, as thatch battens;   • to knit;   • to fish with a pole;   • to turn the soil;   • to turn a rope for children to jump;   • to remove, as a cataract from the eye with the edge of a blade of kūkae puaʻa grass;   • to snare, as birds;   • to curse (especially if used with ʻino; cf. kāmalū, to do evil to another in secret; to forbid, warn in secret...);   • to murder; murderous; murderer, dead shot. For kā i ka waha, see waha.

kā₁₂

czar.

kā₁₃

tar, asphalt.

kā₂

canoe bailer; to bail.

kā₃

beater, knee-drum beater made of dried ti leaves or braided fiber.

kā₄

cross-stitching.

kā₅

vine, as of sweet potato; to send out a vine, to vine, to grow into a vine.

kā₆

root cutting, as of breadfruit; to send forth shoots.

kā₇

pelvic bone.

kā₈

incoming, of a current (au).

kā₉

container, hanger.

Kēhau₂

name of a gentle land breeze, as of West Hawaiʻi; Kapaʻa, Kauaʻi; Kula, Maui; Hālawa, Molokaʻi and Oʻahu.

Kēhela

name of a star.

Kēkēmapa

December.

Kēkēpue₂

name of a star.

Kēpia₂

name of a wind associated with Hilo.

Kēwai₂

name of a Hilo wind.

kēhau anu

cold dew, frost.

kēhaupaʻa

ice.

kēhau₁

dew, mist, dewdrop.

kēhu

Var. spelling of ke ehu.

kēhue

yellowish, of soil.

kēhōhō

bray, to bray, as a donkey.

kēkake₁

donkey, jackass.

kēkake₂

same as piula, a card game.

kēkewe

bloated, swelled, as with dropsy; so fat that the stomach overhangs.

kēkēpue₁

to shun others; to withdraw from others, as in shame.

kēkē₁

distended, enlarged, as a stomach in pregnancy; big-bellied.

kēkē₂

a kind of fish (And), perhaps a variant name for ʻoʻopu hue, puffer fishes.

kēlau

to put out first leaves.

kēlou

hook; to hook.

kēlā…kēia

this and that, all, every, everything, here and there; miscellaneous, various (kēlā always precedes kēia)

kēlō

sail ho!

kēlū

quail. The usual name is manu kapalulu.

kēnā₁

to command, order, give order, summon, send on business.

kēpama

sperm.

kēpau

• lead, pewter;   • printers' type;   • sinker on a fishing line.   • pitch, tar, resin, gum, as on ripe breadfruit; any sticky juice, as of pāpala [shrub];

kēpau kaʻa

resin.

kēpau kāpili mekala

solder.

kēpau kāpili palapala

sealing wax.

kēpau pōkā

lead, bullet lead.

kēpia₁

dandruff.

kēpuka

sleight-of-hand trick; to play such tricks.

kēpā

spur, as used by horseback riders.

kēpū

zebu.

kēueue

to push against, oppose, seek to remove a person from his position.

kēwai₁

• watery, dripping,   • misty;   • damp,   • dewladen;   • spoiled, of eggs.

kēwā₁

far-off place inhabited try spirits.

kēwā₂

to anticipate.

kēʻae

to saturate, soak in.

kē₁

• protest, complaint, criticism; to criticize;   • critic, especially a hula critic;   • formerly a hula master who was invited by another hula master to criticize his class;   • to push, shove, struggle against, oppose,   • shun, avoid, abstain from, refuse.

kē₂

to clang, as a bell or gong; to dingdong, strike, as a clock.

kē₃

to flatten out, adjust to a surrounding level, as in removing a heap of earth.

kē₄

player of the pūhenehene game.

kē₅

same as kā₁₀, the interj., mild disapproval, surprise.

kē₆

the letter "k'."

Kīhaelāʻī

breeze at Puʻuʻōhua on the Hāmākua side of Hilo. lit., to shred ti leaves.

Kīkomohana

Key West.

Kīkī-ʻula

name of a star. lit., red emitting.

Kīnaʻu₅

Kalani Ahumanu i Kaliko o Iwi Kauhipua o Kīnaʻu [c. 1805 – April 4, 1839], daughter of Kamehameha I and Kaheiheimālie, and wife of Kekūʻanaōʻa; she was the mother of Kamehameha IV, Kamehameha V, Victoria Kamāmalu, and Kekūāiwa. After Kaʻahumanu's death she became Kuhina Nui for Kamehameha III, an office she held until her death in 1839 at the age of 35 (RC 348). In a chant in her honor, Kīnaʻu is said to have been named for a mythical.bird, Kamanukīnaʻu-a-Pae. lit.: flaw. .

Kīpuʻupuʻu₁

name of a chilly wind and rain at Waimea, Hawaiʻi.

Kīpuʻupuʻu₂

name of a company of warriors from Waimea in Kamehameha I's time, named for the wind.

Kīʻaha₂

the Big Dipper (modern).

Kīʻailana

Sea Island, Gossypium barbadense, a variety of cotton grown in Hawaiʻi.

kī Kepanī

a weed (Cassia leschenaultiana). Niʻihau. lit., Japanese ti (its leaves were used for tea).

kī alakaʻi

tonic, keynote (music). lit., leading key (Eng.).

kī hoʻoikaika

staccato mark (music); small dot or wedge placed over a musical note.

kī hōʻalu

slack key (the first and last strings of the guitar are tuned to D, instead of E; the strings are picked individually and are not chorded).

kī kaola

crossbar or beam used to close a door or gate. lit., beam key.

kī lāʻau

wooden key or latch, as in a gate.

kī nehe

the Spanish needle (Bidens pilosa), a lowland weed; young fresh plants are still brewed for tea (kī). Similar to koʻokoʻolau, also used for tea.

kī pololei

to shoot straight; sharpshooter.

kī pōkā

to shoot.

kī pū

to shoot, fire or discharge a gun.

kī ʻaʻala

sweet basil (Ocimum basilicum), an aromatic herb of the mint family, with small white to reddish flowers, the leaves used to flavor food. lit., fragrant kī.

kī ʻulaʻula

a red ti grown for ornament, long in Hawaiʻi but not native.

kī-

intensifying prefix. Numerous examples follow, including kīhelu, kīkaha, kīkākala, kīlaha, kīmanamana, kīʻoʻe, kīʻohuʻohu, kīʻōnaha.

kīau

• to gallop;   • to walk lightly and swiftly;   • fast movement.

kīauau₂

encouraging workers, as in drawing an unfinished canoe hull from the forest to the shed at the seashore where it was to be completed.

kīauau₃

to smooth out wrinkles from tapa or clothes with light, deft touches.

kīhae₁

• to tear or strip, as leaves;   • to remove thorns from pandanus leaves;   • to shred, as ti leaves for dance skirts.   cf. hae, to tear.

kīhae₂

inspired with a wrathful spirit.

kīhakahaka

to force a wedge into an opening (formerly said of fighting).

kīhalalē

perhaps intensifier kī- + halalē.

kīhamu

to eat voraciously.

kīhapa

incomplete, partly finished; half-covered, as with a shawl over one shoulder.

kīhau

frugal, saving; sparingly; to ration carefully.

kīhei

• shawl, cape, afghan;   • cloak of makaloa matting;   • rectangular tapa garment worn over one shoulder and tied in a knot;   • bed covering;   • to wear a kīhei.

kīhei moe

light bedspread.

kīhei pili

two sheets, as of printed percale or patchwork, sewn together at edges, used as bed covering over the sleeper and under the nicer quilt. In some, the lower edges are left open so that a blanket may be inserted. lit., clinging covering.

kīhei ʻaʻahu noʻenoʻe

decorated cape. lit., colored garment cape.

kīheihei

to wear a kīhei.

kīhele

• hook; to hook;   • to feed poi to a child on the finger, which is bent (like a hook) so as to dislodge the poi.

kīhelu

to scratch.

kīhene

bundle or basket of ti or other leaves, as used to carry sweet potatoes, flowers, etc.

kīheu

to remove tiny weeds.

kīheʻaheʻa

• stained, streaked, especially with red or with blood;   • streak of fire, as seen in the wake of a fire-brand sailing aloft.

kīheʻaheʻa palaʻā

coloring matter for tapa made from the palaʻā fern.

kīheʻe

to pour.

kīhoe

to lead a roving life, without fixed abode, wander; vagabond.

kīholo₁

large wood fishhook, as used for sharks and large fish.

kīholo₂

large fish net about 20 fathoms long, held by a canoe at each end.

kīholo₃

long ti-leaf food package, more commonly called holo ʻai.

kīhonua

side or bank of a canal or ditch.

kīhāpai₁

• small land division, smaller than a paukū; cultivated patch, garden, orchard, field, small farm;   • parish of a church, diocese;   • department of a business or office;   • formerly various religious duties were divided into kīhāpai, as tending the altar, offering sacrifices.

kīhāpai₂

Madagascar periwinkle (Catharanthus roseus, syn. Vinca rosea), a perennial herb or small shrub, from tropical America, grown for ornament; flowers rose-purple or white.

kīhā₁

belch, burp; to belch or burp.

kīhā₂

to rise and pitch, as a canoe in heavy seas; to dive under water, as a porpoise.

kīhēhē

• to be or become deified;   • to pass into the air or to live invisibly there.

kīkaha

• to soar, glide, poise, wheel, skim along, as a frigate bird;   • to turn aside, detour, veer, deviate;   • to maneuver, as fighting cocks;   • to walk along absentmindedly, ignoring everyone.

kīkahō₁

to splash.

kīkahō₂

to speak or interrupt rudely.

kīkala hāneʻeneʻe

pyelitis, kidney disease; sacroiliac strain; lumbosacral slipped disks. lit., sliding hips.

kīkala moa

name of a seaweed that irritates the throat if eaten alone.

kīkala pai

flat, thin buttocks.

kīkala paʻakea

a rare idiom referring to hard-working tenant farmers in 1851.

kīkalakē

kind of fishhook.

kīkala₁

• hip,   • coccyx bone;   • posterior;   • stern, as of a canoe.

kīkanu

to cover, bury.

kīkau

to give freely and with good will.

kīkaʻelekē

frisky, restless; to jump here and there.

kīkenenei

to contract, shrink; to crouch or squat.

kīkepa₁

tapa or sarong worn by women under one arm and over the shoulder of the opposite arm.

kīkepa₂

• to lean over to one side,   • to cover one side;   • to turn to the side;   • to place in a one-sided manner;   • on the side, as a tapa or lei worn over one shoulder and under the opposite arm.

kīkepa₃

to bite sideways, snap.

kīkepa₄

edge, rim, as of a canoe.

kīkepa₅

pig of one solid color with a spot of another color on the shoulder.

kīkeʻe

• to bend, crook; bending, zigzag;   • perverted.

kīkeʻekeʻe

redup. of kīkeʻe, to bend, crook; bending, zigzag.

kīkiʻi₁

• to lean back;   • to tilt, heel, as a ship;   • to stretch out, extend.

kīkiʻi₂

spiral fishhook with the end curled back fairly close to the shaft.

kīkohu

spots, stains, blemishes; to stain, spot [contraction of kiko and kohu].

kīkoi₁

rude, sarcastic.

kīkoi₂

to do in irregular, haphazard fashion, as skipping about while reading; irregular.

kīkomo₁

to inlay; to mix, as sap from tree-fern fronds (palaholo) and māmaki bark with wauke bark while beating tapa.

kīkomo₂

pole fishing in shallow sea.

kīkoni

• small adze used for smoothing and finishing a canoe;   • to smooth and finish a canoe;   • to soften wauke bark for tapa making;   • to pierce or lance a swelling; a piercing,   • to peck; a peck,   • to blaze, as a tree; a blaze;   • to rap on the forehead, usually with a single knuckle, especially as a gesture of rudeness or contempt, hence to treat contemptuously.

kīkoʻo panakō

bank check.

kīkoʻo pānaʻi

bill of exchange. lit., exchange disbursement.

kīkoʻolā₁

sarcastic, rude, tart, impertinent, insolent.

kīkoʻolā₂

• haphazard, miscellaneous; here, there, and everywhere: topsy-turvy;   • carelessly performed,   • entangled;   • of awkward shape, as a package.

kīkoʻo₁

• span; extent;   • to stretch, reach or stick out;   • extend, as the hands, or as a bird its wings.

kīkoʻo₂

a measure from the end of the thumb to the end of the index finger.

kīkoʻo₃

chord of an arc.

kīkoʻo₄

a bent bow; to shoot, as from a bow.

kīkoʻo₅

a long surfboard, 3.7 to 5.5 m long.

kīkoʻo₆

to move; to step in order to reach.

kīkoʻo₇

to pay out money, disburse, draw money from the bank.

kīkoʻu

• to cultivate with a hoe or digging stick;   • to rap or strike with a club;   • to tap.

kīkā Pukikī

a mandolin, usually with 12 strings. lit., Portuguese guitar.

kīkākala₁

to strike with spurs, as fighting cocks.

kīkākala₂

to draw up with a hook, as in fishing octopus.

kīkākapu

various species of butterfly fishes of the genera Chaetodon and Cheilododactylus. Varieties are qualified by the terms alo lua and koʻa.

kīkāmū

suspicious, wary; gathering in silence, as fish about a hook they hesitate to bite.

kīkānia lei

a kind of nightshade (Solanum aculeatissimum), the round, scarlet fruits used in leis.

kīkānia pipili

Spanish clover (Desmodium uncinatum), a weedy, South American perennial herb with small clinging pods.

kīkānia₁

weed (RSV), tares (KJV). zizania.

kīkānia₂

cockleburs (Xanthium spp.), coarse herbs, bearing tenacious burs about 2.5 cm long.

kīkā₁

ʻōpelu fish, when about the length of a finger.

kīkā₂

strong, energetic; having authority and force, as a magistrate.

kīkā₅

the cigar flower (Cuphea ignea), from Mexico, a small, smooth shrub with narrow, red, tubular, odorless flowers nearly 3 cm. long. The flowers are used for leis.

kīkē ʻalāna

crashing sound, as of lava rock (ʻalā) smiting rock, or as made by an active aa lava flow; to sound thus.

kīkēkē₁

to knock, rap, tap, pound. cf. ʻelelū kīkēkē and kīkoni, to tap with a single knuckle.

kīkēʻōlelo

to argue, talk back, banter.

kīkē₁

• to rap, tap, knock;   • to break open, as with a hammer;   • to click glasses, as in drinking a toast.

kīkē₂

to share.

kīkīao

sudden wind gust, squall. fig., sudden burst of passion.

kīkīkoʻele

done to completeness, perfection.

kīkīkoʻu₁

chirping or screeching, as of a flock of birds; deep tone in chanting; tapping noise.

kīkīlona

to incite.

kīkīpalapala

a variety of taro.

kīkīpani₁

conclusion, last, end, every last one.

kīkīpani₂

severe stomach pains that make breathing difficult; to endure such.

kīkīʻalo₂

to dodge quickly.

kīkī₁

Redup. of kī₃,   • to shoot, as a gun;   • to incite or sick, as a dog;   • to spout.

kīkī₂

to do up the hair in a type of knot.

kīkī₃

crude temporary basket or bundle, as made of ʻilima, ti, or morning-glory plants and used to carry food.

kīkī₄

a bird resembling the plover.

kīkī₅

name given a shellfish.

kīkī₆

a seaweed.

kīkū

to lean back firmly.

kīlaha

broad, wide, ample, enlarged.

kīlau₁

bracken or brake (Pteridium aquilinum var. decompositum), a cosmopolitan, stiff, weedy fern, with creeping underground stems and long-stemmed, triangular fronds 60 or more cm long, much divided. Also kīlau pueo, paiʻā.

kīlau₂

ti stalk with shredded leaves, as held by a fishing director (kilo iʻa) and used to guide the fishing canoes; ti stalk used to flip water of purification.

kīlea

small but conspicuous hill.

kīleo₁

soft palate including uvula.

kīleo₂

trigger of a gun.

kīleo₃

ring of ʻie, a vine, sewed to the top of a fish basket to hold fish in place.

kīlepalepa

streamer, banner, tassel.

kīlepalepa kō

sugar-cane tassel.

kīlepa₁

to float in the wind, to flutter, flap, flip.

kīlepa₂

irregular, uneven, of varying lengths.

kīlepa₃

rooster comb, wattle.

kīloa

to put away for safekeeping, as bundles on a shelf.

kīlou

hook; to catch with a hook.

kīlua

to do with determination.

kīmanamana

branching in various directions.

kīmopō

night assassination, secret rebellion or coup; to waylay in the dark; to assassinate. fig., of any underhanded act.

kīmoʻo₁

neat bundles of stripped pandanus leaves ready for plaiting; to lay strips together and tie in long bundles, as of pandanus leaves or mulberry bark.

kīmō

• to pound,   • bruise,   • mash, as with stick or stone;   • to smash, break into bits;   • to dub out the inside of a canoe log with an adze, tamping and smoothing the surface;   • to crack, as nuts.

kīmōmō

to pound at a fast, steady rate.

kīnana

• mother hen or bird and her brood;   • a brooding place, chicken house.

kīnana hale

home, including the house grounds.

kīnaʻu₁

stain, blemish, defect, minor flaw or imperfection, mistake, blunder.

kīnaʻu₂

an eel.

kīnaʻu₃

young of aku and kawakawa.

kīnohi

decorated, spotted, ornamented; decoration, ornamentation.

kīnohinohi

printed, as calico. see ex., hoʻopukalia.

kīnā

• blemish, blotch, flaw,   • disfigurement or physical defect of any sort;   • disfigured, blemished, malformed, handicapped, imperfect, maimed;   • to mar, mutilate.   • blight; loss of crops due to any natural disaster, as drought, excessive rain, insects;   • sin, wickedness;

kīoeoe

long, tall, as a ship mast or giraffe neck.

kīoe₁

small surfboard.

kīoe₂

to turn the head with a rotary motion, as of a bird watching its prey.

kīolaola hao lio

horseshoe pitching; to pitch horseshoes.

kīolaola lina

ringtoss.

kīolaola₁

redup. of kiola, to throw, toss.   • tossing back and forth or up and down, as in juggling;   • to cast for fish;   • to sort and distribute, as sweet potato cuttings.

kīolaola₂

a form of black magic, by which a special stone was prayed over and hurled at a victim; it entered through the anus or mouth and destroyed the victim, and then returned to the magician.

kīpaepae

stone pavement or steps for entering a house. fig. transition, ceremony.

kīpahulu

place where soil is worn out (pahulu) from constant farming; worn-out soil.

kīpaipai

to encourage, inspire.

kīpalaheʻa

smeared, stained.

kīpalalē

• disorder, jumble, tumult; disorderly, unsystematic, without method;   • rapid flow, as of a swollen stream;   • to spread, extend in a disorderly fashion.

kīpaopao

to scoop out the earth from the side, as by the sea hammering on a coast.

kīpapa₁

• pavement, level terrace;   • to pave, lay stones in pavement or terrace;   • to wall in, as with stones.

kīpapa₂

to be close together, as clouds, or as taro neatly packed in a load; to shoot together (see papa₃).

kīpapa₃

a sweet potato.

kīpapa₄

prone position on a surfboard; to assume such.

kīpau

to overturn completely.

kīpaʻi₁

• to shoo away, as by clapping (paʻi);   • to drive away animals;   • to pat with the hands;   • to strike with the wings, as an angry bird.

kīpaʻi₂

to cover or spread leaves.

kīpehi

to pelt, throw at. fig., to assail with rough language, speak harshly.

kīpeʻa

to cross sticks, as in building a temporary shelter.

kīpohopoho₂

small arable patch surrounded by lava beds, smaller than a kīpuka.

kīpoho₁

• small, shallow pool, basin, or hollow in a rock, as where salt water collects;   • small container.

kīpoho₂

to dive, dip or pitch downward, as a kite.

kīpola

wrapper, such as ti leaves about fish; to wrap up, bundle up; to keep warm with wraps, as a sick person.

kīpolipoli

nook and cranny.

kīpolo

type of prayer used in black magic requesting that the victim be led to a place of death.

kīponapona₂

a small, climbing, native shrub (Phyllostegia racemosa) in the mint family, with small, downy leaves, and small, purplish-white flowers in whorls.

kīpou

to drive down, as a stake into the ground; to go downward; descend; to lean, as a post.

kīpoʻi

• to cover, conceal, hide;   • to protest giving away objects to others.

kīpoʻipoʻi₂

sweet potato patch.

kīpoʻohiwi₂

gun.

kīpoʻopoʻo

indented, pitted with holes; pits.

kīpuka ʻili

leather lasso.

kīpuka₁

variation or change of form (puka, hole), as   • a calm place in a high sea,   • deep place in a shoal,   • opening in a forest,   • openings in cloud formations, and especially   • a clear place or oasis within a lava bed where there may be vegetation.

kīpuka₂

short shoulder cape; cloak, poncho.

kīpuka₃

loop, lasso; snare, as for catching owls (a rat was tied to a sharp stick in a net; the owl, pouncing on the rat, was pierced by this stick).

kīpulu

fertilizer, mulch; to fertilize, mulch.

kīpuni₁

to gird, wrap around, surround.

kīpupū

• to hinder, draw back;   • to jerk and start, as an automobile.

kīpā

Chinese gambling game chee-fah; to play this game.

kīpāpali

cliff brink, small cliffs; hilly.

kīpē₁

bribe, bribery (Ioba 15.34) ; to bribe.

kīpē₂

to pelt with stones; to strike, as hail stones.

kīpē₃

a large ti-leaf bundle tied at one end.

kīpōʻaeʻae

armpit (pōʻaeʻae) and shoulder above it.

kīpō₂

depot.

kīpū lani

• immobile, motionless in the sky, as clouds, stars;   • steadfast and loyal to one's chief.

kīpūkai

seaside heliotrope (Heliotropium curassavicum), a prostrate, perennial American herb 30 to 60 cm long, with narrow, hoary leaves, white or pale purple flowers, considered indigenous to Hawaiʻi. Formerly the plants were dried and brewed for tea used as a tonic. Also nena and poʻopoʻohina or lau poʻopoʻohina on Niʻihau.

kīpū₁

• to hold back or brace, as a canoe on a wave with a paddle;   • to rein in, as a horse;   • to remain, as mist or rain;   • to fold tightly about one, as a blanket;   • steersman.

kīpū₂

tranquillity.

kīwawā₁

unintelligible sound of voices.

kīwawā₂

mulberry bark partly beaten into tapa.

kīwaʻawaʻa₁

full of ruts and furrows, rough, rutty, uneven; broad-shouldered, muscular, as a strong man (so called because the muscular furrows suggest canoes, waʻa).

kīwaʻawaʻa₂

type of coarse, rough tapa.

kīwaʻa₁

name of a mythical bird.

kīwaʻa₂

to dredge.

kīwaʻa₃

stick formerly used as a vise to hold the canoe while attaching the gunwale strakes (moʻo).

kīwila

civil, civic; civilian.

kīwini

brazen.

kīʻaha inu waina

wineglass.

kīʻaha kī

teacup.

kīʻaha puaniki

goblet. lit., holding cup.

kīʻaha ʻoʻoma

pitcher (pika is now in common use), vase. lit., concave tumbler.

kīʻahaʻaha

to pour liquid out of a cup or container (ninini is now in common use).

kīʻaho

cord or rope, as for hoisting a flag.

kīʻalo

to dig out, as the eyes, to scoop out; to reach out with a scooping movement.

kīʻamo

plug, stopper; sanitary napkin or napkin of any sort; any nozzle inserted in the rectum (ʻamo).

kīʻapu

ti leaf folded into a cup and used for dipping water; the two hands rounded to form a cup for drinking water; to cup the hand; to catch with cupped hands, as tiny fish; ladle.

kīʻeke

bag, satchel; basket.

kīʻililī₁

to squat on haunches; to perch.

kīʻililī₂

to trill, of a bird.

kīʻohuʻohu

mist; misty; misty place.

kīʻoki

striped; creased with fat; stripes.

kīʻoni

key to animate a toy.

kīʻopa

lame; to limp.

kīʻope₁

a bundle;. to make a bundle.

kīʻope₂

to scatter a fire in order to put it out.

kīʻope₃

a fish resembling kawakawa.

kīʻoʻe

• ladle, dipper, cup; scoop or spoon made of coconut shell;   • dip, as of poi;   • to skim, as cream from milk;   • to dip, ladle, scoop;   • arm or wrist motion in paddling or dipping;   • net-mending instrument; to join nets together;   • to twist and snap, as breadfruit with a lou stick.

kīʻoʻe poi

finger or single dip of poi.

kīʻōnaha

bent, crooked, curved.

kīʻū

latch on sewing machine to which the bobbin is attached.

kī₁

ti, a woody plant (Cordyline terminalis) in the lily family, native to tropical Asia and Australia. It consists of a branched or unbranched, slender, ringed stem, ending in a cluster of narrow-oblong, leaves 30 to 60 cm long, from among which at times rises a large panicle of small, light-colored flowers. The leaves were put to many uses by the Hawaiians, as for house thatch, food wrappers, hula skirts, sandals; the thick, sweet roots were baked for food or distilled for brandy. (Neal 203–4) Besides green-leaved tis, which rarely fruit, many ornamental varieties are grown in gardens, having leaves wide to narrow, large to small, the colors purple, crimson, scarlet, rust, pink, or green, striped or plain. Red tis may have red flowers and berries. Green ti leaves are still believed to afford protection from spirits and to purify a menstruating woman.

kī₂

the Spanish needle (Bidens pilosa), a weed from tropical America, a kind of daisy with simple or compound leaves, small yellow flower heads, and narrow black bristle-tipped fruits. Also kī nehe.

kī₃

• to shoot or aim, as with a gun;   • to squirt water, as with a syringe;   • to blow from the mouth, as a fisherman spitting chewed kukui nut on the sea to quiet it;   • to spit, as an angry cat;   • to travel fast, jet, hurry, especially on horseback (Kauaʻi).

kī₄

bundle of 40 pandanus leaves, sorted for size and length and set aside for plaiting; to sort leaves for such a bundle.

kī₇

trigger of a gun.

kī₉

gee.

Kōkiawailau

stroke in lua fighting.

Kōkua Hou₁

Counselor (RSV), Comforter (KJV).

Kōmomona

wind associated with Kahauiki, Honolulu. lit., sweat sugar cane.

Kōwā₂

star name (no data).

kō Kina

a kind of sugar cane, 1857. lit., Chinese cane.

kō Pākē

a variety of sugar cane, probably imported by the Chinese.

kō i kua

to go behind one's back, to do in a person's absence what one would not do in his presence.

kō ia ala

his, hers.

kō iwi

your own interests, your own

kō kula kai

lowland dweller; belonging to the lowlands.

kō kākou

our, ours (o-form, plural, inclusive).

kō kānāwai

law enforcement; to enforce the law.

kō kāua

our, ours (o-form, dual, inclusive).

kō laila

those of that place; local.

kō pua ʻole

a variety of flowerless sugar cane.

kō waʻa

line used for towing a canoe, especially for dragging canoe hulls from the forest where they were hollowed out to the shore; to tow or drag a canoe.

kō ā kai

shore dweller; belonging to the shore or sea.

kō ā uka

upland dweller, belonging to the uplands.

kō ʻaki

sugar cane (so called to distinguish from kōpaʻa and kōomoomo).

kō ʻaneʻi

the local, as kō ʻaneʻi poʻe, the local people (o-class; cf. kā ʻaneʻi).

kō ʻiʻo

accomplished, come to pass, come true, as a prophecy. lit., truly accomplished.

kō ʻolua

your, yours (o-, dual).

kō ʻoukou

your, yours (o-, plural).

kōaheahe

blowing gently, as the wind.

kōaniani

to waft, as a soft cooling breeze; to make a breeze with a fan; cooled by a breeze.

kōanoano

dark, gloomy, fearful.

kōekōe aku

go away.

kōelepālau

pudding made by peeling and mashing cooked sweet potatoes, then adding coconut cream gradually. Also pālau, poi pālau.

kōhahe

desolate, destitute, uninhabited.

kōhanahana

warm, hot.

kōheoheo₁

to fall, as through the air; to tumble.

kōheoheo₂

poisonous.

kōheoheo₃

coattail.

kōheoheo₄

stick or buoy that floats a fishhook.

kōheoheo₆

nose flute (hano is more common).

kōheo₁

to show off, parade, strut.

kōheʻe

to train or practice, as for foot races.

kōhi ʻai

to separate taro corm from stalk; to pick taro.

kōhikōhi

to cull, separate, grade, as fish or sweet potatoes.

kōhikōhikūpalalā

children's guessing game, with an object hidden in the earth or sand.

kōhina

part of taro where the corm is cut away from the top; splitting of a breadfruit for cooking.

kōhi₁

• to gather, as fruit;   • to break off neatly, as taro corm from the stalk with a stick or knife;   • to split, as breadfruit;   • splitter, as stick, stone, knife.

kōhi₂

fat, rich, as food; fatness.

kōhi₃

to fill or heal, of a wound.

kōhi₄

• to hold back, check, restrain:   • to strain, especially as in childbirth, to travail;   • to hold or hold back by pressing a person's arm, as in withholding consent, or as in urging someone not to be generous;   • labor pains,   • travail.   fig., agony, fear. Also haʻakōhi.

kōhi₅

prolonged, as a sound; long.

kōhi₆

to dig (For. 4:510).

kōhoko

an infection, probably luetic.

kōina

• urging, insistence;   • fine (as punishment).   • fig., firm attachment, as to a beloved child.

kōkala₁

• thorns on the edge of a pandanus or pineapple leaf;   • spines on a dorsal fin.   • Maka kōkala: thorny eyes, said (sometimes jestingly), (For. 5:83) of the Puna people, who concealed the placenta of a newborn child in a pandanus tree, believing that the child's eyelashes would then grow long as the pandanus thorns, giving the child a bright, keen look.

kōkala₂

porcupine fish (Diodon hystrix, Diodon holocanthus, Cheilomycterus affinis); both spines and flesh are regarded as poisonous; in some localities an ʻaumakua.

kōkaʻa

lean, of meat; dry, barren.

kōkeano

silent, deserted, uninhabited.

kōkeʻe

to wind, bend.

kōkikiu

away up high. fig., ambitious.

kōkoia

beating, as the heart.

kōkolikoli

dark, burned, of a kukui nut candle.

kōkoʻo

partnership, partner, associate, companion (nearly always followed by a number designating the number of associated persons, as kōkoʻolua, kōkoʻokolu. (See koʻo-)

kōkoʻohia

how many? (Of associated persons.)

kōkoʻohā₁

companionship, partnership, association of four persons; one of four associates.

kōkoʻokolu

partnership of three, one of three associates.

kōkoʻolua

companion, partner, associate, fellow worker, mate, partnership, second (in a dual), union (always of two).

kōkua Hou₂

new help; to help again.

kōkua kauka

doctor's aide, intern.

kōkua kumu

assistant teacher, substitute teacher.

kōkua luna kānāwai kiʻekiʻe

associate or deputy judge of the supreme court.

kōkua makamua

second team (horse or oxen following the lead team).

kōkuahaʻina

adverb. lit., aid in speaking.

kōkā₁

to lash back and forth, as the tail of an animal.

kōkā₂

to gag, stuff the mouth.

kōkē

to strike, hit, punish.

kōkēkōkē

the noise of hitting.

kōkīkī

sagging, bending; place where a branch divides off.

kōkī₁

extremity, tiptop, topmost; upper limit.

kōkī₂

to don a helmet.

kōkō lele

meaningless syllables occurring in chants...

kōkō puʻupuʻu

very fine kōkō net for a calabash carried by kahu of high rank with chief's food. lit., knotted net.

kōkō pūʻalu

netted bag made of sennit with large plain mesh. lit., loose net.

kōkō ʻula

network of red color, as of a spreading rainbow.

kōkōliʻi

thick black cloud.

kōkōwaikī

pith of banana stalk.

kōkō₁

• a carrying net, usually made of sennit, as used for hanging calabashes;   • a string hammock, as formerly used for carrying the very old.

kōkō₂

• to tie up strings, as of a calabash;   • lacings, as of sharkskin to a drum body.

kōkō₃

to pull, jerk, drag, push, massage; to set a bone by applying pressure.

kōkō₄

pregnancy; pregnant, heavy with child.

kōkō₆

cocoa.

kōlani

sitting hula in honor of a chief (lani).

kōlea lau liʻi

a native small tree or shrub with small leaves (Myrsine sandwicensis).

kōlea lau nui

a native tree (Myrsine lessertiana) in the rain forests, with narrow to wide, large leathery leaves clustered at branch tips, bearing many small round red or black fruits usually just below the leaves. Wood is not very hard, but was formerly used for house posts and beams.

kōlealea₁

to play with a child, as bobbing it up and down on one's leg and singing ditties with the refrain kōlealea.

kōlea₁

• Pacific golden plover (Pluvialis dominica), a migratory bird which comes to Hawaiʻi about the end of August and leaves early in May for Siberia and Alaska.   • fig., to repeat, boast; a scornful reference to foreigners (Kel. 70) who come to Hawaii and become prosperous, and then leave with their wealth, just as the plover arrives thin in the fall each year, fattens up, and leaves;   • a less common figurative reference is to one who claims friendship or kinship that does not exist;   • in some localities the kōlea is an ʻaumakua;   • to call kōlea. cf. hula kōlea and saying, kauhua₂.

kōlea₂

stepparent, as makuahine kōlea, makua kāne kōlea.

kōlea₃

the mottled periwinkle, probably Littorina pintado.

kōlea₄

native species of trees and shrubs (Myrsine [Rapanea, Suttonia]) with oval to narrow leaves more or less crowded at branch tips, small flowers, and small round fruits among or below the leaves. Uses: red sap and charcoal from the wood to dye tapa, wood for houses, logs for beating tapa.

kōlikoliko₁

swollen, enlarged, fat, greasy.

kōlikoliko₂

young wauke, bark.

kōlilelile

to glisten, sparkle, glitter.

kōliʻuliʻu

dim, obscure, indistinct, as a distant object or sound.

kōloa₁

long cane with a crook.

kōloa₂

to make a prolonged sound, roar.

kōluilui

continued ringing sound.

kōlulu

to defend, shield, ward off.

kōlīlili

to vibrate, as heat.

kōlīliʻi

dwindling, diminishing, as of water in a stream or pool, or of something in the distance, or of pain; convalescing.

kōlīlā

thin, bony.

kōlū

to scatter; to drop, as bombs; bombing.

kōmike

committee, committee member.

kōmike hui

joint committee.

kōmike komo ʻāpana

visiting committee.

kōmike ola

welfare committee.

kōmike wae

select committee.

kōmi₁

to press, bear down, rub, as in massage; to pull taut, as a fishline.

kōmou

prepared poi not yet mixed with water, softer than paʻi ʻai.

kōmōmo

candy.

kōnalelewa₁

variety of ʻaʻawa, a fish.

kōnale₂

quiet, tranquil, peaceful.

kōnane hoʻopaʻi

tapa-beater design.

kōnane pepehi

tapa-beater design.

kōnane pūpū

a tapa-beater pattern; a kōnane checkerboard design with rounded pits (pūpū) in the middle of each square.

kōnane₁

bright moonlight; to shine, as the moon; clear, bright.

kōnane₂

ancient game resembling checkers, played with pebbles placed in even lines on a stone or wood board called papa kōnane; to play kōnane. cf. nane, riddle; mū, papamū.

kōnane₃

tapa-beater design.

kōnea

restored to health.

kōniuniu

dizzy.

kōnui

stricken with great heat, as by the sun's rays.

kōnunu

rounded and well shaped, as a lehua flower.

kōomoomo

candy. lit., sucking cane.

kōpaʻa hoʻokeʻokeʻo

refined sugar.

kōpaʻa hōʻae

powdered sugar.

kōpaʻa mānoanoa

coarse sugar.

kōpaʻa puʻupuʻu

lump sugar.

kōpaʻa ʻulaʻula

brown sugar.

kōpiko kea

a species of kōpiko (Psychotria [Straussia] kaduana) with short-stemmed, rather oblong leaves, small flowers in long drooping clusters, and with small fruits. The wood is orange.

kōpiko ʻula

a kind of kōpiko (Psychotria [Straussia] hawaiiensis) with large leaves to about 18 by 9 cm, on stems 2.5 cm long, with midrib reddish below; the flowers covered with reddish down.

kōpiko₁

about 13 native species of trees belonging to the genus Psychotria, a member of the coffee family. Leaves are thick, leathery, blunt or pointed; flowers small, white, clustered at the ends of long stems at branch tips. Called ʻōpiko on Hawaiʻi.

kōpiko₂

torpedo.

kōpili₁

thin, transparent tapa made of mulberry bark.

kōpili₂

small white tapa placed over images and altars during religious services; the ceremony; to perform the ceremony. Also kōpilo nui.

kōpili₃

birthday gift to a child.

kōpī

• to sprinkle, as salt, sand;   • to salt, as fish or meat.

kōwehe

to billow or flutter out, as a dancer's skirt.

kōwelo

• to stream, flutter, wave;   • to trail behind, as the train of a gown.

kōwelokā

to trail or drag, as a dress train.

kōwā₁

• intervening space or time;   • channel, canal, strait,   • gulch;   • separated, as by a passage or channel.

kōwē

to go away.

kōā₁

var. spelling of kōwā₁, intervening space or time; channel, canal, strait, gulch; separated, as by a passage or channel...; crack or space, as between fence boards. cf. ʻoā, split, cracked, burst... [He wahi ma waena o ʻelua mea. Ke kai ma waena o ʻelua moku.]₁₄,₁₇

kōī₁

sharp, shrill, as a voice.

kōī₂

to flow with force, as water over a dam.

kōī₃

to string, as flowers for a lei or candlenuts on a coconut leaf midrib for a light; such a string.

kōī₄

sliding game; child's game with sticks dug into earth or sand while repeating a jingle.

kōī₅

a small tree (Coprosma kauensis), a native of Kauaʻi, related to the pilo.

kōū

to look about in all directions.

kōʻai

• to stir with a circular motion of the hand;   • to wind around, creep around, as a vine;   • to gird around, as a pāʻū sarong;   • to brace with a paddle.

kōʻalaʻala₁

probable redup. of koʻana₁, with n changed to l; food scraps.

kōʻalaʻala₂

quickly.

kōʻala₁

to broil or barbecue (of meat, fowl, fish). cf. kunu, pūlehu, and ʻala₁, fragrant.

kōʻala₂

fast, quickly.

kōʻehaʻeha

heat, sultriness; sultry, uncomfortably hot. fig., physical or mental distress or discomfort; distressed.

kōʻeleʻele₁

small, edible red seaweeds (Gymogongrus spp.), with rather thick, flattened stems and branches.

kōʻele₁

small land unit farmed by a tenant for the chief; to be worked as a kōʻele.

kōʻele₂

Friday, so called because commoners worked on the chief's farm, called kōʻele, on this day. Any work for a chief.

kōʻele₃

any variety of large, tough ʻopihi (the shells were used as scrapers and peelers).

kōʻele₅

a small pond, reserved for a chief, where fish could be kept alive until required.

kōʻele₆

less desirable portions of meat or fish.

kōʻieʻie₁

plaything, toy, used in water.

kōʻieʻie₂

rapid current or what it carries; to rush, as water.

kōʻiuʻiu

distant, faraway, so high as to be barely visible.

kōʻā

arid, barren, rocky and unfruitful; dry or tasteless, as overdone meat. fig., rude, nasty.

kō₁

sugar cane (Saccharum officinarum), a large unbranched grass brought to Hawaiʻi by early Polynesians as a source of sugar and fiber. The thick stems are full of sweet juicy pulp. In time, many different kinds of cane were produced, with many different attributes and names. Cane yields one of the most valuable plant products known. For commercial purposes the yield has been increased by hybridizing with such success that the sugar industry was for many years the largest industry in Hawaiʻi. (For. 5:582–9) lists types of kō, all are listed in the Dictionary except kō malolo (also known as kō puhala and kō ʻailolo).

kō₂

• dragged, towed, to drag, tow, push, pull, tug,   • wind-borne;   • long, as a vowel sound; prolong, drawl;   • to hold a note for several beats in singing or chanting;   • massage.

kō₃

• to fulfill, come to pass, succeed, do, complete, foreclose; fulfilled.   • to win in dispute;   • to become pregnant;

kō₄

to break up lumps in poi by pressing against the side of a container.

kō₅

second note in musical scale, re.

kō₆

and interj. A call to pigs, fowl. Also kolo, kolo, kolo.

kō₇

of (o-form possessive). Note idiomatic use with ā, as far as, plus a direction word: kō ā uka, those of the uplands; kō ā mua, those in the foreground; kō ā hope, those behind.

kō₈

your (of one person; singular possessed object; replacing both kāu and kou, often with affectionate connotation).

Kū Kahi₁

name of the third day in the lunar month.

Kū Kanaloa

to pray to the god Kanaloa, as on the Kāloa days of the month.

Kū Kolu

name of the fifth day in the lunar month.

Kū Lua

fourth day of the old lunar month; also, the name of the 17th day and second after the full moon.

Kū Pau

name of the sixth day of the lunar month, and last of the four taboo days of Kū.

Kūaliʻi

one of the last great chiefs, a descendent of Līloa's wife Pineʻa, said to have subjugated first his own Oʻahu, and then the remainder of the Hawaiian Islands. He was succeeded by his son Peleiōhōlani (Pele at Hōlani [a mythical realm] ). (Kam) says he died in 1730 at the age of 175 (For. 4:432). In a 610-line chant he is praised as a mortal (kanaka), a god (akua), one who flies from heaven (ulele mai ka lani), and a foreigner (haole) from Tahiti (For. 4:394-395). lit., royal Kū.

Kūea

star name (no data).

Kūkalahale

name of a rain and wind famous at Honolulu.

Kūkauakahi

said to be an old name for the gods Kāne, Kū, and Lono. The theory of a trinity is believed due to remaking of Hawaiian legends by Kepelino, Kamakau, and Fornander to conform to the Bible. see Barrère-1969.

Kūkoaʻe₂

name of a god appealed to in ʻanāʻanā, evil sorcery.

Kūkulu o Kahiki

Pillars of Kahiki; it was believed that the sky was supported by a vertical wall along the horizon; the section of the wall over Kahiki (formerly Tahiti) was the Kūkulu o Kahiki.

Kūkāʻilimoku

Kamehameha's war image.

Kūlanihākoʻi

mythical pond or lake in the sky; its overflow comes to the earth as rain. lit., like heaven agitated.

Kūlōlio

name of a wind at Hāmākua, Maui. (Probably a contraction of kū kololio, gusty state.)

Kūmakua₂

name of a strong wind.

Kūmau₃

North Star.

Kūmokuhāliʻi

a god of forests and canoe makers; his wife was Lea. lit., Kū island spreader.

Kūpoʻilaniua

name of a star. lit., stands the rainy sky cover.

Kūpuku₂

name of a constellation of a cluster of seven stars.

Kūpāʻaikeʻe

god of canoe makers.

Kūʻiakānakaheleokapō

a stroke in lua fighting. lit., people traveling at night are hindered.

Kūʻīlioloa

a giant man-dog. He was killed by Kamapuaʻa (pig man), who stuffed his own weed bodies down the dog's throat and cut his way out (HM 202). The hero Kaulu tore him apart; therefore dogs are small today (HM 348). A girl fled down his throat and his tail was cut off; hence dogs have short tails (HM 500). lit., Kū long dog.

Kū₁₀

name for the third, fourth, fifth, and sixth days of the month, usually called respectively Kū Kahi, Kū Lua, Kū Kolu, Kū Pau.

Kū₁₁

ancient Hawaiian god of war. Prayers connected with this major god include Kūkoliʻi, Kūlawa, Kūlewalewa, Kūpapaʻa, Kūwā, Kūwī... In some accounts, Kū and Hina were the first gods to reach Hawaii, and were followed next by Kāne and Kanaloa, and last by Lono (HM 11). Kū (upright) represented male generating power, and Hina (prostrate) was the expression of female fecundity and the power of growth. Kū also refers to the rising sun, and Hina to the setting sun; hence their realm includes the whole earth and the heavens and all generations of man born and unborn. (HM 12-13). Many fictional characters are named Kū and Hina, with implication of high birth, and most of the few references to infanticide in the stories refer to Kū and Hina, possibly indicating that it occurred rarely and that the motive was racial purity. Dozens of epithets are associated with Kū. Various forms of Kū were appealed to for rain and growth, fishing, and sorcery, but he is best known as a god of war. When gathering medicine with their right hands, people prayed to Kū for success. The third, fourth, fifth, and sixth nights of the lunar month were sacred to Kū. He sometimes assumed the form of the ʻō-hiʻa tree or the ʻio hawk. lit., upright.

kū hele

to get up and go.

kū hou

to rise again, recover from illness, resurrect.

kū ihoiho

candlestick.

kū kahi₂

standing alone, outstanding, unique, first.

kū kaʻawale

to stand apart, be entirely different, independent.

kū paʻakai

to soak in brine, as meat.

kū pona

to stand a bond.

kū uaki

to stand a watch; watchman, sentinel, guard.

kū ā

to turn into; to be similar to. (In some constructions this sequence is followed by particles or qualifiers and may be considered a verb compound; note kūākanaka and kūāmaʻi in (Gram. 8.7.2))

kū ā makalau

having abundant offspring. lit., generation of many faces.

kū ākea

to stand openly or in public; to take a public stand.

kū … kā

used only in the idiom ʻo kū! ʻo kā! This originated in Wahineʻōmaʻo's chant: ʻO kū, ʻo kā ʻo Wahineʻōmaʻo, wahine a Lohiʻau ipo (PH 184), bam! boom! Woman-in-green, wife of Sweetheart-Lohiʻau. Wahineʻōmaʻo did not know how to dance or chant; her song was merely a rhythm beat to which she marched about comically. Hence the idiom has come to mean 'a lick and a promise, do it as quickly as possible and get it over with.'

kū-

qualitative and stative prefix.

kūakalikea₁

kind of cloth with white on its edges.

kūakalikea₂

whorish [especially of Hawaiian women having love affairs with white men]. lit., becoming white vagina.

kūakā

boom, boom!

kūaluʻula

red cords used to decorate a chief's canoe.

kūamuamu

to revile, blaspheme, curse, swear, damn, insult; to chant a curse or reviling song.

kūanoano

highly respected. (Malo text, chapter 16, section 15).

kūauʻi

according to Emerson (UL 95), same as lūauʻi.

kūau₁

an endemic fern (Asplenium kaulfussii) with oblong fronds about 60 cm. long, with twelve or more pairs of narrow, pointed pinnae.

kūau₂

a sea creature (perhaps Aplysia sp.).

kūaʻai hoʻ olilo

sale.

kūhaka

of high position, as one possessed by the gods. lit., stand perch.

kūhalahala

to find fault with, criticize; dissatisfied.

kūhalakau

aerial tubers of uhi, yam, hoi, and related plants.

kūhaluka

many, numerous, as of a crowd; crowded, huddled together.

kūhana

each of two gable posts in the old Hawaiian house.

kūhana ʻole

lazy, indolent, do-nothing. lit., condition of doing nothing.

kūhanu

a mat motif consisting of red bands internally enhanced with a continuous row of white lozenges.

kūhapa

resembling partially; of varying or unmatched size or appearance. lit., partly fit.

kūhau

weak, tottering, feeble.

kūhaʻaliki

to brag, boast.

kūhaʻo

standing alone, independent. fig., unusual, extraordinary, as rain from a clear sky.

kūhaʻu

to harangue, talk on and on urging a point but not saying much,

kūhea manu

bird imitator; fowler.

kūhelahela

weak, feeble.

kūhela₁

an unbroken swell of the sea, drifting in without breaking; to sweep along as the sea.

kūhela₂

game played with sharp ʻūlei sticks.

kūhelemai

name of a gambling game.

kūhewa

• sudden attack,   • stroke, as of heart failure;   • apoplexy;   • sudden wind gust;   • suddenly attacked by a stroke;   • hit without warning or in error;   • to strike.

kūhihi

to censure, condemn, especially of innocent persons; to involve, entangle, embroil.

kūhili₁

to stain or dye by soaking in water containing mashed bark, as nets or mulberry bark before it is pounded into tapa.

kūhili₂

to blunder.

kūhilo

to wander about aimlessly; senseless digression.

kūhinu

greasy, oily, polished; to rub with oil, polish, grease; a name applied to women (except kāhuna) because they were not permitted to make offerings to the gods with their hands.

kūhipahipa

to mutter indistinctly; unintelligible gibberish.

kūhiwa

special taboo made by a chief; to be subject to this taboo.

kūhoe₁

quartermaster of ship.

kūhonu

an edible spotted-back crab (Portunus sanguinolentus). lit., turtle back.

kūhonua₁

suddenly struck, as by disease.

kūhou poʻo

to dive headfirst.

kūhulukū

goose flesh, as from chill; quaking, as during an earthquake; agitated, disturbed. see prayer, kualakai.

kūhākakai

swollen, fat.

kūhōhō

deep ravine; deep.

kūikawā

• temporary, for the time being, transient,   • ad hoc, makeshift,   • occasional,   • provisional, acting   • special;   • free and independent, not bound to a chief in opinion or course.   lit., standing at the time.

kūkae manu

bird dung, guano.

kūkae pōpolo

excreta after eating pōpolo greens, a term for a chief whose mother was said to be a commoner.

kūkae ʻuaʻu

excreta and scent of ʻuaʻu birds, as left in their holes.

kūkaeakua

a brownish substance, sometimes noticed under trees in the shape of paste squeezed from a tube; if the substance contains red, it is believed to be the excreta of the ghost of a dying person, and a sign that someone is dying. lit., ghost excrement.

kūkaehao

rust; rusty. lit., iron excrement.

kūkaehipa

spiny bur (Acanthospermum australe), a branching, prostrate tropical American weed, 10 to 60 cm long, bearing small star-shaped bristly fruits. lit., sheep dung. Also called ʻihi kūkae hipa, pipili.

kūkaehoki

a rattlepod (Crotalaria incana), an erect tropical American weed, about 94 cm high, with three-parted leaves, yellow flowers, and hairy, dark-brown pods, each pod 2.5 cm or more long and containing 20 or more seeds. lit., mule dung.

kūkaekoloa

a kind of grass.

kūkaelio₁

toadstool, mushroom.

kūkaelio₂

a name for unidentified wild grasses growing where horses are pastured. lit., horse dung.

kūkaeloli

mildew; mildewed.

kūkaelā

eggs deposited by flies, as in meat. lit., sun excrement.

kūkaemoa

a small tree (Pelea clusiaefolia subsp. sapotaefolia [synonym, P. microcarpa]) that grows at high altitudes on Kauaʻi. lit., chicken dung, named for the appearance of the seed capsules. Also alani kuahiwi, all species of Pelea.

kūkaenalo₁

mole on the body, believed to be deposits of flies during infancy. lit., fly dung.

kūkaenalo₂

beeswax.

kūkaenalo₃

unbleached muslin.

kūkaenēnē

lit., goose dung.

kūkaepaʻa

constipation. lit., hard excreta.

kūkaepele

sulphur, brimstone, match. lit., Pele's dung.

kūkaepuaʻa

a weedy, creeping grass (Digitaria pruriens), native to Hawaiʻi; some introduced species of Digitaria are also sometimes called kūkaepuaʻa, as D. sanguinalis and D. adscendens (syn. D. henryi); a plant form of the pig demigod Kamapuaʻa. lit., pig dung.

kūkaepuaʻa uka

crab grass (Digitaria violascens) 30 to 60 cm tall, forming clumps. lit., upland kūkaepuaʻa.

kūkaepueo₁

a weed.

kūkaepueo₂

a seaweed.

kūkaeuli

ink squirted by octopus to discolor water. fig., prostitute, as in whalers' days, so called because of their alleged cleverness at escaping from precarious situations. lit., black excreta.

kūkaeʻiole₁

small hard spots on an umbilical cord, the number of spots indicating the number of children the mother is to bear. lit., rat's dung.

kūkaeʻiole₂

taro found growing in inaccessible spots, as a tree crotch, believed carried there by rats.

kūkaeʻiole₃

insignificant trifles.

kūkaeʻiwa

a form of gourd having fruit green with white splotches, still grown on Molokaʻi and East Maui. lit., dung of ʻiwabird.

kūkaeʻuaʻu

a medicinal plant (no data).

kūkaha

to stand sideways, as in making room for another to pass.

kūkahalakē

scolding, raving and ranting in a fit of temper.

kūkahekahe

to while the time away in pleasant conversation, jesting, laughing, and telling anecdotes; pleasant conversation, chatting. lit., stand flowing.

kūkai

dipped frequently in the sea.

kūkaikea

faded, as cloth. fig., boring, dull, uninteresting.

kūkaka

similar to kaka₁, translated 'purified' by Emerson. cf. (Malo text, Chapter 26, section 36).

kūkake

glib hanger-on, parasite; one who lives with others, depending on glibness of tongue; to be glib.

kūkala

to proclaim publicly, tell abroad, announce; herald.

kūkala hewa

false alarm.

kūkaliki

boasting; to boast. (See liki₁)

kūkanawao

general name for weeds. lit., resembling the kanawao, wild taro.

kūkanono

excessive, more than usual.

kūkapihe₁

lamentation. lit., the wail arises.

kūkapihe₂

a strong purge made from bark of the shrub called koko and sap of the green kukui nut; it was administered only as a last resort and often resulted in death.

kūkapu

chastity; chaste; taboo-surrounded and unapproachable; in a state of taboo.

kūkaula

deep-water fishing with hook and line; fishing grounds at about 80 fathoms depth.

kūkaulani

with great care, with esteem, in chiefly fashion.

kūkawowo₁

to care for young plants or seedlings.

kūkawowo₂

to spread, reach a goal (of a sorcerer's prayer).

kūkawowo₃

to rush or gurgle, as water.

kūkaʻawe

convoy, guard; safe, protected, convoyed; to place in custody for protection; to convoy, guard.

kūkaʻa₁

• roll, bolt of cloth; rolled pack, as of pandanus leaves ready for plaiting;   • to roll up, as a bundle of cloth or tapa;   • to swell up.

kūkaʻa₂

wholesale.

kūkaʻi leka

to correspond back and forth; to exchange letters.

kūkaʻi makani

to attempt to induce the spirit possessing a person to talk through the person and reveal the reason for the possession.

kūkaʻi ʻōlelo

to converse, narrate; recount.

kūkaʻi₁

to exchange, as greeting (aloha), conversation (kamaʻilio), letters (leka). (kū₁ + -kaʻi).

kūkaʻi₂

to appear.

kūkaʻi₃

to stand guard as soldiers.

kūkaʻi₄

rope fastening fish nets together.

kūkele₁

muddy, slippery; to slip, slide, as in mud.

kūkele₂

to sail, as a boat.

kūkia

firm, steady, steadfast.

kūkilakila

majestic.

kūkinikini

grouped together.

kūkini₁

runner, swift messenger, as employed by old chiefs, with a premium on their speed; to run swiftly, as of a messenger; to race.

kūkini₂

close together, in great numbers, as plants.

kūkini₃

cushion.

kūkiʻo

small pool of water. lit., standing pool.

kūkoaʻe₁

temple for purification ceremonies (Malo 151–2, Emerson note 156), for prayers for food (Malo 188).

kūkona

unfriendly, cross, sullen. cf. konā, haughty; mākonā, malevolent.

kūkonukonu

excessive, overmuch, deep, profound, serious.

kūkulu kumuhana

to pool thoughts and prayers to solving common problems, as during hoʻoponopono (Nānā 78–80); to set up topics for discussion, as an agenda.

kūkulu o ka honua

region just below the horizon where sea and sky meet. lit., pillars (or borders) of the earth. cf. (Isa. 45.22) .

kūkulu o ka lani

region just above the horizon where sea and sky meet. lit., pillars (or borders) of the sky.

kūkulu papa

to pile in regular order; to arrange, classify, as plants, words. Less used than hoʻonoho papa.

kūkulu₁

• pillar, post,   • side, border, edge,   • horizon.

kūkulu₃

• to tie, tether (so called because formerly horses were tied to erected [kūkulu] stakes);   • to park.

kūkulu₄

to sit with one knee raised high towards the chin, considered bad form for women.

kūkulu₅

• type of battle in which opposing forces were formally drawn, up in line against each other;   • front, as in modern warfare.

kūkā

consultation, discussion; to consult, confer, discuss, deliberate.

kūkā kamaʻilio

interview, conference; to hold such, negotiate. lit., confer chat.

kūkā moʻo₁

to study or consult genealogy. lit., confer lineage.

kūkā moʻo₂

to use enchantment. lit., consult moʻo spirits.

kūkākaʻikahi

standing wide apart; scattered widely, as houses.

kūkākūkā

to discuss, negotiate.

kūkālā

auction; to sell at auction. lit., stand dollar (Eng.).

kūkāne

male.

kūkīhelei

to straddle, stand with legs far apart.

kūkū kāne

grandpa.

kūkū wahine

grandma.

kūkūau

a large grapsid crab (Metopograpsus thukuhar).

kūkūohi

sharp, steep, conspicuous, as house roof.

kūkūʻēʻē

redup. of kūʻē and kūʻēʻē.

kūkū₂

• to shake in jerks,   • bounce,   • trot, as on a horse;   • bumpy.

kūkū₃

gourd beat; the gourd is thumped down on a pad three times, and on the third rise, it is slapped; to beat thus.

kūkū₄

sea gull (RSV), cuckoo (KJV).

kūlana

station, rank, title, condition, position, place, quality, grade, rating, reputation (see ex., kuene), stance, attitude, poise, carriage, posture, situation, patch, site; outstanding, prominent (kū, stand, + -lana, nominalizer).

kūlana kai

probably the same as kūlana nalu, place where the waves swell up and the surf rider starts paddling...

kūlana nalu

place where the waves swell up and the surf rider starts paddling and racing the wave, usually at the most distant line of breakers. Also kūlana heʻenalu (Laie 453 [70]).

kūlana paʻa

standard, as weight or money.

kūlana pilikia

jeopardy.

kūlana pule

prayer meeting or other religious service.

kūlana waewae

fussy, fastidious, choosy.

kūlanahale

house site.

kūlanalana

unsteady, tottering, unsettled, wavering, wobbly, undecided, uncertain, fluctuating.

kūlani

of chiefly nature.

kūlapa₁

earth piled on the sides of a ditch, as of a plowed furrow or as on the edge of a taro patch; to dig or plow and cast up earth or furrow.

kūlapa₂

• to frolic, jump, or skip about in sport;   • to struggle, twist, turn, writhe.

kūlele₁

to scatter as does the wind.

kūlepe₁

• split open from head to tail, as fish prepared for drying and salting; to slit thus;   • to hew out roughly, as a canoe;   • to make a hole or dig out.

kūlepe₂

• to flap, flutter;   • strong, of wind.

kūlepe₃

harelip. (Less common than ʻūlepe.)

kūlewa

moving slowly through space, as clouds; swaying, dangling, hanging. fig., far away in space, as the ocean beyond sight of land or as its profound depths.

kūleʻa

successful, competent; happily.

kūlia₁

to stand, halt, etc.

kūlia₂

to try, strive.

kūlia₃

outstanding, fortunate, lucky.

kūlihi

grazed, as by a bullet; hit but not seriously hurt; hooked but escaped, as a fish.

kūlike

• alike, identical,   • conforming,   • resembling;   • standing in similar fashion or in even rows.

kūlikiliki

tight.

kūlina

corn, maize (Zea mays).

kūlina pohāpohā

popcorn. (Zea mays).

kūlina wali

cornmeal. lit., fine corn.

kūlina ʻono

sweet corn (Zea mays). lit., delicious corn.

kūlipeʻe

to creep along, as a sick person; to stumble awkwardly along; to walk as though weak-kneed.

kūlipo

• dark, dank, deep, as a cave.   • fig. extremely, intense, much

kūliʻa

to desire greatly.

kūliʻu₁

• deep, as a voice;   • penetrating, profound, as thoughts;   • late, remote, of the distant past.

kūloa

name of the lengthy ceremonies on the night before graduation day in hula; a 'long waiting' with feasts and ceremonies lasting for hours; lengthy religious prayers, ceremonies.

kūloaʻa

prosperous, well-supplied with needs.

kūloko

local, domestic. lit., state of being inside.

kūloku

falling, flowing, as rain or stream; flattened, as plants by rain.

kūlola

helpless, inactive, due either to infirmity or laziness; sluggish.

kūlolohili

long in doing a thing; to tell a story with many unnecessary details; garrulous.

kūloma

slow, dull, stupid, awkward, helpless.

kūlono₁

sheer, precipitous.

kūlono₂

leaky, as a calabash.

kūlono₃

insignificant, as an idea.

kūlou

• to bow the head,   • bend;   • to beckon with the head. Also kūnou.

kūlou poʻo

to bow the head; to dive headfirst.

kūlua

pairing off, as of mates; twins.

kūlālā

plant propagated by slips or scions, formerly of pandanus aerial roots; to plant thus. lit., stand branch.

kūlē

to seize, meddle in the concerns of others, oust, remove.

kūlō

short for kūloa, name of the lengthy ceremonies on the night before graduation day in hula...

kūlō pia

the long process of sweetening arrowroot starch (pia); to do this.

kūlōhia

languid, lounging about. lit. state of slowness.

kūlōlia₂

of changed appearance, as of plants in different seasons (Kep. 89); grief-stricken, said to apply particularly to a mourner who wears a malo or pāʻū of the deceased about his neck as an expression of grief: he is breaking a taboo and has 'changed' (loli).

kūlōʻihi

to wait a long time; to stand long; to last long, endure; to take a long time.

kūmahakea

to work in gardens; such work.

kūmaka

• seen by the eye, seen,   • visible;   • eyewitness;   • associated with;   • to see for oneself.

kūmakahiki

annual, yearly; yearly contract (see ex., lōpā₁).

kūmakani₁

windbreak; wind-resisting.

kūmakua₁

same as ʻāhihi₂, a lehua bush.

kūmalolo

reverential bowing during old prayers.

kūmano

water dam (rare), reservoir.

kūmanomano

a bur grass (Cenchrus agrimonioides).

kūmanō

to catch sharks with bait and noose.

kūmaua

lazy, inactive.

kūmaumau₂

same as maumau; constant, continuous, together.

kūmau₁

customary, usual, regular.

kūmau₂

deep wooden bowl with a thick base, as for poi.

kūmeka

shoemaker.

kūmene

blunt, flat, of the nose.

kūmimi

small crabs such as Lophozozymus intonsus. Varieties are kūmimi mākaʻo (Petrolisthes coccineus) and kūmimi pua (Lybia tesselata). Both were used in sorcery and are inedible.

kūmoana

large deep-sea crab (no data).

kūmoe

bedstead. lit., standing bed.

kūmoena₁

long strip commencement of a mat.

kūmoena₂

pile of mats; spread out as a mat or landscape.

kūmoho

to rise, overflow, as water.

kūmole₁

smooth, slippery, sheer, steep, rounded.

kūmoʻo

lineage, as of chiefs or priests.

kūmā-

prefix to numbers as ʻumi kūmākahi, ʻumi kūmālua, iwakālua kūmākahi, kanakolu kūmālua, etc.

kūmākena

to lament, bewail, mourn loudly for the dead, grieve.

kūmīmī

frail, feeble, blighted.

kūmūmū

dull, blunt, obtuse.

kūmū₁

goatfish (Parupeneus porphyreus). The stages of growth are kolokolopā, ʻāhuluhulu, kūmū aʻe, and the adult kūmū.

kūmū₂

good-looking, handsome, especially of a sweetheart. modern slang.

kūmū₃

a variety of red-stalked taro; varieties are qualified by the terms ʻeleʻele, kea, kū loa poni, ʻulaʻula, welo-welo lā.

kūnapa

insecure, unsteady, as an infant or invalid.

kūnaʻau

to have a grudge, bear ill will. lit., standing intestines.

kūnaʻe

to stand firmly against opposition; unyielding.

kūnaʻina

to conquer, push over; conquest.

kūnehi

ocean sunfish (Ranzania laevis, Mola mola, Masturus lanceolatus).

kūneki

filled to overflowing; to flow away.

kūneuneu

a kind of loli, sea cucumber, perhaps a Stichopus.

kūnewa

to pass, of time; to age.

kūnihi₁

steep, sheer, precarious.

kūnihi₂

• ridge, as of a precipice;   • ridge of a feather helmet;   • ridge of uncut hair on the head;   • on edge;   • sideways;   • sheer;   • partly open, as a door.

kūnoni

to progress or move slowly.

kūnono₁

red, bright red; fiery (see ex., welo₃).

kūnono₂

stubborn, willful, headstrong.

kūnounou₁

a kind of loli, sea cucumber.

kūnounou₂

var. name for kūpoupou, a fish.

kūnāhelu

moldy smelling.

kūnāhihi

• weak, as from shock;   • numb, dazed,   • dismayed, shocked, horrified.

kūnānā₁

puzzled, stumped, at wit's end, hesitating, undecided, bewildered; uncertain. lit., stand look.

kūnānā₂

goat.

kūnānā₃

same as ʻānaunau and naunau, a plant.

kūola

alive and safe, as after escaping from danger.

kūolokū

trilling song of a bird; to warble, trill.

kūoʻe

to saunter, trudge.

kūoʻo

serious, dignified, sedate, earnest, stern, solemn.

kūpahu

to brace oneself, as while being pushed; to hurl, as a spear.

kūpaka

• to kick,   • thrash, as one in anger or as a child having a tantrum;   • to writhe, twist, struggle (Isa. 21.3) ;   • contorted.

kūpaku

to recover, as from a nearly fatal illness, or as a dying plant (rare); resuscitation, as related in legends.

kūpalaha₁

designation for a koa tree with a thick, straight trunk, perhaps flat on one side or leaning close to the ground, good for a canoe hull.

kūpalaha₂

temporary heiau temple.

kūpalaiki

to quiet, soothe; soothing.

kūpalaka₁

congested; blocked, as stagnant water.

kūpalaka₂

too loose, large, as of a garment.

kūpala₁

an endemic gourd (Sicyos pachycarpa).

kūpala₃

a wild sweet potato or morning-glory with enlarged tuber, eaten in time of famine.

kūpale

defense; to defend, ward off.

kūpali

to pole fish from a rock or cliff, to stand on a cliff.

kūpaloloi

to vibrate, as the ruffle of a drum; to trill; to drum with the fingers.

kūpalu

• to stuff with food, fatten, hence to make a favorite;   • to attract fish by chumming, as with decayed pork;   • to mash to a pulp, sometimes said of tapa particles or cloth beaten into tapa as it is being prepared.

kūpani

wind-blown, as of clothes against the body.

kūpaoa₁

strong permeating fragrance, as of jasmine.

kūpaoa₂

night cestrum (Cestrum nocturnum) and other strong-smelling plants; by some authorities Peperomia spp., Railliardia spp., and a plant used to scent tapa (see pele₃).

kūpaoa₃

stone from which octopus fishing sinkers were made.

kūpapakū

bedrock; to stand on bedrock; depths of the earth.

kūpapalani

chief of the highest rank; state of heavenly foundation.

kūpapaula

to stand facing the wind, as a house; exposed to the wind.

kūpaukolo

to reverberate.

kūpau₁

entirely finished.

kūpau₂

fearful, shrinking.

kūpaʻa

steadfast, firm, constant, immovable; loyal, faithful; determined; loyalty, allegiance, firmness.

kūpaʻakai

to eat poi or sweet potatoes with salt or relish such as ʻinamona, and without meat or greens; hence a place without fish or meat.

kūpaʻewa

imperfect.

kūpaʻi

heap, pile, stack, lot; to pile, stack, heap up, as in a disorderly fashion.

kūpehe

to walk slowly, unsteadily, as of a sick person.

kūpehi

to pelt, throw at.

kūpeleleu

sprawling, occupying all the space so that others have no room; broad, as hips.

kūpele₁

to knead, as bread dough or very hard fresh poi.

kūpele₂

to dub out the inside of a log for a canoe hull; to scoop out, as a trench; to dig and plow, as a taro patch.

kūpele₃

concoction of juices of herbs mixed with poi, tender taro leaves, coconut cream, mashed sweet potato, and other food.

kūpele₄

to fatten.

kūpelo

camphire, camphor.

kūpene

permanent, stationary; to reside long in one place.

kūpenu

• dip, to dye by dipping;   • to sop up;   • to dab as with a wet cloth;   • to plunge into water, immerse.

kūpeʻe lima

bracelet.

kūpeʻe niho ʻīlio

dog-tooth anklets.

kūpeʻe pipi

to bind feet of cattle, especially with the lasso.

kūpeʻe₁

bracelet, anklet; fetters, manacles, handcuffs; to put or tie on bracelets, anklets, fetters; to hogtie.

kūpeʻe₂

an edible marine snail (Nerita polita); the shells were used for ornaments, the rare ones by chiefs. Varieties are qualified by the terms ānuenue, ʻeleʻele, kāniʻo, mahiole, palaoa (lit., ivory, (rare), puna (rare), ʻula.

kūpihipihi

tiny, small, insignificant; to become insignificant.

kūpika

cubit.

kūpikiʻō

agitated, raging, turbulent, as wind or storm. fig., mentally disturbed. cf.     pikipikiʻō rough, stormy, choppy, as the sea. fig., agitated in spirit...     kūpikipikiʻō redup. of kūpikiʻō, agitated, raging, turbulent...

kūpilikiʻi

• crowded, packed,   • distressed, severe; critical, as in a crisis; in dire trouble; difficulties.

kūpina

subpoena.

kūpinaʻi₁

• to echo, reverberate;   • to mourn, wail, lament.

kūpinaʻi₂

to crowd, throng; crowded.

kūpipi

crowded, as people, stars, or pipipi shells.

kūpipipi

to throng.

kūpoepoe

round; bundled up with clothes, as in cold weather.

kūpoho

calm.

kūpoki

plaiting process of turning a pandanus leaf back, thereby giving the product a neat edge; to plait thus.

kūpola

to roll, wrap up, as a package; to wither and curl up, as a banana leaf.

kūpololū

vaulting on a long pololū spear.

kūpolō

unresponsive, fatigued, exhausted, spiritless.

kūpono ʻole

unsuitable, improper, disqualified, ill-fitting, inauspicious.

kūpopou₂

Kauaʻi.

kūpoukia

socket in canoe for mast. lit., stand mast pole.

kūpouli

befuddled, stupefied, mentally clouded, dazed, carried away with emotion, stricken.

kūpoupou₂

the name may be qualified by lelo, yellowish.

kūpou₁

• to go down,   • walk downhill fast,   • stagger;   • to bend far forward, as one reeling drunk. see kānāwai... the kānāwai of Kūkauakahi that no one might bend forward (kūpou)...

kūpou₂

cigar wrasse fish (Cheilio inermis).

kūpuku₁

clustered, thick, rank.

kūpule

days set aside for prayer; to set aside time for prayer.

kūpuni

to stand around, surround.

kūpuʻu

taro or sweet potatoes eaten with no preparation other than scraping or baking, i.e., without being pounded into poi or mixed with coconut cream; to take food from the oven and eat it informally; to have potluck.

kūpā

swivel adze (said to be named for a god of canoe makers); to dig, scoop, hew, till.

kūpākūpā

boom, boom, as of drums.

kūpāpā₁

to grope, feel, as when looking for flaws in a wooden bowl.

kūpāpā₂

hand-to-hand fight, struggle; to fight thus.

kūpāʻai keʻe

adze.

kūpāʻoi

to speak well of one.

kūpāʻoʻi

to limp; to travel slowly.

kūpē

two pairs, as in poker.

kūpēkia

nervously afraid.

kūpīpī₁

a reef fish (Abudefduf sordidus). Also ʻōʻō nui.

kūpīpī₂

var. of kāpīpī, to sprinkle; to dash, as spray.

kūpī₂

abscess.

kūpōlua

fragrance (similar to kūpaoa).

kūpō₁

long net stretched across the track of fish, one end anchored in deep water, the other in shallow (Malo 210, 212); to set a net at night.

kūpō₂

scoop net.

kūpū

thick, as gravy, or moisture-laden lomi fish; to jell.

kūwaho

outside, outer, foreign.

kūwaiū

sinker on an ʻōpelu net.

kūwalawala

topsyturvy, handspring; to turn cartwheels.

kūwaluwalu

much, many.

kūwelu₁

woody shrub with a long tail-like inflorescence resembling cockscomb, perhaps an amaranth.

kūwiliwili

redup. of kūwili₁ to move restlessly, embrace, pet, caress...; awhirl, whirling [see the song, Kūwiliwili iho au (I am all awhirl) by Henri Berger.

kūwili₁

• to move restlessly,   • embrace,   • pet, caress;   • to spin in a dance.

kūwili₂

implement for piercing an ivory ornament.

kūāhewa

• huge, vast;   • name of a farm inland from Kailua, Hawaiʻi, tilled by Kamehameha.

kūāhua

heap, pile; heaped or piled up; rising up, as a whale's back above water. lit., back heap (āhua).

kūāilo

to be devoured by worms (ilo).

kūākino

transformation, as from animal to human form.

kūākiʻi

to stand with hands on hips or crossed in front, as suggestive of the stance of an image (kiʻi) considered a sign of rudeness and an indication that one wants to lord it over others, or as a sign that one will not cooperate.

kūākāhili

one of high birth who stands by a kāhili feather standard, beside the high chief, in contrast to the paʻa kāhili who carries the kāhili.

kūālani

sour, especially of calabashes that have held poi and have not been soaked in the sun after washing.

kūālauwili

repetitious, confusing in talk and writing.

kūālole

faded.

kūāʻino

to turn from good to evil; wicked.

kūō

to cry loudly, as with joy or pain; to howl, as a dog; to roar, as a lion.

kūʻaeʻa

to wander, stray.

kūʻai hoʻōla

to ransom. lit., to bargain to save life.

kūʻai pohō

to buy or sell at a loss or very cheaply.

kūʻaki

impatient, annoyed, irritated.

kūʻakū

sarcastic; sarcasm.

kūʻamiʻami

motions of turning hinges; motions of sexual intercourse; to turn on hinges.

kūʻaoʻao

attendant or witness at a wedding. lit., standing [at the] side.

kūʻau

• handle,   • stem, stalk, shaft,   • stick or mallet used in beating;   • shank limb of a fishhook.

kūʻau kui kele

needle clamp on a sewing machine. lit., large needle shaft.

kūʻau lima

arm below the elbow.

kūʻau wili

crank. lit., turning handle.

kūʻau wāwae

leg; shinbone.

kūʻauhau

genealogy, pedigree, lineage, old traditions; genealogist, historian; to recite genealogy.

kūʻaupaʻa

bundle, as of pololū spears.

kūʻauʻau

to tread water. lit., stand bathe.

kūʻelekā

shiftless; to vagabond.

kūʻena

glowing, burning.

kūʻewa

askew, placed obliquely.

kūʻike₁

to know by sight, to understand or know in advance or beforehand.

kūʻike₂

cash.

kūʻiʻo₁

• fact, a true statement; true.   • sincerity;   lit., a state of truth.

kūʻiʻo₂

fleshy, fat. lit., a state of flesh.

kūʻoha

venereal disease of genitals, either sex.

kūʻoho₁

a variety of taro; petiole is grass-green with darker shading midway, light above. Hawaiʻi.

kūʻoho₂

medium-sized, deep bowl.

kūʻokoʻa

independence, liberty, freedom; independent, free.

kūʻolo

sagging, baggy, as clothes; old, as a person with sagging cheeks; to sag.

kūʻonoʻono₁

well-off, comfortably situated, rich, wealthy, well-to-do, well-supplied.

kūʻono₁

• nook, cranny,   • interior of a house opposite the door,   • inside corner of a house;   • gulf, bay, cove,   • indentation,   • cell (of a beehive).

kūʻono₂

deep, as a cave; deep down, profound.

kūʻou

possible var. of kūlou, bow the head...

kūʻoulena₁

a kind of coarse tapa.

kūʻoulena₂

listless, uninterested.

kūʻoʻili

steep, difficult to climb; to climb with great difficulty.

kūʻula

any stone god used to attract fish, whether tiny or enormous, carved or natural, named for the god of fishermen; heiau near the sea for worship of fish gods; hut where fish gear was kept with kūʻula images so that gear might be impregnated with kūʻula mana, usually inland and very taboo. lit., red Kū.

kūʻulukū

rough, high, as billows.

kūʻululū

• chilled, shivering with cold;   • shy, abashed.

kūʻānoʻa

parched.

kūʻē

to oppose, resist, protest; opposite, versus, adverse, contrary, antagonistic, unwilling; objection. lit., stand different.

kūʻēʻē₁

disagreement, dissension, opposition, quarrel, bickering, animosity; to quarrel, bicker, disagree.

kūʻēʻē₂

double canoe with one canoe longer than the other.

kūʻōʻō

broken fragments of sweet potato, as cut by ʻōʻō, digging stick, or spade.

kū₁₂

to set apart a period for prayers for a special object; to pray for.

kū₁₃

months of pregnancy.

kū₁₄

abruptly, rudely, defiantly, unceremoniously, without observance of taboos or niceties, brusque.

kū₁₅

stew; to stew.

kū₂

• stand, pedestal, base;   • stem, as of a goblet;   • frame of a bed, including footboard and headboard;   • end, as of a rainbow.

kū₃

• in a state of,   • resembling, like,   • due to, because of (often followed by i or ā).

kū₄

• to appear, appearance; arrival.   • to start, go; beginning,   • to achieve;   • to change into, transform;   • to show, reveal;

kū₅

to run in schools, as fish; numerous, as octopus in season.

kū₆

• suitable, proper, O.K., appropriate, fitting;   • ready, prepared;   • to fit, as clothes;   • merit, cause;   • to deserve.

kū₇

to rule or reign, as a land.

kū₈

to soak, as clothes.

kū₉

to post, as a bond.

L K

abbreviation for luna kānāwai, judge.

Lae Manaʻolana

Cape of Good Hope.

Laehao

Cape Horn.

Laemakaʻu

Cape Fear.

Laenihi

sister of the antihero Halemano, who often assumed the form of the fish of the same name and once that of a chicken. She found Halemano's sweetheart for him, and twice brought him back to life after he had died of love sickness.

Laka₄

goddess of the hula, maile, ʻieʻie, and other forest plants (UL 24), often identified with Kapoʻulakīnaʻu.

Laka₅

a hero whose log, which was felled for a canoe, was found growing upright the following morning.

Laka₆

a god worshiped by canoe makers; also known as Kuʻōhiʻalaka (upright ʻōhiʻa tree Laka).

Lalakoʻa₁

Rarotonga, Rarotongan. (Tahitian; the regular Hawaiian correspondent of Tahitian Rarotoʻa would have been Lalokona; the second a in Lalakoʻa probably assimilated to the preceding a).

Lalana₃

old term for London.

Lamapeka

Lambeth.

Lanakamalama

name of a star. lit., the light floats.

Lanakeka

Lancaster.

Lanakila₂

wind, Hauʻula, Oʻahu.

Lanikūhana

name of a star. lit., chief stands [at] work.

Lanipaʻina

a rain known at ʻUlupalakua, Maui.

Lanipōlua

rain name. see chant, lanipō.

Lapelana

Lapland.

Lauaʻe₅

wind, Honopū, Kauaʻi.

Lauhuki₂

name of a goddess worshipped by tapa makers.

Laukamani

wind associated with Hālawa, Molokaʻi. lit., kamani leaf.

Laukōwai

wind associated with Maui. lit., water dragnet.

Laumaʻomaʻo

wind, Punakou, Molokaʻi. lit., green leaves.

Lauʻawaʻawa

a gentle wind and rain associated with Hāna, Maui.

Lawaiʻa₃

name of a group of seven stars.

Lawakua₃

name of a mountain wind at Nāpali, Kauaʻi.

Lawakua₄

a lua fighting stroke.

Laʻalūʻau

name of a legendary people who were said to worship images and not gods, in the time of Wākea or of Hawaiʻi Loa.

Laʻamaikahiki

an early immigrant brought from Kahiki by Kila. He introduced image worship in the form of an image called Lonoikaʻoualiʻi lit., sacredness from afar.

Laʻelaʻe₃

name of a star.

Laʻikū₂

name of a wind associated with Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

lae honua

to bow low, as the head. lit., earthward forehead.

lae kiko

Kauā, outcast, with a dot tattooed on the forehead. lit., dotted forehead.

lae la lae

syllables repeated in songs at ends of verses to mark time and for gay effect, similar to laʻehana.

lae lua

prominent, as a ridge. lit., double brow.

lae lāʻau

forested point, whether at sea or inland.

lae mamo

Mamo (bird) brow, a derisive name for kauā, outcasts, perhaps because the mamo, like some kauā, has a black mark on its brow (the yellow feathers of the mamo were prized, not the black).

lae oʻo

an expert. lit., mature brow.

lae paʻa₁

hard headed, obstinate, stubborn, closed in mind and hostile to new ideas. lit., hard brow.

lae paʻa₂

term for kauā, outcast. lit., marked forehead, probably referring to tattoo marks on forehead.

lae puni

term for kauā, outcast.

lae puʻu

bulging forehead.

laehaokela

unicorn, rhinoceros. lit., brow with protruding horn.

laehina

same as noio, a tern. lit., white brow.

laekoloa

type of hard, red stone, as used for adzes.

laeloa

a kind of wine-red cotton cloth. lit., long brow.

laenihi

name applied to various high-headed labroid fishes of the genera Hemipteronotus and Iniistius; this name may be qualified by the terms ʻeleʻele, kea, nēnē, pūkea. lit., sharp forehead.

laeʻula

a well-trained, clever person; expert. lit., red brow [red being the sacred color].

lae₂

cape, headland, point, promontory.

lae₃

wisdom; mental or emotional qualities. cf. idioms at pohā₁ (to burst, crack...), poʻohū₁ (wound, swelling...)...

lae₄

an insulting term, followed by qualifiers, referring to kauā, outcasts, who had dots tattooed on their foreheads.

laha ʻole

rare, choice, unique; not spread, not common.

lahaina₁

a variety of sugar cane, usually free tasseling, heavy stooling, and with rather semierect to recumbent growth; large, long heavy tops.

lahaina₂

a variety of sweet potato.

lahaina₃

poising; leaping.

lahalaha

redup. of laha₁, extended, spread out... also said of a hen covering her chickens with her wings.

lahalaha wai

broad puddle, pool.

lahalawai

slippery, muddy.

lahalile₁

dark navy-blue calico cloth with small white prints or polka dots.

lahalile₂

a variety of sweet potato.

laha₁

• extended, spread out, broad,   • published, circulated, distributed, disseminated, promulgated,   • advertised, broadcast, widespread,   • increased, numerous,   • common, general, ordinary.

laha₂

gourd calabash painted with patterns.

laha₃

a kind of yam with white flesh under the skin (HP 168), contrasting with those with purple-red flesh under the skin that were liked for medicine.

lahi kahakaha ʻākala

a variety of sugar cane; a pink or light red, striped mutation of lahi₂, and otherwise same as lahi. lit., pink-striped lahi.

lahilahi₁

• redup. of lahi₁, thin, frail, delicate....;   • weak, as coffee;   • flimsy.

lahilahi₂

single-flowering, as a hibiscus.

lahi₁

thin, frail, delicate.

lahi₂

a variety of sugar cane; the yellow mutation of laukona, otherwise same as laukona without variegations and stripes and more robust in growth.

lahi₃

a variety of banana.

laho heʻe

hernia, rupture.

laho kole

raw scrotum (an insulting reference to poverty).

laho oʻo

mature scrotum, said of a male who reaches maturity.

laho paka

crinkled scrotum (implication that there has been excessive drinking of kava).

laho pipi

bull scrotum, as eaten.

laho pōkaʻokaʻo

dry scrotum (an insult similar to laho kole).

lahokū

promiscuous male.

laholaho

miserly; to hoard.

laholena

lazy, indolent, idling.

laholio₁

rubber; automobile tire; elastic, rubbery. lit., horse scrotum.

laholio₂

India rubber (Ficus elastica).

lahopipi

eggplant (Solanum melongena).

lahoʻula

red scrotum (an insult similar to laho kole).

laho₁

• scrotum;   • with qualifiers, a term of abuse.

laho₂

• male, as below.   • (fig., promiscuous male).

laiki loloa

long rice.

laikini

license.

laikini hahai holoholona

hunting license.

laikini kalaiwa kaʻa

driver's license.

laikini kaʻa

auto or vehicle license.

laikini kī pū

firearms license.

laikī

litchi.

laimana

layman.

laina kaula waha

reins, lines. lit., bridle (rope mouth) lines.

laina mokuahi

steamship line.

laina₁

hives, urticaria

laina₃

cane trash, bagasse.

laipela

rifle.

laipila

libel; to libel.

lai₁

name applied to the species of Scomberoides, fish.

lai₂

rye.

lakaheke

loghead [loggerhead, thick-headed or stupid person].

laka₁

tame, domesticated, gentle, docile; attracted to, fond of; to tame, domesticate, attract.

laka₂

lock, padlock; to lock.

laka₃

lark.

lakeke

jacket, blouse.

lakika₁

radix.

lakikū

latitude.

lakio

ratio.

lakio like

proportion, equal ratio.

lakio like huli hope

indirect-inverse or reciprocal proportion.

lakio like kaukahi

simple proportion or ratio.

lakio like kūpono

direct proportion, equal ratio.

lakio like ʻano hui

compound proportion.

lako

supply, provisions, gear, fixtures, plenty; wealth; well-supplied, well-furnished, well-equipped; rich, prosperous.

lako hale

furniture and fixtures for a house.

lako kaua

war supplies, ammunition, munitions, armament.

lako keʻena

office supplies.

lako kula₁

school supplies.

lako kula₂

jewelry, especially gold.

lako kākau

stationery supplies.

lako lawaiʻa

fishing tackle.

lakua

to talk incongruously, mixing proper and improper talk.

lakuna

raccoon.

lalahela

lazy, sinful.

lalahiwa

dark, as of a cloud.

lalahū

convex; swelling; increasing in size; erect, as male organ.

lalakoʻa₂

prayer for luakini dedication.

lalala

to sun, bask; sunny.

lalana₁

spider.

lalana₂

warming, as at a fire.

lalau

• mistake, blunder, blunder, err,   • going astray; to go astray, wander, miss the way.   • gad about, have sexual affairs,

lalau hewa

to wander in error, sin.

lalawe

thrilling, overwhelmed, transported with emotion; to itch.

lala₁

diagonal, slanting, oblique; diagonal surfing or surf.

lala₂

to warm, as over a fire, to warm oneself by a fire; to bask in the sun; to cook over a fire.

lala₃

bright, shiny.

lala₄

thin.

lala₅

cap visor.

lala₆

a small bait fish (no data).

lala₇

to straighten.

lala₈

a style of diagonal quilting.

lala₉

the four corners of a house.

lale₁

• to hasten, hurry, push on;   • to encourage, urge on, stir up to action.

lale₂

legendary bird mentioned in old tales and songs as a sweet singer.

lali

greasy, as pork fat; slippery and shiny, glittering, sparkling, bright; sticky.

lalolalo

of humble origin, lowly.

laloloa

a variety of sweet potato.

lalo₂

leeward, lee, southern.

lalu

name of a ravenous sea bird, perhaps a gull (RSV); cuckoo (KJV).

lama hoʻohuihui ʻia

mixed alcoholic drink, cocktail, highball. lit., mixed rum.

lama kea

a tree mentioned in a chant in (Kam. 76:118).

lama kuhikuhi

beacon, signal light.

lama paʻipaʻi ʻia

lit., mixed rum.

lamakū₁

• large torch, formerly 60 to 90 cm [2 - 3 feet] tall, with the light coming from burning kukui nuts strung on a coconut midrib and wrapped in dried ti leaves and placed at the tips of bamboo handles;   • signal fires;   • lantern (Lunk. 7.16) ;   • sparks, as of a torch (Isa. 50.11) .

lamakū₂

name for a medicine applied to sores.

lamalama₁

torch fishing; torch; to go torch fishing.

lamalama₂

• fair-complexioned;   • bright-looking;   • animated;   • vivacious;   • to glow.

lama₁

all endemic kinds of ebony (Diospyros, synonym Maba), hardwood trees with small flowers and fruits. lama wood was used in medicine and placed in hula altars because its name suggested enlightenment; huts were built of lama wood in a single day during daylight (lama) hours, and the sick were placed inside them for curing.

lama₂

torch, light, lamp.

lama₃

rum; any intoxicating drink.

lamie

ramie, an introduced plant (Boehmeria nivea), related to the māmaki, and yielding a strong fiber used for rope, paper, cloth.

lana hele

to drift, as a ship.

lanaau

to float or drift with the current; to look about in every direction, wander, ramble, drift aimlessly.

lanahaʻakei

haughty, superior-acting. lit., proudly floating.

lanahua

crook, protuberance, hump; bent out, convex.

lanahō!

land ho!

lanakoi

to ask for insistently; to desire greatly; great desire.

lanalana₂

lashings, as of ornamental sennit binding the float (ama) to outrigger booms (ʻiako).

lanalana₃

spider.

lanalana₄

ylang-ylang (Cananga odorata).

lananuʻu mamao

oracle tower; the lowest floor was the lana, the second and more sacred floor was the nuʻu, and the top, where the high priest stood to conduct services was the mamao.

lananuʻu₁

high frame where heiau images were placed.

lananuʻu₃

image placed in front of a heiau.

lanau

unfriendly, unsociable.

lana₂

lowest floor of the oracle tower where offerings were placed.

lana₃

to be aware of noises as one wakes.

lana₄

frog.

lani aliʻi₁

royal chief.

lani haʻahaʻa

low sky, of the low sky, a poetic reference to Hāna, Maui, and its rains.

lani kua kaʻa

poetic name for a very high chief or the highest heaven. lit., sky with rolling ridge [i.e., clouds].

lani nuʻu

highest heavens, an epithet for royalty.

lani paʻa

firmament. lit., solid heaven.

lani wai

similar to lemi wai, a water lemon (Passiflora foetida). Niʻihau.

lani wela

Canada fleabane (Conyza canadensis), a weedy composite herb from temperate North America, with long, straight hairy stem, hairy, narrow leaves, and clusters of small flower heads. On Niʻihau Conyza bonariensis.

lanikaʻe

individual privileged to sit with the chief while the latter ate; he might eat the remnants of the chief's food, thus preventing them from falling into the hands of a sorcerer. lit., chief at edge.

lanikeha

legendary part of heaven; frequent name for residences of high chiefs, as that of Kamehameha III at Lahaina, Maui. lit., lofty heaven.

lanikuʻuwaʻa

wind of Kalalau, Kauaʻi. lit., heaven releasing canoe.

lanipō

dense, dark, lush, as of plants, rain; said of luxuriant growth.

laniuma

both flowering and aromatic-leaved pelargoniums also called rose geraniums.

lani₂

• very high chief,   • majesty;   • host (Isa. 34.4) ;   • royal, exalted, high born, noble, aristocratic.   This meaning is most common in personal names, as Leilani, royal child or heavenly lei; Pualani, descendant of royalty or heavenly flowers.

lani₃

kinds of flowers. see:     lani aliʻi₂, lanialiʻi, same as nani aliʻi, shrubs, allamandas...     lanipō, dense, dark, lush, as of plants, rain; said of luxuriant growth.     laniuma, both flowering and aromatic-leaved pelargoniums also called rose geraniums.     lani wai, laniwai, similar to lemi wai, a water lemon (Passiflora foetida). Niʻihau.     lani wela, laniwela, Canada fleabane (Conyza canadensis), a weedy composite herb

laoa

var. of haoa₃,   • eel-catching stick [gorge];   • to fish with this stick;   • to choke, as on a bone.   (var. pronunciations are laʻoa, haoa, and haʻoa.)

laolao

deep booming sound, as of distant surf.

lapa ahi

flame, blaze.

lapa koko

blood clot.

lapa uila

lightning flash; to flash, as lightning.

lapa wai

agitated fresh water, rippling water, cascading water; shining water, as in the sunlight.

lapaiki

small drum.

lapakū

excessively active.

lapalapa₁

steep-ridged, many-ridged.

lapalapa₂

redup of lapa₂, overactive, energetic, mischievous; gamboling and cavorting...;   • to bubble, boil,   • blaze;   • to cavort.

lapalapa₃

clotted.

lapalapa₄

native mountain trees (Cheirodendron), in the panax family, conspicuous for the slender-stemmed leaves, each leaf with three to five, rarely six or seven leaflets that flutter (lapalapa) in the breeze. see also hū ʻōlapa.

lapalapa₅

name for a large mahimahi, dolphin.

lapauila₂

booms joining hulls of a double canoe, corresponding to ʻiako of a single canoe.

lapawai

amniotic fluid.

lapawāwae

shin, shank. lit., leg ridge.

lapaʻau

• medical practice; medical, medicinal.   • to treat with medicine,   • heal, cure;

lapa₁

ridge, slope, steep side of a ravine; ridged.

lapa₂

• overactive,   • energetic,   • mischievous;   • gamboling and cavorting, as a young animal;   • roughhouse;   • to flash.

lapa₃

bamboo liners, for tapa printing.

lapa₄

orifice of the womb.

lapa₅

clot, as of blood.

lapa₆

a variety of sweet potato.

lapa₇

a variety of taro.

lapa₈

male mahimahi fish.

lapa₉

to slacken off the lower section on an ʻōpelu bag net; part of the catch remains in the water, and the top part only of the net is raised to the canoe and the catch taken; a large catch would be too heavy to bring up at once.

lapi

rabbi.

lapu

• ghost (Isa. 34.14) , apparition, phantom, specter;   • haunted; to haunt;   • to act as a ghost.

lapulapu

• to pick up, as sticks for fuel;   • to collect, gather;   • to handle,   • tie.

lapuʻuna

a hump, crook, arch; a humping, arching.

lau alelo

tongue tip.

lau hau

leaf of hau tree.

lau kalo

taro leaf.

lau kapalili₁

same as hukilau, seine fishing, but reportedly used in deeper water and with yellowed ti or banana leaves. lit., trembling net.

lau kapalili₂

legendary name for trembling leaves of the first taro, said to have been born of a woman.

lau koa

leaf of a koa tree.

lau kī pala

yellowed ti leaf.

lau kī₁

ti leaf.

lau kī₂

tea leaf.

lau liʻi

small-leafed; qualifying term for some plants, as maile.

lau loa₁

a long leaf.

lau loa₂

length; lengthwise.

lau lole

wauke leaf. lit., clothing leaf.

lau makani

puff of wind.

lau manamana

a divided leaf; many leaves, many branches; descendants, as of a family.

lau mauʻu

blade of grass.

lau nahele

plants, forest growth or leaves, herbs, greenery.

lau niu

coconut leaf, frond. see hair.

lau pala

fading leaf turning yellow, red, or brown. fig., person failing in health.

lau poʻopoʻohina

Niʻihau.

lau wai

stream or pond full of water; many streams: abundance of water.

lau ʻai

salad. lit., edible leaves.

lau ʻawa₁

kava leaf.

lau ʻawa₂

first two or three taro leaves, as offered with kava leaves with prayers for a good food supply.

lau ʻoliwa

• olive leaves;   • perhaps formerly used fig. for letters.

lau ʻōpae

shrimp net, about a fathom long, placed around a heap of rocks called ahu or imu (fish and shrimp were prodded and frightened from the rock pile into the net); this type of fishing.

laua

not much remaining to do, progressing, nearly finished (commonly used after a negative).

lauahi₁

• to destroy, as by fire or lava flow.   • fig., quick, deft (as after lima);   • greedy, lecherous.

lauahi₂

bag net used for fish, as ʻōhua.

lauaki

to cooperate, work together, as of experts; to concentrate on the same task; to pool talents.

lauaʻe haole

a fern (Phlebodium aureum), hare's-foot fern, from tropical America, much like the lauaʻe, but with larger, dull light-green scentless fronds. First collected in Hawaiʻi in mountains of Kauaʻi (August, 1909), probably as an escape.

lauaʻe₁

a fragrant fern (Phymatosorus scolopendria syn. Microsorium scolopendria); when crushed, its fragrance suggests that of maile; famous for its fragrance on Kauaʻi (see lauaʻe₂). Pieces were strung in pandanus leis between the keys. see chant, punia.

lauaʻe₂

beloved, sweet, of a lover.

lauaʻe₄

to gather together, collect.

lauele

to wander mentally, imagine.

lauhalalana

vagabond, drifter, one as useless as pandanus leaves adrift in the sea. lit., floating pandanus leaf.

lauhau

brightly colored butterfly fish (Chaetodon quadrimaculatus and C. umimaculatus). This name may be qualified by the terms kapuhili, kīkākapu, maha uli, nuku ʻiʻiwi or nuku ʻiwi, and wiliwili.

lauhihi

Niʻihau.

lauhoe₁

blade of a paddle

lauhoe₂

to paddle together and uniformly, either in the same or different canoes.

lauhua

a kind of ʻoʻopu, a fish.

lauhue₁

a variety of poisonous gourd; to spread, of this vine.

lauhuki₁

tapa soaking, to soak tapa.

lauhulu₁

• dry banana leaf;   • to wrap, as a bundle, with ti leaves inside and banana leaves outside.   • fig., outsider, one from another locality (sometimes said disparagingly).

lauhulu₂

• fast, swift, as of destruction;   • to seize, as an ʻahi seizes a hook.

lauhuʻe

to clear, remove, as mulch.

lauia

a parrotfish (Scarus dubius).

laukahi kuahiwi

mountain laukahi.

laukahi lau nui

a species of laukahi. lit., big-leafed laukahi.

laukahi liʻiliʻi

a native sword-shaped fern (Elaphoglossum sp.) lit., small laukahi.

laukahi nunui₁

native sword-shaped fern (Elaphoglossum aemulum).

laukahi nunui₂

broad-leafed plantain. lit., large laukahi.

laukahi₁

broad-leafed plantain (Plantago major), a Eurasian stemless weed, with thick broad leaves, 2.5 to 25 cm long, forming a rosette near the ground, and with tiny flowers developing in a cylindrical head at the tip of a slender stalk; used externally to ripen and heal boils, internally for diabetes and other ailments. lit., single leaf.

laukahi₂

marsh pennywort (Hydrocotyle verticillata). Niʻihau. cf. pohe₂ and (Neal 659).

laukalakoa

snowbush (Breynia disticha syn. B. nivosa) from South Pacific islands. It has rounded-oval leaves, mottled green and white, or, in one variety, green, white, red, and pink. lit., calico (Eng.) leaf.

laukamana

laudanum.

laukana

uninterested in religion, indifferent to religion.

laukanaka

densely populated, having many people; many people; to populate.

laukani

tough, hardy.

laukanu

planted sweet-potato vine.

laukapalala

legendary name for broad leaves of the first taro, said to have been born of a woman.

laukea₁

a small tree or shrub (Claoxylon sandwicense, var. tomentosum and degeneri; C. helleri) on Kauaʻi only, in the euphorbia family, having leaves to about 8 by 18 cm and small clustered flowers.

laukea₂

hard gray stone, used for adzes.

laukea₃

gray with age or sickness; pale, as an invalid.

laukoa

to feather out, as young birds.

laukona

a variety of sugar cane with green and yellow striped canes and leaves; used in sorcery, because of the meaning of laukōnā, to break the influence of the hana aloha love magic and change love into hatred.

laukua₁

confused, repetitious, mixed, incoherent, as speech; miscellaneous; irregular-shaped, as some leaves.

laukua₂

to take or gather indiscriminately. Similar to hāpuku.

laukua₃

one skilled in many trades, a jack-of-all-trades.

laukua₄

fish pond.

laukāhiʻu

a kind of shark, possibly thresher. lit., much hit tail.

laukī

a cosmopolitan tropical weed (Cassia leschen-aultiana), a small shrub with finely divided leaves, yellow flowers, and small narrow pods.

laukō

dragnet.

laukō pua

fishing for young fish (pua) with fine nets.

laukōnā

• hardhearted, merciless, heartless,   • unfriendly, implacable;   • furious, very angry.

laukūkahi

a native fern (Lindsaya macraena), with narrow, divided fronds. Hawaiʻi. lit., leaf that is alone.

laulaha

• spread far and wide, as news, widespread;   • circulated, publicized;   • of common or general knowledge;   • spread contagiously, as a disease.   • lit., much spread.

laulahilahi

thin.

laulama

design on a Niʻihau mat. lit., many torches or lama tree leaves.

laulauna

sociable, friendly, gregarious, genial.

laulau₂

hat rim.

laulau₃

pregnant.

laulau₄

paddle blade.

laulele₁

butterfly weed or milkweed (Asclepias curassavica), a tropical American perennial herb 60 to 90 cm high, with umbels of small orange and yellow flowers and pods full of tufted, wind-borne seeds; the leaves were eaten in time of famine; the Monarch butterfly feeds on the leaves. lit., flying leaf. see also hī laulele.

laulele₂

dandelion (Taraxacum officinale).

laulele₃

net fishing with small nets as in shallow water (usually used with lawaiʻa or papa)

lauleʻa

peace, happiness, friendship; restoration of a disrupted friendship; happy, glad, genial, courteous, peaceful.

laulihilihi

a slender, prostrate shrub in the pink family (Schiedea stellarioides), endemic to Kauaʻi, with small, linear leaves, and large open panicles of small flowers. lit., bordered leaf.

laulima

cooperation, joint action; group of people working together; community food patch; to work together, cooperate. lit., many hands.

lauloa₁

a variety of taro, said to be the original taro brought to Hawaiʻi. Sometimes poetically called hāloa₃, long stalk, because a god of that name was said to have been in the form of this taro. This name may be qualified by the terms hāʻeleʻele or ʻeleʻele; ʻeleʻele ʻōmaʻo, ʻeleʻele ʻula or palakea ʻeleʻele; hāʻula, koko, ʻulaʻula, or palakea ʻula; uliuli or hāuliuli; keʻokeʻo; manini; ʻōniʻoniʻo; palakea or palakea papamū; pānaʻe; poni. (HP 33), (TC 3).

lauloa₂

a variety of sugar cane. When young, yellow-green, striped with light yellow-brown; with exposure, a deep olive, striped with dark brown-red; broad, long, green leaves; large stalks.

lauloa₃

long wave or surf, as extending from one end of the beach to the other.

laulā

• broad, wide;   • liberal;   • width, breadth, extent;   • widely known;   • publicly.

laumaki₂

low stroke in club fighting.

laumanamana

a variety of sweet potato.

laumania

• smooth,   • sheer,   • steep,   • even.

laumaʻewa

insult, taunt, sneer, reproach, contempt; to insult, taunt, mock; taunting, mocking, sneering, derisive.

laumaʻu

design on a tapa beater, said to suggest the maʻu leaf.

laumeki₁

a kind of barbed spear.

laumeki₂

to recede, ebb, as the tide or flood waters.

laumeki₃

to wilt, as plants without water.

laumilo₁

to writhe, turn, twist, squirm, torture, destroy.

laumilo₂

a species of eel, so called because its color was thought to resemble a yellow milo leaf (lau milo).

laumāewa

to sway with the movement of the wind, as leaves; to move to and fro, as algae in the sea; blown here and there, as sea spray.

launa aloha

friendly association, fellowship.

launa male

marriage relationship; marital rights (RSV), marital duties (KJV).

launa palapala

correspondence; to correspond.

launa ʻole₁

unequalled, incomparable, unsurpassed, superior (similar to ana ʻole and lua ʻole).

launa ʻole₂

unsociable.

launea

bare, as of leaves.

launiu

design on a tapa beater.

launui

a variety of taro. lit., large leaf, large design.

lauoha₁

sail of a vessel.

lauoha₂

dense, lush, of vegetation.

lauoha₃

variation in vision, depending on distance of the object seen.

lauoho kuʻi

hair switch, wig. lit., added hair.

lauoho uliuli

one with dark hair, brunette; dark hair.

lauohoopele₁

Pele's hair, volcanic glass spun out in hairlike form.

lauohoopele₂

a fine, hairlike seaweed, found at Waikīkī.

lauone

soil light, fertile, and easy to cultivate; alluvial soil, sandy soil. lit., sand surface.

laupalai

to shine, glitter, sparkle, as dew in the sun.

laupapa₁

a broad flat, as of coral, lava, reef.

laupapa₂

board, lumber.

laupau

a kind of fish.

laupaʻapaʻani

merry, jolly, humorous, laugh-provoking, funny, playful, witty. lit., much playing.

laupaʻe

first two leaves of a taro shoot (according to some, the first three leaves).

laupaʻi₂

a great many, multitude, great quantity, heap; to increase, multiply; to have much of; well supplied with.

lauwili

• circuitous, roundabout, indirect,   • turning, twisting,   • unstable, fickle, changeable, inconstant,   • double-tongued,   • variable.

lauwiliwili nukunuku ʻoiʻoi

butterfly fishes (Forcipiger longirostris and F. flavissimus). lit., sharp-beaked wiliwili leaf.

lauwiliwili₁

a butterfly fish (Chaetodon miliaris).

lauāhea

rumor, hearsay.

lauākea

common; commoner. lit., much public.

lauʻalo

contraction of lau kalo, taro leaf.

lauʻamaʻu

tapa-beater design. lit., ʻamaʻu fern pattern.

lauʻapoʻapo

type of lau fishing outside the reef, seine. lit., catching seine.

lauʻauʻa

to withhold; stingy. fig. to withhold or conceal strength, as a warrior (Malo 196, 203) or gambler; this may refer to the common tale motif of the idol hero who enters the battle only after his confederates are losing, as of Kawelo, Pele, Panaʻewa. Another figurative use concerns a woman unattractive to males, and (AP) a lottery or game of chance.

lauʻawa

pagoda flower (Clerodendrum buchananii var. fallax), a low shrub with downy heart-shaped leaves and clusters of scarlet flowers, native to Java.

lauʻehu

a grass endemic to Niʻihau, Panicum niihauense. lit., red leaf.

lauʻekī

top, as of sugar-cane tassel or of shell ginger about to bloom.

lauʻena₁

to glow with heat, anger, passion

lauʻiʻi

a native fern (Doodia spp.), somewhat like kupukupu₃.

lauʻulaʻula

a kind of sweet potato. lit., red leaf.

lauʻulu

indistinct, as the voice of a sick person.

lauʻī

ti leaf. Also lāʻī, lau kī.

lauʻī pekepeke

short, stunted ti leaves; a term of opprobrium for the kauā (outcast), as such ti leaves were of less value than long leaves.

lauʻō₁

sugar-cane leaf (same as lau kō).

lauʻō₂

young white coconut leaves near the heart.

lau₂

dragnet, seine, so called because formerly made of ti leaves (lau) tied to a rope.

lau₃

sheet; surface; blade, as of grass.

lau₄

to be much, many; very many, numerous; four hundred. [traditional 4-based counting: kāuna 4; kaʻau 40; lau 400; mano 4,000; kini 40,000; lehu 400,000]

lau₅

pattern, as for quilts; design; print of a cloth.

lau₆

thatched mountain hut, as used by farmers, canoe-makers, birdcatchers.

lau₇

tip, as of the tongue; top (probably related to wēlau and ʻēlau, tip).

lau₈

sweet-potato slip or vine.

lawa lua₁

very strong.

lawa lua₂

to bind tightly.

lawa puni

enough for all, well-supplied or equipped.

lawaaʻeaʻe

white mixed with a darker color, as of a chicken; dark hair streaked with gray; white chicken with sprinkling of red feathers.

lawaiʻa kō lau

the old name for hukilau fishing.

lawaiʻa kōkō

fishing within the reef, as by women and children, with long bags of fine mesh into which fish were driven.

lawaiʻamanu

birdcatcher, birdcatching with a net. lit., to fish birds.

lawaiʻa₂

cormorant.

lawakua₁

strong-backed, muscular, of strong physique, bulging with muscles.

lawakua₂

• to bind or tie fast, as on the back.   • fig., to be a dear friend or companion.

lawalawaihonua

type of large wooden bowl.

lawalawaiʻa

to fish here and there.

lawa₂

possessed of enough or ample knowledge, hence wise, capable, competent.

lawa₃

as soon as.

lawa₄

strong, husky; strong man, as in a king's retinue.

lawa₅

to bind, make fast, tie securely.

lawa₆

white, as of a cock or dog.

lawa₇

a large shark fishhook.

lawe hae

to bear a flag; color bearer.

lawe hele

to take here and there.

lawe hānai

to adopt, as a child.

lawe kapakahi

to act with partiality.

lawe kāhili

bearer of the feather standard of royalty (kāhili).

lawe lima

to carry by hand.

lawe ola

manslaughter, homicide; to take a life; to take alive.

lawe pio

• conquest; conquer,   • to capture, take captive, take a prisoner, carry into captivity.   • abduct

lawe wai

a great flow of water; water carrier; water-borne.

lawe wale

extortion, seizure of property with the owner's knowledge; to extort, take without right.

lawe ʻōhua

passenger carrier; to carry passengers.

lawe ʻōlelo

• talebearer, tattle;   • gossip; to gossip, bear tales;   • microphone.

laweau

to drift apart; to depart, as in death.

lawehala

• sin, sinner, sinful; to sin, transgress.   • delinquency, delinquent,   • offense;   • evil.

lawehana

workman, laborer; industrious; to do labor, work.

lawekeō

cry of the kioea, curlew bird: 'Kioea, kioea, lawekeō, lawelawekeō'.

lawelawe hana

function, administration.

lawelawe iwi

one who cares for the bones of the dead.

lawelawe kolohe

to take illegally, without permission, tamper with.

lawelawe lima

• to carry in the hand; anything carried in the hand.   • to pitch in and lend a hand, help;   • to assault, beat, tackle;

lawelawe₁

• to serve, work for, minister to, tend, attend to, serving (HE).   • do, perform, transact;   • to treat, as the sick;   • to wait, as on tables;   • to handle.

lawelawe₂

to pilfer, make off with.

lawelua

to study both sides of a question; to act impartially. lit., take two.

lawena₁

getting, acquiring, taking, carrying, acquisition; movement, as of dancing hands.

laweālani

highest heavens.

laweʻaiʻē

to borrow, take on credit.

lawe₂

finally to become; to become.

laʻa kea

sacred light, sacred things of day, as sunshine, knowledge, happiness. lit., light sacredness.

laʻa make

season when plants die or grow slowly, like autumn in cooler climates. lit., dead season.

laʻa ua

rainy season.

laʻa uli

sacred or doomed darkness, ignorance, gloom, the unknown, misfortune.

laʻa ulu

spring, time of growth.

laʻa ʻula

autumn. lit., red time [of leaves].

laʻaloa₁

varieties of small, narrow-bodied kitchen roaches including the brown-banded cockroach (Supella supellectilium) and the German cockroach (Blatella germanica or Symploce hospes). Perhaps named for Olaʻa, Hawaiʻi.

laʻalāʻau

• small sticks, twigs,   • herbs,   • shrubs,   • bush.

laʻamia

calabash tree (Crescentia cujete), introduced from tropical America, fruit used for hula rattle with aliʻipoe seeds.

laʻa₁

• sacred, holy,   • devoted, consecrated,   • set apart or reserved as for sacred purposes,   • dedicated.

laʻa₂

• cursed, defiled (Kanl. 22.9) ,   • bound under an oath,   • doomed to death or destruction (FS 120–3),   • in great trouble.

laʻa₃

time, season (perhaps short for lāʻau and a missionary introduction).

laʻa₅

to propagate plants by inarching [to graft by uniting a growing branch to a stock without separating the branch from its parent stock].

laʻa₆

also, together with, so, besides, such as, like.

laʻe

pure in sentiment.

laʻehana

syllables repeated in chants at ends of verses to mark time and for gay effect, similar to ehehene.

laʻelaʻe₁

• bright,   • shiny,   • clear,   • serene, calm,   • pleasant.   •

laʻelaʻe₂

a variety of sweet potato.

laʻi

• calm, stillness, quiet, peace, contentment, tranquillity;   • solace;   • serene, as of sea, sky, wind;   • quiet, silent, peaceful, pacific, tranquil, contented;   • to find peace.   see ex., forecast.

laʻikū₁

great calm, quiet, peace, serenity; becalmed.

laʻilaʻi₁

redup of laʻi, calm, stillness, quiet, peace, contentment, tranquillity; solace; serene, as of sea, sky, wind...; light-hearted.

laʻilaʻi₂

a variety of sweet potato.

laʻiokona₁

a variety of sweet potato. lit., calm of Kona.

laʻiokona₂

design on a tapa beater.

laʻipū

to be peaceful.

laʻolaʻo₂

lack of satisfaction, even discomfort, resulting from eating unaccustomed or foreign food.

laʻolaʻo₃

• kindling;   • small sticks placed at a break in a bank of a taro patch;   • trash.

laʻolaʻo₄

rough, pitted, calloused.

laʻo₁

having something in the eye, as a mote or eyelash.

Lea₁

goddess of canoe builders... wife of Kūmokuhāliʻi, and sister of Hinapukuʻai, who sometimes assumed her form. Both sisters took the form of an ʻelepaio flycatcher to help canoe makers choose proper logs (see Hinapukuʻai). She was also called Hinakūwa'a (canoe upright) and Laea.

Lea₂

name of a star.

Lehuakona

star in the Milky Way, perhaps Antares. lit., south lehua flower.

Lehua₇

name of the small island just west of Niʻihau. As the westernmost of the Hawaiian Islands (except for the Northwest Hawaiian Islands), Lehua is associated with a setting sun (see chant, kalakalaʻihi). In poetry, the extent of the Hawaiian Islands is shown by coupling Lehua Island and Haʻehaʻe and Kumukahi on East Hawaiʻi . A breeze is named for this island.

Lekahone

Leghorn (city and chicken)

Lekinekona

Lexington.

Leleaka

Milky Way.

Leleiona₃

Milky Way.

Lelekuʻilua

name of a strong, wintry wind.

Leleuli

name of a gusty, wintry wind.

Lena₅

name of a star, perhaps Sirius.

Lena₆

name of a yellow-tinted rain famous at Hanalei, Kauaʻi, and on Maui.

Lepanona

Lebanon.

Lepupalika₁

Republican (political party). A newspaper, 1901–2, was entitled Home Rula Republalika.

Lewalewa₃

nickname for Gilbertese, because their stretched ear lobes dangled. [see Grimble's Tungaru Traditions for a description of this former Gilbertese practice]

Lewa₅

name of a star.

Lewika

Levites.

Leʻa₃

the zenith star Arcturus.

leha₁

to glance about, as with expectation or furtively.

leha₂

lazy, neglectful; to loaf.

lehe luhe

pouting lip.

lehe ʻoi

sharp-lipped, an epithet often applied to Pele because she devoured everything in her path; sharp-tongued, of one who makes cutting remarks.

lehelehe kiʻi

indolent talker; to do nothing but talk. lit., image lips.

lehelehe nui

thick lips.

lehelehenui

a variety of sweet potato.

lehelehe₁

• lips;   • labia of vagina;   • language (Kin. 11.1; rare) ,   • mouth of the iheihe net.   • fig. cf lehelehe kiʻi, indolent talker; to do nothing but talk, lehelehe nui (thick lips), hoʻolehelehe nui, sullen, obstinate, sulky, pouting, lehe ʻoi, sharp-tongued, of one who makes cutting remarks....

lehe₁

lip (used with complements, as lehe luhe, lehe ʻoi).

lehe₂

stretched, loose.

lehe₃

deep-sea fish resembling ulua, perhaps Caranx chelio.

lehia

skilled, expert, as in fishing; deft.

lehiwa

admirable, attractive; to admire.

leho ahi

a species of cowry (Cypraea mauritiana). lit., fire cowry.

leho kupa

the serpent-head cowry (Cypraea caput-serpentis). lit., native cowry.

leho kōlea

a species of cowry (Cypraea maculifera, C. mauritiana). lit., kōlea bird cowry, perhaps so called because its brown streaks suggest the kōlea bird.

leho kūpeʻe lima

a species of cowry shell (Cypraea caput-serpentis), used for bracelets, kūpeʻe lima.

leho lei

same as leho puna, sometimes used in leis.

leho maoli

the common dotted, brown cowry. lit., genuine cowry.

leho nuku

a cowry with the extremities drawn out, a beaked cowry, such as Cypraea cicercula var. tricornis; sometimes used in leis.

leho palaoa

same as leho puna, but with a yellow hue. lit., ivory cowry.

leho paʻa

a cowry of a solid color, as Cypraea mauritiana.

leho pouli

a very dark-brown cowry (Cypraea mauritiana).

leho puna

a white money cowry (Cypraea moneta). lit., coral cowry.

leho pāuhu

cowries, as Cypraea schilderdrum, C. carneola.

leho ʻuala

a rare dark-yellow money cowry (Cypraea moneta). lit., sweet-potato cowry.

leho ʻula

the rare and highly prized red cowry, probably Cypraea sp.

leho ʻōkala

a species of cowry (Cypraea granulata). lit., rough cowry.

leho ʻōmaʻo

a greenish cowry (diseased cowries sometimes turn green).

leho ʻōpule

a species of cowry (Cypraea helvola). lit., variegated cowry.

leho ʻōpuʻupuʻu

lit., bumpy or rough cowry.

leholeho₂

potbellied.

lehopulu

earth-clinging rainbow. lit., wet cowry shell.

leho₁

general name for cowry shell; they were used as octopus lures.

leho₂

callus, as on shoulders from carrying heavy loads.

leho₃

covetous. cf. maka leho.

lehu ahi

ashes. lit., fire ash.

lehu ane

ash dust.

lehu pele

volcanic ash.

lehu ʻula

red ashes; reddish dust or dirt.

lehua haole

red- or white-flowered species of Calliandra shrubs from various parts of America. lit., foreign lehua.

lehua haʻakea

lit., white lehua.

lehua hāmau

poetic reference to the lehua tree. lit., silent lehua, so called because bird-catchers were silent when snaring birds on branches of this tree and this activity was taboo.

lehua kahiki

clover. lit., foreign lehua.

lehua keʻokeʻo

a variety of taro called waiākea in Kona, Hawaiʻi. lit., white lehua.

lehua lau liʻi

a form of ʻōhiʻa lehua tree with very small leaves. lit., small-leafed lehua.

lehua maka noe

a small shrub (Metrosideros pumila var. makanoiensis), restricted to the high bogs of Kauaʻi, with leaves and flowers like those of lehua. lit., lehua with misty face.

lehua maka ʻiʻi

a variety or taro. lit., small-eyed lehua.

lehua mamo

a form of ʻōhiʻa lehua tree with yellow flowers. lit., mamo-bird lehua, so called because the mamo has yellow feathers.

lehua mau loa

globe amaranth (Gomphrena globosa). lit., everlasting lehua, so called because its flowers when used in leis do not wilt. Also lehua pepa and leihua.

lehua neʻeneʻe

lit., spreading lehua. same as lehua neneʻe, lehua maka.

lehua palaʻiʻi

a variety of taro, of common upland culture in Kona, Hawaiʻi. The plant is short to medium, slender, with lilac-purple corm flesh and dark green petioles; used for poi.

lehua papa

a native shrub or small tree (Metrosideros rugosa), found in high forests of the Koʻolau Range, Oʻahu, and distinguished by its rounded, leathery, grooved leaves.

lehua pepa

lit., paper lehua, so called because the texture of the flowers and the fact that they do not wilt suggest paper.

lehua pua kea

a form of ʻōhiʻa lehua tree with white flowers (pua kea).

lehua ʻeleʻele

a variety of taro; corm white or slightly pink; may be a sport of a true lehua. lit., black lehua.

lehua ʻāhihi

a variety of lehua (Metrosideros tremuloides), noted in songs and chants of Nuʻuanu Valley, Oʻahu.

lehua ʻāpane

a kind of lehua tree bearing dark-red flowers.

lehua ʻōniʻoniʻo

a variety of taro. lit., spotted lehua.

lehuakūikawao

a variety of pink lehua taro. lit., lehua standing in the uplands.

lehuakūkuahiwi

a variety of taro. lit., hill-standing lehua taro.

lehuakūmakua

a form of lehua with sessile cordate leaves.

lehua₁

the flower of the ʻōhiʻa tree (Metrosideros macropus, M. collina subsp. polymorpha); also the tree itself. The lehua is the flower of the island of Hawaiʻi, as designated in 1923 by the Territorial legislature; it is famous in song and tale. see nāpolupolu, pōkiʻi₁, ʻūpolu. fig., a warrior, beloved friend or relative, sweetheart, expert (see lehua₉). The plant has many forms, from tall trees to low shrubs, leaves round to narrow and blunt or pointed and smooth or woolly. The flowers are red, rarely salmon, pink, yellow, or white. The wood is hard, good for flooring and furniture, formerly used for images, spears, mallets. (Neal 637–8). It grows abundantly in wet areas (see ex., ʻūpolu). It was believed that picking lehua blossoms would cause rain. For rain and wind names associated with lehua see Kanilehua, Kinailehua. Kinimakalehua, Kiu Wai Lehua, Līlīlehua, Moanianilehua, Moelehua. see also lū lehua, Moaʻe Lehua, ʻōiwi₂ (chant). cf. Marquesan heʻua

lehua₂

laden, as a lehua tree with beautiful blossoms.

lehua₃

rainbow-colored mother-of-pearl shell used for fishing lure.

lehua₄

a variety of taro, used for red poi. Cultivars may be qualified by the terms keʻokeʻo (white) or maoli (native).

lehua₅

globe amaranth (Gomphrena globosa).

lehua₆

a variety of yam; the stem has red wings and the tuber has light pinkish flesh.

lehua₉

expert, as in fishing.

lehulehu

• multitude, crowd, population,   • the public;   • great number, numerous, legion, very many, innumerable, myriad.

lehuliʻu

white-hot, as oven stones.

lehuuila

flashes of lightning; to flash.

lehu₁

ashes; ash-colored or gray, as a chicken. see saying, ash.

lehu₂

a variety of sugar cane, probably recently introduced, extensively planted by Hawaiians. The stunted mature stalks look dead except for their green leaves. A gray to green-brown frosted-looking cane covered with hairs; pith green-white; both sides of leaves bearing long scattered hairs.

lehu₃

the number 400,000; numerous, very many. [traditional 4-based counting: kāuna 4; kaʻau 40; lau 400; mano 4,000; kini 40,000; lehu 400,000]

lehēlehē

fat, bulging with fat, unwieldy.

lei aliʻi

royal lei, chief's lei, crown (Hoik. 4.4) , diadem.

lei haku

braided lei, as of ferns and flowers.

lei hala

lei made principally or solely of pandanus keys, sometimes considered bad luck because hala, pandanus, also means to pass away, to fail.

lei hili

a plaited lei, as of ferns and maile but without leaves.

lei hoaka

necklace made of crescent-shaped (hoaka) hog's tusks, usually naturally, so shaped, but sometimes carved; a pendant of a single crescent-shaped tooth.

lei hulu

feather lei, formerly worn by royalty. fig., dearly beloved child or choice person.

lei humuhumu

cloth lei.

lei kolona

rosary, prayer beads. lit., crown (Eng.) lei .

lei kui

a strung lei, as of plumeria.

lei kukui

kukui nut lei.

lei kāmoe

feather lei with feathers tightly folded together so that it suggests a rope, in contrast with the flat lei papa.

lei leho

lei of cowry shells.

lei niho ʻīlio

dog-tooth necklace.

lei ole₁

dog-tooth lei.

lei ole₂

same as ʻana, pumice stone used for medicine and for polishing.

lei palaoa

ivory pendant, originally probably whale's tooth, rarely of stone or wood, later also of walrus tusk; necklace of beads of whale's teeth; today, any pendant shaped like the old whale-tooth pendant, such as of beef bone. lit., ivory lei.

lei papa

flat lei, as for a hat; any lei on a flat surface, especially a feather lei.

lei paukū

lei with stripes or bands of varying colors. lit., link lei.

lei piki

lei made of feathers of uneven length that protrude unevenly, as of mamo feathers.

lei pipi

ox yoke.

lei pipipi

lei of pipipi shell, a new type of lei; formerly kūpeʻe ornaments were called lei pipipi because of a superficial resemblance

lei poepoe

lei with flowers strung on stems or sides of flowers.

lei poʻo

lei worn on the head (poʻo).

lei pāniʻo

lei of various colors, as feather leis. lit., spotted, motley lei.

lei pāpahi

• leis of alternating groups of flowers and leaves,   • entwined leis of same or different flowers;   • adornment of several leis, usually both on head and around neck.

lei pāpale

hatband.

lei pūpū

shell lei, the most famous being from Niʻihau, especially kahelelani and momi. These leis represent Niʻihau in the leis of the islands, as designated in 1923 by the Territorial legislature.

lei pūpū puka

lei of white sea-perforated shells worn by men and women about the neck, popular in Hawaiʻi since the late 1960s. lit., perforated shell lei.

lei waena

lei strung in the center of flowers.

lei wili

a lei that is not strung (kui): the leaves or flowers are entwined about each other, as maile leis.

lei wiliwili

pendant carved of wiliwili wood; lei of wiliwili seeds.

lei ʻoni

lei with spirals of several colors, as the kīkā lei.

lei ʻāʻī

any lei worn on the shoulders, as maile; necktie, scarf, neckerchief. fig., beloved person, especially child or mate. lit., neck lei.

lei ʻōpuʻu

whale-tooth pendant that tapers down to a point, rather than being hook-shaped, as the lei palaoa; especially worn by Oʻahu chiefs. lit., bud lei.

leiau

an ancient type of prayer.

leihala₁

a variety of eel.

leihala₂

plaiting and tapa designs consisting of a series of inverted triangles, suggestive of a hala lei.

leihua

lit., fruit lei, so called because the flowers are round like a fruit.

leikō

let go. Usually used as follows...

leilei₁

to wear a lei or leis.

leina

spring, leap, bound; place to leap from.

leinekia

reindeer.

leioa

tall, thin.

leiohiʻiaka

a small native tree (Pelea elliptica and related species), related to the mokihana.

leiomano

a weapon, a large shark tooth set in a piece of wood about 6.4 cm long, with a string loop for attaching to the finger (probably from lei o manō, a shark's lei).

leiowī

tuberculosis, consumption.

lei₂

• to leap, spring forward;   • fling, toss,   • to rise, as a cloud. (Nah. 10.11) Usually used with hoʻo-.

leka₁

sticky, slimy, as mucus.

leka₃

leek (Allium porrum). (Neal 198), (Nah. 11.5) .

lekema

jacinth (RSV), ligure (KJV).

lekeona

legion; a large number (Mar. 5.9, 15) ; used figuratively of one possessed by the devil or intoxicated.

leke₁

come.

leke₂

lady.

leki

tape for dress trimming.

lekia

to covet.

lekimana koa

regiment.

lekue

league.

lekuke

lettuce (Lactuca sativa).

lele hapahā

to count by fours.

lele hapakolu

to count by threes.

lele hapalima

to count by fives.

lele hapalua

to count by twos.

lele hapaʻumi

to count by tens.

lele hauli

greatly shocked, astonished, moved, startled, frightened...

lele hoʻokau₁

altar to place (hoʻokau) things on, as sacrifices, especially a temporary altar.

lele hoʻokau₂

peak, top of a peak.

lele kawa

to leap feet first from a cliff into water without splashing or into (at Kaʻū) soft earth.

lele koali

to swing; to jump rope; swinging on a koali vine rope, an ancient sport.

lele koaʻe₁

flight of tropic birds; to fly like a tropic bird. fig., sheer, steep.

lele koaʻe₂

name for kauā, outcasts.

lele koke

to leap suddenly, immediately. fig., short-tempered, excitable, quick to fight.

lele lima

an interval of a fifth

lele loa

completely severed, as a part of the body in fighting.

lele lua₁

an interval of a second in music.

lele lua₂

to leap twice.

lele lupe

to rise and fall, as the forepart of canoe outrigger (lupe). fig., the rise and subsidence of emotion.

lele lāʻau

pole vaulting; to pole vault.

lele pahū

to leap into water with a splash; as this was considered poor diving, the expression may refer figuratively to any poor performance; to leap and land with a thud.

lele pailani

to praise, exalt, extol extravagantly or excessively (stronger than pailani, to praise).

lele pali

to leap or fall off a cliff; to practice the ancient sport of leaping from a precipice into water.

lele pio

to run away in defeat; to avoid capture, as a thief. lit., to flee capture.

lele piʻo

to fly or jump in a curve; to fly as a comet through the sky.

lele pono

to jump carefully. fig., to live a happy life; to transact business justly; to rise rapidly to success.

lele pā-

singing intervals in music (pā is followed by a number).

lele pīnaʻi

to run with a rope around a coconut tree, and when going very fast, to lift the feet off the ground. lit., repeated leaps.

lele ua

windblown rain.

lele uli

to dispel darkness; to purify or cleanse, as in a religious ceremony.

lele wai

to purge, cleanse, purify with water of purification.

lele wale

to fly, jump, move of one's own accord or for no reason; in ancient prayers, to speed on, as a prayer to a god.

lele walo

loud, distant cry; to call loudly.

lele wawalo

to reverberate, as an echo.

lele waʻa

transferring at sea from canoe to canoe or canoe to surfboard for the sport of surfing to shore. lit., canoe leaping.

lele weluwelu

torn to shreds; broken up and scattered.

lele ʻaoʻao

to leap sideways; to shy, as a horse.

lele ʻopu

to dive feet first into water without making a splash. Also lele ā ʻopu. fig., unfavorable.

lele ʻē

to speak prematurely or before one is spoken to; to jump to conclusions.

lele ʻōʻō

to leap or plunge into water feet first. lit., piercing leap.

lelea

prayer uttered by a priest as a chief drinks kava, so that the essence of the kava will fly (lele) to the gods.

leleaaka

to hang, suspend, carry on the back, as a child or load.

leleaka

light windblown rain or mist.

leleaoa

• flying away in groups, as migratory birds; to fly thus;   • to sail, as a canoe fleet.

lelehua

a good thinker, planner.

lelehuna

fine windblown rain spray, dust, mist; to fall as fine rain.

leleiona₁

shark-sucker, remora (Echeneidae spp.); it clings to large fish, such as swordfish, marlin, bonito, shark.

leleiona₂

fidgety, foolish, restless.

leleiwi

a kind of shark, possibly thresher, reported by Hyde (no data), perhaps the same as laukāhiʻu.

lelekepue

hard volcanic rock, as used for adzes.

lelekē

to leap here and there.

lelele

redup. of lele₁ to fly, jump, leap, hop, skip, swing...   • to beat swiftly, as the heart;   • to frisk, hop about, romp, caper;   • inconstant, promiscuous;   • at intervals, here and there.

lelemu

a slowpoke; slow, sluggish, disinclined to get up.

lelemū

to seize victims for sacrifice.

lelepau₁

to trust completely.

lelepau₂

to apply oneself to, concentrate wholly on.

lelepe₁

toothed, sharp-pointed design, as in tapa.

lelepinao

to swing on a koali vine. lit., dragonfly leap.

lelepinau

game said to resemble kōnane.

leleponi

to die suddenly, as by stroke or accident.

lelepoʻipū

to pounce upon.

lelepoʻo

to dive headfirst.

lelepo₂

probably another species of Padina, similar in appearance to ʻaʻalaʻula, a seaweed.

lelepuni₁

a musical interval of an octave.

lelepuni₂

a game said to resemble kōnane.

lelepā

one who jumps over a fence; to fence jump. fig., nonconformer; one who cannot be restrained, especially regarding the opposite sex; wanton; to hurdle.

lelepī

to fly into a rage at the slightest provocation; to lose one's temper; hot-tempered. lit., jump [at a] drop.

lelepō

a species of night-flying (lelepō) mālolo, flying fish.

leleu

name of a fruitful tree (no data).

lelewaʻa

a shark listed by Kamakau, perhaps the friendly shark that was said to lean (kālele) on canoe outriggers for food and company.

lelewa₂

hangers-on about a chief; parasitic persons.

lelewi

ornamental carved figurehead on a bowsprit; a canoe with such. (Malo text, chapter 34, section 35.) Pronunciation uncertain.

leleū

word said to describe sexual relations.

leleʻino

to spring or leap violently, as in an attack or fright; to rush violently, plunge. lit., to fly evil.

leleʻoi

excessive, very great. lit., excessive leap.

leleʻopuhi

to leap obliquely into the water from a height. same as lele pāhiʻa.

leleʻā

a marine creature (no data).

lele₁₀

sacrificial altar or stand.

lele₁₁

a tall variety of wild banana (Musa xparadisiaca), formerly planted near the altar (lele). It was offered to the gods and used for love magic. Its essence was thought to fly (lele) to the gods. It was used (for weaning (cf. lele₈): the banana was placed near the child with appropriate prayers in order to obtain the god's consent for weaning. This banana was taboo to women.

lele₁₂

type of fish (no data).

lele₁₃

followed by hapa- + digit). To count by — (digit). see below.

lele₂

contagious, as of disease.

lele₃

wind-blown, of the rain.

lele₄

separate, detached, as a leaf separated from a plant for ceremonials.

lele₅

a detached part or lot of land belonging to one ʻili, but located in another ʻili.

lele₆

hula step: the dancer walks forward, lifting up the rear heel with each step, with slight inward movement; sometimes with the ʻuwehe step with each foot forward. This can also be done backwards; to dance thus.

lele₇

an interval of music, the difference in pitch between two tones, always followed by a number from one to six, especially lele kolu, an interval of a third, as from C to E, or lele lima, an interval of a fifth. Minor intervals are followed by hapa, as lele kolu hapa, an interval of a minor third. Lele may also be followed by pā- and a number, to skip that number of notes. Lele in this sense also occurs as a verb, to sing thus.

lele₈

• to dry up,   • to have passed the menopause;   • to evaporate.

lele₉

to shrink, as clothes.

lelo₁

tongue (short for alelo, elelo).

lelo₂

yellowish, especially the hue imparted to a whaletooth pendant (lei palaoa) by smoking.

lemi

lemon (Citrus limonia), lime (C. aurantifolia).

lemi wai

a kind of water lemon, sweet granadilla (Passiflora ligularis), a passion fruit with heart-shaped leaves; good-tasting fruits, 5 to 9 cm long, ovoid, orange to purplish.

lemuku

broken off short, as a pole; to start out to do something and not finish it.

lemukū

one who sits around doing nothing, a term of reproach; also said to refer to a woman who is sexually unattractive. lit., standing buttocks.

lemuʻā

rubbish scattered by flood rains.

lemu₁

buttocks (politer than ʻōkole).

lemu₂

slow-moving, sluggish; lagging.

lena₁

• yellow, yellowish;   • jaundice;   • bile.

lena₂

var. name for the ʻōlena or turmeric plant.

lena₃

• to stretch out, as to dry;   • to draw tight, as a belt;   • to sight or aim;   • to bend, as a bow.

lena₄

lazy, idle, indolent.

lenekila

lentils (Lens esculenta).

leo hoʻonani

song of praise, hymn.

leo iki

a low voice; to speak softly.

leo kiʻekiʻe

high-pitched voice, falsetto.

leo kāne

male voice, bass.

leo kāne kiʻekiʻe

tenor. lit., high male voice.

leo kūpinaʻi

echo.

leo lelepuni

a musical interlude of a full tone.

leo lua

duet; to sing in twos; two voices.

leo mana

voice of authority.

leo mele

song tune; notes on the scale.

leo nui

loud voice; to speak loudly.

leo paʻa

deaf-mute, dumb person. lit., held voice.

leo pili aku

active voice, in grammar. lit., voice referring elsewhere.

leo pili ʻia mai

passive voice. lit., voice referred to.

leo uwō

bass or baritone notes or voice; roar, as of a lion.

leo waena

second treble, middle or alto voice.

leo wahine

soprano, soprano voice, feminine voice, falsetto.

leo ʻokoʻa

sounds, as in a language. lit., separate speech.

leo ʻole

uncomplaining, agreeable; considerate of feelings of others; giving generously; noiseless, speechless, silent. lit., no voice.

leokani

vowel. lit., voiced sound.

leokanipū

consonant. lit., sound said together [so called because a consonant in Hawaiian is pronounced with a following vowel].

leokū

song sung to an audience. see ex. below. lit., standing voice.

leokū pāhā

quartet.

leokū pākahi

solo. lit., single standing speech.

leokū pākolu

trio. lit., triple standing speech.

leokū pālua

duet. lit., double standing speech.

leoleo

to speak loudly, angrily, vociferously; to wail, as for the dead.

leoleoā

speaking loudly; boisterous; to speak in a loud, noisy fashion.

leopaki

leopard.

lepahū

to lose courage, give up (contraction of lele, to fly, and pahū, to thud).

lepalepa₁

to hang in fringes or tatters.

lepa₁

flag, ensign, place marked by a flag, tapa cloth on end of a stick, as used to mark a taboo area. [triangular flag, as at used car lots, (NKE)]

lepa₂

hem. (Puk. 28.33.)

lepeamoa

cockscomb (Celosia argentea var. cristata), an ornamental tropical herb, bearing flowers crowded either on narrow spikes, or in large, plumed clusters, or in odd-shaped, crested combs, the colors including white, yellow, pink, and purple. lit., comb like that of a chicken.

lepeka

copper coin (RSV), mite (KJV).

lepelepeamoa

Selaginella arbusculla, small club mosses; used for leis, braided with rosebuds.

lepelepeohina₁

monarch butterfly (Danaus plexippus); Kamehameha butterfly.

lepelepeohina₂

nudibranchia.

lepelepe₁

fringed.

lepelepe₂

wattles.

lepelepe₃

labia minor.

lepelua

a turncoat; unfaithful.

lepeohina₁

a red seaweed (Halymenia formosa) with flat blades bearing fringed and irregular margins, with a variety of colors ranging from red to yellow; common allusion to swirling in water resembling movement of pāʻū in dancing. Also called leheleheʻīlio, lepelepeohina, limupepeohina, pāʻūohiʻiaka.

lepeulu

split or crack in wood, running with the grain.

lepeʻa

to twist, as the arm.

lepe₁

hem or fringe, as of a garment; any loose attachment, as of torn cloth or torn flesh.

lepe₂

rooster comb; turkey wattles.

lepo hānai

dirt; rubbish carried to a pit, as to a compost pit. lit., fed dirt.

lepo kuhue

type of clay. lit., solidifying dirt.

lepo kāwili

adobe; clay. lit., mixed earth.

lepo kīʻaha

potter's clay, clay vessel. lit., cup dirt.

lepo loʻi

taro-patch mud.

lepo mānoanoa

clay. lit., thick dirt.

lepo pohō

marshy ground, marsh, mire.

lepo pō

night soil.

lepo pōpolo

pōpolo herb dirt, an uncomplimentary term for commoners.

lepo uli

ashes of certain woods mixed with water, as for medicine. lit., dark earth.

lepo ʻaeʻae

dust.

lepo ʻulaʻula

red earth. fig., people interrelated for generations (rare).

lepohao

rust; rusty. lit., iron dirt.

lepolepo

dirty, turbid; contaminated, as water.

leponalo₁

a euphemism for kūkaenalo; wax; mole (anatomical); muslin.

leponalo₂

a kind of seaweed.

lepopaʻa

hard earth; constipation.

lepopele

match, sulphur (euphemism for kūkaepele). lit., volcanic dirt.

lepu

hare. (Kanl. 14.7) (1843 Bible).

lepupalika₂

republic.

leu

loins.

leuwī

canoe with extra wide weatherboard; forepoint of a canoe where the two ends of the two weatherboards come together.

lewa hoʻomakua

space just above the surface of the earth.

lewa lani

highest stratum of the heavens.

lewa lani lewa

lower atmosphere, just above the lewa hoʻomakua.

lewa lilo loa

outer space, highest atmosphere.

lewa mawaho

outer space.

lewa nuʻu

space in the heavens lower than the lewa lani; atmosphere reached by birds.

lewaalani

part of a heiau temple where human sacrifices were offered.

lewaanuʻu

probably a part of the lananuʻu mamao turret.

lewalewa₁

oscillate.

lewalewa₂

unconcealed penis of a boy, usually called maʻi lewalewa.

lewawalo

to run calling (probably a contraction of lele wawalo).

lewa₁

• sky, atmosphere, space, air, upper heavens;   • aerial.

lewa₂

• to float, dangle, swing, hang, oscillate; swinging, dangling, pendulous, afloat, unstable;   • limber-jointed, of admired hula dancers.

lewa₃

homeless vagabond, wanderer; landless, homeless.

lewa₄

to know thoroughly, as a type of work; to be thoroughly familiar with, as a place.

lewiakana

leviathan.

leʻaleʻa₂

name of a prayer to Kū, Kāne, Lono, and the ʻaumākua (family gods).

leʻa₁

joy, pleasure, happiness, merriment; sexual gratification, orgasm; pleasing, gay, delightful, happy, merry; delighted, pleased.

leʻa₂

clearly, perfectly, thoroughly, successfully.

leʻema

reem; wild ox (RSV), unicorn (KJV).

leʻolani

lofty, tall; chiefly height, rank.

leʻoleʻo₂

children's leaping game.

leʻo₁

lofty, tall, high.

leʻo₂

a variety of taro that cannot be eaten either cooked or as fresh poi without throat irritation. After fermentation, however, the poi is tasty.

Likemona

Richmond.

Likepona

Lisbon.

Limahuli

wind associated with Haʻena, Kauaʻi. lit., turning hand.

Limaloa

god of mirages.

Limukākanakaomahamoku

stroke in lua fighting.) lit., man-striking moss of Mahamoku.

Linepuka

Lynchburg.

Lio Kelaneke

Rio Grande.

Liolioiwawau

name of a star, and name for the southern sky. (Wawaʻu is a widely distributed Polynesian place name) see (PN 229).

Lipekika

Leipzig.

Lipelia

Liberia.

Lipo₂

name of a star in the southern skies, and hence sometimes the name for the southern sky.

Liwapula

Liverpool.

liaʻakimalala

rear admiral.

lihaliha₁

same as liliha₁,   • nauseated, nauseating, of rich or fatty foods only;   • very rich, of fatty, oily food...   • fig., heartsick, as over a tragedy;   • revolted...

lihaliha₂

many nits.

liha₁

nit, louse egg.

liha₂

dreadful, fearful.

lihi lou

tip of a barbless fishhook.

lihili

confused, bewildered, unsuccessful.

lihilihi hana lima

handmade lace; crocheting; any handmade trimming, as of knitting, tatting.

lihilihi kakahiaka

hairy spurge (Euphorbia hirta). Niʻihau.

lihilihi kui lauoho

Maltese or hairpin lace.

lihilihi mōlina₁

lace edging.

lihilihi mōlina₂

a variety of taro.

lihilihi ʻula

narrow band of red, as on a skirt.

lihilihi₂

eyelashes, eyelid.

lihilihi₃

lace.

lihilihi₄

to crochet.

lihilihi₆

a variety of sweet potato (no data). This may be qualified by the term palu.

lihi₁

• edge,   • rim, brim.   • border,   • boundary,   • margins,   Also nihi. see nihi for PPN.

lihi₂

small quantity, particle, a little bit, minutia; slight.

lihi₃

right or interest in property.

lihi₄

point of fishhook.

lihi₅

pearl-shell lure, as for ʻōpelu fish.

lihi₆

piece of land usually between two ahupuaʻa and of unestablished ownership.

liho

choice, precious.

liholiho

very hot, fiery, glowing.

lika

liter.

like loa

exactly alike, identical.

like me

such as, according to, like.

like pū

just the same, alike, similar.

like ʻole

various, all, different, not alike.

like ʻā like

equal, exactly alike.

liki pahu

iron hoop, barrel hoop. lit., barrel tightener.

likiki

ticket, receipt.

likini

rigging.

likini wāwae

leggings.

liki₁

to boast, brag, exult; boaster.

liki₂

• to tighten,   • gird on;   • to pucker;   • stiff, as a limb.

liki₃

astringent, as medicine.

liki₄

a substance or glaze, such as juice of ti roots, that prevents colors from fading or mixing, a mordant.

liko lehua

lehua bud; red lehua leaves as used for leis or medicine; such a lei, as made in the Kīlauea volcano area.

likolehua₁

a variety of sweet potato

likolehua₂

a kind of seaweed.

likoliko

fresh, young, oily.

liko₁

leaf bud; newly opened leaf; to bud; to put forth leaves. fig., a child or descendant, especially of a chief; youth.

liko₂

shining, glistening, as with dew; sparkling, glowing; burning.

liko₃

fat, fleshy.

liko₄

a Tahitian banana (Musa troglodytarum).

liko₅

to burn.

likula

ligure.

likānia

litany.

lila₂

lyre, harp (Kin. 4.21) ; lyric.

lileiuli

to cleanse, as of sin.

lile₁

bright, shiny, dazzling, sparkling

lile₂

in unison, as chanting.

liliha₁

• nauseated, nauseating, of rich or fatty foods only; very rich, of fatty, oily food, as of the wolu, a fish.   • fig., heartsick, as over a tragedy;   • revolted, disgusted, as by a hideous crime;   • dreadful, fearful.

liliha₂

many nits.

lilihua

prepared, supplied, outfitted.

lilikoʻi

passion fruit, purple water lemon, or purple granadilla (Passiflora edulis), an American vine with three-lobed leaves and edible dull-purple fruits about 5 cm long, growing wild in many forests of Hawaiʻi; said to be named after Lilikoʻi, Maui, where it was first grown. The yellow-fruited lilikoʻi (P. edulis f. flavicarpa), is similar but has yellow, better-tasting fruits; it is grown commercially in the Hawaiian Islands and used for desserts and beverages.

lilina

linen, flax, linseed (Linum usitatissimum).

lilina puʻu mauʻu

grass linen. lit., grass-clump linen.

lilinoe

fine mist, rain.

liliwai

a small native herb (Acaena exigua), growing in bogs, only on top of West Maui and Kauaʻi, the narrow, fernlike leaves forming a rosette.

liliʻi

tiny, dainty, fine.

liliʻu₁

scorching, burning, smarting, as salt in a raw wound or pain in the eyes. (Queen Liliʻuokalani was said to have been so named because at the time of her birth her foster mother's aunt, Kīnaʻu, was suffering with pain in the eyes.)

liliʻu₂

Niʻihau name for pua kalaunu, crown flower.

lili₁

jealous; highly sensitive to criticism; jealousy, envy; anger and mental anguish felt if one's loved ones are criticized.

lili₂

blasted, as fruit.

lilo loa

completely engrossed, dedicated, absorbed; permanently lost, taken, or given; far.

lilolilo₁

openhanded, generous.

lilolilo₂

to break away again and again, as fish from a hook; to hover between life and death.

lilo₂

busy, absorbed, occupied, engaged, engrossed, devoted,

lilo₃

expense, expenditure, outlay of money.

lilo₄

far, distant, out of sight, completely, entirely (often follows a noun).

lima heheʻe

a thinning hand, of one whose poi thins and ferments quickly.

lima hema

left hand; left-handed.

lima ikaika

strong hand or arm; power, strength; to handle roughly, assault, ravish, use force; strong-arm.

lima iki

small hand; little finger.

lima koko

• assassin, murderer, shedder of blood, brute;   • bloody hand.

lima kuhi

index finger; in printing, an index or hand calling attention to a note. lit., pointing hand.

lima kuhikuhi

hands of a clock. lit., pointing hands.

lima kākau

handwriting; hand to write with.

lima lawelawe

pilferer, filcher. lit., handling hands.

lima lewalewa

idler. lit., hanging hands.

lima loa

grabber of other's property. lit., long arm.

lima miki

index finger.

lima nui

big hand; thumb.

lima pili

third or ring finger.

lima pūhaʻuhaʻu

puffed sleeve, as sleeve gathered at shoulder and wrist.

lima ulu

a green thumb.

lima ʻaina

second finger. lit., eating finger.

lima ʻākau

right hand; right-handed; dependable helper, right-hand man.

lima ʻāpā

light-fingered, thieving.

limahana

labor, laborer, worker, employee; industrious, busy. staff (HE). cf. hana lima under lima₁.

limalau

(but some persons limit limalau cooperation to canoe and house building).

limalima pilau

one who handles dirty matter. fig., an immoral wretch, as a pimp.

limalima₁

• to handle, use the hands;   • to pilfer, filch.

limalima₂

to hire.

limalima₃

to massage.

limalima₄

prayer in which the priest gestured with his hands; the ceremony was called:

limameke

short for lima ʻumeke, index finger, so called because poi was dipped from the bowl (ʻumeke) with it.

limanui

to attack violently, manhandle, assault, beat, roughhouse, administer a beating, take by force.

limawīwī

a variety of sweet potato. lit., thin hand.

limu ahi

a tree moss or liverwort.

limu alolo

a limu, Potamogeton pectinatus (pronunciation not certain). Niʻihau.

limu haea

a lichen (Sterocaulon sp.), with erect, branching stalks.

limu holoāwai

a fresh-water moss.

limu hāʻula

a red seaweed (Martensia fragilis).

limu kaha

a kind of liverwort.

limu kala

common, long, brown seaweeds (Sargassum echinocarpum), their stems covered with short branches, bearing rather stiff, twisted, more or less toothed, narrow leaves. Rarely eaten raw because of toughness (though edible); used in ceremonies to drive away sickness and to obtain forgiveness (see kala₁). May be qualified by the terms lau liʻiliʻi or lau nui.

limu kalawai

one or more kinds of dark green, slippery fresh-water algae (usually Spirogyra spp.) consisting of rows of cylindrical cells in unbranched filaments, common to fresh-water rivulets, dripping places, and taro patches.

limu kau lāau

all tiny ferns (such as filmy ferns), lichens, liverworts, and mosses growing on trees.

limu kele

moss growing on trees in rain forests.

limu kohu

a soft, succulent, small seaweed (Asparagopsis taxiformis), with densely branched furry tops that are tan, pink, or dark red, arising from a creeping stem-like portion; one of the best-liked edible seaweeds, prepared in balls for market. Also limu koko and for some informants līpehe, līpehu, līpaʻakai.

limu koko

lit., blood seaweed.

limu kākanaka

a soft, sometimes gelatinous blue-green alga (Nostoc commune) sometimes covering the ground in the wet season as small slippery balls, especially at Hanalei, Kauaʻi. lit., man-striking moss, so called because people are said to slip on it and fall. also limu kākanakaomanuʻakepa

limu lana

floating seaweed. fig., a drifter, vagabond.

limu loloa₁

several species of edible red seaweeds (Gelidium), cylindrical or flattened, more or less pinnately branched, texture firm and smooth.

limu loloa₂

a kind of edible red seaweed (Pterocladia capillacea), like limu loloa₁ above but more finely divided.

limu lūʻau

a red seaweed (Porphyra sp.), growing in the winter on boulders in exposed places, with delicate, thin blades appearing in groups. Best known on Kauaʻi, but known on all the major islands. Also paheʻe₅ or pāheʻeheʻe₂.

limu pae

landed seaweed, said of a newcomer or in a bad sense of a drifter, vagabond, or kauā outcast.

limu paʻakai

limu salted for indefinite storage without refrigeration. On Maui, usually limu līpoa.

limu ʻulaʻula

a red seaweed.

limua

overgrown or covered with moss, seaweed, or any limu.

limumakeohāna

a coelenterate (Palythoa sp.) containing a toxin, reported as deadly poisonous at Hāna, Maui. Also limumakeo Muʻolea.

limuʻahuʻula

an upland moss.

limu₂

• tricky, deceiving,   • unstable   (said to be named for the octopus' ability to change its color, and its waving of a tentacle to and fro like the motion of a seaweed in water).

limu₃

wind gust.

limu₄

coil, curl.

limu₅

soft coral.

lina₁

soft; adhesive, sticky, clayey, gummy, tenacious; glutinous, as taro of poor quality.

lina₂

scar.

lina₃

ring, hoop, race track.

lineka

lynx.

linohau

dressed to perfection, beautifully decorated, ornamented.

linokaipa

linotype,

linoleuma

linoleum.

linolino₂

calm, unruffled.

lino₁

bright, shiny, shining with splendor, dazzling, brilliant.

lino₂

to weave, twist, braid, tie.

lino₄

taut.

linu

tight-fisted, ungenerous, heartless, ungracious.

lio heihei

race horse.

lio holo noho

saddle horse.

lio huila māhu

horse with a steam wheel, an old name for train.

lio hulu ʻaeko

dark-gray horse. lit., eagle feather horse.

lio kau

riding horse.

lio kaʻa

carriage horse.

lio keiki

colt.

lio keʻa

stallion.

lio laho

stallion. lit., testicle horse.

lio lawe ukana

pack horse. lit., horse carry gear.

lio lāʻau

merry-go-round; horse on a merry-go-round; sawhorse; wooden horse, as used in quilting.

lio peki

pacing horse.

lio poʻa

gelding.

lio wahine

mare.

liona

lion.

liona kai

sea lion.

lio₂

tight, taut, as a rope, or of hair or horse's ears pulled back tightly.

lio₃

rope tied to the bottom of a large bag net.

lipaki

liberty.

lipano

frankincense.

lipelala

liberal.

lipi

• adze, chisel;   • any sharp edge;   • sharp mountain ridge;   • sharp, tapering.

lipi hoehoe

adze or chisel with broad, flat blade. lit., paddle-like chisel.

lipi kuke

adze or chisel with thin, tapering blade.

lipi kāhela

adze or chisel with concave blade.

lipilipi

same as lipi,   • adze, chisel;   • any sharp edge;   • sharp mountain ridge;   • sharp,   • tapering...

lipine hoʻokani

tape, of a recorder.

lipine kikokiko

typewriter ribbon.

lipioma

small rounded adze or chisel.

lipo wao nahele

gloom and darkness of a great forest.

lipo₁

• deep blue-black, as a cavern, the sea, or dense forest;   • dim, distant;   • grief

lira

lyre, harp (Kin. 4.21) ; lyric.

liuliu

prepared, ready; to make ready; preparations.

liuā

dissolute.

liu₁

leakage, bilge water; to leak, of a canoe or ship.

liwele

book.

liʻawahine

kukui blossoms used as medicine, named for a woodland goddess. lit., female desire [or fear].

liʻa₁

strong desire; yearning, amorous; to wish for ardently, crave.

liʻa₂

fear, chills.

liʻi₁

small, tiny.

liʻi₂

short for aliʻi, chief, being especially common after nā:

liʻoliʻo₁

bright, dazzling, dazzled.

liʻoliʻo₂

name of the sound made by the ʻaʻo bird; to call thus.

liʻo₂

same as liʻoliʻo₂, the sound made by the liʻo (ʻaʻo) bird.

liʻuliʻu

to pass much time; to spend much time.

liʻulā

• twilight, dusk;   • mirage, hallucination.

liʻu₁

slow, tardy, taking a long time; a long time.

liʻu₂

well-salted, salty, seasoned.

liʻu₃

deep, profound, as of skill or knowledge.

Lohiʻau

Pele's dream sweetheart fetched by Hiʻiakaikapoliopele from Kauai. In some accounts he is destroyed by Pele after reaching Kīlauea because of her jealousy at seeing him embrace Hiʻiaka. lit., tardy [he is an antihero] .

Loke ʻAilana

Rhode Island.

Lokeka

Rochester.

Loko Paʻakai

Salt Lake City.

Loma₂

Rome; Roman.

Lonoikamakahiki₁

the god of the annual fall harvest makahiki circuit of the islands when taxes were collected. He was symbolized by a tapa banner suspended on a mast with a tiny carving of a human head at the top.

Lonoikamakahiki₂

a younger son of Keawenuiaʻumi who became chief of Hawaiʻi Island and defeated the invading forces of Kamalālāwalu of Maui. He was also famous as a debater (hoʻopāpā) and mokomoko fighter. (HM 392-394), (For. 4:256-363), (RC 47-63).

Lonoikaʻoualiʻi

an image god taken by Laʻamaikahiki from Raʻiātea, Society Islands, to Wailua, Kauai. (HM 497) Upon the request of the demigod Māui he lengthened the night so that Māui might kill Peʻapeʻamakawalu (eight-eyed Peʻapeʻa). His taboos were the kapu lama (torch taboo) and the kapu loulu (loulu palm taboo). lit., Lono at the chiefly supremacy.

Lonokaʻeho

an eight-headed chief from Kahiki (afar) who pierced the cliff at Kānehoalani, Kualoa, Oʻahu, and severed Kahuku from Kahipa. He was killed by Kamapuaʻa, who called on his plant bodies to entangle the eight stone foreheads of Lonokaʻeho. (HM 205.) lit., Lono the stone.

Lonomakua

a legendary fire guardian and the name of the makahiki image.

Lono₂

one of the four great gods, the last to come from Kahiki, considered a god of clouds, winds, the sea, agriculture, and fertility. He had also the form of the pig man, Kamapuaʻa. He was the patron of the annual harvest makahiki festivals, and his image (Lonomakua) was carried on tax-collecting circuits of the main islands. Some fifty Lono gods were worshiped.

Lono₃

the 28th day of the lunar month.

Lono₄

name of a star.

loala

to praise, extol, as a chief (poetic).

loaloa

elongated garden plot, as for sweet potatoes (so used in 1848 land claims).

loaʻa … kāu

You'll get what's coming to you (rude).

loa₃

as soon as.

loa₄

head tax officer; government tax as contrasting with king's taxes.

loa₅

a district (And.) or large section of it, contrasting with poko.

loea

skill, ingenuity, cleverness; expert, clever, ingenious, adept, deft, technical, skillful, dexterous, handy, skilled; skilled person.

loea kālai aupuni

statesman.

loea kālaiʻāina

politician, politically expert.

lohaloha₃

cocoon.

loha₁

• drooping, wilting;   • hanging low, as a branch;   • beaten down, as by rain.   fig., sullen, spiritless, depressed, unsociable, subordinate, inferior.

loha₂

trimmings of corners and ridge of a thatched house; to put on these trimmings.

loha₄

a variety of banana.

loha₅

a var. name for the kilu game.

lohe lau āhea

hearsay, rumor

lohe pepeiao

hearsay; to hear of.

lohea

audible.

lohelau₁

wall and gable plates in house. see illus. 1, illus. 2, illus. 3

lohelau₂

exhausted, worn-out, dilapidated.

lohelohe₁

to listen carefully, eavesdrop.

lohelohe₂

larvae of the dragonfly; this was used in hula ceremonies because lohe means to hear and obey. see puaʻalohelohe.

lohelohe₄

cocoon.

lohena

hearing, obedience.

loheʻōlelo

hearsay, gossip.

lohina

delay.

lohiʻau

slow, retarded, backward, languid.

loi

to look over critically; to look at as through searching for flaws, scrutinize.

loialike

royalist.

loina₁

• rule,   • custom,   • manners,   • code, precept, law;   • principle, as of a political party.

loina₂

observation, scrutiny.

loio hoʻokolokolo

prosecutor.

loio kalana

county attorney.

loio kuhina

Attorney general.

loio₁

thin, spindly.

loka₁

rod.

loka₂

log, Hebrew liquid measure.

loke Hawaiʻi

double pink rose.

loke hihi

climbing rose.

loke huihui

a pinkish-white rose, very fragrant and growing in a cluster; possibly the Duchess of Brabant, still common.

loke kūkaepele

sulphur rose.

loke lani

the common small red rose. It has been substituted for the pink rose, now rare, as the flower of Maui.

loke lau

green rose (Rosa chinensis, f. viridiflora).

loke pihi

tiny buttonhole roses (Rosa chinensis var. minima).

loke wai kāhuli

a kind of rose, red on the outside of the flower and pink in the center; used for hedges. lit., rose [with] changing color.

lokeli

lottery.

lokema

broom tree (RSV), juniper (KJV).

lokeokaluapele

a pink rose growing in the Kīlauea area, Hawaiʻi, commonly called volcano rose. lit., rose of the volcanic crater.

loke₁

rose; rosy.

loke₂

roast.

lokia

roan, as a horse.

loko hāiki

hardhearted, narrow-minded; tightfisted, parsimonious; such a person; ill will.

loko iʻa kalo

combination fishpond and taro patch.

loko kai

lagoon.

loko kuʻi

man-made salt-water pond. lit., artificial lake.

loko liʻu₁

salt pond.

loko liʻu₂

cross, embittered, sour in disposition; such a person.

loko paʻakai

salt pond or lake.

loko ulu

seedling bed. lit., inside growing.

loko wai

fresh-water pond or lake; fountain.

loko ʻino

merciless, heartless, evil, malevolent, barbarous, cruel; such a person.

loko ʻume iki

shore fishpond with lanes leading in and/or out of the pond, used for trapping fish and probably only on Molokaʻi. lit., small pond drawing in.

lokoloko

puddles, small pools.

lokou

word, logos

loko₂

character, disposition, heart, feelings. cf:     loko hāiki, hardhearted, narrow-minded...     loko ʻino, merciless, heartless, evil, malevolent...     loko liʻu₂, cross, embittered, sour in disposition...     lokomaikaʻi, kind, humane, gracious, benevolent...

loko₃

pond, lake, pool.

loko₄

mainland of the United States (noted in a chant dated 1860, State Archives).

loko₅

in spite of, regardless.

loko₆

by means of.

loku

• downpour of rain; to pour, of rain; torrential.   • blowing of wind; to blow, as a gale;   • fig., to feel deep emotion, pain, sorrow;   • to weep profusely;   • intense.

lola hoʻopalaha

roller. lit. flattening roller.

lola māhu

steam roller.

lola₁

drooping, hanging downward; droopy, sluggish, lazy, idle.

lola₂

a native fern (Asplenium acuminatum), with much-subdivided fronds.

lola₃

a variety of taro.

lola₄

roller, rolling pin; to roll.

lole holoi

laundry; soiled clothes ready to be washed, washing.

lole hāpai

maternity dress.

lole komo

clothes, garments. lit., clothes to put on.

lole lauoho

sackcloth of hair.

lole lepo

soiled clothing, laundry.

lole moe pō

nightgown. lit., night-sleeping clothes.

lole paikau

marching garments, regalia, full regalia.

lole papamū

checkered dress, especially gingham.

lole pia

laundry washed, starched, and dried but not ironed. lit., starch clothes.

lole wai

laundry washed and dried but not starched or ironed. lit., water clothes.

lole wāwae

trousers, pants, panties, slacks. lit., leg clothes.

lole wāwae loloa

long trousers.

lole wāwae moe pō

pajamas. lit., trousers for night sleeping.

lole wāwae pōkole

short trousers, shorts.

lole wāwae pūhaʻuhaʻu

bloomers. lit., puffed-up trousers.

lole wāwae ʻekekeʻi

shorts.

lole wāwae ʻepane

overalls, coveralls. lit., apron trousers.

lole ʻauʻau

bathing suit.

lolea

worn smooth by friction, wear, or constant handling; turned inside out; weathered; skinned, flayed.

lolehau

limping, lame.

lolelau

thatching and trimming, of a house. lit., handle leaves.

lolelua

changeable, fickle, unstable, inconstant, inconsistent, variable; turncoat.

lolena₂

limp, flexible, as cloth; inefficient, unproductive, idle, sterile, barren, faded.

loleʻaeʻae

fine cloth, gauze.

lole₂

• to unfold, turn inside out, reverse;   • to strip or peel off, as bark;   • to skin, flay (Mika 3.3);   • to scalp;   • to handle, turn over with the hands.

lole₃

depigmentation, as of palm of hand or soles of feet.

loli kaʻe

a variety of loli, sea slug.

loli kohola

a variety of loli (Holothuria), black and cylindrical. lit., reef loli.

loli koko

a variety of loli, perhaps Chirodota rigida. lit., blood loli.

loli lūʻau

a variety of loli (Holothuria). lit., tarotops loli.

loli mākoko

a variety of loli, perhaps Chiridota rigida. lit., blood-red loli.

loli pua

a species of edible loli (Holothuria). lit., flower loli.

loli ʻano

change of nature, as of words and their etymology.

loliloli₁

changing, turning, changeable.

loliloli₂

soggy, gummy, tough and watery, as overripe taro.

lolina

a change, alteration.

lolio

skinny, thin.

loli₂

sea slug, sea cucumber, beche-de-mer, trepang (Holothuria spp.); for some people an ʻaumakua. see kūkaeloli and saying, ʻīloli.

loli₃

spotted, speckled, daubed; to color in spots, as tapa.

lolo iwi

bone marrow.

lolo niu

• embryonic sponge in a coconut;   • coconut sheath.

lolo poʻo

brain. lit., head brain.

lolo waʻa

canoe-launching ceremony; to perform the ceremony.

loloaʻu

flying gurnard, a fish (Dactyloptena orientalis).

loloa₂

a seaweed, probably the same as limu loloa.

lolohe₁

to listen carefully, attentively, with good hearing.

lolohe₂

stubborn; hard to move, as a rock.

lolohi

slowpoke.

lolohuamea₂

variegated colors, as of the distant sea.

lolohuā

one who is jealous and constantly stirring up trouble; jealous.

loloiāhili

to wander, as one lost; to stray, dilly-dally; to digress and wander in speech; roundabout.

lolokaʻa

dizziness, with spinning head; dizzy. cf. niu lolokaʻa, pōniuniu.

lolokia

coconut stem.

lolokukui

to be raped, sexually molested or ravished; such a victim.

lolokū₁

midday. cf. kau ka lā i ka lolo under lolo₁.

lolokū₂

muscle on back of the head, probably the occipito-frontalis muscle; the nervous system.

lololo₁

intelligent, brilliant; deep thinking.

lololo₂

tasty, rich, fat, as marrow.

lolomū

unsuccessful, unlucky.

loloniu

canoe hull made of coconut log.

lolopaioea

tall, spindly, thin.

lolopili

name of a design used on Niʻihau mats.

lolopio

to die calmly and easily.

lolopua

zenith.

loloʻa

bleached, as a shell in the sea.

lolo₁

• brains,   • bone marrow.

lolo₂

• religious ceremony at which the brain of the sacrificed animal was eaten (such ceremonies occurred at a canoe launching, start of journey, completion of instruction);   • to have completed the lolo ceremony, hence   • expert, skilled.

lolo₃

pithy, white sponge in a sprouting coconut.

lolo₄

long slender pole placed above the second ridgepole of a house, functioning as a batten for the attachment of additional layers of thatch.

lolo₅

first brew made from ti root.

lolo₈

serves you right! I told you so!

lolōiele

dull. redup. of lōiele, sluggish, slow; slowness; to loiter, dillydally...

loma₁

lazy, indolent, slow, idle.

lomilomi

redup. of lomi to rub, press, squeeze, crush, mash fine, knead, massage...; masseur, masseuse.

lona₁

block of wood used to support a canoe out of water.

lona₂

useless, vain.

lona₃

straight, direct.

lonikū

longitude.

lono honua

to hear surprising or sudden news.

lonohiʻi

to cry to be carried, of an infant carried too much; to fret in a spoiled way to be carried. lit., hear carry.

lonokū

on the back; backward.

lonolau

large-sized gourd.

lonolupe

a banner held up by two staffs.

lonomakaihe

art of spear throwing, named for a god.

lonomea

a native tree (Sapindus oahuensis), to 10 m high, with ovate leaves 10 by 20 and 5 by 13 cm; it is found only on Oʻahu and Kauaʻi. Kauaʻi. On Oʻahu it is called kaulu.

lonopapa₁

news spread far and wide; news so well bruited that everyone has heard repeatedly; spread far, of news.

lonopapa₂

name of an unknown disease or fever.

lonopūhā₁

art of healing, especially of wounds, abscesses.

lonopūhā₂

a class of heiau, probably for healing.

lonoā

hearsay, rumor, gossip; to keep hearing, as rumor.

lono₁

news, report, tidings, remembrance (Kanl. 32.26) , rumor (sometimes formerly preceded by ke).

lonu

cheat, liar, rogue; to cheat, lie.

lopi

thread.

lopi hoʻoholoholo

basting thread.

lopi huluhulu

worsted thread, yarn.

lopi humulau

embroidery thread.

lopi kāholo

basting thread.

lopine

robin.

lopu

consecrated adze, as used in carving.

loulou₁

to link or hook together.

loulou₂

finger-pulling contest: two players hook fingers and see who can keep his finger hooked the longest.

loulu hiwa

a small native fan palm (Pritchardia martii), with thick trunk to 1.9 m high. lit., dark loulu.

loulu lelo

a native fan palm (Pritchardia hillebrandii), with trunk to 6 m high. lit., yellowish loulu.

loulu₁

all species of native fan palms (Pritchardia). Hats are plaited of its leaves bleached white. also noulu.

loulu₂

umbrella, so called because the loulu palm leaf was formerly used as protection from rain or sun.

loulu₃

Alutera monoceros, a fish, perhaps so called because its greenish-white skin resembled the loulu palm; used in sorcery to cause death because the name contains the word lou, to hook.

loulu₄

type of heiau said to be built for prevention of epidemics, famine, destruction; long rituals dedicating a temple including kauila nui, fetching of the ʻōhiʻa logs for images (haku ʻōhiʻa), kuili and hono rituals.

louulu

betrothal gift, as sent from one family to another.

lou₁

hook; to hook, to fasten with a hook; to hook off, as with the lou pole.

lou₂

very long fruit-plucking pole, with short sticks lashed obliquely near the end for plucking, as for breadfruit; to pluck.

lou₃

pain in the side, stitch.

lou₅

buckle, clasp

loʻaʻā

rough jagged stone, either coral or lava; hence, hard, severe, as a taboo.

loʻe

curve of a fishhook.

loʻi

irrigated terrace, especially for taro, but also for rice; paddy.

loʻi Pōʻalima

a 'Friday' taro patch, meaning one worked for the konohiki (supervisor), as Friday was the work day.

loʻi paʻahao

a 'prison' taro patch, meaning that if a tenant failed to pay for use of the land he was imprisoned.

loʻiloʻi₁

pools of water; having many pools; taro patches.

loʻiʻai

taro patch.

loʻohia

• possessed,   • overwhelmed, stricken;   • to befall, happen.

loʻu

• to overhang, as a cliff;   • to bend over, as with grief or laughter;   • bent over, as a laden branch.

loʻu pali

shelter formed by an overhanging cliff. (Malo text, chapter 33, section 3).

loʻulu

an endemic fern (Coniogramme pilosa) with leaves somewhat like those of the breadfruit tree (ʻulu) but the divisions narrower and deeper.

Luahoʻomoe

name of a star, said to appear in the month of Hinaiaʻeleʻele.

Luha

wind associated with Hanalei, Kauaʻi.

Luikiana

Louisiana.

Luikini

Lewiston.

Luikiwila

Louisville.

Lukela

Lutheran.

Lukia₂

Russia, Russian.

Luna Kānāwai Kiʻekiʻe ā Kaulike

Chief Justice

Luwele

Louvre.

Luʻeluʻe₃

lua fighting stroke

Luʻukia₂

A legendary chiefess, sister of Kāwelu, daughter or wife of ʻOlopana.

lua ahi

pit of fire; hell.

lua ahi hoʻomaʻemaʻe

purgatory. lit., cleansing fire pit.

lua hoʻokiʻo wai

cistern.

lua huna

hidden or secret cave or pit, as where bones of the dead were hidden.

lua koʻi

adze quarry.

lua kupapaʻu

tomb, grave.

lua liʻiliʻi

outhouse, toilet. lit., small pit.

lua meki

deep pit or cave.

lua pao

burial cave. lit., cave pit.

lua paʻahao

dungeon. lit., jail pit.

lua pele

volcano, crater. lit., volcanic pit.

lua puhi₁

blowhole.

lua puhi₂

eel hole.

lua pālolo

clay pit.

lua unu

refuse pit in a heiau.

lua ʻeli waiwai

mine.

lua ʻole

superior, incomparable, unequalled, second to none, unique, unsurpassed (similar to ana ʻole and launa ʻole).

lua ʻōpala

rubbish pit.

lua-

to enjoy oneself.

luaahi₁

victim, as of wrath.

luaahi₂

fearful, mighty.

luahaka

outhouse.

luahele

pitfall, seduction, deception; to lead astray, seduce, deceive.

luahoana

halo or rainbow around sun or moon. lit., polished pit.

luaiele₁

to live a dissipated life, reckless of health; to dissipate.

luaiele₂

swaying.

luakaha

• enjoyable, pleasant, as a place to which one is attached;   • to while away the time enjoyably.

luakele

cave for concealing. For roots cf. lua (pit) and hūnākele (to bury).

luakini

temple, church, cathedral, tabernacle; large heiau where ruling chiefs prayed and human sacrifices were offered; to perform temple work.

luakālai

lit., hewn pit.

lualaʻi

(lua- + -laʻi, transitivizer)

lualuaʻi₂

to raise and chew the cud.

lualua₁

uneven, full of holes, rough, bumpy, as a road.

luana

to be at leisure, enjoy pleasant sorroundings and associates, live in comfort and ease, enjoy oneself, relax, be content. (see lua-, -na.)

luana iki

to pause a moment; to enjoy oneself a little.

luanuʻu

dressed out in tapa, as temple images in Lono's temple on important occasions.

luapaʻū

refuse pit in the luakini or temple enclosure. fig., any place of destruction, lit., damp pit.

luapō

grave. lit., night pit. midnight (ka hola luapō) (Hopita).

luawai

well, cistern (Isa. 36.16) , pool, pond, reservoir.

luaʻa

to pound poi.

luaʻehu

many and colorful.

luaʻeli pōhaku

quarry. lit., pit for diging stones.

luaʻi

• vomit; to vomit, retch,   • volcanic eruptions; erupt;   • to banish, expel, drive out, as people.

luaʻi koko

any kind of sickness with vomiting of blood; to vomit blood.

luaʻi pele

volcanic eruption, lava, sulphur, brimstone.

luaʻikū

disgusting, nauseating, sickening.

luaʻoni

second person to fall in battle, the second victim.

luaʻuhane

the inner corner of each eye, next to the nose; tear duct. lit., soul-pit, so called because it was believed that the soul leaves and enters the body of sleeping persons at this point.

luaʻāpana

jester (For. 5:479); hilarity, sport; to laugh, jest, indulge in uproarious merriment.

lua₃

• two, second, secondary, twice, deuce, double;   • doubly, much, a great deal.

lua₄

equal, likeness, duplicate copy, match.

lua₅

companion, mate.

lua₆

a type of dangerous hand-to-hand fighting in which the, fighters broke bones, dislocated bones at the joints, and inflicted severe pain by pressing on nerve centers. There was much leaping, and (rarely) quick turns of spears. Many of the techniques were secret. Lua holds were named (see fight). Lua experts were bodyguards to chiefs. see Oʻahu.

lue

rue.

luea

seasickness, nausea, dizziness.

luehu₁

easily scattered, dispersed, blown away; scaly, as skin. lit., scattered fine.

luehu₂

kind of soft, porous stone that breaks easily.

luelue

bag net with meshes the width of a finger, as held open by a hoop of walaheʻe wood and baited and lowered into the sea by tour long cords.

luhe

to hang down, overhang, sag, droop, wilt, wither.

luheluhe

to sag with fat, overhang.

luhi hewa

tired without accomplishing anything; weary from efforts that bring no results.

luhia

a variety of shark.

luhiehu₁

beautiful, attractive, festooned.

luhiehu₂

soft, cooked soft.

luhina

a laboring, wearying, caring for, etc.

luhi₁

• weary, tired, fatigued; wearisome, burdensome, tiresome, laborious, tedious;   • burden, wearisome or tedious task;   • labor, work, pains, toil.

luhi₂

• a child or other person tended and raised with devoted care;   • to care for and attend with care and affection;   • protégé.

luina

sailor.

luka

rood, in surveying.

lukaluka₃

tapa sarong, as worn by men.

lukapia

root beer.

lukau

lookout; to look out, be careful.

luke

lute.

lukipa

Lucifer.

luku

massacre, slaughter, destruction; to massacre, destroy, slaughter, lay waste, devastate, exterminate, ravage.

luku lua

doubly destroyed, said of opposing forces despairing of victory and by mutual consent stopping fighting.

luku wale

vandalism, useless slaughter or destruction; to destroy thus; massacre (eh)

lukuna

destruction, slaughter.

lukānela

lieutenant.

lula hoʻokeonimana

rules of gentlemanly conduct, etiquette.

lula kumu

fundamental or basic rule.

lula ʻole

disorderly, unruly, without manners, uncouth.

lula₁

• rules, manners, regulations,   • ethics, etiquette.

lula₂

ruler, tape measure

lule₁

• to quiver, as jello;   • to sag, as flesh of a fat person;   • weak,   • flexible

lule₂

a variety of pili grass.

luli

• to shake, as the head in approval or disapproval;   • to pitch and roll, as a ship;   • to totter, be unsteady;   • to sway to and fro (Mat. 11.7)   • wag

luliluli

agitated;

lulo

a rare word used to describe a fearless and physically perfect chief, used with napa and a negative. Pronunciation uncertain.

luloni

to sleep soundly.

lulu

• calm, peace, to be calm;   • shelter, lee,   • protection, shield, to shield.   • cloak;   • to lie at anchor;

lulu aliʻi

royal feather cloak (rare); chiefly protection.

luluhi₂

black and heavy, of clouds; overcast, threatening.

luluka

peace, calm.

lululu

dead calm, great calm; becalmed; hanging limp, as a sail in a calm.

lulumi

crushed, crumpled, wrinkled...   redup. of lumi₁:   • to crowd uncomfortably;   • to overturn,   • pound, crush, as the surf;   • to press...;

luluāʻina₁

freckles.

luluāʻina₂

to pound ʻina and hāʻukeʻuke sea urchins as for bait.

luluʻu

same as luʻuluʻu₁, bent or bowed down, as with weight, sorrow, or trouble...; said also of a tree laden with fruit, a person laden with leis.

luma ʻia

capsized.

lumahaʻi₁

certain twist of the fingers in making string figures, perhaps named for a place on Kauaʻi.

lumahaʻi₂

a medicine.

lumakika

rheumatism, arthritis, neuritis.

lumaʻi

to douse,   • duck;   • to upset,   • tumble,   • capsize, as in the surf.   • fig., to destroy, overwhelm, as with trouble (luma + -a ʻi or -ʻi, transitivizers).

lumaʻina

drowning, etc.

lumi holoi

laundry room.

lumi hoʻoluana

lounge, reception room.

lumi hoʻāhu

storeroom.

lumi hulahula

ballroom.

lumi hāiki

narrow room, cell.

lumi waiho pā

pantry. lit., room for leaving plates.

lumi waiho ukana

storeroom. lit., room to leave goods.

lumi ʻauʻau

bathroom. lit., washing room.

lumiʻaina

dining room.

lumi₁

• to crowd uncomfortably;   • to overturn,   • pound, crush, as the surf;   • to press;   • to be overwhelmed with trouble;   • to destroy by black magic.

luna ana ʻāina nui

surveyor general.

luna aupuni

government official.

luna awa

harbor master.

luna hale kiaʻi

commander or chief guard of a fortress.

luna hana

overseer, foreman, anyone in charge of work.

luna haneli

centurion. lit., overseer of hundred.

luna haʻi

confessor, as Catholic priest. lit., speaking superior.

luna helu

census taker. lit., counting supervisor.

luna helu kālā

teller, as of a bank. lit., officer who counts money.

luna hoʻohana

manager, administrative head, overseer. lit., supervisor to cause work to be done.

luna hoʻokō

executive officer. lit., officer who accomplishes.

luna hoʻokō kauoha

executor.

luna hoʻoluhi

taskmaster. lit., officer who makes weary.

luna hoʻomalu

chairman; speaker, as of the House of Representatives; presiding officer; comptroller.

luna hoʻonā

commissioner who settles land claims.

luna hoʻoponopono

editor, supervisor, administrator, director.

luna hoʻoponopono waiwai

executor, as of an estate; trustee.

luna hoʻopuka

publisher. lit., officer who makes appear.

luna hōʻoia

auditor. lit., proving officer.

luna hōʻoiaʻiʻo palapala

certifier of title. lit., officer who certifies the truth of document.

luna kanalima

leader of fifty men.

luna kaua

war officer, captain, commander.

luna kaukani

officer in charge of a thousand or more men. lit., Officer of a thousand (Eng.)

luna kia

upper part of a pillar, chapiter.

luna kiaʻi

supervisor; overseer of others; bishop.

luna kiʻekiʻe

high officer.

luna koa

military officer.

luna koʻikoʻi

ambassador; important officer.

luna kula

school superintendent, schoolmaster, school committee (old term).

luna kulanui

school superintendent (old term).

luna kākau kope o ke aupuni

notary public. lit., officer who writes the government copy.

luna kālā

comptroller.

luna kānāwai

judge, magistrate; Book of Judges in the Old Testament; referee, as in a fight; judicial. lit., law officer.

luna kānāwai hoʻokōkauoha

probate judge.

luna kānāwai hoʻomalu

police justice.

luna kānāwai kaʻapuni

circuit judge.

luna kānāwai kiʻekiʻe

chief justice.

luna kānāwai kōkua

associate justice.

luna kānāwai ʻāpana

district judge.

luna lawe hana

chief servant, minister. lit., officer undertaking work.

luna lawelawe no ke kenelala

aide-de-camp. lit., officer serving for the general.

luna leka

postmaster. lit., letter officer.

luna mele

chorister.

luna mākaʻi

district sheriff, chief of police.

luna mālama waiwai

trustee.

luna noho

chairman.

luna nui

chief officer or foreman, especially head overseer of a sugar plantation, superintendent.

luna nānā

inspector; judge, as in song contests.

luna nānā helu

auditor.

luna nānā koho

election official.

luna pai

officer who called warriors to battle. lit., urging officer.

luna wai

water master, one in charge of water distribution.

luna wehe pilikia

representative in the old Hawaiian parliament. lit., officer who removes trouble.

luna ʻae male

officer who permits marriage (1851 term).

luna ʻahaʻaina

toastmaster, director of a feast.

luna ʻai

food inspector.

luna ʻauhau

tax collector (Luka 7.34) , tax assessor, publican, master of tribute.

luna ʻekalesia

alderman, lay church official.

luna ʻohana

head of a family; headman of a tribe.

luna ʻohi kuke

collector of customs.

luna ʻānela

Archangel.

luna ʻāpono

censor, approving officer.

lunakahiko

elder (Puk. 3.16) ; elderly leader.

lunamakaʻāinana

representative in the legislature. lit., people's officer.

lunawaemanaʻo

conscience. lit., officer that selects thoughts.

lunaʻikehala

conscience. lit., officer who knows wrong.

lunaʻohi kālāʻauhau

tax collector.

lunaʻōlelo

apostle; communication officer; proclaimer.

luna₃

chief piece in the kōnane game.

luni

limping, unsteady.

lunihini

perhaps a land shell.

lupalupa₁

flourishing, of luxuriant growth, lush, thriving.

lupalupa₂

purifying ceremonies of various sorts, as to insure growth or to cleanse contaminated persons, as those who have buried the dead; prayer for the soul of one who has just died; to conduct such ceremonies.

lupea

pleasing, attractive, as plants.

lupepa₁

rhubarb (Rheum rhaponticum).

lupepa₂

calomel and tartar emetic.

lupeʻa

drunk, intoxicated; to distress.

lupeʻakeke

Hawaiian stormy petrel (Oceanodroma castro cryptoleucura).

lupe₁

kite. Four types of lupe were said to exist;   • lupe lā, a round kite, lit., sun kite;   • lupe mahina, kite with tapa covering cut in a crescent shape, lit., moon kite;   • lupe manu, kite with wings on the side, lit., bird kite;   • lupe maoli, kite suggestive of European kites in shape, lit., genuine kite.

lupe₃

flattened end of the forward end of the outrigger float outside of the joining of the outrigger boom to the float.

lupe₄

a kind of seaweed.

lupo₂

wolf.

luʻaloa

large fishhook, as used for large fish or sometimes for bonito.

luʻaluʻa

aged,

luʻa₁

old and wrinkled, worn and shabby with use, worn-out; sagging, hanging down, flimsy, soft, pliable.

luʻe

loose, as a garment; hanging loose, long and flowing; loosened.

luʻeluʻe₂

loose gown or robe, as of Biblical characters.

luʻi₁

imaginary or indistinct sound.

luʻi₂

to abolish, nullify.

luʻoni

one who delivers a victim to the sacrificial altar; to so deliver.

luʻu kimo

to dive headfirst.

luʻu poʻo

to dive headfirst.

luʻu ʻili

tanner of skins and hides.

luʻukia₁

coconut fiber lashing; to lash thus.

luʻuluʻu₁

• bent or bowed down, as with weight, sorrow, or trouble;   • painful, sorrowful, sad, wretched, woeful, bereaved, downcast, depressed, toilsome, overladen.

luʻuluʻu₂

to set a hīnaʻi, fish trap.

Lā Hoʻomaikaʻi

Thanksgiving Day. lit., day to bless.

Lā Hoʻālohaloha

Thanksgiving Day. lit., day for expression of affection.

Lā Kau Pua

Decoration Day. lit., day to place flowers.

Lā Kāpaki

Sabbath Day.

Lā Lū Pua

Decoration Day. lit., day to scatter flowers.

Lā ʻAi Pelehū

Thanksgiving Day. lit., turkey-eating day.

Lāhei

a lua fighting stroke.

Lākana₂

London.

Lākina

Latin.

Lālani₂

a name for the Milky Way (Kep. 81), and also of a single star.

Lānaʻi₁

Lānaʻi Island. perhaps lit., day conquest. also Nānaʻi.

Lānui o nā Limahana

Labor Day. lit., holiday of the laborers.

Lāʻau Kū Kahi

eighteenth day of the lunar month.

Lāʻau Kū Lua

nineteenth day of the lunar month.

Lāʻau Pau

twentieth day of the lunar month.

Lāʻieikawai

the heroine of the romance of the same name called 'the masterpiece of Hawaiian romantic fiction' (HM 534). Lāʻie was hidden at birth in a pool at Lāʻie, Oahu, and later reared in a sacred house of yellow feathers at Paliuli, a mythical paradise on Hawaiʻi. ʻAiwohikupua of Kauaʻi vainly wooed her. She adopted his Maile sisters. They found her a god husband who lived in the sun — Kaʻōnohiokalā (the eyeball of the sun) — but he was unfaithful. Lāʻie was worshiped as ka wahine o ka liʻulā, the lady of the twilight. Using traditional motifs, Haleʻole (in (Laie)) wrote this long story in imitation of European romances. lit., ʻie leaf in the water. see Kaʻōnohiokalā; Maile; Waka.

Lāʻie₂

place name, windward Oʻahu. Mormon Temple and Brigham Young University-Hawaiʻi site.

lā anoano

person presiding over the game of kilu. lit., quiet day.

lā hana

workday.

lā hiki

eastern sun, rising sun; eastern.

lā hoʻokahakaha

holiday on which everyone dresses up, enjoys sports, parties. lit., display day.

lā hoʻomalolo

Day of preparation (Mat. 27.62) ; day before the taboo day, hence Saturday.

lā hoʻomanaʻo

Day of commemoration, anniversary day.

lā hoʻāno

Holy day, day of worship.

lā huikala

Day of purification ceremonies.

lā kau

setting sun.

lā kea

white fin.

lā kulāia

Day of celebration in honor of a chief.

lā kōʻele

days of labor required of tenants. Also kōʻele, lā paʻahao.

lā maka kanaka

holiday; festive day on which people gathered for parties and celebrations. lit., day of people's faces.

lā noa

weekday. lit., day without taboo.

lā paʻahao

days of labor required of tenants. Also kōʻele, lā kōʻele.

lā piha makahiki

birthday.

lā-₁

short for lau₁, leaf, frond... with k- of the following word omitted: lāʻalo for lau kalo, taro leaf; lāʻī for lau kī, ti leaf; lāʻō for lau kō, sugar-cane leaf. Also lāʻie for lau ʻie, lākī for lau kī.

lā-₃

third person, in the dual and plural pronouns only, lāua and lākou.

lāhai₁

to poise aloft, as a kite; hover.

lāhai₂

rare var. of lēhei, lēkei, to leap.

lāhai₃

short wing fence to guide cattle to a corral.

lāhea

vile-smelling; stench; one of unsavory reputation.

lāhoe₂

cactus.

lāhui hui pū

united nation.

lāhui kanaka

nation, people, tribe, multitude; mankind, humanity.

lāhui₁

nation, race, tribe, people, nationality; great company of people; species, as of animal or fish, breed; national, racial.

lāhui₂

to assemble, gather together.

lāhui₃

to prohibit, forbid, lay a taboo, proclaim a law (possibly -i is a transitivizer; cf. and Samoan lafu, to prohibit).

lākana₁

lantana (Lantana camara), a thorny tropical American bush with variegated flower heads, yellow, orange, red, white, and pink. Eng. Also lanakana (Niʻihau), mikinolia hihiu, mikinolia hohono, mikinolia kukū.

lākea

fair, white, of complexion.

lākike

lattice.

lākā

lascar [East Indian sailor].

lākī₁

ti leaf (short for lau kī).

lākī₂

stunted, as of plants that have matured.

lākō

sugar-cane leaf (same as lāʻō, contraction of lau kō).

lālaha

broad. lit., broad surface.

lālahalaha

to rise and swell, of surf before it breaks; broad, as a surface.

lālahi

thin, delicate. lit., thin surface.

lālama₁

daring, fearless, clever, as of a climber of precipices or trees.

lālama₂

to pilfer, meddle, grope, reach here and there; to be scattered here and there, as houses; pilfering.

lālani poepoe

curve, arc.

lālau

to seize, take hold of, grasp, reach out for, pick up, hold fast.

lālau lima

to grab in the hands, tackle, manhandle.

lālau ʻino

to snatch away or grab roughly or ruthlessly.

lālauahi

gray, stormy-looking, smoke-colored.

lālaʻau

rotten, as of eggs; disturbed, addled.

lālea

buoy, beacon; prominent object or landmark ashore to steer by.

lālei

cluster, bunch, as of bananas; assembled together, as flowers in a lei.

lāliʻi

detailed; to do detailed work, attend to small details.

lālā kanu

a cutting (to plant).

lālākea

whitetip shark (Pterolamiops longimanus), up to 4 m long. lit., white fins.

lālākoʻa

with strong limbs. lit., coral branch.

lālākukui

many.

lālāwai

prosperous, successful, well-to-do, rich.

lālā₂

member, as of a society.

lālā₃

term in fractions.

lālā₄

slip, as of hibiscus. Also lālā hoʻoulu.

lālā₅

sweet potato produced on a branch vine.

lālā₆

barb or hook, as of bone or coconut shell, on a mother-of-pearl lure; bone point of a composite hook.

lālā₇

fins.

lānahu

charcoal, coal.

lānahu pōhaku

cinders.

lānaʻi₂

a variety of sweet potato.

lānia

to warm, toast, or wilt over a fire, as young pandanus leaves.

lānihinihi

thin, narrow. lit., edge surface.

lāpaki

rabbit, hare. cottontail (HE)

lāpeʻe

bent, crooked, doubled up; curled up, like the tail of a pig; coiled, flexed.

lāpuʻu

• bunched up, humped up, curled up;   • crooked, bent over, arched;   • head bent forward, as of a bucking horse.

lāuaʻaua

counselor.

lāuli₁

dark, overcast, shady; darkness. lit., dark sun.

lāuli₂

a variety of ulua, a fish. lit., dark fin.

lāwalu

fish or meat bound in ti leaves for cooking; to cook thus.

lāʻaeʻoia

past days of youth, strength, beauty, prosperity.

lāʻahaʻaina

feast day.

lāʻalo

mature taro tops too tough to eat, and good only for wrapping (contraction of lau kalo, taro leaf).

lāʻau Kalikimaka

Christmas tree.

lāʻau aliʻi

children of chiefs by second matings; their children were termed laʻa uli.

lāʻau ana

yardstick, ruler, surveying rod, measuring stick.

lāʻau hamo

salve, ointment. lit., rubbing medicine.

lāʻau hili

switch, club.

lāʻau hope

after endpiece of a canoe.

lāʻau hoʻohanuhanu

inhalant.

lāʻau hoʻohiamoe

drug, narcotic, soporific, medicine to cause sleep, chloroform.

lāʻau hoʻoikaika

tonic, any medicine that strengthens.

lāʻau hoʻokani pahu

drumstick. lit., drumplaying stick. cf. ʻuha moa.

lāʻau hoʻokaʻa

rolling pin, any wooden roller.

lāʻau hoʻomake mū

insecticide. lit., medicine to kill insects.

lāʻau hoʻomalule kino

narcotic, drug. lit., medicine to relax the body.

lāʻau hoʻomālielie

tranquilizer.

lāʻau hoʻonahā

cathartic medicine.

lāʻau hoʻonoenoe

drug, as opium. lit., befogging plant.

lāʻau hoʻopiʻi

emetic. lit., medicine to make come up.

lāʻau hoʻopololei

splint.

lāʻau hoʻopā

medicine to prevent fecundation.

lāʻau hoʻowali ʻai

implement for mixing poi or poi palaoa.

lāʻau hānō₁

asthma medicine.

lāʻau hānō₂

Jimson weed (Datura stramonium), a cosmopolitan weed, related to nānāhonua (Brugmansia candida), a coarse annual herb with white or pale purple or blue trumpet-shaped flowers 5 to 10 cm long and spiny fruits about 5 cm long. The plant is strongly narcotic and poisonous. A drug called stramonium, extracted from dried leaves and flowering tops, is used to treat asthma.

lāʻau hū

any gum-producing tree or plant, as candlenut, spruce.

lāʻau ihu

bow endpiece of a canoe.

lāʻau iki ʻai ʻia

edible herb. cf. (Roma 14.2) . lit., small eaten plant.

lāʻau kaha

boom of a vessel. lit., turning stick.

lāʻau kahi hā

one-by-four lumber.

lāʻau kalakala

lantana. lit., thorny plant.

lāʻau kaʻa

• cypress (RSV),   • fir tree (KJV) (Zek. 11.2) ;   • terebinth (RSV),   • elm (KJV) (Hos. 4.13) ;   • conifer.

lāʻau keʻa

wooden cross or crucifix; bar to hold a gate shut, brace, bolt.

lāʻau kia

stick for snaring birds.

lāʻau kinipōpō

ball bat of any kind.

lāʻau kiʻi

easel.

lāʻau kumu ʻole

parasite. lit., plant without foundation. A legendary koa tree with this name at Kahikikolo, Kauaʻi, was said to have only branches and no trunk.

lāʻau kuʻi

ladder, tree with crosspieces used as a ladder. lit., joined wood.

lāʻau kuʻi kope

coffee huller.

lāʻau kuʻi palu

wooden palu pestle.

lāʻau kāhea

a type of faith healing of broken or crushed bones or sprains. lit., calling medicine.

lāʻau kāpalapala

bamboo stamp for marking tapas. lit., printing stick.

lāʻau kī

bar to hold a gate shut, bolt.

lāʻau kū

house post, post, doorpost; mast. lit., standing stick.

lāʻau kūpeʻe

stocks, wooden fetters, handcuffs. lit., bracelet sticks.

lāʻau lalo

boom of a vessel. lit., down stick.

lāʻau lapaʻau

medicine. lit., curing medicine.

lāʻau liʻiliʻi

small bush, plant, or stick.

lāʻau loke

rosewood.

lāʻau lua hā

two-by-four lumber.

lāʻau lālau meaʻai

chopsticks.

lāʻau make

poison.

lāʻau moekū

wooden bedstead.

lāʻau mākaʻi

policeman's club.

lāʻau paepae

boom of a vessel.

lāʻau pahupahu

billiard cue. lit., billiard stick.

lāʻau palupalu

herbs, tender vegetables.

lāʻau pauka makika

punk for mosquitoes. lit., stick mosquito powder.

lāʻau paʻi kinipōpō

ball bat, tennis racket, pingpong paddle; any kind of paddle for slapping a ball. lit., stick for beating ball.

lāʻau pili

name of a gambling game. lit., betting stick.

lāʻau pālau

fighting club.

lāʻau ʻaila

castor-oil plant; lit., oil plant.

lāʻau ʻoʻoi

bramble, briar, thorny tree.

lāʻau ʻōhikihiki niho

toothpick. lit., stick to pick teeth.

lāʻauʻai

chopsticks.

lāʻauʻala

fragrant wood, especially sandalwood.

lāʻau₂

medicine, medical.

lāʻau₃

lump or knot in the flesh, as eased by the rubbing kahi massage; to feel such a knot or stiffness; cramp. Charley horse; to have a cramp.

lāʻau₄

picture frame.

lāʻau₅

general name for canoe endpiece.

lāʻau₆

nights of the moon beginning with Lāʻau, see:     Lāʻau Kū Kahi - 18th day of the lunar month...     Lāʻau Kū Lua - 19th day of the lunar month...     Lāʻau Pau - 20th day of the lunar month... see also (Malo Ch. 12: Divisions of the year, 30-36).

lāʻele

• old leaf, ready to fall or beginning to dry (a contraction of lau ʻelemakule, old leaf).   • fig., aged; old age.

lāʻie₁

short for lau ʻie, ʻie vine leaf.

lāʻiki

tight, as a dress; painfully stuffed, as the stomach after overeating; narrow, as a gate opening (contraction of lāʻā, wide, and iki, small).

lāʻā

width, breadth, as of cloth.

lāʻī

ti leaf (contraction of lau kī).

lāʻīpala

a bright-yellow reef fish (Zebrasoma flavescens). lit., yellow ti leaf.

lāʻō₁

same as lau kō, sugar-cane leaf.

lāʻō₂

a bright-colored greenish fish, about 1.3 cm long (Halichoeres ornatissimus).

lā₁₀

common refrain in songs, as in (EM 90).

lā₃

a sail.

lā₄

fin.

lā₅

each of two cross sticks holding corners of the dip net called ʻupena ʻākiʻikiʻi.

lā₆

common demon. occurring after both nouns and verbs, and as the last part of the demon. kēlā that (far, see table 12 in (Gram. 7.2)) and pēlā, like that; following directionals it is usually unstressed and written as the concluding part of the directional (aʻela, akula, ihola, maila). It occurs also in the sequence ua (noun) lā, that aforementioned. A var. is ala₅.

lā₈

the letter 'l'.

lā₉

sixth note on the musical scale, la.

Lēhei₂

a rain associated with Makawao, Maui.

Lēhei₃

a lua fighting stroke.

Lēkēmapa

December.

lē

to go about aimlessly, to do no work; listless, lazy.

lēhau

crowded, as with people.

lēhei₁

• to jump, hop, as a goat over a wall;   • to leap, start up and fly.   lēkei is a common variant.

lēkei

var of lēhei.   • to jump, hop, as a goat over a wall;   • to leap,   • start up and fly...

lēkō

watercress (Nasturtium microphyllum).

lēkō keʻokeʻo

a variety of watercress, said to be light green. lit., white lēkō.

lēkō ʻeleʻele

a variety of watercress with dark stems and leaves. lit., black lēkō.

lēpela

leprosy, leper; leprous (Oihk. 13.2) . Formerly only leprosy, and not leper.

lēpelo

(formerly only leper).

lēʻia

abundance; full.

lēʻiwi₂

a kind of canoe with a flat manu.

lēʻī

crowded, full. Also lēʻiwi.

Līanu

a wind reported at Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

Līloa₁

name of an early chief, the father of ʻUmi.

Līlīlehua

name of a wind and rain, famous at Pālolo, Oʻahu, and Waiehu, Maui. lit., lehua chill.

lī anu

cool chill.

lī kākini

garters. lit., tie stockings (Eng.).

lī kāliki

corset lace; to lace up a corset.

lī kāmaʻa

shoelace; to lace shoes.

lī lua

extremely chilly.

lī ʻapu

a variety of taro (no data).

lī-

a prefix to many kinds of seaweeds, short for limu.

līhau₁

gentle cool rain that was considered lucky for fishermen (UL 241); moist and fresh, as plants in the dew or rain; cool, fresh, as dew-laden air.

līhau₂

a variety of sweet potato (no data).

līlia

any kind of lily.

līlia palaʻai

day lily (Hemerocallis spp.). lit., pumpkin lily.

līlialanaikawai

water lily (Nymphaea spp.) lit., lily floating on the water.

līliaokeawāwa

lily of the valley (Convallaria majalis).

līloa₂

a long time ago.

līlā

• spindly, undeveloped, as of plants;   • thin, as a line of words across a page.

līlē₁

var. of līlā,   • spindly, undeveloped, as of plants;   • thin, as a line of words across a page...

līlē₂

upland patch, as of olonā. Kauaʻi.

līlīlehua₁

the Texas sage (Salvia coccinea), a weedy herb from southern United States, 30 cm high or more, with toothed, ovate leaves and red flowers, 2.5 cm long, borne in long narrow clusters.

līlīlehua₂

a variety of taro (no data).

līmanamana

a kind of seaweed. lit., branching seaweed.

līpahapaha

a general term for sea lettuce (Ulva fasciata and Monostroma oxyspermum), common green seaweeds with delicate broad blades, usually with wavy margins. Eaten as a minor element mixed with other tastier seaweeds. Also ʻīliohaʻa, līpaha, līpālahalaha, pahapaha (probably restricted to Kauaʻi), pakaiea (restricted to Hawaiʻi), and pālahalaha (Maui, Molokaʻi, and Oʻahu).

līpaheʻe₁

Called līpāhoe on Maui.

līpaheʻe₂

Kauaʻi.

līpalu

a seaweed much like hulu ʻīlio₃, and perhaps the same; edible, green, soft, slippery tufts.

līpaoaoa

a seaweed. lit., fragrant seaweed.

līpaʻakai

limu salted for indefinite storage without refrigeration; on Kauaʻi usually limu kohu from Niʻihau. Some consider līpehe, līpehu, and līpaʻakai as variants of limu kohu.

līpehe

same as līpaʻakai, salted limu.

līpepeiao₁

a seaweed. also limu pepeiao, limu kulapepeiao.

līpepeiao₂

a fresh water moss, usually qualified by wai.

līpeʻepeʻe

some native species of a genus of edible red seaweeds (Laurencia parvipapillata, L. dotyi, L. succisa), short, with stiff, knobby branchlets, nestling especially in basaltic rock.

līpoa kuahiwi

a nonedible mountain moss.

līpoa₁

bladelike, branched, brown seaweeds (Dictyopteris plagiogramma and D. australis) with conspicuous midrib on blade, unique aroma and flavor; highly prized on all islands.

līpuʻupuʻu

an edible green seaweed (Valonia utricularis), with turgid joints and short branches.

līpāhoe

Maui.

līpālāwai

edible, green, fresh-water algae, consisting of tufts of branching threads (Pithophora spp. and Stigeoclonium spp.), or of a network of threads (Hydrodictyon), or of simple threads (Spirogyra spp.).

līpēpē

Niʻihau.

līwali

soft, thin, as poi or dough.

līʻō

to act wild, as a frightened animal; to open the eyes wide in terror; to quiver, leap away, shy, as a frightened horse.

lī₁

chills; to have chills; to tremble with cold; shuddery feeling of horror.

lī₂

lace, as of shoes; to lace or tie.

lī₃

• to hang,   • gird;   • to furl or reef, as a sail.

lī₄

third note in musical scale, mi.

Lōkālia₂

Rosalie.

Lōʻihi₂

young undersea volcano 30 kilometers southeast of Hawaiʻi Island.

Lō₄

a line of Oʻahu chiefs.

lō-

prefix, perhaps short for loʻo-, to obtain. cf:   lōhai, lever or stick used in prying up or raising heavy articles...   lōkahi, unity, agreement, accord, unison, harmony... (kahi one...)   lōkea, long European knife with a white handle... (kea white...)   lōmilo, to spin with fingers; to twist, as thread in making rope or cord... (milo₂ twist...)   loʻohia, possessed; overwhelmed, stricken; to befall, happen...   loʻokahi, var. of lōkahi, unity, agreement...   lōpiʻo, to bend over, as one nodding, sleeping... (piʻo₁ bent...)   lōuhu, same as uhu, to bolt, strain...

lōhai

lever or stick used in prying up or raising heavy articles; to lift thus.

lōiele₁

sluggish, slow; slowness; to loiter, dillydally.

lōiele₂

fool.

lōkahi

unity, agreement, accord, unison, harmony; agreed, in unity.

lōkea₁

long European knife with a white handle.

lōkea₂

child of a nīʻaupiʻo, piʻo, or naha chief, whose mother was related to him but of a junior line.

lōkālia₁

coral plant (Russelia equisetiformis), a Mexican low shrubby plant, 30 to 120 cm high, with many leafless, green, quadrangular branches, used for low hedges and in rock gardens; it bears bright-red flowers resembling small firecrackers.

lōkālio

rosary. Less common than lei kolona.

lōkū

a game, perhaps like kilu (FS 163); a place for indoor games; evening entertainment (Ii 63–4).

lōliʻi

relaxed, at ease, without worry, carefree.

lōlā

to sun.

lōlōkuli

deafness, as from disease.

lōmilo

to spin with fingers; to twist, as thread in making rope or cord.

lōnū

to swell up, as with disease.

lōpiʻo

to bend over, as one nodding, sleeping.

lōpālauʻeka

worthless, shiftless squatter (contraction of lōpā pālauʻeka, worthless lōpā).

lōpā₁

one who farms under a tenant (hoa ʻāina), peasant, farmer; shiftless. see naunau₁ for an insulting epithet.

lōpā₂

an uncertain term in the phrase hoʻāo lōpā, marriage with a relative 24 generations removed.

lōʻohu

to buck, of a horse. Kauaʻi.

lō₁

a black insect, earwig (Dermaptera).

lō₂

front half of the skull.

lō₃

lord.

Lūhaupua

a wind associated with Ōlaʻa, Hawaiʻi. lit., scattering dew and flowers.

Lūkini₂

Russian.

Lūlaukō

name of a rain associated with Kauaʻi. lit., rain that scatters sugar-cane leaves.

Lūpua

wind name associated with Wainiha, Kauaʻi. lit., flower scattering.

lū hau

shaking down of dew or rain drops from tree boughs by a breeze; to fall thus; scattered dew, dewladen.

lū heleleʻi

to scatter, strew; to let hair hang loose and unbound.

lū lehua

to scatter lehua flowers, said poetically of rain.

lū pua

to scatter flowers, as by a flower girl at a wedding; to decorate graves with flowers.

lūauʻi

true parent, as contrasting with foster parent or aunt or uncle (makua).

lūheʻe

fishing for octopus with line and cowry lure; the octopus lure; to fish thus.

lūkea

a kind of taro, probably Kauaʻi name for haokea.

lūkini₁

perfume.

lūkini₃

lemon grass (Cymbopogon citratus), a grass with fragrant leaves, lemony odor, edges sharp; the leaves are dried and used for tea.

lūkē

to prod open, as bivalves.

lūlehua

a red tapa design.

lūlā

calm, windless, dead still; bored.

lūlō

lei of braided leaves or ferns. cf. (And).

lūlū hua

sower; to sow seeds.

lūlū lima

to shake hands; handshake.

lūlū₁

• to scatter, sow, as seeds;   • to fan, winnow;   • to shake, as dice or the hands, or as an earthquake.

lūlū₂

donation, offering, as in church; to make an offering.

lūlū₃

raffle, lottery.

lūmanawahua

stomach disorder accompanied by gas and looseness of the bowels; to suffer thus.

lūpō

a fish said to resemble the pāpiopio.

lūʻau₃

greenish meat in a turtle, considered a delicacy; so named because the color of its meat suggested the color of taro tops.

lūʻau₅

kind of soft porous stone, as used in the ground oven.

lū₁

• to scatter, throw, as ashes;   • to sow, broadcast;   • to shed, as a chicken its feathers or a tree its leaves;   • to push aside;   • to drip, as water;   • to shake;   • to cast off, as grief;   • to spend recklessly, squander,   • discard.

lū₂

seeds of the pua kala, prickly poppy.

lū₃

gunshot, so called because the pellets suggested the lū seeds.

lū₄

scalloped hat braid, as made of bamboo, sugar-cane stem, pandanus, or coconut.

Mahapili

name of twin stars (no data).

Mahikiokaluakanaka

stroke in lua fighting.

Mahiʻai₂

name of a star (no data).

Mahomeka

Mohammed; Mohammedan.

Maiakū

stars in the belt of Orion.

Maiao

name of a star used in navigation.

Maikonekia

Micronesia; Micronesian.

Maile₃

four sweet-scented sisters with human and plant forms: Mailehaʻiwale (brittle maile), Mailekaluhea (fragrant maile), Mailelauliʻi (small-leaved maile), Mailepākaha (Laie 454-455). They appear in numerous legends, in the most famous as guardians of Lāʻieikawai and her house thatched with bird feathers in legendary Paliuli. Fragrance had supernatural power and was associated with gods (HM 531), royalty, and religion, especially for worshipers of Laka, the hula goddess.

Maine

Maine.

Maka-ʻamoʻamo

name of a star or constellation in the Milky Way. lit., twinkling eye.

Makahaiaku

name of a star.

Makahaiwaʻa

name of a star. lit., eye following canoe.

Makahiki Hou

New Year.

Makaholowaʻa

name of a star, perhaps variant name for the North Star. lit., sailing-canoe eye.

Makaihuwaʻa

star name.

Makaikiolea

wind name, probably at Kauaʻi. lit., small eye of Lea.

Makaiwa₂

nine guiding stars.

Makakakeka

Madagascar.

Makakukeka

Massachusetts.

Makalaukoa

rain name.

Makaliʻi₂

Pleiades; Castor and Pollux. see Pleiades.

Makaliʻi₃

Hawaiian month name; the six summer months collectively.

Makaliʻi₄

a chief of Waimea, Kauai, father-in-law of Manokalanipō, and famous as an agriculturalist. A month and the summer season collectively were named for him. During the makahiki festivals food plants were symbolically dropped from his net (HM 366-367). Several times Kamapuaʻa killed all of Chief ʻOlopana₁'s men except Makaliʻi, who as the sole survivor took the news to ʻOlopana₁. Later, when Makaliʻi had become chief of Kauaʻi, he was frightened by Kamapuaʻa's long chant of his victories; he then chanted Kama's name songs, and so his life was spared, but he was sent away to live in the mountains. (FS 198-203, 230-239). In one account (For. 5:364-365), the gods Kāne and Kanaloa sent messengers up (i luna) to ask Makaliʻi whether Kaulu, a noisy kava drinker, was man or god. Later Makaliʻi gave his nets to Kaulu so that he might entangle and kill Haumea. His name is given to the Pleiades. By some he was considered a navigator.

Makanihānailoli

name of a gentle wind; it is said to permit loli to come out of their holes and feed. lit., wind that feeds sea slug.

Makao₁

star name (no data).

Makao₂

Macao, a city governed by Portugal, near Hong Kong.

Makaʻimoʻimo

name of a constellation in the Milky Way. lit., blinking eyes, twinkling eyes.

Makaʻiolani

name of a star. lit., eye of the royal hawk.

Makaʻunulau

name of a navigational star. lit., eyes drawing many.

Makaʻālohilohi

name of a star. lit., bright eye.

Makeaupeʻa

name of a star or constellation.

Makekonia

Macedonia.

Makela

Madeira.

Makelika

Madrid.

Makona

Mason.

Makuakaʻūmana

name of a star, said to be in the Kaulua constellation.

Makula

Saturn.

Makulu₂

Saturn.

Malae

Malaya; Malay.

Malae

Malaya.

Malaia₂

Malay, Malaya, Malaysia.

Malailua₁

name of a strong, blustering wind at Nuʻu-anu; to blow, of this wind.

Malaka₃

Malacca.

Malalei

stroke in lua fighting.

Malamaiku

unidentified star, pronunciation uncertain.

Malanai

name of a gentle breeze associated with Kōloa, Kauaʻi, Hāna, Maui (For. 5:97), and Kailua, Oʻahu.

Maleka₁

America.

Maleka₂

Mars.

Maliu₂

name of a star.

Maliʻo₂

a mythical woman.

Malukoʻi

name of a rain associated with Kahaluʻu, Oʻahu.

Malulani

name of a star. lit., celestial shade.

Mana Lani Kahikolo

Almighty Holy Trinity.

Manakekeka

Manchester.

Manakulia

Manchuria.

Manakū₂

name of a star.

Manawahine

name of a star, said to appear in the first night of the month Nana and to vanish after the night of Muku. lit., female power.

Manila

Manila hat, named for the city.

Manila

Manila.

Manini₉

Hawaiian name of a well-known Spanish immigrant, Francisco de Paula Marin, who knew Kamehameha for more than 25 years.

Manokalanipō

name of a chief of Kauaʻi... husband of Nae [or Na'e]kapuani (the daughter of Makaliʻi), and an ancestor of Kawelo. Kauaʻi is sometimes referred to poetically as Kauaʻi o Mano (RC 194), Kauaʻi o Manokalanipō (HM 141, 366) or Manō.

Maukele

place name at Puna, Hawaiʻi.

Maukuku

name of a star, perhaps related to Konamaukuku.

Mauliola

place name at Kīlauea Volcano, Hawaiʻi.

Mauli₃

twenty-ninth of the old month.

Mauna Hora

Mount Hor.

Mauna Huka

Mount Hood.

Mauna Kalemela

Mount Carmel.

Mauna Kea

the highest mountain on Hawaiʻi. lit., snow mountain.

Mauna Kupalali

Mount Souffrière.

Mauna Loa

the second highest mountain on Hawaiʻi; a mountain and village on Molokaʻi. lit., long mountain.

Mauna Pōhaku₁

Rocky Mountains.

Mauna Pōhaku₂

poetical name for Utah.

Maʻaʻa

name of a famous wind associated with Lahaina, Maui. also ʻA ʻa.

Maʻaʻa Kua Lapu

wind at Kahaluʻu, Hawaiʻi.

Maʻaʻa Paʻimalau

wind name. lit., Portuguese man-of-war Maʻaʻa.

Maʻiola

a god of healing... who was said to occupy certain trees, the wood of which counteracted the noxious effects of poison from the kālaipāhoa wood. lit., cured sickness.

ma o

because of, due to, by means of, through.

ma-

stative prefix indicating quality or state...

maao

kind of fish.

maea

• stinking, as of unwashed bodies;   • malodorous, as a swamp;   • offensive-smelling, as vomit.

maemae

damp, as clothes suitable for ironing. fade (Aniani 27)

maha lāʻau

clump or grove of trees.

maha mea

name of a deep-sea fish, said to be striped (no data).

maha pepe

broad-browed. lit., flat brow.

maha wela

a variety of fish (no data).

maha ʻulu

grove or clump of breadfruit trees.

maha ʻōʻō₁

a fish of the ʻahi type.

maha ʻōʻō₂

piece of sweet potato broken off by the ʻōʻō, digging stick. same as the more common kūʻōʻō.

mahae₁

to tear, split, separate.

mahae₂

a fish, said to belong to the lāʻīpala group.

mahae₃

net mesh, about 10 cm and above, between māhā and mālewa.

mahaha

a surgeonfish (Acanthuridae).

mahahaʻulaʻula

a variety of taro.

mahakea₁

once uncultivated land, as for bananas, sweet potato, taro; fallow land.

mahakea₂

a variety of taro.

mahakea₃

a variety of kava, usually called mākea.

mahalua

rude, disrespectful, saucy, overbearing; encroaching on the property or rights of others. lit., double temple.

mahamaha kea

white-jowled, as of a pig or dog.

mahamaha₁

gill plate.

mahamaha₃

to show or feel pleasure, love, affection; affectionate.

mahamaha₅

a variety of taro, sometimes qualified by keʻokeʻo, white.

mahamoe₁

attractive, sleek, as a plump animal; smooth.

mahamoe₂

an edible bivalve (no data).

mahana₁

warmth, heat; warm.

mahana₂

rest.

mahana₄

a class of chiefs.

mahaoʻo

mature in wisdom; wise; wise person. lit., mature temple.

maha₁

temple, side of the head.

maha₁₁

fishes.

maha₂

gill plate of a fish.

maha₃

wings of a flying fish.

maha₄

preputium, foreskin.

maha₅

lower portion of a canoe manu.

maha₆

• rest, repose, vacation;   • freedom from pain;   • at ease, comfort

maha₇

severed portion.

mahele hana

duty, work section, shift.

mahele kaua lewa

air force.

mahele koa

military unit, squadron.

mahele kālā

dividend.

mahele lāʻau

portion of medicine, dose.

mahele manawa

division of time, as of a fiscal period.

mahele waiwai hoʻopuka

share of profits, dividend.

mahele ʻōlelo

interpreter, translator; to translate, interpret.

mahele₂

to translate, interpret.

mahena

heap, pile, as of trash.

maheu₂

to dig and rake the earth, as for planting.

maheu₃

kind of porous stone, used to rub, scour, polish, and as an octopus lure.

mahi kō

sugar-cane plantation.

mahi pua

flower garden or patch; horticulture.

mahi waena

weed cultivator; to cultivate and weed. lit., weeding farm.

mahi waina

vineyard; grape raiser; to cultivate grapes.

mahikina lā

crack of dawn.

mahiki₁

• to jump, leap, hop, move up and down,   • vibrate;   • to spatter;   • to teeter, seesaw; a seesaw.   • to weigh, as on scales;

mahiki₂

• to cast out spirits, exorcise, especially with mahiki shrimps;   • to treat in turn, as troubles in hoʻoponopono family therapy.

mahiki₃

any kind of shrimp used ceremoniously.

mahiki₅

• to pry;   • peel off, as a scab

mahiki₇

a variety of taro.

mahiki₈

to appear (of the sun)

mahikū

to clear land for planting; plantation clearing not yet planted.

mahili₂

to strip away property.

mahina hapalua hope

waning of the moon. lit., last half of the moon.

mahina hapalua mua

waxing of the moon. lit., first half of the moon.

mahina hou₁

new moon, new month.

mahina hou₂

church offering on the first Sunday of the month, of Congregationalists.

mahina piha

full moon.

mahina poepoe

full moon. lit., round moon.

mahinakēhau

a variety of sweet potato.

mahinalua

a small creeping native fern (Grammitis tenella), with simple narrow fronds 5 cm long or longer, each bearing none to many round spots of spores.

mahina₂

crescent-shaped fishhook.

mahina₃

eye of the snail at the end of its horn.

mahina₄

farm, plantation, patch.

mahina₅

a variety of onion, similar to silver onion.

mahina₆

a variety of sweet potato.

mahiole

feather helmet, helmet; to wear a helmet.

mahiʻili

to plunder thoroughly; to take all, as a chief taking all the property of his subjects. lit., dig skin.

mahiʻopu₁

bold, rude.

mahiʻopu₂

to dig, as with a pickax.

mahi₁

to cultivate, farm; a farm, plantation, patch.

mahi₂

strong, energetic, as a worker.

mahola₁

to spread out; to smooth out, as a cloth to dry; to extend, expand. see hola₁ and ex. heʻe₁.

mahole

to bruise, skin, scrape, as a flesh wound; to injure as the feelings.

mahoʻa

thick, as a cloud. Maui.

mahu kai loloa

• same as ʻaʻau loa, long stalks;   • fig., long-suffering and patient, as of a chief who cared for his people (Malo text, chapter 18, section 54, 59, 63).

mahua

mockery, derision, spying (rarely used without hoʻo-).

mahuakala

disbelieving, cynical, skeptical, as of religion; irreligious, atheistic.

mahuka

to run away, flee, escape, elope; fugitive.

mahulukū

aerial roots of pandanus or other trees, as banyans.

mahumahu₂

silent, weak, brittle.

mahuʻe

to open, as a box; to take out, remove, as gear.

mahuʻi

to guess, suppose, surmise, expect, suspect, assume, imagine; clue.

mahuʻē

same as mahuka ē, to flee beforehand.

mahāha

soft, tender, weak; soft and mealy, as a baked potato.

mahū

weak, flat, as diluted kava or stale beer; insipid, as fresh poi kept too long in the icebox; quiet, peaceful, undisturbed.

mahūmahū

redup. of mahū, weak, flat... (commonly said of tasteless poi).

mai laila

from there, thence, whence.

maialile

quiet, calm, still.

maiapilo

a low, smooth shrub (Capparis sandwichiana) with vinelike branches, a member of the caper family, growing on some beaches and lava flows; leaves rounded-oblong; flowers white, pea-shaped, 5 cm long, with four petals surrounding a mass of long white stamens, open and fragrant only at night.

maiau

• neat and careful in work;   • skillful, ingenious, expert;   • correct, careful, as in speech;   • thorough, meticulous tidy, dainty.

maiele₂

eloquence, skill in speaking; eloquent; skilled in asking questions to puzzle and confuse.

maiewa₂

deep-sea fishing net.

maihoʻikau

(usually written as three words).

maihua

a variety of taro.

maihuli

presents made at the birth of a child.

maika₂

strengthening the body, as by athletics.

maika₃

tired, weary, lame.

maika₄

tasteless, insipid.

maiko

a surgeonfish (Acanthurus nigroris).

maila

the directional mai plus lā, there, then.

mailani

to extol, praise, treat as a chief or great favorite, indulge, spoil, favor.

maile haole

the myrtle (Myrtus communis), an aromatic shrub from the Mediterranean region and western Asia, a favorite garden plant in many countries, and formerly used in Rome for wreaths to crown the victor. The leaves look like those of maile and formerly were used by Hawaiian for leis like maile, the bark being stripped from the stems in the same way, with teeth holding one end.

maile haʻi wale

a variety of maile (f. myrtillifolia) with small, rounded leaves. lit., brittle maile.

maile hohono

a tropical American annual composite (Ageratum conyzoides and A. houstonianum), both a weed and an ornamental. It is a hairy, branching, weak-stemmed herb, with light-blue (rarely white or pink) florets borne in small tufted heads.

maile kaluhea

lit., sweet-smelling maile.

maile kā kahiki

lit., foreign vine maile.

maile kūhonua

a maile seedling about 8 cm or less high, with two or three leaves.

maile lau liʻi

a variety of maile (f. angusta), with narrow pointed leaves. lit., small-leaved maile.

maile lau nui

a variety of maile (f. sulcata), with large leaves. lit., big-leaved maile.

maile pilau

stink vine (Paederia foetida). lit., stinking maile.

maile pākaha

a variety of maile (f. rotundata), with blunt ovate leaves.

maile₂

maile sticks attached to the end of the ʻaukuʻu (pole) used for catching birds (the maile was gummed with lime, and birds perching on it were caught); name of a snare used in catching plovers around the leg; rod or wand used in the games of pūhenehene and ʻume; piece securing an ox's neck to the yoke.

maina hoʻopahu

explosive mine.

mainaina

anger, wrath.

maine

mine.

maipoinaiaʻu

forget-me-not.

maiʻa Kāne

an Oʻahu name for maiʻa Polapola.

maiʻa Nuhōlani

a variety of introduced banana cultivated by Hawaiians for many generations. The trunk is tall, green; the fruit yellow, edible raw or cooked. lit., New Holland (Australian) banana.

maiʻa Polapola

a species of banana (Musa troglodytarum, syn. M. fehi) recently introduced to Hawaiʻi, known in the South Pacific from Mangareva west to the Moluccas. It has a tall, black trunk and upright fruiting stalk bearing large fruits with reddish-orange skin, yellow flesh, edible when cooked, sometimes made into poi maiʻa. lit., Borabora [i.e., Tahitian] banana. (HP 177), (Neal 250).

maiʻa Puna

lit., Puna banana.

maiʻa Pākē

Chinese banana (Musa xnana, syn. M. cavendishii), a stocky tree to more than 2 m high, a native of southern China, brought in 1855 to Hawaiʻi from Tahiti.

maiʻa akua

Maui name for maiʻa Polapola. lit., god banana.

maiʻa aʻeaʻe

lit., prematurely gray banana.

maiʻa haikea

a Hawaiian variety of banana that bears yellow fruit, edible raw or cooked. lit., pale banana.

maiʻa haʻa

a Hawaiian variety of banana, with short trunk and leaves, but taller than maiʻa Pākē. The fruit is yellow, edible raw or cooked. lit., low banana.

maiʻa hilahila

lit., bashful banana.

maiʻa hinu puaʻa

lit., hog's-grease banana.

maiʻa hua lua

lit., bearing two bunches, twin banana.

maiʻa hua moa

lit., egg banana.

maiʻa hua nui

a variety of banana lit., big-fruited banana.

maiʻa hua waena

lit., central fruit banana.

maiʻa hākea

lit., whitish banana.

maiʻa hāpai

a Hawaiian variety of banana of medium height, the fruit maturing within the trunk. The fruits are small, ten or fewer in a bunch, yellow, sweet, edible raw. (HP 175), (Neal 250).

maiʻa hēʻī

Fēʻī is the Tahitian name.

maiʻa iho lena

a Hawaiian variety of banana, popular and common. The trunk is green, purple, and pink. Fruits are salmon-pink, edible raw cooked; one of the few bananas formerly permitted to women. lit., yellow-cored banana.

maiʻa ihu ʻū

a Hawaiian variety of banana, growing wild on Kauaʻi and Hawaiʻi, rarely cultivated. The fruit is yellow, edible only when cooked. lit., snub-nosed banana.

maiʻa kahiki

a variety of banana growing wild on Maui, rarely cultivated. The trunk is tall; the fruit long, skin yellow, flesh white and edible only when cooked. lit., foreign or Tahitian banana.

maiʻa kahiki hae

a Hawaiian variety of banana, similar to maiʻa kahiki, but having short trunk.

maiʻa kahiki mauki

a Hawaiian variety of banana with tall, green trunk. The fruits looks like maiʻa kahiki.

maiʻa koana

a Hawaiian seed-producing variety of banana.

maiʻa koaʻe

a Hawaiian variety of banana, beautifully striped leaves, trunk, and young fruit. Fruit is yellow and round; flesh yellow, edible cooked or raw. Also called maiʻa aʻeaʻe, maiʻa manini. lit., tropic bird banana.

maiʻa lahi

an ancient Hawaiian variety of banana. lit., delicate banana.

maiʻa lele

a common wild Hawaiian variety of banana of the uplands; trunk tall, yellowish-green; fruit yellow; flesh pink, edible raw or cooked, good for piepiele, eczema. Root of shoot used in medicine. The fruit was commonly offered to gods, the tree planted to shelter the altar. It was planted far from a dwelling house, for fear it would cause the occupants to lele (fly) elsewhere. lit., altar banana.

maiʻa liko

lit., bud banana.

maiʻa loha

an ancient Hawaiian variety of banana; trunk and leaf like maiʻa lele, fruit like maiʻa iho lena. lit., droopy banana.

maiʻa mana lua

lit., two-branched banana.

maiʻa manini

lit., manini (fish) banana.

maiʻa maoli

a Hawaiian variety of banana, growing in uplands and lowlands. It has a green trunk, large leaves. The fruit is long, waxy-yellow, and has yellow flesh, edible raw or cooked. lit., indigenous banana.

maiʻa moa

a Hawaiian variety of banana with a tall, yellowish-green trunk. The fruit is large, somewhat egg-shaped, and yellow; the flesh yellow, edible raw or cooked. lit., chicken banana.

maiʻa māhoe

a Hawaiian variety of banana, the stem bearing two bunches; fruit small, yellow, flesh light salmon and very palatable. lit., twin banana.

maiʻa mālei

a Hawaiian variety of banana; trunk green and pink, streaked with brown; fruit like maiʻa puhi.

maiʻa mālei ʻula

a Hawaiian variety of banana, common both cultivated and wild in the uplands. Fibers of the stalk are used for stringing flowers for leis with a coconut-leaf needle (mānai). Ripening fruit changes from maroon (ʻula) to green to yellow; the flesh is orange, edible only when cooked. also maiʻa mālai ʻula, maiʻa mānei ʻula, maiʻa mānai ʻula.

maiʻa noʻu

a Hawaiian variety of banana, usually cultivated; the trunk green, with pink and brown markings; fruit short, thick, yellow, the flesh cream-colored, edible raw or cooked. lit., short banana or big-mouthful banana.

maiʻa poni

lit., purple banana.

maiʻa puapua nui

a Hawaiian variety of banana. lit., big-tailed banana.

maiʻa puhi

an ancient Hawaiian variety of banana with green and brown trunk. The fruit is twisted when young; when ripe long, thick, yellow, the flesh yellow and edible only when cooked.

maiʻa pālua

lit., banana in pairs.

maiʻa pō lua

an ancient Hawaiian variety of banana.

maiʻa pōpō ʻulu

a Hawaiian variety of banana, with short, green trunk; one of two varieties not taboo to women in old times; the root of young plants used medicinally. Fruit is rounded and yellow, the flesh salmon-pink, edible raw but preferred baked. lit., breadfruit ball-like banana.

maiʻa wai mūhea

an ancient variety of Hawaiian banana. lit., insipid water banana.

maiʻa ʻanoʻano

a variety of banana with seeds. lit., seeded banana.

maiʻa ʻau lena

an ancient variety of banana. lit., yellow-stem banana.

maiʻa ʻaʻao

tall, wild bananas.

maiʻa ʻeka

a Hawaiian variety of banana; fruit with skin changing from red to green to yellow, edible when cooked. lit., discolored banana.

maiʻa ʻeke ʻula

an ancient Hawaiian variety of banana.

maiʻa ʻeleʻele

a Hawaiian variety of mountain banana with black trunk, the skin of which is used to make designs in mats. The fruit has orange flesh, which is edible when cooked. lit., black banana.

maiʻa ʻili pakapaka

a kind of rough-skinned banana.

maiʻa ʻoa

probably a distinct species of Hawaiian banana, according to W. T. Pope, being unique in producing fertile seeds. Trunk and leaves dull-green, tinted with bronze and purple; fruit inedible.

maiʻa ʻohe

an ancient Hawaiian variety of banana. lit., bamboo banana.

maiʻakaualau

a Hawaiian variety of banana. Fruit like that of maiʻa maoli, except that the young, dark-green fruit has light-green spots like raindrops; when ripe, yellow, waxy, with flesh light-yellow, good only when baked. lit., many rain drops banana.

maiʻao

nail of finger or toe; hoof of an animal; claw of a bird.

maiʻapōpōʻulupuapuanui

a Hawaiian variety of banana, resembling maiʻa iho lena, but the fruit broad-tipped. lit., bigtailed pōpō ʻulu banana.

maiʻapōpōʻuluʻililahi

lit., thin-skinned pōpō ʻulu. same as maiʻapōpōʻululahi.

mai₃

imminence-marking part. Almost, nearly, as though.

maka ala

faint path or trail; beginning of a path.

maka hakahaka

sunken eyes, as one long sick; deep pit or hollow; open space, as a clearing in a forest or clear space in a lava flow.

maka helei

eye with lid drawn down; ectropion.

maka hilahila

bashful eyes; bashful, timidly averting one's gaze.

maka hinu

bright face, cheerful look.

maka hou

beginning, new start.

maka hīʻō

eyes that dart in every direction, as if looking for mischief; a mischievously alluring look.

maka ihe

spear point.

maka ihu

bowsprit of a canoe; sharp point at the bow. lit., bow point.

maka iki

eye smaller than the other. lit., small eye.

maka ila

a senile pigmentation caused by sunburn of the eye, as found among Hawaiians; person with such an eye (such persons were said to be observant and critical). lit., birthmark eye.

maka kakaʻa

shifty eyes; to have such.

maka kanaka

many people, crowds of people.

maka keleawe

brazen look; horse eye of a whitish color, but with good vision. lit., brass eye.

maka kihi

to look out of the corner of the eyes; eye drawn back at the corner.

maka kila₁

a name given to the kala poni, sweet potato.

maka kila₂

pen; steel point, as of a weapon. lit., steel (Eng.) point.

maka kilo

observant, watchful eyes; to watch with great attention.

maka kiʻekiʻe

proud look (Sol. 6.17) ; haughty air.

maka kiʻi

flirtatious eyes; to lure or attract with the eyes.

maka koa

bold, unafraid, fierce. lit., brave eye.

maka koali

wild sweet potato found in Puna, Hawaiʻi; it may have been eaten in famine times; fed raw to pigs.

maka koʻa

landmark for a fishing ground. lit., fishing-ground point.

maka kui

needle or nail point; stitch. cf. maka o ke kui, eye of a needle.

maka lalau

cross-eyed, with eyes that seem to look inward. lit., roving eyes.

maka launa

friendly, having many friends and associates; sociable.

maka lehua

lehua flower petals. fig., attractive, as young girls.

maka lena₁

unfriendly, suspicious glance from under the eyelid; to glance thus. lit., drawn eye.

maka lena₂

yellow center of a flower, as of a daisy.

maka leʻa

twinkle-eyed, happy-eyed, mischievous.

maka lilio

eyes with epicanthic fold.

maka loa

very green, as a fruit; barely cooked, very raw.

maka lokomaikaʻi

bountiful eye (Sol. 22.9) ; one who looks kindly, charitably, and with good will. lit., good-hearted face.

maka lole

eyelid turned back, exposing the under side of the lid; an insulting term, as prisoners were tortured by tattooing the exposed eyelid. lit., turned eye.

maka lua₁

two-face, double-edged; two-fold, as a plaited mat; hypocritical.

maka lua₂

socket of the eyeball. fig., depths of the sea.

maka lua₃

fishing net with mesh wide enough to admit two fingers. lit., double mesh.

maka luhi

tired eyes, tired people, especially those who have been working hard on a community project.

maka mino

indented, non-protruding nipple, as is difficult for a baby to grasp.

maka moena

mesh in mat made by plaiting over one and under one; similar style in quilting; check plait. lit., mat mesh.

maka mua

• first, beginning, commencement, first time;   • first child of a family.   lit., first end.

maka nui

a variety of sweet potato.

maka nunui

big eyes. cf. kiʻi maka nunui under kiʻi₁.

maka ole

• eyetooth;   • point of a dog's tooth,   • fig., point of an ʻōʻō, digging stick; sprouting plant.

maka onaona

a sweet, lovely, or tender expression of face or eyes; also said of the eyes of the kole, a fish.

maka pala

soft, ripe; ready to burst, of a boil.

maka pela

dirty face; sticky, dirty eyes.

maka peni

pen point.

maka piapia

eyes sticky with viscous matter; watery eyes; insulting epithet for one who does not find what he is looking for.

maka puaʻa

breast nipple that stands out and is easy for a baby to take; pig nipple.

maka puhi

fishhook with two opposite barbs, as used for eels. lit., eel point.

maka pī

running eyes, bleary eyes.

maka pōniuniu

dizziness, faintness, lack of courage; obscure, dizzy, faint. lit., dizzy eye.

maka uhi₁

face tattooed solid, without patterning.

maka uhi₂

tattooed eyelid, as a humiliating sign of a warrior's defeat.

maka uhi₃

downcast eyes.

maka uli

black eye, as from a bruise.

maka wai

watery-eyed; eyes welling with tears; tender-eyed.

maka waiū

nipple of the breast.

maka weli

glaring, threatening eyes; to glare, glower.

maka ʻaha

sennit mesh; fairly fine mesh.

maka ʻaiau

envious eye; to eye with envy.

maka ʻaloʻalo

shifty-eyed. lit., dodging eye.

maka ʻeu

mischievous or roving eyes, naughty eyes.

maka ʻike

to see clearly and with keen powers of observation; to see more than most, especially to see supernatural things or ghosts not seen by others; to have the gift of second sight. lit., seeing eye.

maka ʻino

to look at with hatred; to lose affection for one; one who looks with hatred.

maka ʻoi

piercing, penetrating, sharp eyes.

maka ʻou

excelling eye, epithet for a councilor (kālaimoku), who had served under three rulers in three generations, and hence was regarded as full of wisdom.

maka ʻulaʻula

pinkeye; inflamed or bloodshot eye. lit., red eye.

maka ʻupena

net mesh.

maka ʻā

wide, staring eyes. lit., glowing eye.

maka ʻāhewa

walleyed; cross-eyed. lit., eyes that err.

maka-ʻupena

design, as carved on a tapa beater and used in quilting.

makaau

to look around; a roving eye.

makahai

hasty; active, as a child into everything.

makahani

to step lightly, touch lightly, to skim lightly.

makaha₁

inflamed or swollen eye.

makaha₂

pig disease.

makahehi

• admiration, to admire;   • desire for,   • wonder;   • amazement;   • attractive, entrancing;   • be entangled.

makahekili

hailstone. lit., thunder eye.

makahi

a kind of fish.

makahia

roving, unsteady, restless eyes; sleepless.

makahiapo

first-born child, oldest child. lit., firstborn person.

makahiki leleʻoi

leap year. lit., year jump ahead.

makahiki lā keu

leap year. lit., extra-day year.

makahiki₂

ancient festival beginning about the middle of October and lasting about four months, with sports and religious festivities and taboo on war; this is now replaced by Aloha Week.

makahinu

kind of hard stone.

makahune

fine mesh or weft, as of net or mat.

makahālili

a marine shell (Peasiella tantilla).

makaia

a rare term defined in (For. 5:165) as a swift runner; probably makaiʻa.

makaiauli

a limpet, Celluna exarata; flesh within ʻopihi shells.

makaihuwaʻa

phosphorescent light seen in water at night.

makaili

rocky patches where sweet potatoes or taro were cultivated (For. 6:165); soil consisting of coarse sand, cinders, or gravel.

makailo

young shoot, as for transplanting.

makaiwa₁

mother-of-pearl eyes, as in an image, especially of the god Lono.

makaiʻa₁

whitened pupil of a blind person's eye, cataract. lit., fish eye.

makaiʻa₂

a kind of stone, used for adzes and poi pounders.

makakai

sea-washed; spray.

makakiʻi

mask. lit., image face.

makakuʻikuʻi

to scowl, leer hatefully. lit., pounding eyes.

makakēhau

heart's desire. lit., dew eye.

makakī

to look at with hatred.

makakū

creative imagination of an artist.

makalae

beach, shore, coast near a point (lae).

makalahia₁

sleepless, awake.

makalapua

handsome, beautiful; to blossom forth.

makalau₁

carbuncle, boil.

makalau₂

cluster of spears.

makalau₃

many buds, as on a pussy willow. fig., many offspring.

makala₁

• to loosen, undo, untie,   • open a little,   • liberate or set at liberty;   • to remit, as a debt;   • to forgive;   • to free of defilement or uncleanness;   • to open or unfold, as a flower.

makala₂

a trail.

makaleha

to look about as in wonder or admiration, to glance.

makaleho

• covetous, lustful, wanton, lascivious;   • incontinence;   • to admire (Kel. 17), desire.   lit., cowrie eye, perhaps so called because the octopus clings to the cowrie.

makalele

name of a major illness (no data).

makalena

fine muslin cloth.

makalena puʻu

dotted swiss cloth. lit., lumped muslin.

makalika

marguerite, daisy.

makalike

uniform, as in color, style, clothes. lit., similar face.

makalio

taut, as a rope. lit., tight mesh.

makaliʻi₁

tiny, very small, fine, wee, small-meshed; narrow wefts.

makali₂

barely cooked, underdone.

makali₃

glowing, bright, as of fire.

makali₄

to bait a hook.

makaloa₁

a perennial sedge (Cyperus laevigatus), found in or near fresh or salt water in warm countries. From a horizontal, creeping stem rise long, slender unbranched stems, each topped by a small inflorescence. Formerly the plants were valued in Hawaiʻi for making the fine Niʻihau mats.

makaloa₂

general name for shellfish with long sharp edges (Thais intermedia, Drupa morum). see also ʻōlepe makaloa.

makaloa₃

a seaweed.

makaluku

to plan slaughter; to determine to destroy.

makalē

mackerel, canned sardines.

makamae

precious, of great value, highly prized, darling.

makamaka heluhelu

reader, as of a newspaper. lit., reading friend.

makamaka hānai

friend.

makamaka nui

one with a host of friends because of a genial, kindly, or hospitable nature; many friends.

makamaka₁

intimate friend with whom one is on terms of receiving and giving freely; pal, buddy; host. fig., anything very helpful, as education.

makamaka₃

buds, as forming on the corm of a taro.

makame

Madame.

makamua

lead horses or oxen in a team.

makana aloha

gift of friendship or love; freewill offering.

makana hele

parting gift. lit., going gift.

makanahele

wild, untamed; of the wilderness or forest. lit., forest person.

makanau

twinkling of eyes.

makanaʻā

plants growing on lava beds (probably a contraction or maka i nāʻaʻā, budding in the lava).

makani hau none

ice-cold mountain wind. lit., icy, annoying wind.

makani hele uluulu

hurricane.

makani holo ʻūhā

cold wind. lit., wind running [over] thighs.

makani kamaʻāina

usual wind of a place.

makani kaʻa wiliwili

tornado. lit., wind revolving twisting.

makani kū honua

sudden strong wind, gust. lit., wind arriving suddenly.

makani noho

spirit that possesses a medium and speaks through him. lit., spirit that takes possession.

makani pāhili

cyclone, hurricane.

makani pūkīkī

gust, strong wind.

makani uluulu

hurricane.

makani wili

whirlwind, twisting wind.

makani ʻoluʻolu

favorable or fair wind, refreshing breeze.

makani₂

ghost, spirit.

makani₃

call of sentinel, similar to "all's well".

makanunui

widely spaced, as grooves on a tapa beater.

makapaʻa

person blind in one eye, one-eyed; blind in one eye (it was considered bad luck to meet such a person); blind. lit., closed eye.

makapehu

• swollen;   • suffering from hunger;   • hungry person.

makapepe

fine-meshed, as a mat of medium weft, as 1.5 cm.

makapipipi₁

small eyes; pregnant women were discouraged from eating pipipi shellfish lest their children be born with small eyes, hence the name.

makapipipi₂

tiny, twinkling stars.

makapuʻu

variety of fish (no data). lit., bulging eyes, hill point.

makapāpipi

hollow worn in lava rock by the sea, where salt is collected, natural salt pan.

makapā₁

feeble, of light, as firelight in the daytime; shy, wild, as a bird.

makapā₂

stones that break in a fire, not desirable for the imu.

makapōuli

dizziness; dizzy, faint. lit., blacknight eyes.

makau

fishhook.

makau pāweo

small shell hook, as used for ʻōpelu fishing. lit., hook to turn away.

makauaua₂

to toughen by drying, as hide. lit., tough face.

makaua₁

hardhearted, unfriendly; troubled, vexed. lit., tough face.

makaua₂

to increase, grow larger.

makaua₃

a variety or taro.

makauliʻi₁

• economical, thrifty, provident;   • miserly, avaricious, eager to own.

makauliʻi₂

broad-backed, thick-shelled, of a turtle.

makawai

small outlets for water through banks of taro patches; small waterways; water sources.

makawalu₁

numerous, many, much, in great quantities (sometimes used with implication of chiefly mana). lit., eight eyes.

makawalu₂

type of fighting on plains covered with brush, with irregularly grouped warriors.

makawela₁

• glowing, burning;   • full of hate, fury, anger.   • fig. term for the despised kauā, outcasts.

makawela₂

type of stone from which weights for cowry octopus lures were made.

makaʻaha₁

hammock, swinging netted bed.

makaʻaha₂

skin eruption, itch.

makaʻala

alert, vigilant, watchful, wide awake; to attend to vigilantly.

makaʻalā

blind, but with eyes that look normal.

makaʻeleʻele

• chilled, frozen.   • fig., benumbing, intense, tense, as emotion;   • exhausting, wearisome, of labor.

makaʻina

guard; watchful.

makaʻopihi₁

opihi scooped out of its shell.

makaʻopihi₂

a fine pandanus mat, of 6 cm strands. lit., fine mesh.

makaʻu kiʻi

fear of images representing gods.

makaʻu kūhewa

sudden fear, panic.

makaʻu wale

coward, cowardice; afraid for no reason, easily frightened.

makaʻuo

gathering and tying, as pala fern for a heiau service,

makaʻupena

midriff, fat.

makaʻuwāwae₁

excrement lying exposed on the ground. lit., feared [by] feet.

makaʻuwāwae₂

anything on which one fears to tread.

makaʻāloa

a small reddish crab (Macrophthalmus telescopicus) found on mud flats. lit., long, bright eyes.

makaʻāwela

kind of soft, porous stone.

makaʻā₁

a fish (Malacanthus hoedtii).

makaʻā₂

a variety of sugar cane.

makaʻē

to look at with disfavor; to look askance.

makaʻīʻō

same as maka līʻō, wild eye.

makaʻōpio

a variety of taro.

makaʻūpē

grief.

maka₂

• beloved one, favorite;   • person.   cf. makamaka (very common), makana, pula, ʻōnohi. The pig god was affectionately called kuʻu maka (FS 199) by his grandmother, rather like "apple of my eye."

maka₃

• point,   • bud,   • protuberance;   • center of a flower, including usually both the stamens and pistils;   • nipple, teat;   • sharp edge or blade of an instrument;   • point of a fishhook;   • beginning, commencement;   • source;   • any new plant shoot coming up.   • fig., descendant.

maka₄

• mesh of a net,   • mesh in plaiting;   • stitch, in sewing.

maka₆

probably same as manu, canoe bow and stern pieces

maka₇

a seaweed. see alani, brown seaweeds, and below.

maka₈

varieties of sweet potato.

maka₉

recognition token.

make anu

to be very cold, chilled, freezing.

make kaka ola

death caused by capturing the spirit of a live person. lit., death strike [the] living.

make loa

to die (in contrast to make, which may mean "defeated, faint"). For a pre-Christian concept, see make₁.

make pilau

complete defeat, as in card games, to be completely defeated.

make pōloli

to die of starvation; faint with hunger.

make ulu niu

madness; to be mad. lit., death [from] whirling.

make wale

to die of itself, to die without cause, to die or wilt easily.

palaʻie₁

flexible, inconstant, changeable.

palaʻie₂

to play the game of loop and ball; the game itself: a flexible stick made of braided coconut leaflets with a loop at one end and a tapa ball on a string attached below the loop, the object being to catch the ball in the loop; this game was often played to a chant.

palaʻo₁

walrus.

palaʻā₁

the lace fern (Sphenomeris chinensis syn. chusana), a common wild fern in Hawaiʻi; also known in other parts of Polynesia and in Asia. Long, slender stems support smooth, ovate, pointed fronds, about 30 cm long, which are subdivided three times. Formerly a brown dye was extracted from the fronds. [(Neal 15): "The palaʻā is said to have been worn about the hips of Hiʻiaka, sister of Pele, the volcano goddess, and was the fern that she sent to trip and entangle the moʻo, or dragons, when she fought against them. In female ailments, the palaʻā was used to disperse disease, as Hiʻiaka used it to disperse her foes."]

palaʻā₂

a tapa of māmaki bark dyed brownish-red with palaʻā fern, of silky quality.

palaʻā₃

brownish-red.

palaʻā₄

type of stone, used for sinkers for octopus fishing.

palaʻīloli

discolored, as of pandanus fruit that darkens; to assume a softer, darker color.

pala₁₀

seaweeds or scum.

pala₁₁

parlor.

pala₂

• daub,   • smear, smudge, blot;   • dab of excreta   (cf. pala kūkae).

pala₃

underdone.

pala₄

coated, as the tongue.

pala₅

a form of gonorrhea.

pala₆

intoxicating drink made of watermelon juice.

pala₇

a native fern (Marattia douglasii), with a short trunk and large, long-stemmed, much divided, dark-green fronds. In time of famine, the thick, starchy, hoof-shaped bases of the frond stems, which cover the short trunk, were eaten after being baked in an imu over night. The mucilaginous water resulting from slicing and soaking the raw stems in water was used medicinally. Pieces of the fronds mixed with maile leis enhanced their fragrance. The fern was used also in heiau ceremonies.

pala₈

a variety of sweet potato.

pala₉

a variety of taro.

pale ahi

fire protection; fireproof.

pale hauhana

cloth protecting (pale) lashing of ʻiako, outrigger boom, to the canoe float

pale hope₁

after part of a canoe.

pale hope₂

bearers of the after part of a canoe.

pale hou

sweatband, in a hat; protection from perspiration.

pale huila

fender, as of a car. lit., wheel guard.

pale hāliʻi moena

coarse mat covering, as spread on the ground; insulting epithet for worthless, low person.

pale hānai

child's bib.

pale kai

breakwater; any wall or embankment that protects the land from the sea, levee; taffrail of a vessel; railing of a vessel. lit., sea guard.

pale kaua

war defense, shield (Kin. 15.1) , defensive armor.

pale kauoha

to break or ignore a law.

pale kaʻa

car bumper.

pale keiki

to deliver a child; midwife.

pale keʻehi

stirrup shield.

pale kiko

repeat mark in music.

pale kila

armor. lit., steel shield.

pale kolo

horse or ox next to wagon tongue.

pale kōhina

boundary left by cutting; division between taro patches.

pale kōkō

in music, vertical row of dots which forms a repeat mark. lit., prolonging bar.

pale lauʻī

ti-leaf covering; said also to be a prayer asking for release from a taboo that prevents one from leaving a taboo spot.

pale lima

a shield, worn on the arm; armguard.

pale lio

saddle blanket. lit., horse guard.

pale lua

double bar in musical notation.

pale lua ʻeleʻele

heavy black bar in musical notation.

pale lā

awning. lit., sun protection.

pale maka

veil that conceals the face, especially as worn by Arab women. mask, blindfold, goggles (HE).

pale makani

windshield.

pale moe

bed sheet.

pale mua₁

fore part of a canoe.

pale mua₂

bearers of the fore part of a canoe.

pale noho

seat cover.

pale nui ʻeleʻele

heavy black bar in musical notation.

pale poʻohiwi

shoulder pads or protection.

pale pukaaniani

window curtain, drapes.

pale pākaukau

table cloth.

pale pākaukau ʻaila

oilcloth.

pale pāpale

hat lining.

pale uhi

veil, covering.

pale uluna

pillowcase. lit., pillow guard.

pale umauma

breastplate, as in armor. lit., chest shield.

pale umauma unahi

brigandine (Ier. 46.4) , coat of mail. lit., scales chest shield.

pale wai

breakwater.

pale waiū

brassiere. lit., breast guard.

pale waʻa

persons who protect (pale) a log canoe being carried from the forest to the sea. Those in front were pale mua, those aft were pale hope.

pale wāwae

foot covering or protection; house slipper or sandals (also kāmaʻa pale wāwae); leather part of stirrups covering the rider's feet.

pale ʻumeke

dish towel. lit., bowl protection, so called because dish towels were tied about poi bowls to prevent dust or insects from falling in.

paleha

loose, slack, sagging; shaking, as a loose object.

palehui

brace or bar, in punctuation. lit., joining border.

paleka

carbuncle.

palekaiko

paradise.

palekalapa

paragraph.

palekama

balsam.

palekana₁

safe, saved, rescued; convalescent; to ward off, brush aside, rescue, protect; to recover from illness; defense, savior, safety, security. (pale₁ + -kana, nominalizer).

paleki

brake.

palekoki

petticoat, skirt.

palekona

falcon.

palela₁

lazy, indolent, slow-moving; to saunter along as though bored.

palelei

head covering of tapa wrapped over the head with the ends hanging down in front.

palelona

furlong, in surveying.

palemaʻi

underdrawers; sometimes used for undershirt. lit., genital protection.

palemaʻi o lalo

underdrawers.

palemaʻi o luna

undershirt.

palemo₁

• to sink, be sunk,   • slip away, vanish;   • drowned.

palemo₂

promiscuous.

palemo₃

young of uhu, a fish.

palena ʻole

boundless, without limit, vast.

palenaʻāina

land boundary.

palena₁

• boundary, border,   • limit,   • margin,   • juncture,   • separation,   • partitioning;   • terms of a fraction.

palepale₁

redup of:   • pale₁ to ward off, thrust aside, parry...; to parry, as in boxing.   • pale₂ to deliver, as a child...;   • pale₃ to cover, overlay, line; to form a barrier...;

palepiwa

all species of eucalyptus trees. lit., prevent fever, so called because the leaves were used as fever medicine, and in the pūloʻuloʻu steam bath.

palewāwae₁

the joy weed (Alternanthera amoena), a small herb front Brazil, used as a low border for paths and flower beds. It has red, branching stems and variegated red, green, and yellow, small oval leaves.

palewāwae₂

small, fan-shaped brown seaweeds (two species of Padina [P. commersonii, light-brown, and P. vickersiae, larger, darker-brown]), common on the reef, each fan more or less split and curled. Not eaten.

paleʻaʻahu

underclothes, underwear.

paleʻili o lalo

underdrawers.

paleʻili o luna

undershirt.

paleʻōpua

to pardon offenses, as by a priest's offering, in pagan times only. lit., ward off billowy clouds.

pale₁

• to ward off, warding off, thrust aside, parry, fend off, repulse, resist,   • bar, barrier, shield, guard;   • defend, defense,   • protect; protection,   • prevent,   • to ignore a command or law,   • make void, nullify, break, avoid, not adhere to;   • curtain (Puk. 26.4) ; partition,   • bib,   • bar, railing, bulwark,   • shield, sheath,   • outer garment.   (preceded by both ka and ke).

pale₂

to deliver, as a child.

pale₃

• lining, as of a garment;   • leaf lining of a ground oven;   • flap of a malo;   • to cover, overlay, line;   • to form a barrier.

pale₄

gunwale lashed to a canoe.

pale₅

an interval of time in music, a bar in music which separates the staff into measures. see below.

pale₆

presser foot on a sewing machine.

pale₇

apron, bib.

pale₈

barley (Hordeum spp.), bran.

pale₉

• division,   • canto of a song,   • scene of a play,   • division of song in a hula

pali kuʻi

notched, toothed cliff; joined succession of cliffs.

pali kāmoe

low hillock, terrace.

pali kū

vertical cliff.

pali loa

distant or tall cliff. fig., distant, aloof, disdainful; aristocratic, regal.

palika₁

carbuncle.

palikea

a sweet potato.

palila

an endangered gray, yellow, and white Hawaiian honey creeper (Psittirostra bailleui, P. kona); endemic to the island of Hawaiʻi. Its bill is especially suited for opening māmane tree pods. Its only home is on Mauna Kea, Hawaiʻi.

palili

small weak taro shoot (preceded by ke).

palima

primer; to study a primer.

palipali

precipitous, full of cliffs and steep hills.

palipaʻa

cliff.

palipaʻa maoli

base of a cliff.

paloke

broken.

palola

parole.

palolo

glib-tongued, garrulous; gossiping, as maliciously.

palolo hua

glib in speech, garrulous.

palomeka

barometer.

palo₁

revelation, as from the gods. see (For. 6:4).

palo₂

parlor.

palu lāʻī

ti-leaf relish, a term of derision for the people of Hawai'i, because at a feast for Kamehameha I on O'ahu there was not enough food, and the late-comers were said to have had to lick the ti-leaf food wrappings.

paluhē

reduced to pulp, as palu; cooked to a pulp; cooked to the point of failing apart, as meat.

palula

cooked sweet-potato leaves.

palule

commoner.

palunu₁

a creeping plant (no data).

palunu₂

a dull thud; to thud.

paluʻai

vegetable food. Kauaʻi.

palu₁

to lick, lap.

palu₂

a relish made of head or stomach of fish, with kukui relish, garlic, chili peppers; fish bait made of fish head or stomach, also used for chumming.

palō₁

to feign ignorance.

palō₂

to act the goody-goody.

palū

flu, influenza.

palūpalū

a kind of yellow tapa.

pamomoa

a fish (no data).

pana iʻa

fishing spear shot by a bow; to shoot fish thus.

pana kai₁

to flip, as salt water with finger or fingers during a purification ceremony.

pana kai₂

to heel over, ts a vessel.

pana poʻo

to tap or snap the head (it was rude or provocative to tap another's head, as the head was sacred).

pana pua

to shoot with bow and arrow; archer, archery.

pana ʻiole

to shoot rats or mice with bow and arrow, an ancient sport; bow and arrow.

panaiki

diagonal.

panakalupa

bankrupt.

panaleʻa

dexterous, gleeful, quick, as in danger.

panalāʻau

colony, dependency, territory, province (Ezera 4.15) ; colonist. In early times Hāna, Maui, was a panalāʻau (dependency) of Hawaiʻi.

pananā

weak, tottering; such a person.

panapana

to strike gently, as the butt of a coconut midrib used as a pole for catching crab.

panapana nīʻau

to shoot a coconut leaf midrib (the leaf was bent like a bow and released so that it sprang away).

panapanapuhi

a kind of shellfish.

panau

• to move up and down as a seesaw;   • to flip along, as a lobster;   • restless, uneasy, always on the move;   • to gad about;   • pulsating motion of male organ;   • a vulgar or contemptuous gesture signifying the latter, made with the fist of one hand, while the other hand grasps the elbow joint, jerking the forearm and clenched fist upwards.

pana₁

• to shoot, as marbles, arrows, bow;   • bow and arrows;   • to snap, as with fingers and thumb to punish a child;   • to flip.

pana₂

heartbeat, pulse; beat in music; to beat time, pulsate, throb.

pana₃

celebrated, noted, or legendary place; to be such.

pana₄

pan.

pana₅

bung. (stopper for the opening in a cask).

panehū

quick.

paneka

panther.

panekai

to move in, of the tide.

panekalupa

bankrupt.

panena

answer.

panepane

to retort, talk back.

panepoʻo

• pinnacle, summit;   • topmost,   • most important   (preceded by ke). lit., hind part [of] head.

paneʻehā

to drag, haul.

paneʻeʻūpiki

clamp feed, of sewing machine.

paneʻe₁

to move along, bring, push along a little; pushed forward.

paneʻe₂

• delayed, postponed; delay, postponement;   • to do in installments, as to serialize a novel in a newspaper.

paneʻe₃

old, worn-out. Kauaʻi.

pane₂

(preceded by ke).   • hind part of the head;   • top or summit, as of a mountain

pane₃

to pull. Kauaʻi.

pani haka

lit., closing breach.

pani hakahaka

to substitute, fill a vacancy, replace; substitute, replacement, successor, deputy, proxy.

pani kai

levee, dike, sea wall or any protection against the sea.

pani pūpū

a cat's-eye, operculum, valve or round substance that closes a shell. lit., shell closure.

pani wai

dam, sluice, levee, dike.

pani ʻōmole

bottle stopper, cork.

paniana

banyan (Ficus spp.)

paniinoa

pronoun. lit., name substitute.

paniinoa huli ʻauikumu

reflexive pronoun (a concept not used in present-day Hawaiian grammars). lit., pronoun reverting to the subject case.

paniinoa kuhi laulā

indefinite pronoun (a rarely used concept), lit., pronoun pointing widely.

paniinoa kuhikuhi

lit., directing pronoun.

paniinoa kālele manaʻo

emphatic pronoun (a rarely used concept). lit., pronoun that supports thought.

paniinoa ninaninau

interrogative pronoun.

paniinoa pelu hope

reflexive pronoun. lit., pronoun folded back.

paniinoa pilikino

personal pronoun.

paniki

coloring matter, as for tapa.

panikū₁

• to slam shut, as a door, to close abruptly, as in slamming a door in one's face;   • to foreclose, as a mortgage.

panikū₂

to pound, break.

panina₁

• end, closing, closure, very last, conclusion, finish, cessation,   • breaking off or cutting short;   • definitive,   • classic.

panina₂

plump cheeks.

paninikū

the name of a seaweed.

paniola

late var. of paniolo, cowboy.

panipani₂

coition, or to practice such (vulgar).

panipani₃

small outrigger canoe.

panipipi

cat's-eye. lit., shell closure.

panipū

plug or wad of a gun.

paniʻo

smooth.

paniʻole₁

a variety of sweet potato.

paniʻole₂

a variety of taro.

pani₂

substitute, replace, represent, fill a breach or vacancy; substitute, vice- (sometimes preceded by ke).

pani₃

odd-shaped pandanus key that fits, like a keystone at the bottom of a pandanus cluster; when this is knocked out, the others fall easily.

pani₄

the bottom of a coconut when cracked off by blows around the base of the nut; it fits like a lid (pani).

pani₅

disease with severe pain at the solar plexus and choking.

pani₆

pan.

pani₇

final bit of food closing a period of treatment by a medical practitioner, commonly but not always sea food; final gift in a hoʻokupu ceremony.

pano

dark, as clouds; obscure, black, shiny-black, deep blue-black. fig., unapproachable as the unknown, said of very high chiefs believed to be of divine descent.

pano paʻu

glossy, glistening black, sooty-black; black streaks in grain of wood.

panoa

barren, arid, desert, dry, hot, parched.

panoanoa

full of holes, cracked.

panohiʻiaka

a bird (no data).

panonono

full of holes, cracks; cracked.

panopaʻū

somewhat wet.

panunukuahiwi

a native member of the gourd family (Sicyos cucumerinus), a more or less climbing herb with variable leaves, which range from entire and rounded to many-lobed. The fruit is narrow, about 2.5 cm long, grooved, one-seeded.

pao ahi

to stoke a fire; stoker. lit., fire inserter.

paoa₁

• strongly odoriferous;   • a strong odor, whether pleasant or unpleasant.

paoa₂

unlucky, unsuccessful, as in fishing or sex; bad luck. [But cf. iwi paoa under paoa₁.]

paoa₃

to have a taste or desire for (usually used with waha, mouth).

paoka

powder.

paokeʻe

to slander, betray, defame; slanderer, traitor.

paokoke

to betray one's relatives or those close (koke) to one.

paomoni

to contend with, make war on,

paona kaulike

balance, scales. lit., equally placed poundage.

paona keiki

baby scales.

paona₁

pound, balance, scales, weight.

pao₁

(preceded by ke).   • to scoop out, dub out, as a log for a canoe; chisel out, gouge; digging, scooping, etc.   • or as of the action of the sea on the coast; undermine, erode,   • to peck,   • bore.   • fig., blunt, cruel, harsh in speech; to rebuke;

pao₂

• to insert, stick in, as wood into a fire;   • to stoke, as coal into a furnace.

pao₃

cave, pit, cavern.

pao₄

arch of a bridge, bridge.

papa aliʻi

one of the chiefly class; chiefly class.

papa hana₁

work method, plan, stratagem, policy, program, agenda, project; workbench.

papa hana₂

ceremony for the gods, as in offering kava.

papa hehi

footboard, used for dancing; treadle. lit., board to step on.

papa helu

table, list, enumeration, scoreboard, statistics.

papa holahola kānāwai laʻa

universally sacred decree.

papa hole

smooth, planed lumber; grooved board for making ribbed tapa.

papa holoi

washboard.

papa honua

foundation of the earth.

papa hoʻoholo

slide plate on a sewing machine.

papa hoʻolaha

billboard.

papa hulei

seesaw, teeter.

papa huli honua

experts who determined land boundaries.

papa huluhulu

rough lumber.

papa hului₁

pile, as of winnings, objects.

papa hīmeni

choir, choral group.

papa hōlua

sled composed of two narrow runners, 2 to 6 m long, as used for the hōlua sport.

papa hōʻike

program, timetable, index, schedule, sign, bulletin board, sign board.

papa inoa

list or catalogue of names, register.

papa ipu

shelf for food containers.

papa kahuna

priestly class.

papa kaua

division of an army; group of men armed with pololū, spears, surrounding the king.

papa kea₁

white stratum, sand beach.

papa keʻehina

floor. lit., trampled stratum.

papa koa₁

board of wood of koa, a tree.

papa koa₂

group or band (Oih. 10.1) of soldiers; rank or company of an army.

papa kuhikuhi

table of contents, index, schedule, directory, program, timetable. lit., pointing-out stratum.

papa kuhikuhi manawa

schedule, as of ship arrivals and departures.

papa kuhikuhi mea ʻai

menu, bill of fare.

papa kuʻi

jawbone, lower plate.

papa kuʻi ʻai

poi-pounding board.

papa kākau

slate, writing board. chalkboard (HE)

papa kōlea

plover flats.

papa kōnane

stone on which the checkerlike game kōnane was played.

papa lalo

lower floor of a house, valley bottom, lower stratum.

papa lani

heavenly stratum, heaven and all the spiritual powers; upper regions of the air, upper heavens, firmament.

papa lele kawa

springboard for diving.

papa lewalewa

net used in deep water with the melomelo club.

papa like

of the same species, class, rank.

papa limahana

labor board.

papa loio

legal profession.

papa lua hā

two by four lumber.

papa lua₁

second floor or story

papa lua₂

second class.

papa lāʻau

board, plank, any large wooden platter, lumber.

papa lāʻau mānoanoa

plank. lit., wide wooden board.

papa manamana

grate, grating. lit., branching flat surface.

papa moe

horizontal stratum. fig., sick.

papa mānoanoa

plank.

papa niho

row of teeth, set of teeth; jaw, bridge for false teeth.

papa noho

bench.

papa palaoa

breadboard; cake (Ier. 7.18) ; pancake, wafer (rare).

papa palapala

writing desk, board, or flat surface where writing is done.

papa paʻakai

• salt flat.   • fig., sour disposition.

papa paʻi

printing press.

papa pelena

a flat cake. (Bib.)

papa poʻo

the leading division, class, rank, especially the first company of warriors sent out to plunder in order to provoke war. lit., head rank.

papa puʻukani

choir, choral group.

papa pāʻina

table for eating.

papa pōhaku₁

row or tier of stones.

papa pōhaku₂

slate, stone tablet.

papa pōhaku₃

stone table, stone flat, or stone surface, as for pounding.

papa uhi waʻa

board used to cover space forward of the forward outrigger boom.

papa waena

middle floor or story; middle class or layer.

papa waha nui

large baglike net used for akule fish.

papa wili ʻai

mixing board, food trough, board for kneading poi, kneading trough.

papa wili₁

mixing board or tray.

papa ʻaina

• dining table;   • eating mat, as laid on the floor;   • meal, dinner, mess.

papa ʻiliʻili

arrangement of pebbles in the form of a man used for instruction by a kahuna hāhā.

papa ʻohi

draft board, selection board.

papahele o luna

upper floor, upstairs.

papahola₁

face of a clock or watch.

papahola₂

level pavement beside a heiau.

papahola₃

priests who prohibited noise during taboo.

papahola₄

division of spoils among the victors.

papaholo

lattice.

papahu

to push.

papahāpuʻu

a fish, possibly a hāpuʻu (no data).

papaioa

long reef.

papaiāulu

to blow, rise, as a breeze.

papaiō

sacrifice; propitiatory offering or food offering.

papakema

baptism.

papakōnane

a mat design.

papakū₁

foundation or surface, as of the earth; floor, as of ocean; bed, as of a stream; bottom.

papakū₂

upright (this is said in answer to the question "pehea ʻoe?" and means "I'm fine").

papakū₃

a disease with severe constipation (AP) or accompanied by vomiting, back pains, belching, red eyes (Ka Leo a ka Lahui, Feb. 7, 1893).

papalaulele

small net, as for fishing in shallow water.

papalena

fending off, warding off, pushing aside.

papali

small cliff or slope, as along a ravine.

papamū₁

• stone on which the checkerlike game, kōnane, was played;   • checkerboard;   • plaid;   • checkered, as gingham.

papamū₂

a variety of taro.

papani₁

interception, shutting off, as from view; to block.

papapa

young stage of nenue, rudder fish.

papapau

redup. of papau, deeply engaged... finished... united...; everyone.

papapueo

a variety of taro, grown on Maui; petioles deep-pink at base, grading to light-pink and green with white edge; corm used for poi. lit., owl flat.

papapū₁

row or tier of guns, class of guns.

papapū₂

completely covered, as rocks by shellfish.

papau

• deeply engaged, as in an activity; engrossed, absorbed,   • finished;   • united; all, all together.

papau make

to die, of many; complete annihilation; cemetery (rare).

papaʻaiana

ironing board.

papaʻauwae

lower jaw.

papaʻa₁

• tight, secure, especially of a walled stronghold;   • to hold back.

papaʻiole

irregularly cut, of hair, said to be named for an irregular haircut given to Pikoiakaʻalalā (a demigod born of a crow father, who sometimes appeared as a rat) by his rat sisters, and short for paʻipaʻi ʻiole, rat haircut.

papaʻohe

young of akule, a fish.

papaʻula

a mat motif consisting of a row of opposing triangles with their apices touching.

papaʻunu

to fill up, cram.

papa₂

native-born, especially for several generations (see noho papa₂); offspring of the mating of an individual of piʻo, naha, or nīʻaupiʻo rank, with one of kaukaualiʻi rank; the lowest ranking aristocrat.

papa₃

set close together, thick together, as of growing plants; in unison, all together.

papa₅

a variety of kava. The name may be qualified by the colors ʻeleʻele, kea.

papa₆

middle portion of a fishing net, bag net.

papa₈

stone used as sinker for lūheʻe, octopus lure.

papa₉

wafer.

papekema

to baptize, baptismal; baptism. also papakema.

papekiko₁

to baptize; baptismal.

papulo

papyrus, rush.

papuna

baboon.

papākea

white spray, as of sea; to rise in spray; white caps.

papākolea

to break, of waves.

papālina

cheek, cheeks.

papā₁

• to blow, as the wind;   • to sound, echo;   • to shine, as sun or moon.

pau ahi

destruction by fire, burned; to put out a fire.

pau hananuʻu

plump, wadding.

pau kaua

armistice, truce.

pau lehia

expert; to be such.

pau loa

all, everything, to have all.

pau nui

all (followed by qualifying verb or noun).

pau pono

completely finished, terminated.

pau pāʻele

very black, dirty.

pau pū

• all together, including all;   • completely demolished, etc.

pau ā pau

everyone, all the people (as with the idea of participating in a previously stated act).

pau ʻeka

very dirty.

pau ʻole

endless, unceasing, always.

pau ʻono

very delicious, etc.

pauaho

out of breath, breathless, gasping for breath, panting, worn out. fig., discouraged, faint-hearted, despairing, desperate, weary, exhausted; to die.

paua₂

a rare crab.

paua₃

a variety of taro, extinct in Kona and Kāʻū, Hawaiʻi; petiole dark-green, becoming whitish above; corm white, long-keeping.

pauka kī pū

gun powder.

paukaʻa

all taken, consumed.

pauka₁

powder; to powder.

paukeʻe

curved. fig., dishonest, deceitful.

paukikī

fast, speedily; speed; to do with great speed.

paukū kino

body trunk, torso.

paukū manawa

portion of time, era.

paukū pālahalaha lahilahi

slab. lit., thin flat portion.

paukū ʻolokaʻa

cylinder. lit., revolving section.

paukū₁

• section, link, piece; jointed, linked.   • stanza, verse, as in the Bible; canto; article, as of law; paragraph;   • to section off, cut in sections, slice in sections;   • to make a lei with sections of different colors, as feathers, or roses and begonias;   • land section smaller than a moʻo (Thrum, p. 68);   • a unit of measurement;   • a squad (military; see mokuna);

paukū₂

root of the kāʻeʻe vine, used medicinally.

paula

powder.

paulehia

• to be overwhelmed (Kel. 107);   • completely, totally immersed, absorbed.

paulele

faith, confidence, trust; to have faith, confidence, to believe implicitly; to lean against, rely on.

paulinalina

to gird the waist tightly, to stretch, make taut.

paulāʻī

to walk over the sea or fire, as a god.

pauma wai

water pump.

paumaunoʻonoʻo

keepsake, memento. lit., all continuing thoughts.

pauma₆

pump; to pump.

paumākō

grief, mourning, lamentation; to weep loudly.

paumāʻele

dirty, defiled, sordid, unclean.

pauneʻineʻi

excited; to cry out, as in excitement.

paunihinihi

small, worthless taro shoots.

pauoa

a fern (Dryopteris squamigera) to 90 cm or more high, the stem clothed with tan scales, the frond triangular to ovate and two or three times pinnate.

pauāʻālina

heavy, burdensome.

pauʻakaʻaka₃

neck in a house rafter.

pauʻaka₁

grotesque, odd.

pauʻaka₂

damaging; unreliable, deceitful; to disturb.

pauʻaka₃

of no use, fruitless, unproductive, without reward or profit, discouraging.

pauʻaka₄

quail, so called because of its song.

pauʻali

crooked, perverse.

pauʻiole

a variety of taro.

pau₂

said to be (used in special idioms, unfavorably).

pawa₁

the darkness just before dawn, predawn.

pawa₂

smooth, fat and sleek.

pawa₃

custom.

paūhu

small, narrow-chested.

paʻa ipu kuha

bearer of the chief's spittoon.

paʻa kāhili

bearer of the royal feather standard; to carry a kāhili.

paʻa kāmaʻa

pair of shoes.

paʻa lau

those holding a lau, dragnet; to hold the lau.

paʻa lima

held in the hand; handle.

paʻa lio

team of horses.

paʻa luhi

overcome with weariness.

paʻa male

married couple.

paʻa male hou

bridal couple.

paʻa manaʻo

firm in one's memory; memorized.

paʻa mau noʻonoʻo

a keepsake, memento; to keep a thought of something. lit., hold continued thinking.

paʻa mau₁

regular, customary, usual. lit., continually fixed.

paʻa moʻolelo

versed in lore, legends, history, tradition; documented in such; one so versed.

paʻa mua

ready-made, as clothes.

paʻa poepoe

globe, circular solid, sphere. lit., round solid.

paʻa uma

a type of hand wrestling in which each player tried to push his opponent's hand back to his chest (uma); to wrestle thus.

paʻa walu

octagon.

paʻa ʻahu

a carrier of mats (Kep. 129), a heap of mats.

paʻa ʻāina

landholder; to hold land.

paʻahana₁

• industrious, busy, hard-working;   • workman, laborer, worker, industry.

paʻahana₂

implement, tool, utensil, furnishings.

paʻahao₁

prisoner, convict; to be imprisoned.

paʻahao₂

proceeds (as pigs, sweet potatoes or taro) paid to holders of land on which tenants worked; penalty for failure to pay was imprisonment.

paʻahihi

spread here and there.

paʻahiku

heptagon.

paʻailalo

the earth below.

paʻailuna

heavens above.

paʻakai hao

copperas. [iron (II) sulfate]. Ka Hae Hawaii, May 13, 1857

paʻakai holoi

lye (RSV), nitre (KJV) lit., washing salt.

paʻakai hoʻohanuhanu

smelling salts.

paʻakai inu

epsom salts. lit., drinking salt.

paʻakai mikomiko

a variety of taro.

paʻakai muʻemuʻe

alum. lit., bitter salt.

paʻakaiheleleʻi

a fish, said to be one of the Hemiramphidae. lit., scattered salt.

paʻakaihū

effervescent solution.

paʻakai₂

a variety of taro, usually grown in the uplands, the plant short and stocky; petioles dark-green, edged with red; corm flesh white, used chiefly for poi.

paʻakea

• limestone,   • coral beds, as found on the leeward sides of the islands.   lit., white hardness.

paʻakō

dry lowland plain.

paʻakūkū

to jell, set firmly, congeal; to clot, as blood; to stiffen, as hard poi; avaricious.

paʻalalo

• attendants of a chief;   • bridal attendants.

paʻalima

pentagon.

paʻaloha

keepsake, memento, souvenir.

paʻalole

suit of clothes. also paʻalole komo.

paʻalole makalike

uniform, as of military.

paʻalua₁

a variety of banana.

paʻalua₂

deuce.

paʻalula

• formal,   • according to rule,   • decorous;   • to observe rules, as of etiquette; one who observes such rules.

paʻalā₁

smooth, water-worn ʻalā rock.

paʻamua₁

gaseous condition of the bowels, to have such.

paʻamua₂

dam, windbreak.

paʻamua₃

steadfast in prayer for the welfare of the family, one so steadfast.

paʻanaʻau

memorized, remembered. lit., fixed intestines.

paʻaoloulu

young loulu palm leaves, as used in making hats.

paʻaono

hexagon.

paʻapaʻakai

salt-encrusted.

paʻapaʻani

playful, to play frequently.

paʻapaʻanā₁

to ease, as pain; to soothe; to entertain, amuse.

paʻapaʻanā₂

to hurry, hasten.

paʻapaʻaʻina₁

brittle, crisp, crackling; to snap, crackle.

paʻapaʻaʻina₂

a variety of taro.

paʻapaʻaʻina₃

a variety of sweet potato.

paʻapaʻa₁

dispute, argument, quarrel.

paʻapaʻa₃

a fish (Dascyllus albisella).

paʻapaʻa₄

a kind of sugar cane.

paʻapū₁

• covered with, solid with, teeming with,   • crowded, congested, as people, fog, or clouds;   • dense, impervious, nonporous;   • stifling, stuffy, as a room;   • thick or coarse, of banana fruit peeling (HP 173).

paʻaua

hard physical labor or drudgery; a drudge (perhaps contraction of paʻa, hold, and uaua, tough); to work hard.

paʻauhau

a variety of sweet potato.

paʻawaha

gag; to gag the mouth. lit., make the mouth solid.

paʻawela₁

a burned area; a scar from burning; to burn.

paʻawela₂

probably a wrasse fish.

paʻaʻili

a solid, usually with number of sides following, as paʻaʻili hā. lit., surface solid.

paʻaʻili hā

four-sided solid (this term was said to be used formerly for a pyramid).

paʻaʻili hā like

paʻaʻili [a solid, usually with number of sides following] with equal sides.

paʻaʻili iwakālua

a twenty-sided solid.

paʻaʻili kaulike hiō

oblique parallelepiped. lit., solid leaning similarly.

paʻaʻili kūpono

cube or rectangular parallelepiped. lit., straight solid.

paʻaʻili ono

six-sided solid, cube; cubic.

paʻaʻili ono like

cube. lit., equal six solid.

paʻaʻiliʻumi kumamālua

a twelve-sided solid.

paʻaʻā₁

fiber, as of sugar-cane stalk or of banana sheath (probably a contraction of paʻa, solid, and ʻaʻa, fiber).

paʻa₂

pair, couple; couplet.

paʻa₃

suit of clothes.

paʻa₄

stratum, foundation, especially paʻailalo, earth, and paʻailuna, heavens.

paʻa₅

extremity, border.

paʻa₆

type of sweet potato, pronunciation not certain.

paʻea

a variety of taro.

paʻeke

pocket.

paʻewa

• crooked, misshapen,   • bent,   • uneven, odd,   • imperfect;   • wrong, incorrect; error, mistake.

paʻi aʻa

root system, rootlets, small branches.

paʻi hakahaka

printing, as contrasted with handwriting (kākau); form, questionnaire; blank, as on a questionnaire. lit., space printing.

paʻi hale

to thatch or line a house.

paʻi hewa

misprint, typographical error; to make such an error. lit., mistaken printing.

paʻi hua piku

cake of figs.

paʻi hua waina

cluster of grapes.

paʻi hua₁

bundle of fruit; fruit cluster, as of grapes.

paʻi hua₂

bulge, as in canoe sides.

paʻi kau

equal.

paʻi kinipōpō

baseball bat, tennis racquet; to hit a ball.

paʻi kiʻi

to take pictures, photographs; photographer. lit., snap pictures.

paʻi koli

to trim, cut short.

paʻi kukui

a kind of dark tapa cloth dyed with juice from kukui bark, said to be from Hālawa, Molokaʻi (Ii 83). According to (And), a pale yellow tapa made on Molokaʻi.

paʻi palaoa

cakes of fine flour.

paʻi palapala

printing press; to print.

paʻi pelena

loaves.

paʻi puna

to whitewash, plaster. lit., to slap coral.

paʻi umauma

chest-slapping hula.

paʻi waina

cluster of grapes.

paʻi wale

a draw or tie; to have a draw or tie.

paʻi ā paʻi

equal, as of two persons; to tie, have a draw.

paʻi ʻai

hard, pounded but undiluted taro; heavy, as poorly made cake.

paʻi ʻana

printing, edition.

paʻi ʻuala

cooked and compressed sweet potatoes allowed to ferment slightly and used as a substitute for poi when poi was scarce. Also poi ʻuala by analogy with poi.

paʻia

temporarily deaf, as from ascending to a high altitude.

paʻia kuli

deafening.

paʻiaha

a variety of taro.

paʻihi

• clear, bright, cloudless;   • neat, tidy,   • well dressed in one's best;   • to honor;   • set, as a ship's sails (often preceded by hao ā).

paʻilauʻula

dry pandanus leaves still clinging to the tree. lit., cut red leaves.

paʻimalau₁

Portuguese man-of-war (Physalia). jellyfish (HE)

paʻimalau₂

a fleet of canoes fishing for aku with the malau, bait carrier.

paʻina₁

to crackle, snap, click, tick, pop, resound; crackling, etc; brittle, easily torn.

paʻina₂

Hawaiʻi Island name for pohā₂, cape gooseberry.

paʻiniu

some native Hawaiian lilies (Astelia spp) with long, narrow, silvery or tan leaves forming rosette-shaped plants growing either on the ground or perching on trees. Small yellow or greenish flowers develop in a panicle on a stalk shorter than the leaves. Formerly, Hawaiians braided hat leis out of the shiny outer layer of the leaves and wore them as a sign that they had visited Kīlauea Volcano, where one species is common. Also used, rarely, for house thatch (For. 5:655).

paʻiniu

a very thin type of tapa.

paʻipaʻi lima

to clap, applaud; applause, clapping.

paʻipaʻinahā

tapa cloak worn over the shoulder like a cape.

paʻipaʻiʻiole

rat haircut. said to be named for an irregular haircut given to Pikoiakaʻalalā (a demigod born of a crow father, who sometimes appeared as a rat) by his rat sisters.

paʻipaʻi₁

• to applaud, clap; applause;   • to sprinkle coloring matter (as charcoal or red cloth) on tapa and beat it in.

paʻipaʻi₂

mixed, diluted.

paʻipaʻi₃

to trim, prune, cut, clip, as a plant or the hair; to strip off, as leaves.

paʻipunahele

to fete a favorite (punahele), especially by composing songs in his honor, and staging dances and feasts for him; an expression of love for a favorite.

paʻiua

fine, white tapa.

paʻiāuma

to slap the chest, as in grief. fig., to show grief, wail in lamentation.

paʻiʻula₁

tapa made by beating red rags or tapa pieces to form a mixture of white and red (as outer or kilohana sheet for bedcovers). also welu ʻula.

paʻiʻula₂

calabash receptacle for sarongs.

paʻi₁

• to slap, spank, beat, hit, clap; a slapping, slap,   • to print, publish; stamping, printing   • to snap, as pictures;   • to break, as a taboo; (several old types of tapa begin with paʻi: paʻipaʻinahā, paʻiua, paʻiʻula; preceded by ke).

paʻi₁₀

a heap.

paʻi₁₁

to evict, as from land.

paʻi₂

to tie; a draw; equal; to make an agreement (said to be so called because champions slapped each other's open palms after they had agreed on the terms of a match or race, and with a draw it was as though they had no more than concluded the terms).

paʻi₃

to mix, as ingredients; to mingle.

paʻi₄

to put clothes to soak, as in soapy water.

paʻi₅

a bundle, package, especially of food; to tie up such a bundle; bunch, cluster, as of grapes (preceded by ke).

paʻi₆

to strip, as bark.

paʻi₇

lining, as of pandanus or sugar-cane leaves, inside thatching of pili grass; to line thus.

paʻi₈

decaying, of fruits or plants; blight.

paʻopaʻo

a species of ulua, a fish (Caranx speciosus); green and yellow with vertical green bands; considered one of the best fishes for eating raw.

paʻu ahi

soot, black cindery sand or ash. lit., fire soot.

paʻu hana

constantly at work, drudgery,: tedious, prolonged work.

paʻuhia

• overcome with sleep;   • overwhelmed with desire;   • overtaken by evil or calamity.

paʻu₁

• soot, sooty.   • smudge;   • ink dregs; ink powder;   • ink used for tattooing made of burned kukui shells;   • tar-colored excrement as resulting from hemorrhage;

paʻu₂

drudgery, slaving; tedious and laborious work, toil; toilsome.

paʻē

to strike the ear, as a distant sound.

paʻē pū

to sound together, a deafening roar.

paʻēpaʻē

to publicize.

paʻū

moist, damp, soaked, drenched, moldy. also maʻū.

paʻūpaʻū₂

overlaid tapa (Kam. 76:115) said to be so called because it was wet during its manufacture; sometimes worn by dancers.

Pekania

Bethany.

Pekekaika

Bethsaida.

Pekela

Bethel.

Pekelehema

Bethlehem.

Pekelopolo

Petersburg.

Pekina

Peking.

Peleiake

Pleiades.

Pelekane

Britain, British, England, English, Englishman.

Pelekane Nui

Great Britain.

Pelekania

Britain; British.

Pelekepulikano

Presbyterian.

Pelekia

Persia; Persian.

Pelekiuma

Belgium; Belgian.

Pelekunu₂

wet valley, north Molokaʻi.

Pelelina

Berlin.

Peleminahama

Birmingham.

Pele₆

volcano goddess... The volcano goddess born as a flame in the mouth of Haumea. Epithets coupled with her name include Honuamea (reddish earth), Kawahine'aihonua (the earth eating woman), Kawahineokalua (the woman of the pit), and, rarely, Kawahineokaʻaʻahukeʻokeʻo (the woman with the white garment). Countless stories attribute rocks and land forms to Pele's wrath. Before settling at Kīlauea, she dug craters now extinct — Diamond Head, Punch Bowl, Koko Crater, Salt Lake, Haleakalā, and many others. She appeared at different times as fire, a wrinkled hag, a child, and a beautiful girl. She is sometimes called a malihini who came from Kahiki.

Pelimuka

Plymouth.

Pelukia₁

Prussia; Prussian.

Pelukia₂

Phrygia.

Penekala

Bengal.

Penekekoka

Pentecost; Pentecostal.

Peolia

Peoria.

Peʻehala

name of a wind associated with Hāmākua, Hawaiʻi.

Peʻepāpōhaku

name of a rain associated with Kaupō, Maui. lit., hide [at the] stone wall.

Peʻepūhalahīnano

rain name.

pe neia

same as pe kēia, penei.

pe-

like, resembling (in the demonstratives pēia, pēlā, pēnā, penei and pehea).

peawa

beaver.

peawini

fair wind.

pea₁

fair, carnival, exhibit.

pea₂

pear, avocado (Persea americana).

pea₃

bear.

pehemo

behemoth.

pehe₁

owl snare.

pehe₃

unsteady.

pehi

• to throw, throw at, pelt;   • an overhand throw, as in throwing the ʻulu.

pehina

throwing; pelting, as of rain.

pehu holokū

swelling of entire body.

pehu kumu niu

swelling of lower limbs. lit., coconut tree swelling.

pehu pala

scab (Kanl. 28.27) , scurvy.

pehuakoa

tapa colored with an infusion made of koa bark. lit., koa swelling.

pehua₂

a variety of taro.

pehuea

to increase in volume, of the wind; such an increase.

pehu₁

• swollen; distended; swelling; to swell;   • dropsy, edema.   • fig., swollen with pride or conceit;   • longing to eat, hunger (short for makapehu, eyes big with hunger). Types of pehu, dropsy, were qualified by the terms ale ʻai, food gulping; kālaʻe, clearing. see wāwae pehu (gout, swollen legs or feet), and below.

pehu₂

a variety of sweet potato.

pehu₃

a kind of seaweed.

pehē

to peel off, pare, strip; to remove skin or bark.

pei

bent.

pekalakelia

harp (RSV), psaltery (KJV).

pekale

peccary.

pekana

pagan, heathen.

pekapeka

to tattle, tell tales, act as stool pigeon; tattler, stool pigeon.

peka₂

bekah (ancient Hebrew unit of weight).

pekekue

blunt.

pekelala

federal.

pekepeke₂

ridge (?).

peke₁

• dwarf, brownie, elf, goblin, midget;   • dwarfish, minute; tiny.   • short, as steps or stitches;

pekikini

to present, as arms (petikini i nā pū).

peki₁

pace; to move along step by step, to tread along, trudge along, jog.

peki₂

to back up, as a car.

peki₃

spade, as in playing cards.

peku

a kick; to kick., to ward off, as a spear.

pekula

picul, as used for the sale of sandalwood.

pekuna

a kick.

pekunia

petunias (Petunia xhybrida), garden herbs grown for their bright, attractive, funnel-shaped flowers of various colors.

pekupeku

redup. of peku, a kick; to kick., to ward off, as a spear. to flick out, as bark while scraping olonā.

pela moe

mattress.

pela uea

bedsprings (later replaced by pilina). lit., wire bale.

pela uluna

pillow.

pelakano

plane tree (RSV), chestnut (KJV).

pelamika

pyramid.

pelane

plane tree (RSV), chestnut (KJV).

pelapela

filthy, dirty, nasty, indecent, unclean, vulgar, lewd, obscene.

pela₁

fertilizer, any decomposed material, especially decayed flesh and intestines removed from a corpse; the bones were buried secretly, and the flesh (pela) thrown into the sea (cf. kapa lau).

pela₃

bale; to bale; mattress, cushion; package, as of hard poi.

pela₄

bail; to bail.

pela₅

pail.

pelehū kāne

turkey gobbler.

pelehū₁

turkey (Meleagris gallopavo). lit., swollen swelling.

pelekana

pelican.

peleka₁

perch, in surveying.

peleka₂

spelt (RSV), fitch (KJV).

peleki

brake; to apply brakes.

pelekikena

president; presidential.

pelekona

person.

pelekunu₁

musty, moldy, or rank odor.

peleleu₁

• extended, either longitudinally or horizontally;   • long, broad, wide, as a nose;   • spreading, extending;   • extension, projection.

pelemakani

propeller, as of an airplane. Niʻihau.

pelena

crackers, biscuit, bread.

pelena paʻa

hardtack.

pelepulu

soaked, drenched, as by rain.

peleʻū

mildewed; wet, rotting, and vile-smelling, as of clothes.

pele₁

lava flow, volcano, eruption; volcanic (named for the volcano goddess, Pele).

pele₂

soft, swollen, fat; pounded or kneaded soft, as poi or dough.

pele₃

choice Kauaʻi tapa (FS 252–3), scented with maile and kūpaoa, said to be gray and dyed with charcoal made of burned sugar cane mixed with coconut water (preceded by ke).

pele₄

a term qualifying koʻi (adze), similar to kūpele.

pele₅

bell.

peliala

friar.

pelihele

periphery.

pelika

covenant, bond (formerly said of matrimony).

pelikana

pelican.

pelio

counterfeit.

pelo

to flatter, tell tall tales, lie.

peloka

perch, rod, pole.

peloni

felony.

peluhāʻele

a variety of taro.

pelukia ʻakika

Prussic acid.

pelukua

to turn about; to turn and go back.

peluliahi

a type of kīhei shawl dyed with sandalwood.

pelulo

beryl.

peluluka

rotting, of crops (Malo 199, Emerson note); to soak and squeeze, as in preparing pia.

pelu₁

to fold, turn over or under, bend.

pelu₂

a hem, tuck, as in a dress; to take a tuck, hem.

pelu₃

to turn and go.

pelēpelē

boxing, fighting for sport.

pena hale

house paint; house painter; to paint a house.

pena kiʻi

to paint pictures; picture painter; water colors.

pena mikiʻao

fingernail polish.

pena₁

paint; to paint.

pena₂

package.

pena₃

a Maui word for nīele, curious.

penei

this way, like this, for instance, so, thus, as follows; to be thus (more definite than pēia).

penekine

benzine.

penekuina

penguin.

penekū

to reside at a place for several generations.

pene₁

to reside a long time in one place. Kaʻū.

peni kila

steel pen.

penikenia

Sacrament of confession.

penikila

painkiller.

peni₂

penny.

peno

soaked, drenched; to soak.

penopeno

dirty, smutty.

penu

• to sop up, as gravy;   • to dunk;   • to dab up, as tears.

peo₁

vagina.

peo₂

round, globular.

pepa hahau

playing cards. lit., striking cards.

pepa hale

wallpaper.

pepa hoʻokē

Kleenex or paper handkerchief. lit., nose-blowing paper.

pepa hoʻololi kaʻa

a transfer authorizing change from one vehicle to another. lit., paper changing cars.

pepa hoʻomaloʻo ʻīnika

blotter.

pepa hoʻonani hale

wallpaper.

pepa hāleu

toilet paper, lit., cleansing paper.

pepa kahakaha

scratch paper.

pepa kalakala

sandpaper. lit., rough paper.

pepa kiʻi

joker, in a deck of cards. lit., picture card.

pepa kope

carbon paper, Xerox.

pepa kīkoʻo

check or draft for paying money. lit., withdrawing paper.

pepa kīkoʻo kālā

money order.

pepa lahilahi

tissue paper, thin paper.

pepa lei

crepe paper, as used in lei making. lit., lei paper.

pepa mānoanoa

cardboard. lit., thick paper.

pepa paʻi kiʻi

photographic film.

pepa poʻoleka

postcard.

pepa wahī

wrapping paper.

pepa ʻomoʻīnika

blotter.

pepakene

Cayenne pepper (Capsicum annuum cv. ‘longum’).

pepamina

peppermint (Mentha piperita).

pepa₂

black or white pepper, produced from the fruit of a climbing Oriental shrub (Piper nigrum).

pepehi kanaka

murder, murderer, manslaughter; to commit murder.

pepehi₁

to beat, strike, pound, kill.

pepehi₂

surface of a tapa beater formed by deep grooves with the wide ridges (up to 14) rounded off in the form of an inverted U; sometimes the beater itself was so called.

pepeiao akua

tree fungus, the Jew's-ear (Auricularia auricula).

pepeiao hohono

infected ear; said derisively of farmers with reference to the smoky odor (hohono) of their fires.

pepeiao kuli

a deaf ear, deafness, disobedience, refusal to listen to advice.

pepeiao lāʻau

lit., tree ear.

pepeiao ʻeha

earache.

pepeiaohao

horn of an animal; trumpet or horn made of an animal's horn. (Hal. 118.27) lit., iron ear.

pepeiao₂

cotyledon, as of beans.

pepeiao₃

stipule, as of noni, a tree.

pepeiao₄

scallops in lace.

pepeiao₅

lugs or blocks inside a canoe hull to which the ʻiako, booms, and perhaps the mast (For. 5:633) are fastened.

pepeiao₆

comb cleats for canoe thwarts or seats.

pepeiao₇

Chinese cake stuffed with meat, named for a resemblance to an ear. cf. cup-shaped mea ʻono puaʻa.

pepeiao₈

long nets 30 to 37 m deep, attached at each side of the ʻupena kolo, bag net.

pepeiao₉

valve of the heart.

pepeieʻe

overripe breadfruit or banana kneaded with coconut cream, wrapped in ti leaves, and baked in the oven. This could be preserved for a season.

pepelu₁

repetitious in speech.

pepeua

hard, thick, disobedient.

pepeʻe paka

tobacco plug.

pepeʻekue

• coarse, as lace or hair;   • thick;   • clumsy, lumbering, as a puppy's feet.

pepeʻe₁

twisted, crooked, deformed, misshapen, out of shape; deformity.

pepeʻe₂

young fern leaves, as of hāpuʻu, hōʻiʻo, and ʻamaʻu, that are rolled up, sometimes suggesting a question mark.

pepe₁

flat, as a nose; low, squatty.

pepe₂

small, fine-meshed, as of a mat. pepepe is more common.

pepe₃

(Emerson) however gives "canoe seat" (UL 194) and "chock on which a canoe rests" (PH 114).

peue

dull, blunt. fig., stupid, dull.

peu₁

• to thrust up, push up,   • root, uproot,   • prod, bunt,   • nudge upward, elbow upward,   • pout,   • jostle with the feet as to attract attention;   • to rise up, as grass that has been trod upon;   • to thrust, as a male in coition.

peu₂

a vulgar gesture, in which the fist is doubled and jerked upward; to make the gesture.

peu₃

cartilage of a pig's nose.

peu₄

point at canoe bow.

pewapewa₁

pectoral fins of a fish; to move or vibrate these fins.

pewa₁

tail of fish, shrimp, lobster.

pewa₂

rectangular patch or wedge used for mending bowls, perhaps so called because of a resemblance to a fishtail.

pewa₃

usually following huli.

pewa₄

clump or group, as of trees near a forest.

peʻa heke

triangular sail set above the gaff; topsail.

peʻa hope

mainsail.

peʻa ihu

jib sail. lit., bow sail.

peʻa nui

mainsail. lit., big sail.

peʻa oe

a long sail.

peʻahi lima

• the open hand,   • a hand's breadth (Ezek. 40.5) ;   • to beckon or wave with the hand.

peʻahi uila

electric fan.

peʻahi₁

fan; to fan, brush, wave, signal, beckon, winnow.

peʻahi₂

the open hand, bones of the hand.

peʻahi₃

a native fern (Microsorium spectrum syn. Polypodium spectrum) about 30 cm high, the fronds broad, pointed, commonly three-lobed.

peʻahi₄

a dark-colored stone with grain said to suggest the fingers of a hand.

peʻakua

a trusted relative of a chief who attends to his personal needs. lit., back-cross, so called because such a person might go behind the back of the chief.

peʻapeʻa pōhaku

heap of pebbles, as at the opening of an octopus burrow.

peʻapeʻa₁

crossing. fig., entangled, perplexity.

peʻapeʻa₂

Hawaiian bat (Lasiurus cinereus).

peʻapeʻa₃

small peʻa, starfish.

peʻapeʻa₄

filthy, unclean; slime.

peʻa₁

• a cross (X-shaped; cf. the Christian cross, keʻa);   • to cross, as the hands or arms;   • to cross and tie;   • to turn and go.

peʻa₁₀

base of a leaf.

peʻa₁₁

sacred house.

peʻa₂

bat. cf. more common ʻōpeʻapeʻa.

peʻa₃

starfish, various species of Asteroidea.

peʻa₄

sail, as of a canoe.

peʻa₅

forks or branches made of stalks of feathers bound at their bases with ʻieʻie roots, coming together to form the koʻo (stalk) which in turn is attached to the kāhili staff.

peʻa₆

boundary, edge, border, as of land.

peʻa₇

• menstruating, to menstruate.   • unclean,   • tattered (FS 167);

peʻa₈

kite.

peʻa₉

ti-leaf thatch bundle.

peʻe pao

one who hides in a cave; to hide in a cave; secret cave; term of contempt for vagabonds or cowards.

peʻe poli

to hide in one's bosom, as a secret; secretive.

peʻelua₁

caterpillar (2-Oihn. 6.28) ; (KL. line 287); army worm (Cirphis unipuncta).

peʻelua₂

brindled, striped.

peʻelulu

confusing; confusion.

peʻeone

sand crab that buries itself backwards in wet sand (Hippa pacifica). lit., sand hiding.

peʻepeʻe kua

the game of hide-and-seek; to play the game (short for peʻepeʻe akua, hiding ghost).

peʻepeʻemakawalu₁

large house spider.

peʻepeʻemakawalu₂

alert.

peʻepeʻe₂

Maui.

peʻepeʻe₃

name of an ancient illness (no data).

peʻe₂

coarse, thick.

peʻu

Molokaʻi.

Pikina Hila

Beacon Hill.

Pikoiakaʻalalā

a demigod born at Wailua, Kauaʻi, of a crow (ʻalalā ) father, and with rat (ʻiole) and bat (ʻōpeʻapeʻa) sisters. He was carried out to sea and to Kou (Honolulu) where he won contests in rat-shooting and in riddling. He sometimes appeared as a rat. lit., Pikoi son of the crow.

Pilihala

wind associated with Kaʻawaloa, Hawaiʻi. lit., near pandanus.

Pilikane

Brittany.

Pililua

name of a pair of stars, said to bring ʻōpelu fish.

Pilimaiʻuʻu

a stroke in lua fighting. lit., clinging to fingernail.

Pilinahe

rain name.

Piliʻā

rain name, Kanikū, Hawaiʻi.

Pinilana

Finland, Finnish.

pia maka hinu

a type of stone used for adzes.

pia manioka

starch made of manioc.

piaea

small fish, as ʻōhua manini.

piaia

young manini fish. Niʻihau.

piano

piano.

piapia₁

• the encrusted white matter in the eyes, as from sleeping or sore eyes, "sand" in the eyes; to get such matter in the eyes;   • an abusive epithet applied to one who was unwashed, said to refer to genitals.

piapia₂

a variety of taro.

piapia₃

a variety of sweet potato.

pia₁

Polynesian arrowroot (Tacca leontopetaloides, formerly known as T. pinnatifida), an herb known in the eastern tropics, formerly cultivated in Hawaiʻi for the starchy tubers, which were used for medicine and food. In spring or summer, a few leaves rise on long stems from a tuber and die back in the winter. The blades are much divided, about 30 cm wide, somewhat like papaya leaves in shape. (HP 212), (Neal 228–9).

pia₂

general name for starch; starch made from arrowroot is called pia Hawaiʻi to distinguish from other starches; pia is used in haupia pudding, as medicine, and as talcum powder.

pia₃

pale yellow. cf. hala pia, a pandanus, and hēpia, of the ʻilima flower.

pia₄

a variety of taro.

pia₅

a variety of sweet potato.

pia₆

a kind of stone, as used for adzes.

pia₈

stork.

pie ueue

eczema, a name for kauā, outcasts.

piele₁

mattery eruptions or eczema on the scalp; to have such eruptions.

piele₂

to trade, peddle; trader, peddler.

piele₃

pudding of grated taro, sweet potato, yam, banana, or breadfruit, baked in ti leaves with coconut cream.

piena

offensive to smell, stinking.

piepiele₂

to do small favors in order to receive greater ones; to flatter or fawn in order to receive something.

piha lima

handful.

piha makahiki

yearly anniversary; to have an annual anniversary.

piha pono

completely full, complete.

piha puna

spoonful.

piha pū

completely filled.

piha ʻeu

spirited, enthusiastic.

pihakuʻi

brimful, jammed full, packed tight, crowded.

pihana

fullness, filling up, completion.

pihano

silent, weak-voiced.

pihapiha ʻāʻī

ruff.

pihapiha ʻō koholā

pleated ruffle. lit., whaler's ruffle, so called because such ruffles were stylish in whaling days.

pihapiha₁

• full, complete; filled;   • full and flowing, as a garment;   • filed, as cards;   • completed, as a questionnaire.

pihapiha₂

gills of a fish.

pihapiha₃

ruffle, fringe, as on a dress.

pihaweuweu₁

temporary bed made of dry ʻilima branches, dried banana leaves and grasses, over which a mat or two were spread.

pihaweuweu₂

full of grass, but thin, said of a grass-eating animal that does not put on flesh.

pihaʻekelo

mynah bird (Acridotheres tristis), introduced from India in 1865. lit., full of ʻekelo sound.

pihaʻū

jam-packed, packed tight, full, crammed.

pihe

• din of voices,   • crying, shouting,   • wailing, lamentation;   • to mourn, shout, etc.

pihi pūlima

cuff button.

pihipihi₁

scarred.

pihipihi₂

any small objects shaped like buttons, as washers (preceded by ke).

pihipihi₃

to skip stones on the surface of the water; stone skipping.

pihi₁

scab, scar.

pihi₂

button, badge; to button (preceded by ke).

pihi₃

blunt, dull, as a wooden digging stick.

pihi₄

fish.

pihoa

dizzy.

pihulu

hairy, fuzzy.

pihōpihō

to bob up and down or swamp, as a canoe.

pihō₁

swamp, mire; swampy.

pika pua

flower container, vase. lit., flower pitcher.

pika wai

water pitcher.

pikakani

a rattlebox (Crotalaria pallida, formerly known as C. mucronata), known in many tropical countries, a small, weedy, shrubby legume with three-parted leaves, yellow flowers striped with red, and many-seeded pods to 5 cm long.

pikanini

small (slang, from pickaninny).

pikapika₁

suction cups on octopus tentacles.

pikapika₂

a kind of lava rock with points said to resemble the suction cups of an octopus.

pikapika₃

variegated, spotted; of varying colors, as the ocean.

pikawai

to pick up, as a rooster picks up food.

pika₂

pitcher, vase.

pika₃

beet (Beta vulgaris).

pika₄

picul; half.

pika₅

hot, as peppery food (said in pidgin Eng.).

pikekakio

pistachio (Pistacia vera).

pikele

pitcher.

pikimana

bituminous; coal.

pikineki

business.

pikiniki

picnic.

pikipikiʻō

rough, stormy, choppy, as the sea. fig., agitated in spirit. cf.     kūpikiʻō agitated, raging, turbulent, as wind or storm...     kūpikipikiʻō redup. of kūpikiʻō, agitated, raging, turbulent...     hoʻokūpikiʻō caus/sim of kūpikiʻō, agitated, raging, turbulent...

pikipiki₁

to pinch or squeeze, as in milking.

piki₁

shrunk, shortened, irregular.

piki₂

the peach (Prunus persica), possibly a native of China, introduced to Hawaiʻi but not common.

piki₃

beet.

piko kea

a native variety of taro widely planted; an important poi taro, especially on Oʻahu, distinguished by whitish piko and by leaf stems light-green with pinkish base. also piko keʻokeʻo.

piko lehua ʻāpiʻi

a native variety of taro, with leaves dark-green and crinkled below; the corms with lilac-purple flesh, yielding the popular lehua red poi; the leaves good for lūʻau. lit., curly red piko taro.

piko lua

double crown of the head, a sign that a child will be persevering and determined.

piko pau ʻiole

rat-taken navel cord, i.e., a chronic thief. It was believed that one became a chronic thief if his navel cord was stolen by a rat. Rats were famous for thieving.

piko uaua

a native variety of taro, one of the hardiest piko taros and perhaps the only kind common in upland culture; yields good grade light-colored poi; distinguished by dark-green leaf stems with a pinkish base.

piko ʻeleʻele

a native variety of taro, with darkpurple petioles; common poi and table taro; the leaves are good for lūʻau.

piko ʻulaʻula

a native variety of taro, distinguished from piko lehua ʻāpiʻi by having leaves smooth below; corms yield red poi of good grade.

pikoholo

slipknot. lit., loop rope-end.

pikoohaleakalā

type of braid used in the pāpale ʻie.

pikoowākea₁

Equator.

piko₁

• navel,   • navel string, umbilical cord.   • fig., blood relative, genitals.

piko₂

• summit or top of a hill or mountain;   • crest; crown of the head;   • crown of the hat made on a frame (pāpale pahu);   • tip of the ear;   • end of a rope;   • border of a land;   • center, as of a fishpond wall or kōnane board;   • place where a stem is attached to the leaf, as of taro.

piko₄

a common taro with many varieties, all with the leaf blade indented at the base up to the piko, junction of blade and stem.

piko₅

design in plaiting the hat called pāpale ʻie.

piko₆

bottom round of a carrying net, kōkō.

piko₇

small wauke rootlets from an old plant.

piko₈

thatch above a door.

piku

fig (Ficus carica).

pikumena

coal.

pila haʻawina

appropriation, allotment bill.

pila hāpa

autoharp. lit., fiddle harp.

pila hōʻaiʻē

promissory note. lit., bill to extend credit.

pila koi

requisition.

pila kuolo

violin. lit., rubbing fiddle.

pila kīkoʻo

check, draft, bill.

pila kīkoʻo hale leka

money order. lit., post-office draft.

pila kīkoʻo hoʻohuihui ʻia

blanket warrant.

pila puhipuhi

harmonica, mouth organ. lit., blowing fiddle.

pila ʻaha

string musical instrument.

pila ʻaiʻē

voucher.

pilapilau

somewhat bad-smelling, not quite spoiled.

pilawaiwai

account, reckoning, as of an estate; invoice.

pilaʻumeʻume

accordion. lit., tugging fiddle.

pila₁

any string instrument, formerly the fiddle; violin.

pila₂

a bill; to make out a bill.

pila₃

fir.

pila₄

to build, in a card game.

pili hale

house shingle (preceded by ke).

pili hao

corrugated iron, as used for roofing (preceded by ke). lit., iron shingles.

pili hihia

to become involved in gambling, usually disastrously; in the old days, to bet one's life or wife; to be involved in an entangling affair of any sort.

pili hoʻoipoipo

love affair.

pili koke

to be closely related; to be very close, intimate.

pili koko

blood relationship, blood relative; related by blood.

pili kua

to cling to the back.

pili kāmau

relationship by friendship rather than by blood or adoption. lit., added-on relative.

pili kāpekepeke

uncertain relationship

pili laulā

of wide application, of broad or general interest.

pili lima

a guessing game: to guess the contents of another's folded hand. lit., wager hand.

pili loko

a close relative, closely related; concerning local places.

pili lua

a close companionship of two; to associate, of two; related in two ways.

pili lāʻau₁

wooden house shingle.

pili lāʻau₂

edge of a forest.

pili mua

elder relative; preferred friend or companion; former associate.

pili nohona

family or social structure.

pili papa

shingle roofing.

pili paʻa

• to stick firmly,   • associate constantly;   • to live in harmony;   • to fit closely,   • tenacious.

pili piula

corrugated iron roofing.

pili poli

to be close to the bosom or heart (affectionate).

pili pono

well-suited, well-matched; close-fitting, as clothes; to refer exactly or concisely.

pili pū

• to unite, join,   • cling to;   • hard-pressed, as in danger.

pili uka

a stiff, tufted, native grass (Trisetum glomeratum), 0.3 to 0.9 m high, with leaves 10.2 to 25 cm long and flowers crowded in narrow spikes; a good forage grass, growing only at rather high altitudes. On Hawaiʻi this is apparently called heʻupueo.

pili wale

to cling, etc., for no reason or cause; often used in unfavorable sense of living off other people.

pili ā moʻo

to cling like a lizard, as on a cliff.

pili ʻana wā anō

gram. present participle.

pili ʻana wā hala

gram. past participle.

pili ʻano

to resemble in character or nature.

pili ʻole

unrelated, not concerned with.

pili ʻuhane

spiritual.

pilialo

bosom friend, beloved wife.

pilialoha

close friendship, beloved companionship, beloved relative; loving association; to have a loving or tender relationship, to be in a bond of love, romance.

pilihua

• sad, sorrowful, dejected,   • astonished,   • confused (Ier. 14.9) ,   • bewitched (Oih. 8.9) ;   • weary.

pilikahakai

shore, especially the area between high and low tides; near the shore.

pilikai₁

a vine (Stictocardia tiliaefolia) in the morning-glory family, native from India eastward, possibly into Polynesia, long known in Hawaiʻi, as on roadsides and rocky shores. Flowers are funnel-shaped, rose-purple, about 5.1 cm in diameter, the leaves heartshaped.

pilikai₂

the wood rose (Merremia tuberosa), another kind of morning-glory, with deep yellow flowers and five-to seven-lobed leaves, grown ornamentally in Hawaiʻi for its dry, brown, rose-shaped fruit.

pilikana

(probably pili, to cling, + -kana, nominalizer.)   • relation, relationship,   • kin, family.

pilikino

• personal,   • private,   • subjective,   • worldly.

pilikoʻa₁

hawkfish (Paracirrhites forsteri, Cirrhitops fasciatus, Amblycirrhites bimacula), 18 cm or less in length and light-pink in color, lit., coral clinging. Also Cirrhites pinnulatus and Oxycirrhites typus.

pilikoʻa₂

a native variety of sugar cane named for the fish; stems yellow-green, with pale brown-red stripes when young, changing to bronze-yellow with darker brown-red stripes.

pilikoʻa₃

a stiff kind of pākalakala, a seaweed (Galaxaura lapidescens).

pilikua₁

• giant,   • large strapping fellow,   • country person, one living in the country; countrified.

pilikua₂

beloved husband.

pilikua₃

to fight in single combat.

pililāʻele

dark green pandanus leaves with white bases, above the lāʻele, old leaves.

pilimai₁

a native variety of sugar cane, a yellow-green mutant of ʻakilolo; used in hana aloha, love sorcery, with the prayer for love to cling and hold fast.

pilimai₂

a variety of taro.

pilimai₃

a variety of sweet potato.

pilimeaʻai

lit., close association [for] food.

pilimoe

name of one of the tapas in the game of pūhenehene.

pilimua

gram. article, the part of speech: ke, ka, he, nā.

pilina moe

bedsprings.

pilina ʻohana

kinship.

pilina₁

association, relationship, union, connection, meeting, joining, adhering, fitting.

pilina₂

springs, as of a mattress, watch, car.

pilipili heʻe₁

thin ends of octopus tentacles, as braided together when dried.

pilipili heʻe₂

octopus or squid ink sac (ʻalaʻala) molded about a fishhook for bait.

pilipili ʻāina

close to land.

pilipiliʻula₁

a close blood relationship to one of high rank; this was said by persons entering the hale nauā, desirous of asserting their royal blood. lit., red relationship [red was a sacred color].

pilipiliʻula₂

also Desmodium uncinatum on Niʻihau.

pilipili₁

any sticky matter, adhesive; pasty, gluey, viscid.

pilipuka₁

the period between midnight and dawn. lit., near appearance [of the sun].

pilipuka₂

one of the tapa covers in the pūhenehene game, which were named for different parts of the night.

pilipā

alongside a fence or enclosure; hedge.

pilipōhaku

a fish (no data).

piliwaiwai

gambling, betting, gambler; to bet, gamble. lit., to wager wealth.

piliwi

to believe.

piliʻaikū

• cramped,   • stiff,   • numb.

piliʻaoʻao

mate, spouse, common-law mate with whom one lives openly.

piliʻoki

billiards.

piliʻāina

shore; interisland.

piliʻōlelo

grammar, word or sentence structure.

pili₁₀

a narrow or precarious pass.

pili₁₁

same as ʻume, the game, so called because the wand touched (pili) the players.

pili₂

a grass (Heteropogon contortus) known in many warm regions, formerly used for thatching houses in Hawaiʻi; sometimes added to the hula altar to Laka, for knowledge to pili or cling; thatch (preceded by ke).

pili₃

to refer, concern, relate, pertain, apply.

pili₄

shingles, so called because they replace the pili grass of the roofs of the old houses (preceded by ke).

pili₅

a wager, bet, stake; to bet, wager.

pili₆

border, edge of time units, especially of late night.

pili₇

uncolored sheets in a kapa kuʻina, sleeping tapa.

pili₈

lining of a quilt under the layer of cotton or wool.

pili₉

first stage of poi-pounding, with taro beginning to stick.

pilo kea

a small native tree or shrub (Platydesma spathulata), in the orange family; leaves large, thick, oblong, more or less pointed; flowers few, creamcolored; fruits small, dry, four-lobed.

pilo kea lau liʻi

a native shrub (Platydesma rostratum), with long, narrow leaves, clustered, axillary flowers, and beaked, four-lobed fruits.

pilo₁

• swampy, foul odor, as of a swamp;   • halitosis;   • polluted.

pilo₂

some species of native shrubs, in the coffee family (Hedyotis [Kadual]), the leaves bad-smelling when crushed. see also kōī₅ (Coprosma kauensis) and au₁₃.

pilo₃

all Hawaiian species of Coprosma, a genus of shrubs and small trees belonging to the coffee family, with narrow to rounded leaves, tiny greenish flowers, and yellow, red, or black berries.

pilo₄

same as maiapilo, a low, smooth shrub... (Capparis sandwichiana).

pilo₅

any kind, any whatsoever (used with ʻaʻohe).

pilu

to shake, quiver, vibrate.

pilupilu₂

overdressed, richly and elaborately overdressed, perhaps in a ridiculous way.

pima

beam, as for scales.

pimeneko

pimento (Capsicum annuum).

pinana

to climb; a climb.

pinanaʻiea

to turn aside, as the head, or as the bow of a ship when struck by a large wave.

pinao ʻula

a variety of dragonfly. lit., red pinao.

pinao₁

dragonfly.

pinao₂

flying gurnard, a fish (Dactylopterus orientalis).

pinao₃

blurred, as eyes of a drunkard. similar to pōnalo₂.

pinao₄

broad jump.

pinao₅

perhaps a swing.

pinau₁

to recoil, snap, as a rope.

pine hoaka

lit., crescent pin.

pine kaiapa

safety pin. lit., diaper pin.

pine kaulaʻi

clothespin. lit., hanging pin.

pine niho puaʻa

hog's tooth pin. Formerly also called pine hoaka. lit., pig tooth pin.

pine pā

fence picket.

pine umauma

breast pin, brooch.

pineki

peanut (Arachis hypogaea).

pineʻōmou

stickpin, brooch.

pine₁

pin, compass needle, peg, bolt, picket; stanchion to hold animal's head with yoke and pin; to pin.

pine₂

a tame bullock tied to a newly captured wild cow or bull. When released it would lead the wild animal to a pen.

pinika

vinegar; an intoxicating drink made of fermented molasses and water.

piolo

• to rub back and forth, saw;   • to pucker and unpucker the lips.   • fig., to go over and over in the mind, to mull over, think.

pioloolo₂

to feed such a concoction.

piopio₃

call to chickens.

pio₁

• captive, prisoner, victim, prey; conquered, captured, made prisoner;   • game of tag; to play tag.

pio₃

• to peep, chirp;   • to whistle with fingers on the mouth;   • to pipe on any flutelike instrument;   • peeping, peep.

pio₄

a measure of three iwilei (yards), especially of cloth.

pipi Pākē

water buffalo, carabao. lit., Chinese beef.

pipi kaula

jerked beef (beef salted and dried in the sun, broiled before eaten). lit., rope beef.

pipi kauō

ox. lit., dragging beef.

pipi keiki

calf. lit., child beef

pipi kolo

yearling cow or bull.

pipi kuapuʻu

bison. lit., beef [with] humped back.

pipi kāne

bull. lit., male beef.

pipi kōʻala

broiled beef, steak.

pipi kū

stew beef, beef stew.

pipi laho

bull.

pipi loke

roast beef.

pipi ohi

young cow, heifer.

pipi palai

beefsteak. lit., fried beef.

pipi poʻa

steer. lit., castrated beef.

pipi pulu

bull. lit., bull beef.

pipi wahine

cow. lit., female beef.

pipi waiū

milk cow.

pipika

• to draw away, shrink away, as an octopus tentacle on a fire;   • to crinkle up,   • contract:   • to turn aside so as not to meet,   • avoid.

pipiki

shrunk, crinkled; tight, cramped.

pipili₁

tenacious.

pipili₂

drymaria (Drymaria cordata), a slender, weedy herb, with rounded leaves, tiny flowers, and tiny one-seeded dry fruits with sticky stems, which catch on passersby. It is a tropical shade-dwelling plant.

pipine

promiscuous; promiscuous person.

pipipi kōlea

periwinkle (Littorina pintado, L. scabra). lit., kōlea-bird shell, perhaps so called because ot its color.

pipipi kōlea ihiloa

periwinkle (Planaxis labiosus).

pipipi ʻākōlea ihiloa

a mollusk (Planaxis labiosus). lit., long-necked gourd ʻākōlea shell, so called because of its shape.

pipipi₁

general name for small mollusks, including Theodoxus neglectus.

pipipi₂

• small and close together, as stars or pipipi shells;   • small, squinting, as eyes.

pipiʻauamo

ox yoke.

pipi₁

Hawaiian pearl oyster (Pinctada radiata); in songs this is known as the iʻa hāmau leo o ʻEwa, ʻEwa's silent sea creature [it was believed that talking would cause a breeze to ripple the water and frighten the pipi].

pipi₂

feelers of an insect, as of an ant.

pipi₃

kind of plant... (Psilotum).

pipi₄

a kind of tapa.

pipi₅

body depression; eyeball.

pipi₆

lower part of an adze.

pipī

redup. of pī₂,   • sputtering,   • smoldering,   • to snort, sniffle...;   • squinting;   • twinkling, as stars.   • fig., barely surviving.

piuka

pewter.

piuke

beauty.

piula wai

faucet, water tap, hydrant. lit., water metal.

piula₁

mule, donkey (Molokaʻi).

piula₂

a card game; the player must follow suit in discards, and if he cannot, he draws from a pack; the object is to play all of one's cards, and the player left with a card at the end is the piula.

piula₃

tired, exhausted, wornout. slang.

piula₄

pewter, tin (Nah. 31.22) , corrugated iron as used for roofing; any metal suggesting pewter.

piwa haka

beaver hat.

piwa haʻihaʻi iwi

dengue fever.

piwa hoʻonāwaliwali

typhoid fever. lit., weakening fever.

piwa lenalena

yellow fever.

piwa ʻeleʻele

black plague.

piwa ʻulaʻula

scarlet fever.

piwa₂

beaver.

piʻa

a kind of yam (Dioscorea pentaphylla), a climber with lobed leaves known throughout Pacific islands and in tropical Asia. It bears small aerial and subterranean, edible tubers. (HP 215), (Neal 230–1).

piʻi aliʻi

to claim chiefly blood, whether or not it exists.

piʻi kea

to become light, as the day; to begin to gray, of hair.

piʻi pāwalu

octave. lit., eightfold ascent.

piʻialiʻi

a native variety of taro, one of the oldest varieties grown in Hawaiʻi; formerly known as one of the royal taros and desirable as an offering to the gods; today, an important wet-land poi taro. Leaves and corm are tinged with pink. This name may be qualified by the colors ʻeleʻele, keʻokeʻo, ʻulaʻula. (HP 28), (Whitney).

piʻihālāwai

a variety of taro.

piʻikoi

to claim honors not rightfully due, to seek preferment, to aspire to the best or to more than is one's due; to claim to be of higher rank than one is.

piʻikuma

a type of ancient prayer.

piʻikū₁

to climb a steep slope; to climb, as a coconut palm by grasping the trunk with the hands and walking up with the feet; a steep climb.

piʻikū₂

a medicine made of the sap of young kukui nuts, used as a gargle for sore throat and thrush; if swallowed it causes nausea and looseness of the bowels.

piʻikū₃

transpiration, water drops on leaves of plants.

piʻilae

haughty, proud. lit., forehead rising.

piʻina

climb, ascent, rise, incline, etc.

piʻipiʻi kai

to rise, of a strong sea. fig., to flare, as anger.

piʻipiʻi ʻōlelo

words of anger, emotion, controversy.

piʻipiʻi₁

bubbling forth, as water (Kanl. 8.7) ; to overflow, as charged water; effervesce.

piʻipiʻi₃

curly, curled, wavy.

piʻi₂

to experience personally, or appear, as heat, cold, emotion.

piʻi₅

• intercourse;   • to practice intercourse;   • to mount, as of male animals.

piʻi₆

triangular piece inserted in a holokū skirt to add width, or inserted at the base of the legs of bell-bottom trousers.

piʻi₇

taros...     piʻialiʻi a native variety of taro, one of the oldest varieties...     piʻipiʻi aliʻi redup. of piʻialiʻi, a native variety of taro,     piʻihālāwai a variety of taro.

piʻoi₁

Kauaʻi name for hoi, the bitter yam (Dioscorea bulbifera).

piʻoi₂

Hawaiʻi name for edible fruit of the lama (Diospyros spp.) or perhaps kukui.

piʻolepo

column of dust, cloud of dust. lit., dirt arch.

piʻoloke

• alarmed, startled; alarm   • perturbed, vexed, disturbed,   • confused and excited, agitated; confusion,   • harassed;   • in noisy consternation;   (sometimes preceded by ke).

piʻoāʻea

tactless. Kaʻū.

piʻo₁

• arch, arc;   • bent, arched, curved;   • to arch, of a rainbow.

piʻo₂

marriage of full brother and sister of nīʻaupiʻo rank, presumably the highest possible rank. Their offspring had the rank of naha, which is less than piʻo but probably more than nīʻaupiʻo. Later piʻo included marriage with half-sibling.

Pohu₂

a wind associated with Kona, Hawaiʻi.

Pohākōʻeleʻele

same as ʻIkuwā, a month of storms; also said to be the name of a rain occurring in that month. lit., break forth in storms.

Poinikia

Phoenicia; Phoenician.

Pokekona

Boston.

Pokiulai

Fourth of July.

Poki₂

general name for supernatural dog after the time of Kamehameha I, said to have been taken from the name of Kamehameha's favorite dog, Boss (Eng.), which was deified and worshipped; name of a supernatural dog on Kauaʻi, said to have owned land at Lāwaʻi and Wahiawa (HM, p. 573). According to some, any supernatural animal.

Pokoliko

Puerto Rico; Puerto Rican.

Pokomaka

Potomac.

Pokukala

Portugal.

Polapola₂

Tahiti, Borabora; Tahitian.

Polapola₅

star name, paired with the star Melemele.

Polenekia

Polynesia; Polynesian.

Poliʻahu

snow goddess of Mauna Kea. lit., Bosom goddess.

Polo Ahi Lani

name of a star, said to be associated with Mūlehu.

Pololena

Florence.

Pololika

Florida.

Polo₆

star names:     Polo Ahi Lani name of a star, said to be associated with Mūlehu₂...     Polohilani var. of Polo Ahi Lani, a star...     Polo ʻUla same as Polo Ahi Lani, a star...     Polo Wehi Lani same as Polo Ahi Lani, a star...

Pope₁

Pope; papist, Catholic.

Popoki₂

name of a lua fighting stroke, said to be used by women as well as men.

Pouhānuʻu

name of a star. lit., low post.

Poʻokole

rain said to occur in the month of Welo.

Poʻolipilipi

a rain associated with Kalihi, Oʻahu, and Hilo, Hawaiʻi . lit., adzelike head, said to be so called because this heavy rain forced the people to spend so much time sleeping that their heads were sharpened as though by an adze.

Poʻonui

name of a cold, continuous rain.

poahanui

hollyhock.

poahi₁

dim, obscure.

poahi₂

to revolve, spin, go around; to rotate, of hips in a hula.

poale

• deep, open, as a hole or sore;   • absorbent.

poe pele

bellboy.

poeko

fluent, eloquent, clever and able in speaking.

poepoe honua

globe of the earth.

poepoehāwaʻe

flat sphere; oval. lit., sea-urchin round.

poepoepīkoi

oval; sphere. lit., core roundness.

poepoe₁

round, rounded, circular; compact, compressed; full, as the moon; sphere, globe; to gather together in a circle.

poepoe₂

a euphemism for penis in the phrase ʻoki poepoe, subincision, circumcision.

poe₁

round; rounded.

poe₂

a sweet potato.

poe₃

stone poi pounder.

poe₄

a fish (no data).

poe₅

boy.

poe₆

buoy.

pohala₁

• to revive after fainting, recover consciousness;   • to recover from sickness; recovery.   • relieved of worry; relief, rest,

pohala₂

to open, as flower petals.

pohe haole

the nasturtium (Tropaeolum majus) hybrids, a smooth, succulent, creeping herb, grown for its bright-colored flowers, the leaf blade round and attached near the center to the stem. It grows wild at middle elevations.

pohe kula

the Asiatic pennywort (Centella asiatica), a small, weedy creeper, with round, scalloped leaves indented at the base, and white flowers and seeds.

poheke₁

forced out, squeezed.

poheue

nether region, place of torment.

pohe₂

the marsh pennywort (Hydrocotyle verticillata), a small weed known in many parts of the world, the stem creeping, leaf blade round, scalloped, attached near its center to the stem.

pohihihi

obscure, entangled, mysterious, intricate, confused, confusing, bewildering, baffling, complex; mystery, obscurity.

pohihiu

evasive, obscure, difficult to grasp or comprehend.

poho ahi

matchbox. lit., fire container.

poho aho

container for fishing lines.

poho aniani

glass container or jar.

poho hoʻoluʻu

cup of coconut shell, gourd, or stone, containing dye for tapa.

poho kaha paʻakai

rock with a depression or dish in which salt was extracted from sea water. lit., salt-place receptacle.

poho kukui

stone lamp.

poho kuni ʻanāʻanā

small cup-shaped stone used for sorcery.

poho kāpalapala

container for tapa dye.

poho lima

palm or hollow of the hand; handful.

poho mea kanu

flower pot.

poho paka

tobacco pouch, as a tin, coconut shell, or wooden container.

poho pauka

powder container, compact, vanity case.

poho paʻakai

saltcellar, salt shaker, any salt container.

poho pāpale

inside of crown of hat.

poho pōhaku

stone bowl.

poho wāwae

hollow of the foot, instep.

poho ʻulu

a sinkhole of breadfruit trees, as on Niʻihau, where breadfruit trees were planted in holes.

pohokano

hollow stone containing kukui oil used as a lamp (Malo 63); palm of the hand (stingy).

poholalo

• underhanded, deceitful, dishonest;   • to come up from below, as an undercut blow;   • to undermine, dig under, burrow beneath,   • filch, deal dishonestly;   • to reach up from under the crotch.

poholawa

somewhat rotten, decayed.

poholelua

slow, as a vessel; unskilled, bungling, as in mechanical work.

pohole₁

• bruised, skinned, scraped; bruise, sore.   • peeled, as cooked taro;   • slipped back, as the skin of the sex organ of a man or dog;

pohole₂

Maui name for hōʻiʻo, a native fern, but larger and coarser on Maui.

poholo

• to sink, plunge out of sight, vanish;   • slip into easily,   • to miscarry.

poholopū

to slip through; too large, as a hat.

poholua₁

to billow out, as sails.

poholua₂

cavity of anus or vagina. lit., pit hollow.

poholua₃

to lie to, as a ship.

pohomōkoi

a mat design. Niʻihau.

pohona

sinking in, caving in, hollowing, as cheeks of an aged person; settling; bend, as in a U-shaped fish-hook.

pohopoho₁

patched.

pohopoho₂

same as kawakawa, a fish, so called because of black patch-like dots on its belly.

pohopoho₃

to stick out the buttocks, as in bending over to pick up something, or as a sign of contempt.

pohoʻāina

land basin.

poho₁

• hollow or palm of the hand, hollow of the foot, depression, hollow;   • container, receptacle, pouch, as for tobacco; box, as for matches;   • hollow of a canoe, divided into three parts (mua, waena, hope). .

poho₂

• mortar;   • to knead, as bread or poi.

poho₃

• patch, as in clothes;   • a wooden patch inserted into a calabash, as to mend a break;   • to patch, mend.

poho₄

• to belly out, puff out, as clothes on a line or a sail;   • to hollow or dub out, as a wooden container.

poho₆

a unit of measure equal to half a span (kīkoʻo).

poho₇

a bundle of tapa pieces (moʻomoʻo).

pohu₁

• calm, quiet;   • calmed, quieted, soothed;   • to calm down, become quiet.   cf. (For. 5:93), He pohu ko Kona, the pohu is of Kona.

pohā kaʻa

rolling stone; thunder, peal of thunder, so called because thunder was believed caused by the gods hurling stones in the heavens.

pohā kea

bursting forth of light, as dawn.

pohāpohā₁

(cf. Marquesan pohapoha)

pohāpohā₂

a kind of passion flower, called running pop (Passiflora foetida), a tropical American weedy vine, the hairy leaves commonly three-lobed; the fruit, enclosed in lacy bracts, is round, red or yellow, popping when crushed.

pohāpohā₃

a non-edible, green seaweed (Dictyosphaeria cavernosa), small, round, hollow, that bursts with a pop when stepped on.

pohā₁

• to burst, crack, break forth, crash, pop, bang;   • bursting, cracking, as of explosives or of a whip;   • to ferment (of poi);   • breaking of bubbles.   • flashing of light,

pohā₂

the cape gooseberry (Physalis peruviana), a South American perennial herb in the tomato family, growing wild. Flowers are yellow; round, orange, many-seeded fruits develop singly within the heart-shaped, papery, enlarged calyxes; they are edible raw and are also cooked for jam. called paʻina on Hawaiʻi.

pohī

to sink, settle, ebb.

pohō maʻū

a complete loss; to be such.

pohō₁

• loss, damage;   • out of luck;   • vain [futile, without value or success].

pohō₂

• bog, swamp, mire, slough;   • sunken, sinking;   • to settle, as earth.

poi maiʻa

mashed ripe bananas and water.

poi palaoa

flour poi, made by stirring flour in hot water, eaten alone or mixed with taro poi.

poiʻulu

breadfruit poi.

poi₂

boy.

pokaka

potash.

pokakaʻa

revolving, gyrating, whirling, spinning; wheel, as on a pulley or cart, swivel.

pokake

mushroom-shaped; head of the penis.

pokaʻi

to go along, as wind-blown smoke.

pokela

potter; pottery.

pokepola

phosphorus.

pokeʻo₁

child, childhood; preadolescent.

pokeʻo₃

a type of ancient prayer.

pokia

pole smeared with gum so that birds lighting on it will be caught.

pokiko

portico.

pokini

boatswain.

pokipaʻa

to bind together, as the bones of a chief for preservation and honoring.

pokipoki kua paʻa

lit., hard-backed pokipoki.

pokipoki ʻau moana

a kind of deep-water crab. lit., sea-swimming pokipoki.

pokipoki₁

a parasitic isopod found clinging to the skin, gills, fins, mouths, and tails of fish.

pokipoki₂

a gray hard-shelled box crab (Calappa hepatica), not liked as food.

pokipoki₃

sow bug, pill bug (Isopoda).

pokiwai

a drink of either warm or cold water, with sugar and cream.

poki₁

fine, as stitches or mesh; small, dainty, close together.

poki₄

boss.

poki₅

boat.

pokoke

kidney disease, urinary leakage.

poko₂

greasy cutworm, such as Agrotis ypsilon and Lycophotia margaritosa, the variegated cutworm; caterpillar.

poko₃

small division of a district, sometimes the personal lands of a chief.

polalauahi

haze, as during a volcanic eruption.

polapola₁

recovered from sickness; well, after sickness; to get well, convalesce; filling out, as after loss of weight; sprouting, as a bud.

polapola₄

flapping.

pola₁

• flap, as of a loincloth or sarong;   • tail of a kite.

pola₂

platform or high seat between the canoes of a double canoe.

pola₃

blossoms and sheath of a banana.

poleke

to have lost property by authority of a chief.

polepole₂

a child's game. The children put their clenched fists on top of each other; each child makes a wish or suggests a game to play, and sings a chant such as the following:

poli lima

center of the palm (poho) of the hand.

poli make

dead breast. fig., see poli ʻawa.

poli wāwae

hollow of the foot, instep.

poli ʻai

to nurse at the breast; a nursing breast. lit., eating breast.

poli ʻawa

a bitter breast. fig., one who has lost several mates in death.

polie

shining, gleaming; a gleam, flash of light.

polikia

tied tightly, not easily unfastened. fig., severe suffering.

polikika

political.

polikua

the dark, invisible beyond, as on beyond the horizon or in the upper stratum. lit., back bosom.

polina

resplendent, shiny black.

polinahe₁

soft and gentle, as low music or a breeze.

polinahe₂

slim-waisted and broad-shouldered.

polipoli₁

a soft, porous stone as used for polishing or for octopus lure sinkers

polipoli₂

rounded, of an adze.

poliwaiū

wet nurse. lit., milk bosom.

poliʻahu

to caress.

poli₁

bosom, breast; depression; (poetic) heart, arms.

poli₃

coconut husk attached to a fishing line.

polo wai

water polo.

polo-

an initial part of certain words referring to pandanus: polohīnano, polokā, polopeʻa, polopoloua.

polohi

smooth, as of skin.

polohina

gray, misty, smoky. fig., affectionate grief, pity.

polohiwa

dark, glistening black, as clouds or tapa.

polohuku₁

large, plump, swelling, bulging; rich, prosperous.

polohuku₂

boat hook.

polohīnano

white male pandanus bloom (hīnano) with its stem.

poloka kuea

square pole, in surveying.

polokake

slippery; wobbly; saturation.

polokalama

program, a term invented in the mid-1970s for the Hawaiian language radio program.

poloka₁

frog, toad, bufo.

poloka₂

broker.

poloka₃

broth.

poloka₄

canna (Canna indica).

poloke

broken; broke, without funds (slang).

polokika

political; politics,

polokā

ripe pandanus fruit.

polokāwaʻe₁

fish spear.

polokāwaʻe₂

pining, wasting sickness.

polokē

fresh poi.

pololei₂

a land shell (Lamellaxis), frequently followed poetically by the epithet kani kua mauna, singing in the mountain ridges.

pololei₃

fresh poi. Kauaʻi.

pololei₄

an adder's-tongue fern (Ophioglossum concinnum), a small native fern with single narrow-oblong blade, which supports one narrow spore-bearing spike about 2.5 cm long.

pololia

jellyfish.

pololo

talkative; to talk without tact.

pololoa

blundering, awkward; to go astray.

pololū

long spear.

polopeka

professor; professorial; to be a professor.

polopeʻa

thick stem of a pandanus fruit.

polopolona

musty odor; rancid, moldy odor, as of mildewed clothes; stuffy or stale smell of a room long closed.

polopoloua

unripe, growing pandanus fruit.

poloʻai

• to summon, command to appear, invite;   • to proclaim publicly.

polo₁

large, thick, plump.

polo₂

to poke, stab.

polo₃

special prayer offered to the spirits of the dead.

polo₄

var. of pololei₂, and also usually followed by the epithet kani kua mauna.

polo₅

polo.

poluea

nausea, dizziness, seasickness; hangover; seasick, qualmish, dizzy. (cf. -ea.)

poluhi

dull, sleepy.

poluluhi₂

cloudy, misty, shady.

polupolu

flabby, fat.

poluā

nausea, retching.

pomeikalana

the pomegranate (Punica granatum), an ornamental and fruit-bearing shrub from Persia.

pomekelane

pomegranate.

pomelaike

pomegranate.

pona kūpale

defense bonds.

ponanā₁

dry, arid.

ponanā₂

lame, stiff, sore, as legs.

ponapona

jointed.

ponawaʻa

circle of canoes.

pona₁

• socket;   • eyeball,   • eye socket;   • joint of sugar-cane stalk, bamboo;   • hollow, as left after a sweet potato vine has been dug.

pona₂

spotted, as the sea with various shades, variegated.

pona₃

bond.

pone

pony.

poni liʻulā

early glimmer of dawn.

poni mākuʻe

dark purple.

poni mōʻī

coronation; to crown a king or queen.

poniaka

poniard.

ponimōʻī liʻiliʻi

the sweet William (Dianthus barbatus), a relative of the carnation, grown in gardens for its abundance of small, bright-colored flowers.

poni₁

• to anoint, to daub;   • ointment, oil,   • consecrate, crown, ordain, inaugurate;   • appoint

poni₃

a variety of taro, used as medicine. The term poni may be qualified by the colors ʻeleʻele or uliuli, kea, ʻulaʻula.

poni₅

a variety of sweet potato.

poni₆

a variety of yam.

pono hale

furniture, household goods.

pono hana

tools.

pono kai lawaiʻa

fishing rights.

pono kaulike

equal rights.

pono koho pāloka

right of suffrage.

pono kīwila

civil rights.

pono paʻa mau

fixtures.

pono pilikino

private rights.

pono wai

water rights.

pono ʻuhane

spiritual welfare.

ponokalapa

phonograph.

ponokope

copyright; to copyright; to copy in any way, not necessarily properly.

ponopono₁

neat, tidy, in order, arranged, cared for, attended to, administered.

ponopono₃

comfortably well off, wealthy.

pono₂

completely, properly, rightly, well, exactly, carefully, satisfactorily, much (an intensifier).

pono₃

property, resources, assets, fortune, belongings, equipment, household goods, furniture, gear of any kind, possessions, accessories, necessities.

pono₄

use, purpose, plan.

pono₅

hope.

pono₆

careless, informal, improper, any kind of. (preceding a stem).

popela

poplar.

pope₂

poppy.

popohe

round, shapely; neat and trim, as flowers; roundness, a round or clean-cut object.

popoiwi

inside corner.

popoki₁

short, thick.

popoli

arched, curved, warped.

popopo

rot, as of wood or cloth; decay, as of teeth; moth-eaten; worm offal; rust (Bible); rotten, decayed.

popoʻi₂

overwhelm...; redup of poʻi₂, top or crest of a breaking wave; to break, of waves...

poropoleme

problem.

pou alo

house wall posts, front row of posts.

pou hiō

bent corner post, probably as supporting the ridgepole of a canoe house.

pou hoʻopaʻa lio

hitching post.

pou kihi

corner post. see illus. 1, illus. 2, illus. 3

pou kua

house wall posts, back row of posts.

pou kukuna

gable post, wall post

pou lua

shaft of the lūheʻe, octopus lure, perhaps so called because one side has a stone attached, with a cowry on the other side. lit., double shaft.

pouhana

post set in the middle of each end of the house, supporting the ridgepole. fig., support, mainstay, as of a family.

pouhananuʻu

short, stout.

poukū

cleats supporting canoe seats.

pouli₂

eclipse.

pouomanu

house post; post designating place of human sacrifice, said to be named for an ancient deity; center post. see illus. 1, illus. 2, illus. 3

pouono

fishing net.

poupou₁

short and stocky, stout, thickset.

pou₁

post, pole, pillar, shaft.

pou₂

ridge, as of nose; lump

pou₃

mast of canoe.

pou₄

machine gun.

pou₅

part of snood lashing on composite hook, as for bonitos; sometimes shaft of a hook is so called.

pou₆

spool pins on a sewing machine.

pou₈

a canoe, broad for its length and wide and blunt at the ends, used for baggage.

pou₉

an internal hardening or tumor.

powehi

dim, obscure, indistinct, vague, faint, unclear.

poʻaka

scar; mark, as of tattooing or tapa design.

poʻalani

a variety of fish (no data).

poʻana₂

weary, sore, lame, fatigued.

poʻapoʻai₂

a worm shell, a marine mollusk of the family Vermetidae.

poʻapoʻapōlā

to gad about from house to house, especially of persons who eat constantly at houses of others.

poʻaʻaha₂

the same as wauke, but the leaves commonly smaller, entire, and rounded. The leaves of wauke are commonly lobed.

poʻaʻala

to thump, as a drum with the base of the hand.

poʻa₁

castrated, emasculated; eunuch.

poʻa₂

a sudden sound, as of flapping wings of a rooster, or of the thumping sound of the palms of the hands pressed together with fingers locked, or of hands striking the surface of the water; to make such sounds.

poʻa₃

to dig under, undermine.

poʻe kūʻai

merchants.

poʻe₄

a native purslane (Portulaca selerocarpa), with narrow, succulent leaves which have many hairs in their axes and white flowers.

poʻi kalo

mulch for dry-land taro. lit., taro cover.

poʻi lani

high heavens (preceded by ke).

poʻi pō

night attack or ambuscade; to attack thus.

poʻi wai holoi

washbasin, finger bowl. lit., water container for washing.

poʻi ʻuhane

soul snatching; to snatch or capture the souls of either the dead or of living persons, as by sorcery.

poʻikū

overpowering, as love.

poʻimalau

Portuguese man-of-war (Physalia).

poʻipoʻi

redup. of poʻi₁, to cover...; poʻi₄, to catch between cupped hands, to pounce, snatch...; poʻi₅, to mound up...;... to conceal, as property that one does not want to share with others, or as a secret; to cover up, as the truth; to smother, as a fire; to hush the wailing of a child.

poʻipū₁

• to cover over entirely, as of clouds or engulfing waves;   • to attack, overwhelm; onslaught, attack.

poʻipū₂

a kind of tapa.

poʻiu

afar, very high, of high rank, glorious, sacred.

poʻi₁

cover, lid; to cover (preceded by ke.)

poʻi₃

container, basin, as for liquids.

poʻi₄

to catch between cupped hands, as a small bird or butterfly; to pounce, as a cat on a mouse; to snatch.

poʻi₅

to mound up, hill up.

poʻo hina

gray- or white-haired; ash-colored.

poʻo hou

symbol of a paragraph. lit., new heading.

poʻo hoʻolewa

a very taboo chief whose shadow might not fall on himself or on any other person; he was carried about at night. lit., carried head.

poʻo huaʻi

splitting headache.

poʻo huku

top point of a hill, ridge; sharp tips of ridges of a file or rasp. lit., protruding head.

poʻo hulu

chief featherworker for a chief, a hereditary office.

poʻo huna

hidden, mysterious, invisible, as the gods.

poʻo kanaka

human head, skull.

poʻo kepa

hair cut in an extraordinary manner, as of one in mourning in the old days, with only part of the hair cut. lit., sideways head.

poʻo keʻokeʻo

white-haired; platinum blonde.

poʻo kihikihi

cocked, as a hat; angular, as a head.

poʻo koʻi

adze-headed, a term of ridicule for one with a sharp or projecting forehead; also an insulting term for evil sorcerers, so-called because they were "frequently" beheaded.

poʻo kuakea

gray-haired. lit., bleached head.

poʻo kumu

school principal. lit., teacher head.

poʻo lau

leaf base; butt end of a leaf.

poʻo lua

child sired by other than the husband, but accepted by both husband and sire; this acceptance increased the number of relatives of the child who gave their loyalty to him as kinsmen; it thus fostered the prestige of children of chiefs; translated "adulterous" in the 1843 Bible (Mar. 8.38) , but changed in later editions.

poʻo luluhi

lit., tired head.

poʻo maunu

bait remainder.

poʻo niuniu

dizzy head.

poʻo noʻo

a thinker, a thoughtful head.

poʻo nui

hangover, worried head, worry; to be a "headache" or source of trouble.

poʻo paʻa

hardheaded, stubborn, obstinate, unreasonable, set in one's ways.

poʻo pepe

flathead, a name for lesser gods.

poʻo puʻu

bulging head; hilltop. fig., sullen, unsocial person.

poʻo wai

water source or head, dam.

poʻo ʻōpae

shrimp head, an opprobrious term because the shrimp's excretory organs are said to be in its head.

poʻohala

to carry on the virtues, arts, and skills of the family. lit., passing on the head.

poʻohiwi₁

shoulder.

poʻohiwi₂

wing of the body (manu) of a kite.

poʻohū₁

wound, swelling, as on the head.

poʻohū₂

prolonged resonance, as of a gong or as heard after striking a certain kind of stone.

poʻokanaka₁

a variety of watermelon. lit., human head.

poʻokanaka₂

Kohala name for pansy.

poʻokaʻeo

bent over, as in carrying a heavy load.

poʻokela

foremost, best, superior, prime, outstanding, greatest, supreme, utmost, superlative; champion; to excel.

poʻokiʻekiʻe

high beads, a name for the great gods, Kāne, Kana, and Lono.

poʻokiʻi

mask, jack-o'-lantern. lit., image head.

poʻokoi

envied.

poʻokoʻi

sorcerer.

poʻoleka

postage stamp. lit., letter head.

poʻoleka kaua

war-savings stamp. lit., war stamp.

poʻolima

a half note (music). lit., arm note.

poʻolā nui

a native species of koʻokoʻolau (Bidens cosmoides), on Kauaʻi only, with yellow flowers 5 cm across.

poʻolānui

young stage of dragonfly, between the larval stage (lohelohe) and adulthood (pinao); beggarticks. lit., great sun head.

poʻolā₁

stevedore. lit., sun head.

poʻolā₂

the few Hawaiian varieties of small native trees (Claoxylon sandwicense), in the euphorbia family, with soft wood, large oblong, toothed leaves, small clustered flowers, the fruit a three-parted capsule.

poʻomahiole

crest, as of a bird. lit., helmet head.

poʻomana

an eighth note (music). lit., branching note, named for the stem mark.

poʻomanakolu

a thirty-second note (music). lit., triple branching note.

poʻomanalua

a sixteenth note (music). lit., doubly branching note.

poʻomanaʻo

topic, title, theme, heading, headline; subtitle, as of law. lit., thought heading.

poʻomuku

cut off, severed, shortened.

poʻonui₂

top-heavy, as a house.

poʻopalaoa

a kind of white shell (no data). lit., ivory head.

poʻopaoʻo

name for highest tip of the canoe endpiece.

poʻopaʻa

hawkfish (Cirrhites pinnulatus), about 10 to 22cm long with large scales on body and small scales on face, colored in blotches of blue, brown, and red with white vertical bars; eaten raw, broiled, or salted and dried. lit., hard head. Also ʻoʻopu kai, ʻoʻopu poʻopaʻa, pilikoʻa.

poʻopoʻohina

Both names on Niʻihau.

poʻopoʻo₁

• sunken, as eyes of a sick person;   • indented, deep (as a bay penetrating the coastline);   • nook, cranny.

poʻopuaʻa₁

head pupil in a hula school. lit., pig head, so named because the head pupil provided a pig or pig-head offering. cf. (UL 29).

poʻopuaʻa₂

image of a pig, carved of wood such as kukui, placed on the stone heap marking the boundary of an ahupuaʻa land division.

poʻopuaʻa₃

offering.

poʻopāpale

a drooping crest, as of some birds. lit., hat head.

poʻopūʻali

any depression in the head, as a sunken temple.

poʻouli

honeycreeper (Melamprosops phaeosoma), discovered in 1973 by Tonnie Casey and James Jacobi, upper Hāna rainforest, Maui, named by Kawena Pukuʻi. lit., black head.

poʻou₁

wrasse (Cheilinus rhodochrous). Varieties are qualified by the colors kea and ʻula.

poʻoʻele

quarter note (music). lit., black full note.

poʻoʻole

illegitimate. lit., no head.

poʻoʻōlelo

title, as of an article; text, as of a sermon. lit., speech heading.

poʻo₂

a whole note (music).

poʻo₃

• depression, cavity;   • to dip, scoop, hollow out, dub, erode, dig;   • to splash, as water by scooping the base of the palm;   • to make a squeaky sound by placing one hand against the armpit of the opposite arm, and pressing that arm against the hand;   • to make a noise by snapping the lips with the fingers.

Puaahi

name of a star. lit., fire flower.

Puahiohio₂

wind, Nuʻuanu, Oʻahu.

Puakaiāulu

rain name. probably same as Kaiāulu.

Puakauahihaehaekamanu

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the smoke blows, the birds rage.

Puakaʻilima

Howland Island, a name used by Hawaiian guano diggers there in about 1856. lit., the ʻilima flower. see song, (Pukui-Korn 80–2).

Puanakau

the star Rigel, tutelary star of West Maui.

Puanane

name of a star.

Puaʻakāhuluhulu

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the pig strikes body hair.

Pua₈

a Molokaʻi sorcery goddess... A Molokai sorcery goddess of possession with human and mudhen (ʻalae) forms. It was believed that if an ʻalae flew over a house crying at night, trouble would follow. lit., rising [as smoke] .

Puepelo

Pueblo.

Puhi-ʻula

name of a legendary eel; according to one authority, a Conger cinereus eel. lit., red eel.

Pukikī₂

a tight-waisted dress, supposedly worn once by Portuguese.

Pulelehua Kea

the Greater Magellanic Cloud. lit., white butterfly.

Pulelehua Uli

the Lesser Magellanic Cloud. lit., dark butterfly.

Pulema

Burma.

Pulo Eʻe Moku

Bureau of Emigration. lit., bureau for boarding ships.

Pulo Hoʻolaha lʻa

Bureau of Fisheries.

Pulukalia

Bulgaria, Bulgarian.

Pulukelina

Brooklyn.

Pupue₂

name of a star in the constellation Kaulua.

Pupūhale

rain famous at Hāmākua, Hawaiʻi. lit., [rain] remaining [near] house.

Puʻukapele

same as Puʻupele, the name of a wind at Mānā, Kauaʻi.

Puʻukaʻala

wind, Mt. Kaʻala, Oʻahu.

Puʻukōlea₂

wind associated with Kapaʻau, Hawaiʻi.

Puʻulena

name of a famous cold wind at Kīlauea, Hawaiʻi and at Puna.

Puʻunahele

wind associated with Waipā, Kauaʻi. lit., forested hill.

Puʻuokona

wind associated with Kuliʻouʻou, Oʻahu.

Puʻupā₃

a lua fighting stroke.

Puʻuwai Laʻahia

Sacred Heart.

Puʻuwepa

name of a star (no data).

pu kihi lua

double-barreled gun

pua Pākē

a genus (Chrysanthemum) in the daisy family, including many species of ornamental annual and perennial herbs, with small to large flower heads, which are white to red, yellow, or purple. Most species are from the Eastern Hemisphere.

pua Pākē pihi

dwarf pua Pākē, a genus (Chrysanthemum) in the daisy family...

pua aheahe

to blow gently; light, as work.

pua ahi

to glow like fire. For figurative use see koʻikoʻi.

pua aliʻi

descendant of a chief.

pua ehu

to blow spray or dust.

pua hala

bright yellow base of a pandanus (hala) key that may be used for leis.

pua hau₁

blossoms of hau, a tree.

pua hau₂

yellow, as a malo.

pua hilahila

the sensitive plant (Mimosa pudica var. unijuga), a low, spreading American plant, with round pink flower heads. The leaves, compound, with many small leaflets, droop and close when touched. lit., bashful flower.

pua hipa

lamb.

pua hōkū

a tropical American herb (Laurentia [Isotoma] [Hippobroma] longiflora), 30 to 60 cm high, with few or no branches, with long, narrow, lobed leaves, and starlike flowers with 7.5 cm long tube. The plant is related to the lobelias. It is poisonous, especially to stock. lit., star flower.

pua hōkū hihi

the waxflower (Hoya bicarinata), an ornamental vine from Samoa, Tonga, and Fiji, in the milkweed family. Leaves are thick, broad-oval, paired, at their bases bearing short clusters of waxy, fragrant, white and pink, star-shaped flowers used for leis. lit., entangled star flower.

pua iʻa

fish spawn.

pua kalaunu

the crown flower (Calotropis gigantea), a large shrub, native from India to the East Indies, belonging to the milkweed family. The crown-shaped flowers, white or lavender, are commonly used for leis, and the plants for hedges in dry areas. called liliʻu on Niʻihau.

pua kala₁

the beach or prickly poppy (Argemone glauca), a Hawaiian species closely related to a southern United States species, a gray, prickly plant with stiff, lobed, toothed leaves and fragile, white-petaled flowers. Formerly, Hawaiians used the yellow juice to relieve pain. lit., thorny flower. also kala, naule, pōkalakala.

pua kala₂

a native prickly lobelia (Cyanea solenocalyx), a shrub with large ovate or oblong, prickly leaves and hairy, purple flowers, found in gulches of Molokaʻi.

pua kala₃

the spear thistle (Cirsium vulgare), a coarse, prickly European weed, 60 to 150 cm high, with large, spiny, lobed leaves, and dark-purple, spiny flower heads about 5 cm.

pua kaʻaona

dart made of the stem of sugar-cane tassel smoked reddish-brown (kaʻaona).

pua kepalō

Bougainvillea. lit., devil flower [so-called because of thorns]. Hawaiʻi.

pua kukui

blossoms of kukui.

pua kāhala

small kāhala, a fish.

pua kī

flower of the ti.

pua kīkā

cigar flower.

pua kō

stem and tassel of sugar cane (the stem was used in making hats).

pua laha ʻole

a choice and rare flower. fig., a beloved person. lit., flower not widespread.

pua lahilahi

single flowering. lit., thin flower.

pua lani

descendant of a chief.

pua lei

flowers for leis; cherished blossom or child.

pua lēʻī

flower that attracts many (lēʻī), as a lehua that attracts birds.

pua maka nui

lit., large-eyed flower.

pua makahiki

annual flower.

pua male

a kind of vine (Stephanotis floribunda), in the milkweed family, from Madagascar. It has oval, leathery, paired leaves and clustered, fragrant, white, tubular flowers, which are sometimes worn by brides in Hawaiʻi. lit., wedding flower.

pua niu₁

coconut flower.

pua niu₂

color of the coconut flower; ivory-colored.

pua nānā honua

a tree (Solanum auriculatum syn. S. carterianum) native to Madagascar and tropical Asia, related to the tomato, having large, downy, oblong leaves, and blue flowers clustered at branch tips. lit., flower looking [at] earth.

pua nānā lā

the common sunflower (Helianthus annuus), a coarse annual herb, 1 to 4.5 m high, from the western United States. It is a member of the daisy family and has flower heads from 8 to 35 cm across, the yellow ray florets surrounding a brown-purple center. lit., flower looking [at] sun.

pua pepa₁

the everlasting or straw flower. lit., paper flower.

pua pepa₂

Bougainvillea (Bougainwillea spectabilis). Niʻihau.

pua pihi

all kinds of zinnias, especially one (Zinnia elegans), a Mexican annual grown ornamentally for the flowers. The flower heads are 5 to 13 cm across, single and daisy-like, or double and somewhat round, and of various colors. In Hawaiʻi is also found a wild species (Z. pauciflora), from Mexico and South America, with 2.5 cm-wide, single flower heads, the central florets yellow, the rays yellow, red, or purple. lit., button flower.

pua pilipili

the Spanish clover (Desmodium uncinatum), a South American herb, long established in Hawaiʻi. It is good fodder. The plant is 30 to 90 cm high, each leaf having three ovate leaflets with a light area along the midrib. Flowers are small, pink or whitish, pea-shaped. Pods are narrow, flattened, chainlike, 2.5 to 5 cm long, clinging to clothing and animals. also kīkānia pipili.

pua puaʻa

piglet.

pua pupupu

double flowering.

pua āholehole

young āholehole (young stage of the āhole, Hawaiian flagtail)

pua ʻanuhe

lit., caterpillar flower.

pua ʻehu

to shine brightly, as reddish flowers.

pua ʻena

to glow brightly.

pua ʻilima

ʻilima flower; eaten as a mild cathartic, especially by children.

pua ʻole

same as ʻāwela, a flowerless (pua ʻole) sugar cane.

pua ʻulaʻula

natal grass (Rhynchelytrum repens), grown for forage; highly ornamental.

puaaneane

extremity of life, extreme old age.

puaea

to expire, breathe one's last.

puahala

design in tapa and patchwork quilts.

puahala₁

a medium-sized bowl, as used for serving poi, named for a supposed resemblance to a pandanus key (pua hala).

puahala₂

a variety of sugar cane.

puahekili

one of the native loosestrifes (Lysimachia hillebrandii). lit., thunder flower.

puahia₁

spry, quick.

puahia₂

hazy, gray.

puahina

gray.

puahio

to come and go swiftly, as a puff or gust of wind.

puahiohio₁

whirlwind, gust. fig., worthless talk.

puahuku

a term of contempt; perhaps literally rising octopus head; said also to refer to erections not followed by satisfaction.

puaināwele

thin, weblike, weak.

puaiohi

small Kauaʻi thrush (Phaeornis palmeri).

puakai₂

red of tapa or malo dyed with noni juice (Malo 49); a red tapa used in kuni ceremonies.

puakala₁

to assume the appearance of kala seaweed, said of octopus in the sea.

puakala₂

a kind of crab.

puakauhi

Kauaʻi.

puakawaihae₁

a variety of taro.

puakawaihae₂

a variety of sweet potato.

puakea₁

pale-colored, especially a tint between white and pink, as sunset clouds; the color of a buckskin horse.

puakea₂

to spread, as a ship's sails or as fog.

puakelekino

a spiny climbing vine (Caesalpinia sepiaria) from India, first grown in Kaʻū, Hawaiʻi, by Father Celestino. lit., Celestino flower.

puakiʻi₁

thin, skinny.

puakiʻi₂

to take, as without permission.

puakoali

a tapa colored by beating in sandalwood.

puakī₂

a young eel.

puakī₃

a red seaweed (Liagora decussata), somewhat calcified but flexible, branched; not edible; related to pāpaʻakea.

puakōʻula

red, as lehua blooms.

pualalea

clear, bright.

pualau

to carry on the hip, as a child.

pualele₁

the sow thistle (Sonchus oleraceus), a weedy herb in the daisy family, from Europe. It is 30 cm tall or more, the leaves narrow, lobed, toothed, the flower heads clustered, yellow, about 3 cm in diameter. The light seeds are tipped with hairy tufts. The plant is sometimes fed to pigs and the leaves eaten by people during famine.

pualele₂

a weed (Emilia fosbergii, misidentified as E. javanica). Niʻihau. cf. (Neal 854–5).

pualena₁

yellow color; to appear yellow, as said of dawn or muddy water.

pualena₂

lazy; to loll about.

pualewa

unsettled, unfixed, always on the move; upset stomach.

pualiʻi₂

kind of tapa used for loincloths and sarongs.

pualu₁

a species of surgeonfish (Acanthurus xanthopterus and A. mata), up to 15 and 20 cm in length and brown or dull-gray in color. It resembles the palani in tough skin and strong smell but may be distinguished from the latter by a blue line across the soft part of the fin.

puamana

caret sign of omission.

puanaiea

weak, sickly.

puanaʻī₁

front of the neck and throat.

puana₂

pronunciation, utterance.

puana₃

to surround, encompass, crowd.

puanea

mournful.

puanihi

young taro, taro tops.

puaniki₁

to bind tightly.

puaniki₂

small wooden bowl, as for an individual serving of poi.

puaniu

a tapa dyed with coconut, probably oil; a tapa dye.

puaokalani

false daisy (Eclipta alba). lit., flower of the chief [or heaven]. Niʻihau.

puaokama

a gourd (Sicyos niihauensis), first collected and identified by H. St. John. cf. kūpala and (Neal 808).

puapoʻo

comb or crest of a bird, as of a chicken. lit., head issue.

puapua moa

tall feathers of a chicken.

puapuamoa₁

long-tailed dinner coat.

puapuamoa₂

a kind of adder's-tongue fern (Ophioglossum pendulum), found in Polynesia westward into Madagascar, commonly growing on trees. It has ribbon-like fronds, erect or bent and hanging, 60 cm long or less, some bearing short, narrow, spore-filled spikes.

puapuanui

a variety of banana.

puapuaʻi

to pour continuously or often.

puapua₁

• tail feathers, as of a cock;   • rump, as of a chicken;   • streamer;   • coattails;   • this word is used as a means of avoiding answering questions:

puapua₃

spike in the back of sphinx moths.

puapua₅

a variety of banana.

puawa₁

same as pua awa, young awa, fish.

puawa₂

Niʻihau.

puaʻa hame

ham.

puaʻa heʻa

blood-stained pig, hence a sacrificed pig, also said of human sacrifice.

puaʻa hinu

greasy pig. fig., human sacrifice.

puaʻa hiwa

a solid-black pig, much desired for sacrifice.

puaʻa holo honua

the Tahitian name for horse, perhaps used at one time in Hawaiʻi. lit., pig runs [on the] ground.

puaʻa hulu ʻole

hairless pig, a figurative name for taro leaves, since they might sometimes replace pig as sacrifice.

puaʻa kai

certain fish (as āhole, ʻamaʻama, ʻanae, humuhumunukunukuāpuaʻa, kūmū, pualu) used as substitute for pig offering. lit., sea pig.

puaʻa kau

hog offered as sacrifice.

puaʻa kumulau

sow, pig who has borne young.

puaʻa kāne

boar.

puaʻa laho

boar; term of reproach for a lecherous male, named for the pig demigod, Kamapuaʻa. lit., scrotum hog.

puaʻa lau

name for plants that might replace pig in some sacrifices, a favorite being young taro leaves. Others were ʻamaʻu, hāpuʻu, kūkaepuaʻa, kukui, olomea, and ʻuhaloa. They were considered the plant forms of the pig demigod, Kamapuaʻa. lit., leaf pig.

puaʻa māiki

small pig.

puaʻa nui huelo huluhulu

horse (old name, Lānaʻi). lit., big animal hairy tail.

puaʻa ohi

a young female pig that has not borne young.

puaʻa olomea₁

a striped pig.

puaʻa olomea₂

poetic name for the olomea, a tree. Kamapuaʻa took this form when pursued by Pele.

puaʻa pipi

early name for cattle when brought to the islands by Vancouver. lit., beef (Eng.) pig.

puaʻa pūkoʻa

spotted pig. lit., coral head pig.

puaʻa wahine

sow.

puaʻa wāwae loloa

human sacrifice...

puaʻa ūkō

pig offering at the death of a chief as a plea to the ʻaumākua gods to receive the spirit of the departed. lit., fulfillment pig.

puaʻa ʻehuʻehu

red pig, a poetic name for ʻāmaʻumaʻu, ferns. The demigod Kamapuaʻa took this form when he ran from Pele to the forest of ʻamaʻu ferns and turned into a fern himself.

pūwahanui

a medicinal plant (no data).

pūwai

a sentinel's call of alarm, a trumpet call, as in war.

pūwaʻawaʻa

stupid.

pūwelawela

warm, hot.

pūwā

to shine, glitter, reflect brightly, as a night fire.

pūʻai

to share a little food, take potluck.

pūʻalalā

to scream, shriek, cry out, bleat; to cry loudly like a baby.

pūʻalaʻa

short for puʻu ʻālaʻa, heap of small taro tubers.

pūʻala₂

overcooked, as taro.

pūʻali inu wai

temperance league. lit., water drinking host.

pūʻali kaua kaʻi wāwae

infantry. lit., war army proceeding afoot.

pūʻali kaua lio

cavalry.

pūʻali koa

armed forces, troops, regiment, brigade, corps.

pūʻali koa hoʻohanohano

honor guard.

pūʻali koa lio

cavalry. lit., horse-soldier army.

pūʻaliʻali

of varying thickness, as a cord or ʻilima lei not carefully woven.

pūʻali₁

• warrior, soldier, so called because Hawaiian fighters tied (pūʻali) their malos at the waist so that no flap would dangle for a foe to seize;   • army,   • host, multitude.   Various types of military formations are listed below.

pūʻali₂

• to gird tightly about the waist, as of malo-clad warriors, or as corseted women; tight belt.   • compressed, constricted in the middle;   • grooved, notched; notch;   • irregularly shaped, as taro;

pūʻali₃

isthmus.

pūʻali₄

slender abdominal stalk on a wasp's body.

pūʻali₅

in music, a decrescendo followed by a crescendo.

pūʻali₆

irregularly shaped ravine.

pūʻali₇

a vague term for an adopted man or boy who had no servants.

pūʻalu

loose, slack; crumpled, crinkled, as ruffles.

pūʻao₁

mesh about 0.5 to 1.3 cm wide, of mats.

pūʻao₂

womb.

pūʻau

ti-leaf blossom stem.

pūʻawa₁

young white pandanus leaves that are good for plaiting.

pūʻawa₂

bitter; bitterness.

pūʻikaʻika₁

difficult to acquire or do.

pūʻikaʻika₂

packed, crowded.

pūʻilihāluʻa

pūʻili design with one or more hāluʻa ridges or strips between the panels of the beater.

pūʻilikoʻeau

pūʻili and koʻeau designs combined.

pūʻiliʻili₂

to collect.

pūʻili₁

bamboo rattles, as used for dancing.

pūʻili₂

to clasp, hold fast in the hand, embrace, grasp firmly.

pūʻili₃

a type of tapa-beater pattern: tips of zigzag ridges in adjacent surfaces meet and form sunken lozenges. cf. koʻeau, in which the ridges are parallel.

pūʻili₄

berry of the pōpolo plant.

pūʻili₅

a game played with sugar-cane flowers.

pūʻiwaʻiwa

to shy, as a horse; excitable, as a horse that is easily frightened.

pūʻoheʻohe

Job's-tears (Coix lachryma-jobi), a coarse, branched grass closely related to corn, growing in many tropical regions, either wild or cultivated. It is an annual, .3 to 1.8 m high, with long, pointed leaves, and, at stem tips, hard, round, beadlike seeds—black, gray, or white—which are used for leis, mats, food, medicine.

pūʻoleolē

conch horn.

pūʻoʻa

• tower, steeple, pyramid, peak;   • house for depositing a corpse;   • peaked hut, lean-to, tent.

pūʻukiʻuki

• crowded,   • packed tightly,   • difficult.

pūʻukuʻuku

wee, tiny, small.

pūʻula

a seaweed.

pūʻulaʻula₁

red hill, earth bank (short for puʻu ʻulaʻula).

pūʻulaʻula₂

red.

pūʻulu kaua

army, fighting band, division, phalanx.

pūʻuluʻulu

to collect.

pūʻulīʻulī

a variety of small gourd, as used for making feather gourd rattles (ʻulīʻulī), medicine cups (ʻapu), and individual poi containers.

pūʻā hipa

flock of sheep.

pūʻā pipi

herd of cattle.

pūʻāʻā₁

scattered, dispersed; to flee in disorder and fright.

pūʻāʻā₂

bundles, sheaths; to tie many; to besiege frequently.

pūʻāʻī

Adam's apple (probably from puʻu ʻāʻī, neck lump).

pūʻā₁

flock, herd, drove; to flock.

pūʻā₂

• sheaf, bundle, as of grain or fuel that is not wrapped; to tie in bundles,   • binder, bind.   • bunch,   • package;   • clump, as of sugar cane (Kel. 116);

pūʻā₃

to feed by passing directly from mouth to mouth, of masticated food such as fish or poi; infants and the aged were fed thus.

pūʻā₄

to cut crosswise.

pūʻā₅

to besiege. (pua in (2 Sam. 11.1) of the 1843 Bible was changed to pue in later editions; cf. puʻe)

pūʻōniʻoniʻo

a shell (Partridge tun).

pū₁

• large triton conch or helmet shell (Charonia tritonis) as used for trumpets;   • any wind instrument, as horn, trumpet, cornet. The instrument may be distinguished from other pū by the qualifier hoʻokani, sounding.

pū₁₀

a variety of sweet potato.

pū₁₁

inactive, sluggish, quiet, dejected, bored (often following noho).

pū₂

gun, pistol.

pū₃

general name for pumpkin or squash.

pū₄

tree, cluster of several stalks, as of bananas [pū maiʻa], pandanus [pū hala], or kava [pū ʻawa]; clump, as of sugar cane [pū kō]. (always precedes a noun).

pū₅

head of octopus or squid.

pū₆

canoe endpiece, both fore and aft.

pū₇

• coil of hair, topknot of hair; to form a topknot.   • to coil;   • rope or line, as attached to sticks in an ʻōpelu net;   • rope attached to the front of an unfinished canoe to haul it to the shore;   • olonā string used in the game pū kaula;   • snotter holding the end of the sprit of a sail;   • to gather in, as sails;

pū₈

to divide by lot: pebbles or seeds were placed under a tapa, and divided unseen into heaps, and the players drew to get the largest heaps.

pū₉

to eat a little, share potluck, said in a humble invitation, as:

u-₁

prefix to some words to denote plural, as   uhaele, plural of haele, to go, come   ulawaiʻa, to fish, of many persons or often   unoho, plural of noho₂, to live, reside...; noho₃, to possess, as of a medium...   unonoho, plural and frequentative of unoho...   uʻai (to eat), uheʻe (to slide; melt; hang down), uhele (to go), uhohoʻi (to leave, return often), uhoʻi (to leave), uhole (to peel), uholo (to run), uhoni (to kiss), ukaʻawale (to separate), ulakolako (to supply), unaue (to move), upiʻi (to go up)...   (This u- is sometimes written as though forming a word with a preceding o, imperative marker, as Ou haele oukou, you go.

u-₂

prefix to many words with meanings ‘quality or state’; there is variation in some words of u-, ʻu-, and ʻū, especially in rare words. see:   uahi, smoke... (ahi, fire...)   uhaki, to break... (haki, break...)   uhemo, loose, separated... (hemo, loose, separated...)   ʻuhene, snicker... (hene, happy or joyous sound...)   uhinu, oil, grease... (hinu, oil, grease...)   ʻūlika, soft, sticky... (leka, sticky, slimy... [?])   ʻuwaʻa, dig a furrow... (waʻa, canoe...)   and others... uhaʻi, ukali, unahe, uoki, ʻūhini, ʻūkeʻe, ʻūlina, ʻūmalu, ʻūpoho, ʻūkele, ʻūlepe, ʻūliʻi, ʻūmelu, ʻūpī, ʻūpili, ʻūpoʻi, ʻuhane, ʻukemu, ʻuwehe, ʻuwā, ʻuwalu, ʻuwaʻu, ʻuweke, ūpē, ūkō...

Uaakalīpoa

name of a fine, cold rain. lit., rain by the līpoa seaweed.

Uahiapele₅

a wind associated with Kīlauea, Hawaiʻi.

Ualehu₃

wind name, Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

Uamakalaukoa

name of a rain at Nuʻuanu, Oʻahu. lit., rain amid the koa tree leaves.

ua hānai

rain that nurtures the earth.

ua lanipili

a heavy rain, as one lasting for days and days, or a cloudburst.

ua limua

a period of constant rain. lit., mossgrowing rain.

ua noe

misty rain, fog.

ua ona o

aforementioned (often before names of people).

ua pūnohu

a red rain in the sunshine.

ua ʻawa

cold, bitter, drizzling rain. fig., hard experience.

uahi

• smoke; smoked;   • dustlike, spraylike; dust, spray, wisps.

uahi lepo

dust wisps.

uahi wai

mist, spray, steam. lit., liquid spray.

uahi ʻawa

pungent sulphur smoke, as from a volcano. lit., bitter smoke.

uahiapele₁

a native variety of sugar cane, heavy-stooling, light red-purple, the nodes hairy-fringed, the internodes sausage-shaped.

uahiapele₂

several varieties of taro described at Puna, Waipiʻo, and Kona, Hawaiʻi.

uahiapele₃

a variety of sweet potato.

uahiapele₄

a tree (Pelea barbigera), endemic to Kauaʻi, with opposite, elliptical leaves, conspicuous for their smoky-gray color. It is related to the mokihana.

uahoa

hard, severe, harsh, indifferent to the distress of others.

uai

to move, as an object;   • to push aside;   • to move from place to place, as a tethered animal;   • sliding, as a door;   • opening and shutting;   • to be dislocated, as a joint.

uaiki

offspring of a chief and a mother of no rank. lit., little rain.

uakea₁

mist (famous at Hāna, Maui). lit., white rain.

uakea₂

white as mist, mist-white, white as breaking surf or snow.

uakeʻe

bend, crook, as in a path.

uaki hoʻāla

alarm clock.

uaki pūlima

wrist watch.

uakoko₁

a low-lying rainbow. lit., blood rain.

uakoko₂

a rain so heavy that it turns stream waters red-brown with the wash of the hillside.

uakoko₃

reflection of rainbow colors in the clouds.

ualeha

lazy.

ualehe₁

loose, loose-fitting, as a dress; sitting with the knees wide apart; stretching the mouth, as in a grimace.

ualehe₂

wary of a hook, as a fish once caught and having escaped.

ualehe₃

to oust a tenant from his land and deprive him of the fruit of his work; to evict.

ualehu₁

gray, ashy-gray.

ualehu₂

a variety of taro.

ualei

to spread out, as a fish net.

uananahuki

tapa beater.

uaneʻi

short for auaneʻi₂, probably not, especially after words ending with -a. cf. (Oih. 5.39) .

uaoa

light rain, mist.

uapo

wharf, pier, quay, dock, bridge.

uauahi

smoky-gray color, as of tapa; gray quality, as of a whitened sugar-cane leaf; smoky, hazy; a reddish-blue tapa.

uauakaha

stiffness of the cords of the neck.

uaua₁

tough, sinewy, glutinous, viscid, leathery; not easily broken, as cord. fig., hardheaded, willful, obstinate, tough-minded. (For a rare use of uaua as a noun, see ʻīlioholoikauaua.)

uaua₂

a variety of taro. The name may be qualified by the terms ʻeleʻele, keʻokeʻo, mōlina, piko.

uauoʻa

distant sound, as of blended voices.

ua₂

aforementioned, the one talked of. ua is often followed by a noun and nei, here, or lā, there, and is used idiomatically (see ua o, ua ona o, mea₆ ).

uea hakahaka

wire screen; screen, as on windows. lit., space wire.

uea kelepona

telephone wire.

uea kukū

barbed wire.

uea maka ʻupena

chicken wire. lit., net-mesh wire.

uea moana

undersea cable.

uea poepoe

smooth wire. lit., round wire.

uea ʻōlelo

telegraph wire. lit., speaking wire.

ueaʻole

wireless.

uene₁

to move back and forth, oscillate.

uene₂

to break wind slightly.

uene₃

name of a string figure.

uepa₁

wafer.

uepa₂

whip.

uepa₃

wax seal, as used on envelopes; to seal.

ueue

to wriggle, squirm.

ue₁

to jerk, pull, twist, pry, turn, sway.

ue₂

a hula step: the caller announces the step to drummer (who changes the beat) and dancers by calling e ue (e imperative and ue). The right foot is extended forward with toes pointing, while both arms are brought forward to chest level with hands crossed and fingers tipped upward; the left hand stays up, while right arm and foot swing back in an outward arc. Then the right arm and foot are moved forward, and the step is repeated to the left. Then three short steps are taken forward. In the last step the left hand is forward, and the right foot and arm back. To do this step.

ue₃

tall, far apart. rare except in proper names.

ue₄

a kind of mat, made without stripping the pandanus leaves.

Uhumakaliʻi

a stroke in lua fighting. (containing reference to ocean dwellers (EH))

uha

large intestine, alimentary canal, colon. cf.   uhahemo, hemorrhoids   uhalehe, same as wahalehe, fig., to exaggerate. lit., wide mouth   uhalena, lazy, overstuffed with food. lit., lazy colon   uhanui, fat, weak. lit., big colon   uhaʻula, lazy, good-for-nothing.

uhahemo

hemorrhoids.

uhaiāholo

to pursue or run swiftly; to pass swiftly, as time.

uhakeʻe

crooked, as a road.

uhakole

to strain in an effort to evacuate the bowels. fig., disobedient, stubborn. lit., red colon.

uhaku

to put together, roll up.

uhakē

broad, wide.

uhalalē

obese.

uhalena

lazy, overstuffed with food. lit., lazy colon.

uhalu

to deplete.

uhalula₂

lazy.

uhanui

fat, weak. lit., big colon.

uhao₂

cone-shaped base from the kāhili staff to the first feathers, formerly of feathers, later also of silk or ribbons.

uhao₃

tenderloin.

uhau hili kinipōpō

batter (in baseball).

uhau ʻupena

to strike with a net, as a bird-catching net on a long handle.

uhauhakō

used as medicine the name may have been uhau.

uhauhui

presentation of a prayer, especially in ʻanāʻanā sorcery; to present such a prayer.

uhauhumu

to sew together, as sails; to lay together, as stones in a wall; to interlock.

uhau₂

var. of hahau₂,   • to offer a prayer or sacrifice;   • to lay before...

uhaʻi₂

covering for door opening, doorway frame.

uhaʻula

lazy, good-for-nothing.

uhe

offering place for fish on a heiau; to offer, as fish.

uheheu

to fly or hurry as though on wings (ʻēheu).

uhelehe

sulky, annoyed, vexed.

uheule

weak, imbecilic, impotent (an epithet applied to men).

uhi Niʻihau

a variety of yam, the tuber with pink flesh; grown in Kona, Hawaiʻi.

uhi hoʻonohonoho

a variety of yam.

uhi kalakoa

a variety of yam, the tuber with mottled red and white flesh and white skin; grown at Hāʻena, Kauaʻi.

uhi keʻokeʻo

a variety of yam, grown throughout the islands; tuber with white flesh and skin.

uhi lehua

a variety of yam, grown in Kona, Hawaiʻi, having a tuber with pinkish flesh, the vine stem with red wings. Perhaps the same as uhi ʻulaʻula.

uhi maka

veil, mask.

uhi moe

bedspread.

uhi pela

bed sheet, mattress cover.

uhi poni

a variety of yam, the tuber with red skin and red and white flesh; grown on the island of Hawaiʻi.

uhi pākaukau

tablecloth.

uhi pūkuʻi

hub cap.

uhi ʻuala

a variety of yam, the tuber like a sweet potato; grown on the island of Hawaiʻi.

uhi ʻula

a yam, probably the same as uhi lehua.

uhi ʻālela

a variety of yam, the tuber having white flesh and skin; grown in Puna, Hawaiʻi.

uhi ʻāpana

patchwork cover or spread.

uhikino

body covering, garment, shield.

uhina

covering; throw or cast net.

uhipaʻa

mother-of-pearl hook that might be used at any time of day. lit., solid cover.

uhipū

apoplexy.

uhiuhi₂

an endemic legume (Mezoneuron kauaiense), a tree with pink or red flowers and thin, broad, winged pods (Neal 435). The wood is hard and heavy and formerly was used for hōlua (sleds), spears, digging sticks, and house construction. also kāwaʻu₅, kea, kolomona, and the weedy herb Phaseolus lathyroides (Niihau).

uhiwai₁

heavy fog, mist. lit., water covering.

uhiwai₂

type of tapa.

uhiʻāpana

to debate, argue.

uhi₁

• covering, cover, veil, film, lid; to cover, spread over, engulf, conceal,   • solid tattooing,   • tent (Puk. 26.12) ;   • overwhelm;   • to don, as a feather cloak.   • fig., to deceive, hide the truth.

uhi₂

large, bluish-brown birthmark.

uhi₃

the yam (Dioscorea alata), from southeast Asia, a climber with square stems, heart-shaped leaves, and large, edible, underground tubers. The plant is widely distributed through islands of the Pacific, where it is commonly grown for food. (HP 166–172), (Neal 230). In the past botanists have applied the name uhi incorrectly to the hoi kuahiwi.

uhi₄

mother-of-pearl bivalve, mother-of-pearl shank.

uhi₅

turtle shell piece used for scraping olonā.

uhi₆

mark made by the gall of raw pūpū ʻawa (a shellfish) on tapa or on the skin as an ornament. tattoo (NKE12)

uhole

to strip, as tough skin of fish such as manini, humuhumu.

uhu pākali

an uhu fish used as a decoy. fig., to deceive.

uhu₁

the parrot fishes, of which Scarus perspicillatus is among the most abundant and largest; uhu are plant eaters, the teeth are strong and beaklike, well fitted for clipping off food from coral. The name may be qualified by the terms aʻa, ʻāhiuhiu, ʻahu ʻula or ʻula, ʻeleʻele, halahala, kualakai or pālukaluka, lā uli, pānoa, piko ʻula, and uliuli. Name of growth stages are ʻōhua (very young), pānuhu or pōnuhunuhu (medium), and uhu (mature). Variant names are male and ʻōmale for a young stage. The colors of this fish are so pretty that it is sometimes compared to a sweetheart:

uhu₂

a variety of sugar cane.

uhu₃

to bolt, break away, as a horse; to pull, strain, chafe under restraint; willful, headstrong.

uhāuhā

to pant, puff, as a dog or as the wind.

ui kula Sābati

Sunday school catechism.

uia

a variety of taro.

uifi

whiff.

uihā

weary, tired, bored, tiresome, burdensome.

uilani

• to chafe under control, irritated by restraint;   • fret;   • restless,   • constantly seeking pleasure,   • spirited,   • flighty.

uilo

square-shaped braid, as in lei palaoa cord.

ui₁

to ask, question, appeal, turn to for help or advice, query; question, catechism.

ui₂

to stir up, activate.

Ukalialiʻi

the planet Mercury. lit., following the chief [i.e., the sun].

uka lāʻau

forested uplands.

ukalekale

• watery, fluid.   • fig., deceitful.

ukali haʻiinoa

noun complement.

ukali haʻiʻano

adjective complement.

ukali₁

• to follow, come after, succeed, attend, accompany, escort;   • follower, attendant;   • complement, as in grammar;   • reserve.

ukamu

oakum.

ukaukai

fat, feeble.

ukikiʻi

to fetch, of several.

ukione

extreme unction.

ukiuki

• anger, resentment (FS 129); angry, annoyed, offended, vexed, displeased (2-Sam. 6.8) , irritated, peeved; petulant.   • to hate (Kin. 50.15) ;   • fierce,   • adverse, as a wind;

ukokole₁

sore, inflamed, as eyes.

ukokomo

to enter together.

ukoʻo

a human sacrifice or pig substitute, as made after a chief was a victim of sorcery, in order to protect the living.

uku hala

penalty for wrongdoing; to pay for wrong done, as damages. Sugar cane, as halāliʻi, used in ceremonies for the remission of sins might be so called.

uku hana

wages, salary, pay for work; to pay wages.

uku hapa

installment payment; to pay in part.

uku hoʻomau

pension, alimony. lit., permanent pay.

uku hoʻopaneʻe

interest, usury; to pay interest.

uku hoʻopaʻa

premium, as insurance; down payment, deposit. lit., payment [to] solidify.

uku hoʻopaʻi

fine, forfeit.

uku hoʻēmi

cheap or reduced price, discount.

uku kaulele

interest on principal, premium, extra or overtime pay. lit., payment added on.

uku kaʻa

carfare, transportation charge.

uku keu

extra pay, bonus, left-over pay.

uku komo

entrance fee.

uku komokina

commission (pay).

uku koʻakoʻa

coral polyp.

uku kula

school tuition.

uku kuwala

interest payment, bounty.

uku kākoʻo

subsidy, monetary aid, grant-in-aid.

uku kīpē

bribe, to bribe.

uku kūmau

customary or usual fees; dues, taxes.

uku kūʻike

cash payment.

uku lawelawe

tip, gratuity, service charge. lit., service pay.

uku leka

postage, postage stamp.

uku liʻiliʻi

installment payment, small payment.

uku makahiki

annual payment or salary, annuity.

uku makana

tip; gift payment, bonus.

uku male

dowry; marriage fee, as to the minister. lit., marriage payment.

uku manawa

installment payment; to pay on time.

uku moku

steamship fare.

uku palu

lit., soft uku.

uku pohō

damages; to pay damages.

uku pānaʻi

refund, redemption, ransom, reward; to redeem, refund.

uku ʻēkena

agent's fee, commission.

ukuhina

a pouring out, dipping, weaning.

ukuhi₁

to pour out, dip, as water. (-hi is a transitivizer and a reflex of PPN -fi; cf. Tongan ʻutu, to pour, and (Gram. 6.6.4))

ukuhi₂

to wean, as a child.

ukupau

piece labor, pay by the job rather than according to time, as on sugar plantations; used in pidgin for any work that everyone should pitch in gladly to finish; contract labor. lit., finished pay.

ukuwai₁

place in the grass house where host and guests visited, between the sleeping place and the door.

ukuwai₂

name for that portion of a canoe between forward and after outrigger booms.

uku₂

a deep-sea snapper (Aprion virescens).

Ulima

Urim.

Uliulikapaliokahikinui

a stroke in lua fighting. lit., the cliffs of great Tahiti are green.

Uliuli₃

name of a star (no data).

Uli₂

name of a goddess of sorcery, said to have come from Kahiki... called by Emerson (PH 146) the arch-goddess of sorcery, she was invoked by Hiʻiaka in her prayers of resuscitation for Lohiʻau. (PH 144–7).

Uluau

a wind associated with Waiākea, Hawaiʻi.

Uluaunui

name of a stormy Maui wind.

Ulukoa

name of a star.

Ulukou₁

site of the Moana Hotel, Waikīkī, Honolulu.

Ulukou₂

an old name for Howland Island. lit., kou tree grove.

Ululoa

name of a star, said to appear on the night of Muku in the month of Māhoe Mua.

Ulumano

a strong wind blowing from a given direction in each locality, as a strong southeast wind in Kaʻū and Puna, Hawaiʻi, and at Kāneʻohe, Oʻahu. lit., blowing hard.

Uluʻoa

(see (Gram. 2.9) for alternation of glottal stop and k)

ula ahi

fire flames.

ula pāpapa

a gray crayfish (Parribacus antarcticus). lit., flat ula.

ulana₁

to plait, weave, knit, braid; plaiting, weaving.

ulana₂

still, calm.

ulana₃

prophecy of a seer (kilokilo); to prophesy.

ulawaiʻa

to fish, of many persons or often.

ula₁

spiny lobster (Panulirus marginatus and P. penicillatus). Varieties are qualified by the terms hiwa, koaʻe, and poni.

ula₂

a flame; to flame, blaze.

ule hilo

gonorrhea.

ule hole

pulled back penis (an insulting epithet for men).

ule kahe

subincised or circumcised penis.

ulehala

aerial pandanus roots.

ulehelehe

unbound, unfastened, not tied, as a bundle; open, as a wound.

ulehole

channel markers in a harbor.

ulele₁

to leap at, get into action, do quickly, do at once; one moving swiftly.

ulele₂

to set, as type.

ulepaʻa

a male who has not known a woman; not to have or have had relations with a woman. lit., bound penis.

ulepuaʻa

lit., pig penis.

uleule₁

pendulous, hanging.

uleule₂

sty, as on the edge of the eyelid.

uleʻohiʻu

a type of sugar cane, unknown in 1978, once used as a salve (For. 5:585); perhaps the same as ʻāwela melemele and uluhui.

uleʻulu

male breadfruit flower. lit., breadfruit penis.

ule₁

penis. For imaginative compounds see ʻaʻawa₁, ʻaweule, ulehala, ulehole, ulepaʻa, ulepuaʻa, uleʻulu.

ule₂

tenon for a mortise; pointed end of a post which enters the crotch of a rafter (also called maʻi kāne).

ule₃

to hang.

uli koa

bruises or wounds of a warrior.

ulia

accident; sudden; to come upon suddenly.

ulihi₁

a small endemic shrub (Phyllostegia glabra and varieties), in the mint family. Leaves are ovate, 7 to 15 cm long; flowers are small, white, tubular, abundant, in racemes.

ulihi₂

feebleness, of old age.

uliuli₂

a kind of rock from which adzes were made.

uliʻeo

fitness, aptitude; preparedness, as for running.

uli₁

• any dark color, including the deep blue of the sea, the ordinary green of vegetation, and the dark of black clouds;   • the black-and-blue of a bruise.   Some song composers avoid this word because connotations of evil or misfortune are associated with darkness and because Uli is a goddess of sorcery (see Uli₂).

uli₃

early stage in the development of a foetus, as the body begins to form.

uli₄

name given by (Malo) for subjects of the chief; (Emerson) says they are black-haired persons.

uli₅

to steer; steersman.

uli₇

crowing of a cock.

uli₈

type of sweet potato (no data).

ulu hānau

of the same age group, contemporary, lit., birth growth.

ulu hōkū

constellation.

ulu imu

to stir up an oven.

ulu kanu

garden patch.

ulu kau

unexplained acquisition of prophetic and interpretive powers without visible possession by a god. lit., placed inspiration.

ulu koko

first victim slain in battle.

ulu kukui

candlenut grove.

ulu manu

flock of birds.

ulu moku

fleet, collection of ships.

ulu niu

coconut grove.

ulu pali

talus slope, transitional slope between cliffs and base.

ulu pono

to grow well; progressive, thriving, successful.

ulu pua

flower garden, growth of flowers.

ulu wale

• to grow easily or without care;   • spontaneous.

ulu waʻa

fleet of canoes.

ulua aukea

a variety of ulua, probably Caranx ignobilis, one of the largest of ulua. also ulua kea.

ulua kihikihi

a variety of ulua, Alectis sp.

ulua kāniʻo

lit., striped ulua.

ulua kūkaenalo

probably a species of ʻōmilu, a fish. lit., beeswax ulua.

ulua paʻopaʻo

see paʻopaʻo.

ulua ʻeleʻele

a variety of dark-skinned ulua, probably most commonly Caranx melampygus. lit., black ulua.

ulualono

genealogist in the hale nauā.

uluamahi

officer in the hale nauā.

ulua₁

certain species of crevalle, jack, or pompano, an important game fish and food item. cf. ulua aukea, ulua ʻeleʻele, and paʻopaʻo. Unidentified ulua are qualified by the terms kaha uli, kihikihi (or kihi or huli pū), lā uli, mahai, mohaʻi (AP), nuku momi, uli. Growth stages are pāpio (or pāpiopio), pāʻūʻū, and ulua, the last attaining a length of 1.5 m and a weight of over 45 kilos. This fish was substituted for human sacrifices when the latter were not available, probably because of word magic and the meaning of ulua₂. Since an ulua replaces a man, ulua also means "man, sweetheart," especially in love songs.

ulueki

brush, undergrowth, forest.

uluhaka

elevated place in the high chiefʻs house where those of rank might rest.

uluhaʻo

rough, jagged, as rocks.

uluhe

all Hawaiian species of false staghorn fern (formerly known as Gleichenia spp., now listed under three genera: Dicranopteris, Hicriopteris, Sticherus), weedy, creeping, branching ferns, forming dense thickets.

uluhe lau nui

a large species of false staghorn fern (Hicriopteris pinnata, formerly known as Gleichenia glauca).

uluhua

vexed, annoyed, discouraged, displeased (1-Nal. 20.43) , harassed, weary, offended, angry, upset.

ulukai

water chestnut. lit., sea growing.

ulukū

disturbed, upset, restless, depressed, nervous, agitated, perturbed; nervousness, agitation; to disturb.

ululele

a chiefʻs favorite.

ululā

ostrich (RSV), owl (KJV).

ulumāhiehie

festive, attractively adorned and arrayed; to make a fine appearance, decorated, pleasing.

ulunahele

wilderness, place of wild growth.

uluna₁

pillow, cushion, formerly made of pandanus; to use as a pillow (Kin. 28.18) . headrest (e.g. dentist's chair) (HE).

uluna₂

upper part of the arm.

uluna₃

center part of a net, as of a large ʻupena iheihe, (net used for iheihe fish).

uluoʻa

upright, erect.

ulupau

to gather together; to go everywhere.

ulupiʻi

to shiver, shake, tremble, as with cold or fright.

ulupuni

overcome by emotion, hysteria, passion, or an occult influence.

ulupē

intoxicated.

ulupō₁

dark or dense as growth.

ulupō₂

sudden sickness or stroke, the sign of which is a cock crowing at untimely hours; such crowing was also believed to indicate the arrival of visitors or a ship.

ulupō₃

a fish said to resemble the pāpiopio.

uluulu lei

leis offered to the gods.

uluulu₁

growing things.

uluulu₃

tangled, snarled, snagged, mussed, ruffled, frayed; angry, violent, agitated.

uluulu₅

diving or scoop net, its mouth being held open with two sticks.

uluulu₆

sea cavern.

uluulu₇

to munch.

uluwehi

lush and beautiful verdure; a place where beautiful plants thrive; festively adorned. lit., decorative growth.

uluāhewa₁

mania, delusion, craziness; deranged; somewhat crazy, sometimes believed due to possession by a spirit.

uluāhewa₂

overgrowth; to grow wild and lush; bushy.

uluāoʻa₁

• confusion,   • mob,   • disturbance, riot;   • tumult;   • gathered in excitement and confusion.

uluāoʻa₂

jungle; growing in wild profusion.

uluʻeo

name recorded by (Thrum) for a tree with hard wood.

uluʻālana

offering, especially as made to priests for them to offer to the gods.

ulu₂

• possessed by a god; inspired by a spirit, god, ideal, person, as for artistic creation;   • stirred, excited;   • to enter in and inspire.

ulu₃

• grove (see     ulu kanu, garden patch     Ulukou, an old name for Howland Island. lit., kou tree grove.     ulu kukui, candlenut grove     ulu lāʻau, forest, grove of trees     ulu niu, coconut grove);   • assemblage, collection, or flock, as of     ulu hōkū, stars [constellation]     ulu manu, birds [flock]     ulu moku, ships [fleet]     ulu waʻa, canoes. [fleet]

ulu₅

stick used in spreading hot oven stones; to spread the stones.

ulu₆

kind of tapa made at Waipiʻo, Hawaiʻi; name of a quilt design.

ulu₇

center, as of a canoe or net.

ulu₈

a name used repeatedly in (For. 5:703–9) for Kaweloʻs warriors whose names begin with Kaulu (Kaulukauloko, Kaulukauwaho).

ulāheo

to appear and disappear quickly, as steam.

umalei₁

apoplexy, stroke.

umauma

chest, breast. fig., heart, character.

umaumalei

a fish similar to but darker than the palani or pualu. It has bright orange-red spots around the gills and side fins and at the base of the caudal fin where the spike is set. lit., lei [for the] chest.

uma₁

hand wrestling: each tries to force his opponentʻs hand to the mat; to push, press, grip; to pry, as a lever.

uma₂

stern of a canoe.

uma₃

curve.

umo

to moo, bellow; to bark, of seals; mooing.

umu

oven, furnace (Ezek. 22.20) ; a heap of rocks placed in the sea for small fish such as the manini to hide in: this was surrounded by a net and the fish were caught. More commonly called imu.

umu ahi

fire pit.

umu lepo

earth oven.

umu pao

Hawaiian oven built above the ground...

Unulau₁

a wind famous in song noted on Kauaʻi, West Maui, and Niʻihau; according to (Emerson) (UL 196), the trade wind.

Unulau₂

name of a star.

unahe₁

light breeze.

unahe₂

a foliose lichen (Parmelia perlata).

unahi

scales of a fish; scaly; to scale.

unahi kalakala

rough scales, especially from midbody to tail of certain fishes; scute.

unahi pōhaku

lichen growths on stones. lit., stone scales.

unahinahi

many scales.

unahipipi

young pipi shellfish.

unahipiʻi

cracked and peeling, of the soles or heels of the feet.

unahiuhu

a variety of sweet potato.

unana₂

wee, tiny.

unana₃

a bird (no data).

unana₄

a plain.

unauna

hermit crabs in general.

unaunahi

to scale, of fish.

una₁

shell of turtle or tortoise, carapace.

una₂

same as haha kā ʻupena (net gauge or spacer) so called because some were made of turtle shell.

una₄

dice.

une

• lever;   • lever on a sewing machine that raises or lowers the presser foot;   • to pry.   • fig., to urge, disturb, harass.

une kī

shift lever for bobbin winder of a sewing machine.

unea

nausea, exhaustion.

unele

honk of a goose; to honk.

uneune ʻūhā

a kind of sitting wrestling with thighs of contestants shoved back and forth. lit., prying thigh.

unikalio

Unitarian.

uniona

union, labor union.

unoʻo

scorched, partly consumed by fire, inflamed.

unu pehi ʻiole

rat-pelting pebble, insulting epithet for a person of no consequence.

unuhi kūlike loa

literal translation; to make such.

unuhi laulā loa

free translation; to make such.

unuhi pili

close, literal translation; to make such.

unuhi ʻōlelo

to translate or interpret; translator, interpreter.

unuhina

translation.

unuhi₁

to take out, withdraw, as money from a bank, or a drawer from a desk; to unsheath, extract; to take off, as a ring.

unuunu hoʻouluʻai

agricultural heiau.

unuunu₁

• to singe, as the feathers of a chicken before dressing it, or the hairs of a pig or dog by rolling it over hot oven stones;   • to pluck, as feathers from a fowl.

unuunu₃

stick erected as a taboo sign.

unuunu₄

young ʻōhiʻa timber, as used in making images.

unu₁

• small stone, pebble,   • stone chip;   • wedge,   • prop.

unu₂

altar, heiau, especially a crude one for fishermen or for the god Lono.

unu₅

name given for a section of canoe endpiece.

unā

fatigued, weary .

uoa₂

name given for an unknown disease, characterized by aching shoulders.

uoi

to move along, of many; to slouch along together.

uoki

idiom used only in commands. Stop it! Quit! Don't touch! Be careful! (see ex., hāmama)

uolo

to call out; a loud calling.

uouoa

a fish (Neomyxus chaptalii), known as the false mullet or false ʻamaʻama, distinguishable from the true mullet by its narrower and tapered mouth and creamy rather than silvery pectoral fins. The head, when eaten, was supposed to cause sleeplessness and nightmares.

uoʻo

tough.

upai

tall, thin.

upaʻapaʻani

to play together.

upupā

sandpiper; lapwing (KJV), hoopoe (RSV).

uwalo

to call out, as for help; to resound; a call.

uwaʻuwali

soft, limp, weak.

uweka

dirty, bleary, as the eyes.

uweko

bad-smelling, musty.

uwenewene

unclean in habits.

uāniʻi

stiff, as salted fish; stiffness.

uē helu

a wailing call of grief and love, recounting deeds of a loved one and shared experiences; to weep and speak thus. lit., enumerating weeping.

uē kanikau

to wail; wailing prayer.

uē leo nui

to cry loudly, bawl.

uē ʻalalā

to wail loudly, yelp.

uē ʻino

to cry loudly; tantrum.

uē₂

to salute, greet...

uō

to bellow, roar, shout loudly, howl.

uʻauʻa

a tapa dyed as with ʻōlena (turmeric) or noni.

Wahineʻōmaʻo₂

the companion of Hiʻiakaikapoliopele on her trip to Kauaʻi to fetch Lohiʻau for Pele. lit., green woman.

Waia₂

name of a star.

Waia₃

a son of Hāloa noted for corruption and sin. lit., dishonor.

Waikini

San Joaquin.

Waikīkī

place name used as a direction marker in Honolulu. lit., spouting water.

Waikōloa

cold wind associated with Mt. Kaʻala, Oʻahu, and the nearby place of the same name.

Wailau

place names on Hawaiʻi, Kauaʻi, and Molokaʻi.

Waileia

name of a morning star.

Wailoa

name of a star near the Pleiades, said to be a member of the group called Kaulua. It is also said to be a name of an ancient chief. lit., long stream.

Wailuku

a West Maui city, site of a late eighteenth century battle. lit., destructive water.

Waimea

a place name. lit., reddish water.

Wainaku

star name, sometimes called the patron star of Hilo.

Waiolohia

a Kauaʻi wind.

Waipaoa

cool breeze famous at Waimea, Kauaʻi. lit., scooped water.

Waiuli

name of a wind, Honolua, Maui.

Waiʻaleʻale

name of the highest mountain on Kauaʻi.

Waiʻōpua

name of a pleasant breeze at Wailua, Kauaʻi. lit., water of cloud banks.

Wai₂

place names beginning with Wai-, river, stream.

Waka₃

a moʻo guardian in many stories. She had moʻo, human, spider, and eel forms. As guardian of Lāʻieikawai in Paliuli, she prepared for her a house thatched with feathers (HM 526, 529). As guardian of Hinakekā, or equated with her, she floated as a gourd in the sea and was taken into Wākea's canoe (HM 219).

Wakikana

Vatican.

Wakinekona

Washington.

Walawala₂

rain name.

Waleweki

Warwick.

Wale₃

Wales, Welshman; Welsh.

Wanakoua

Vancouver.

Waʻahila

a rain in Nuʻuanu and Mānoa Valleys and the name of a ridge separating Mānoa and Pālolo Valleys. see saying, puʻipuʻi.

wae ʻana

selection, choice; nomination (EH)...

waele

to weed, clear, remove grass or weeds.

waena moku

amidships.

waenakonu

center, middle, midway.

waena₂

cultivated field, garden, vegetable plot.

waewae

selective.

wae₁

• to choose, select, pick out, nominate;   • sort, discriminate, separated, cull,   • to draft, as soldiers;   • to preen, as of a chicken;   • finicky, fussy;   • to reflect, meditate;   • appointment.

wae₂

u-shaped canoe spreader.

wae₃

leg.

wae₄

rib of a ship.

waha haukaʻe

smeared mouth; smutty-mouthed, evil-tongued.

waha kale

to drool at the mouth, talk excessively, gush; one who does so.

waha kole

garrulous, noisy, boisterous and obstreperous in speech; such a person; to rant.

waha koʻu

garrulous, clucking mouth; to gabble.

waha lapalapa

to scold, utter scathing remarks; one who does so. lit., blazing mouth.

waha lina

finicky, of eating. lit., tight-mouthed; such a person.

waha mana₁

voice of authority, person in authority. lit., powerful mouth.

waha mana₂

one who digresses from subject to subject; to digress. lit., branching mouth.

waha nui

a big mouth; to talk too much, tattle; tattler.

waha pala

a coated mouth, said in derision of an ignoramus, especially one who does not know the chants honoring his chief.

waha pilo

halitosis; foul mouth.

waha pio

to be unable to speak; not to dare to speak, speechless. lit., imprisoned mouth.

waha puʻu

protruding lips; unintelligible speech, as of one who has had a stroke. lit., lumpy mouth.

waha wale

deceitful, lying. lit., slimy mouth.

waha wali

glib-tongued.

waha ʻawa

a bitter (ʻawa) and sadistic person who makes impulsive vindicative statements about the one he hates, attempting to strike at his weaknesses or guilts, and usually predicting misfortune that often comes true.

waha ʻā

sharp-tongued, rude; to speak heatedly and rudely. lit., burning mouth.

waha ʻō koko

to slander one's own blood. lit., mouth that pierces blood.

waha ʻōlelo

spokesman, mouthpiece, herald; speaking mouth.

wahaheʻe

to lie; lying, deceitful, false; a lie, liar. lit., slippery mouth.

wahalehe

wide open, as a door; too large, as the neck of a dress. fig., to exaggerate. lit., wide mouth.

wahamana

screen, shutter.

wahapaʻa

to goad, tease, banter; argumentative. lit., hard mouth.

wahawai

to talk glibly, brag. lit., watery mouth.

wahaʻohi

to talk in a foolish, silly, senseless manner; such talk; such a talker.

wahaʻula

to nibble and pick at food without appetite. lit., red [sore] mouth.

waha₂

neck of a dress.

waha₃

to carry on the back, as a child; a load so carried.

waha₄

square notch cut in the upper part of house posts, in which the wall plates (lohelau) were placed; tenon.

wahi hana

workshop, place to work.

wahi hilahila

private parts.

wahi hoʻomalu

shelter.

wahi hoʻopau pilikia

toilet, rest room.

wahi hoʻāhu ʻōpala

dump, garbage pile.

wahi hānai holoholona

cattle ranch.

wahi kaʻawale

vacant place, vacancy.

wahi kiaʻi

lookout.

wahi kū moku

anchorage.

wahi lulu

shelter.

wahi moe

bed (Hal. 132.3) , place to sleep.

wahi mālama pipi waiū

dairy.

wahi noho

dwelling place, address.

wahi nānā

lookout.

wahi pana

legendary place, sacred place, sacred site, cultural site... .

wahi puhi ahi

crematory, incinerator.

wahi waiho lole

clothes hamper.

wahieokeola

lignum vitae (Guaiacum officinale), a small tree from tropical America, with heavy, hard wood, useful for many purposes. The resin yields medicine and stain. The tree is also ornamental, each leaf with two or three pairs of rounded leaflets, the flowers blue and clustered, the fruits yellow and heart-shaped.

wahieʻekeʻeke

upper stroke in club fighting.

wahie₁

fuel, firewood; to serve as firewood.

wahie₂

stroke in spear or club fighting.

wahine hana

female servant.

wahine hiʻu iʻa

mermaid. lit., fish-tail woman.

wahine hoʻowahine

platonic wife, an old Hawaiian relationship. lit., pretended wife.

wahine kapu

taboo woman, goddess (specifically Pele — not a woman who might not have sex relations, as some believe).

wahine kaua

fighting woman, woman in the armed services, Amazon.

wahine kāne make

widow. lit., woman with dead husband.

wahine kāne ʻole

spinster, woman without a husband, single woman.

wahine kāpulu

untidy woman, slattern.

wahine maikaʻi

a gray lichen.

wahine makua

older woman; older sister-in-law or female cousin-in-law of a man.

wahine male

married woman, bride, wife.

wahine manuahi

mistress, common-law wife...

wahine mālama kapa

wardrobe mistress.

wahine noho kula

an endemic shrub (Isodendrion hawaiiense) in the violet family, having the petals equal and without spurs. lit., woman dwelling [on the] plains.

wahine noho mauna

an endemic fern (Adenophorus tamariscinus), with finely subdivided narrow-elliptical fronds 10 to 40 cm long, growing on trees and on the ground. lit., mountain-dwelling woman.

wahine o ka pō

wife of the night. Similar to kāne o ka pō but less common.

wahine ʻole

without a wife or sweetheart; bachelor.

wahine ʻōpio

young woman; younger sister-in-law or female cousin-in-law of a man.

wahine₂

plant names. (see table above).

wahi₂

some, a little, a bit of.

wahi₃

to say, according to (usually followed by the possessive a or by a zero-class possessive and not preceded by either verb or noun particles).

wahu

to take without consent, as food at a feast; to ensnare, trap.

wahuwahū

to interlock arms, as while walking.

wahāwahā

• to treat with contempt, scorn, despise,   • abhor,   • ridicule;   • be disgusted,   • defy.

wahī

wrapper, envelope, case, covering, sheath; a ti-leaf bundle; to wrap, cover, bundle up, fold up, roll up, swathe; to dress, as a wound.

wahī lawe pepa

brief case.

wahī makaaniani

glasses case.

wahīʻeha

bandage.

wai Lūkini

perfume. lit., Russian liquor, so-called because musk was obtained from Russians in early days, the wet product being perfume. deoderant (KAN).

wai ahu

pool of water.

wai aka

water showing a reflection; name of a Nuʻuanu pool.

wai aliʻi

chiefly water; royal liquor, gin (in Kalākaua's song, Koni au).

wai aniani

crystal-clear water, artesian water.

wai anuhea

tepid water, neither hot nor cold.

wai au

swirling water of a current.

wai ea₁

aerated water.

wai ea₂

small house at the entrance of a heiau temple, where the ceremonial cord (ʻaha) was stretched.

wai ea₃

sea water used for purification. lit., water of life.

wai ehu

spraying water.

wai hau

ice water.

wai hili

water obtained by shaking the dew or rain drops from the leaves of plants or trees, as was said to have been done in dry areas. lit., hit water.

wai hoʻoheheʻe

digestive juice.

wai hoʻohui

water color.

wai hoʻomaʻemaʻe

disinfectant; any kind of cleaning liquid, cleansing liquid, liquid soap.

wai hoʻāno

Holy water.

wai hua

water-drop caught as in a taro leaf, much liked for purification and medicine, as it has not touched the earth. also called wai ʻapo.

wai huikala

water for purification.

wai hānai

small well from which brackish water was taken and poured into shallow pools called wai kū; this water later was placed into shallower pools and allowed to evaporate, leaving the salt. Kauaʻi.

wai hī

water oozing as from a precipice or trickling down. lit., purging water.

wai hōʻaʻala

toilet water, liquid spice, scented extract. lit., liquid that perfumes. perfume.

wai hū

gushing spring, overflowing water.

wai inu

drinking water, potable water.

wai kahi

united, of one dye.

wai kai

brackish or salty water.

wai keʻokeʻo

leucorrhea. lit., white liquid.

wai koʻana waiū paka

buttermilk.

wai kula

gold-colored.

wai kī

water in which tea has been brewed, tea.

wai kō₁

water with a strong current.

wai kō₂

sugary water.

wai lani

rain water, especially as used for medicine and purification.

wai laulau

water carried in folded taro leaves.

wai lemi

lemon juice, lemonade, limeade.

wai lāʻau₁

sap of plants.

wai lāʻau₂

liquid medicine.

wai mea ʻino

slop.

wai meli

honey. lit., bee liquor.

wai mimi

urine.

wai momona

soda water, sweet water.

wai niu

coconut water or cream (the distinction was not clear; cf. kai niu, wailewa).

wai nui

a large flow of water; excessive flow of saliva; to flow in great quantities, juicy.

wai pahū

spouting water, geyser.

wai paʻakai

salty water, brine.

wai paʻipaʻi

mixed liquid, solution, or drink of any kind (lama paʻipaʻi is more common for alcoholic drinks).

wai piula

water from a faucet.

wai piʻi

rising water, overflow of water, flood (Ier. 46.7) ; to flow, overflow.

wai piʻipiʻi

charged water, bubbling water.

wai pua

honey from flowers.

wai puhia

wind-blown water or spray, as of a waterfall; name of the "upside-down" waterfall in Nuʻu-anu Valley.

wai puna

spring water. fig., a sweetheart.

wai pūʻolo

water in leaves, as of taro, that could be carried; coconut water. lit., bundled water.

wai pūʻolo i ka lau lāʻau

an ancient name for ice. lit., water in a package of tree leaves, so called because ice was said to be brought down from the mountains in leaves.

wai ua

rain water.

wai welawela

warm or hot spring.

wai ʻapo

water caught in a taro leaf, often used in ceremonies as it was regarded as pure in not having touched the ground. fig., a beloved mate, spouse. lit., caught water.

wai ʻauʻau

bath water; bathing place or pool. A figurative use follows:

wai ʻawa

poisoned or bitter water; bitter. fig., same as poli ʻawa.

wai ʻeli

well water, well. lit., dug water.

wai ʻihi

sacred blood, as of royalty. fig., prominent, royal.

wai ʻona

intoxicating liquor or spirits.

wai ʻono

honey, sweet liquid.

wai ʻula

red liquid, blood, menstrual flow; rain runoff red with soil.

wai ʻōhiʻa

juice or cider of mountain apples; cider in general; tomato juice.

wai ʻūlili

to fix firmly.

waiakua

distant, aloof, unsociable, exclusive, as of a chief too high to mingle with others. lit., godly blood.

waianiani

a variety of Molokaʻi sweet potato.

waianuʻukole

name of a soft porous stone, as used in medicine or for octopus sinkers.

waiawī

the yellow strawberry guava (Psidium cattleianum f. lucidum), a small tree, like the waiawī ʻulaʻula in many ways but bearing larger, yellow fruit.

waiawī ʻulaʻula

the purple strawberry guava (Psidium cattleianum), a small tree from Brazil, with smooth bark, smooth, shiny, obovate leaves about 5 cm long. The purplish-red fruit is round, about 2.5 cm in diameter, and has white pulp, good to eat raw or made into jam or jelly, tasting like strawberries.

waia₁

disgraced; shame, dishonor.

waiehu

a file; formerly a rough stone used to grind and polish.

waihae

agricultural land term commonly used in the 1840s, especially on Maui; meaning unknown.

waihau₁

a heiau where hogs, bananas, and coconuts were sacrificed, but not human beings; a heiau for moʻo spirits.

waihau₂

a small, tight bundle; to do up in such a bundle.

waiho akaaka

to lie or place in full view; easily seen, obvious.

waiho kāhela

to lie widespread before one.

waiho loa

to abandon completely, give up.

waiho mahi ʻole

to lie fallow.

waiho maʻi

to lie sick, remain sick.

waiho ola

to spare the life, to remain living.

waiho wale

to leave without reason; to leave about carelessly; to set aside as useless; to neglect, to expose to view.

waiholomoku

flood.

waihona

depository, closet, cabinet, vault, file, receptacle, savings, place for laying up things in safe-keeping; internal organs of the body, funds, treasury; fiscal. (wai₄ + iho, directional, + -na, nominalizer.) Numerous types of waihona are listed below.

waihona hoʻomanaʻo

memory.

waihona hoʻonanea

playroom, parlor; private rooms of the captain of a ship.

waihona ipu

cupboard, place to keep food containers; bases supporting bath basins in Solomon's temple.

waihona keiki

womb.

waihona kukui

candlestick, lamp stand.

waihona kupapaʻu

burial vault.

waihona kālā

treasury, money depository, fund; fiscal. lit., dollar depository.

waihona lako kaua

arsenal, arms depository. lit., war goods depository.

waihona lānahu

coalbin.

waihona mea laʻa

place for sacred objects; treasure.

waihona meli

honeycomb.

waihona moni

place for keeping money, treasury.

waihona noʻonoʻo

mind, mentality.

waihona palapala kahiko

archives. lit., depository of ancient documents.

waihona panakō

bank account, depository.

waihona pā ipu

cupboard.

waihona waiwai

treasury, depository for goods, property; treasurer.

waihona ʻāina

position of the land, lay of the land, position of the earth, landscape, panorama, scenery, topography.

waihonaʻike

intelligence.

waihonaʻōpala

dump, garbage container.

waihā

water upon which the breath (hā) of the priest has been expelled in order to impart mana; to give mana by breathing upon an image or person; to request earnestly in prayer.

waiiki

a kidney disease that impedes urination. lit., little water.

waikahe

stream (Hal. 124.4) ; to flow, overflow, as a stream. lit., flowing water.

waikanaka

having ways of ordinary folk. lit., human pattern.

waikaua₁

a war temple.

waikea

juice of fresh kukui nuts, as mixed with fresh or brackish water and used as an enema. lit., white liquid.

waikoʻolihilihi

tears that seem to cling to eyelashes. lit., liquid supporting eyelashes. Poetic.

waikulu

alcohol.

waikālā

quicksilver, mercury; silver, silver-colored. lit., silver liquid.

waikī₁

gun.

waikī₂

enema of a concoction consisting of the juice of the poisonous gourd, water, salt, and other matter, drastic and painful. cf. the more mild waikea.

waikī₃

gonorrhea, of males; painful urination, perhaps due to cystitis.

waikī₄

one whose father was a chief but whose mother was not, a term of contempt.

waikōʻihi

waterspout.

waikūlonoʻakoʻakoʻa

an old name for syphilis.

waikūoa

dart, as for war.

wailana₁

calm, quiet, as the sea; still water.

wailana₂

• banished, as for unworthy conduct;   • exile.   (perhaps wai₄, to leave, + -lana, nominalizer)

wailana₃

a prayer uttered to free a taboo period.

wailau₁

large leaf bundles of food, as poi, for carrying.

wailau₂

an ancient variety of tapa.

wailena

bile. lit., yellow water.

wailewa

coconut water. lit., hanging water. see riddle, lewa₁.

wailiʻiliʻi

a decorated tapa. lit., small colors.

wailiʻulā₁

mirage.

wailiʻulā₂

of changing color, as taffeta or a stone; taffeta.

wailua₁

spirit, ghost; remains of the dead.

wailua₂

an ancient variety of sweet potato, presumably introduced from Wailua, Kauaʻi.

wailuku₁

name reported for an ulua fishing line.

waimaka

tears. lit., eye water.

waimaka lehua

waterdrops from the ʻōhiʻa lehua tree; euphemism for menstruation. also waimaka-o-lehua

waimakaiakohi

name of a minor illness (no data).

waimakanui₁

an endemic fern (Thelypteris keraudreniana), with large, broad, pale, subdivided fronds, the last divisions triangular or oblong, the spores arranged in small dots scattered on the frond back.

waimakanui₂

a native fern (Pteris excelsa), with large, broad, bright-green, subdivided fronds, in general like waimakanui₁, but the last divisions longer and subfalcate, and the spores arranged in a line under the curled frond margin.

waimakaopele

Pele's tears.

waimakaua

services to get rain.

waimano₁

stone from which octopus sinkers were made.

waimano₂

adobe.

waimea₁

Maui name for olomea, a shrub.

waimea₂

Kauaʻi name for a kind of māmaki, having leaves with red veins and stems resembling those of the olomea.

waimāhoehoe

to strip the flesh from bones, as for burial.

waina maloʻo

raisins. lit., dry grapes.

waina₁

place with water.

waina₂

depository.

waina₃

pyorrhea, bleeding gums.

waina₄

wine.

waina₅

Isabella grape (Vitis xlabruscana), a strong-climbing vine, bearing blue, loose-skinned fruits. This is a hybrid that succeeds best of any grape introduced to Hawaiʻi; little interest has been shown in the past in the grape industry.

wainohia₂

safe, safety.

waiohinu

all kinds of cultivated dahlias (Dahlia spp.), named for a town on Hawaiʻi where the plant was first grown.

waioleka

fragrant cultivated violets (as Viola odorata).

waiolina

violin.

waiolina kū

cello.

waiolina kū nui

bass viol.

waiolono

careful, cautious about what one says.

waipahē

courteous, gentlemanly, polite, modest, gentle, good-natured, easygoing, agreeable, complacent, gracious. This word is usually used in a favorable sense, but occasionally pejoratively:

waipahū

gunpowder. lit., explosive liquid.

waipalupalu

name recorded for a variety of sweet potato.

waipalupalu

a kind of tapa. lit., soft dye or pattern.

waipaʻa

ice. lit., hard, solid water.

waipuʻilani

waterspout (perhaps from wai puhi lani, heaven-blown water).

waipā

request, prayer, as to the gods.

waipū

gunpowder.

waiwai hapa ʻumi

tithe, tithing. lit., one-tenth property.

waiwai hoʻoilina

inherited property, heritage, estate.

waiwai hoʻolilo

exports.

waiwai hoʻopae mai

imports.

waiwai hoʻopae malū

smuggled goods.

waiwai hoʻopaʻa

security, fixed assets. lit., solid property.

waiwai hoʻopuka

profits.

waiwai hui

assets. lit., combined wealth.

waiwai inoa

par value, as of stocks. lit., name value.

waiwai kaua

war goods, spoils.

waiwai kaulike

par value, just value.

waiwai koko ola

wealth taken to cause by sorcery the death of an innocent person — this was punishable by the sorcerer's own death. lit., live blood goods.

waiwai koko pīlau

wealth taken to cause by sorcery the death of a sorcerer who had prayed others to death. lit., foul blood goods.

waiwai komo

imports.

waiwai kālepa

merchandise.

waiwai kūʻai

investments.

waiwai lewa

movable or personal property; liquid assets; chattel.

waiwai maloko

tribute or wealth from the uplands.

waiwai nui

great wealth, fortune.

waiwai paʻa

real estate, property that cannot be moved.

waiwai pio

booty, plunder, spoils

waiwai puka aku

exports.

waiwai ʻiʻo

true worth, as of heirlooms; marked value, as of stocks.

waiwai ʻole

worthless, useless, of no use or value, good-for-nothing.

waiū haki

a breast that sags, but not long or pendulous. lit., broken breast.

waiū heʻeheʻe

caked breast.

waiū hoʻohuihui

milk combined with other ingredients, as for a baby or person on a liquid diet; formula. lit., mixed milk.

waiū kahe

flowing breast or milk.

waiū kau

breast filled with milk.

waiū kia

condensed milk. lit., deer milk, so called because the first cans of condensed milk had a picture of deer on the label.

waiū kini

canned milk.

waiū luliluli

milk shake.

waiū paʻipaʻi

diluted milk.

waiū puʻu

budding breast, as of a young girl.

waiūhakuhaku

clabbered milk, cottage cheese. lit., lumpy milk.

waiūkoʻa

a breast that has milk from the beginning of pregnancy to long after weaning.

waiūpakapaʻa

cheese. lit., solidified butter.

waiūpaʻa

cheese. lit., solidified milk.

waiʻakika

acid.

waiʻala

perfume, cologne, toilet water. lit., fragrant liquid.

waiʻaleʻale

rippling water, artesian water.

waiʻeleʻele₁

black dye.

waiʻeleʻele₂

ink.

waiʻeleʻele₃

a dark-skinned person.

waiʻele₁

black tapa dye; tapa so dyed.

waiʻele₂

to drug fish with ʻauhuhu.

waiʻolu

cool, pleasant, attractive, soft, gentle, pleasing.

waiʻoʻopu

type of tapa.

waiʻōhiʻa

a variety of sugar cane.

waiʻōpua₁

a disease similar to pulmonary consumption.

waiʻōpua₂

leucorrhea.

waiʻōupe

mirage. lit., deceiving water.

wai₃

grain in stone.

wai₄

to retain, place, leave, remain, earn, deposit (see more common waiho, waihona, waiwai, and less common wailana, waina₂, wai ʻūlili).

wai₆

type of house with thatch purlins separated by a width of two fingers.

wakawaka₁

redup. of waka₁, sharp, protruding....;   • serrated, pointed, sharp, as a rake's prongs or the spikes of a sea urchin;   • hilly.

waka₁

sharp, protruding.

waki kiaʻi hale

house guard.

wala

• to tilt,   • lift backwards,   • fall backwards;   • to throw backwards, as with a backhand flip.

wala kua

to fall over backward; to throw or stab at the back; to turn a somersault backwards; to rear, as a horse.

walakīkē

to toss, hurl back and forth, as spears in battle.

walania

anguish, burning pain, woe, torment; anguishing, smarting.

walanuka

walnut. (Juglans spp.)

walawalakī

to fall back; to plummet to the ground.

walawala₁

redup. of wala,   • to tilt, as a canoe in waves   • lift backwards,   • fall backwards;   • to throw backwards, as with a backhand flip....;

wale hau

sap in hau tree blossoms, chewed and swallowed to relieve constipation, and given to women before labor; slimy liquid obtained by immersing hau bark in water, drunk as a laxative.

wale kea

white mucus, as in the eyes.

wale wai

slimy with saliva. fig., to talk too much.

walea₁

same as nanea:   • interesting, of absorbing interest; fascinating,   • to have a good time, enjoyable;   • repose, tranquility; leisure, at leisure,   • relaxed, at ease,   • amused,   • engaged with, busy with;

walea₂

accustomed; so familiar that one does a thing without effort, as a dance; adept; to do well and effortlessly, as an acquired skill.

waleluka

walrus.

walewaha

to know a thing so well that it can be spoken without thought; letter-perfect; to know by rote or as a mother tongue.

walewale keiki

discharge following childbirth.

walewalena

slimy discharge.

walewale₂

deceived.

wale₁

slime, mucus, phlegm; sticky sap, as from cuts in tree ferns and māmaki wood that is mixed with bark in making tapa.

walina

softness.

waliwali

gentle, easygoing, good-natured, smooth.

walohia₁

pathos; touching, pathetic.

waluhia₂

bird name (no data).

waluna

clawing, scratching.

walu₁

to claw, scratch, rub, grate, rasp, scrape.

walu₂

oilfish (Ruvettus pretiosus), caught in deep water; large, much prized for eating and used as a cathartic.

wana hina

streak of gray, as in hair.

wana kauila

a wana with dark spikes. lit., kauila wood wana.

wanaoʻa

projecting in every direction, as the spines of a sea urchin; sharp-edged and projecting; to bristle, radiate.

wanawana

• spiny, thorny, as cactus;   • spiked, pointed;   • sharp, as jagged cliffs, spine, quills.

wanaʻao

dawn; to dawn.

wana₁

a sea urchin, as Diadema paucispinum and Echinothrix diadema, considered by some an ʻaumakua.

wana₂

sharp-pointed, as sea-urchin spines; jagged, sharp; spike

wana₃

• a long spike or streak of light, as at dawn;   • to appear, as a ray of light.

waniki

varnish; to paint.

wanila

vanilla.

wao

a general term for inland region usually forested but not precipitous and often uninhabited. see ex. below.

wao akua

a distant mountain region, believed inhabited only by spirits (akua); wilderness, desert.

wao kanaka

an inland region where people may live or occasionally frequent, usually considered below the wao akua.

wao kele

rain belt, upland forest.

wao koa

inland region where koa trees grow.

wao lani

mountain area believed occupied by gods.

wao lipo

inland region, said by (Kam) to be between the waoʻeiwa and the wao nahele. lit., dark wao.

wao nahele

inland forest region, jungle, desert.

wao one

desert.

wao ʻilima

an area at a lower altitude than that called wao ʻamaʻu; also ʻāpaʻa.

waohua

to plot to trap.

waoʻeiwa

an inland region.

wauke

the paper mulberry (Broussonetia papyrifera), a small tree or shrub, from eastern Asia, known throughout the Pacific for its usefulness. It belongs to the fig or mulberry family. The bark was made into tough tapa used for clothing, bed clothes; it lasted longer than māmaki tapa.

wauke kuʻikuʻi

bast from fully mature wauke that required more beating (kuʻikuʻi) than younger wauke (wauke ohiohi).

wauke mālolo

a wauke that was used medicinally, perhaps as a substitute for the mālolo (flying fish) often used in sacrifices.

wauke puakai

wauke bast dyed red for use as coloring material in tapa.

wauwau

to travel off the path or crookedly.

wauʻaha

prayer for deliverance or thanksgiving.

wawaha

to storm, rave, rant.

wawai

watered well, watery.

wawaʻu

• redup. of waʻu to grate, scrape, scratch, rasp, claw, wear away by friction...;   • fig., ill-natured, quarrelsome.

wawe

quickly; fast.

wawā

tumultuous; racket, loud talk, echo, sound of distant voices, roar: rumored, talked about, resounding, repeating (see hānau wawā).

waʻa holo hau

sleigh. lit., canoe running on snow.

waʻa honua

a wide canoe.

waʻa kai like

a canoe with little sheer. lit., equal-sea canoe.

waʻa kau hī

canoe for fishing aku.

waʻa kaua

war canoe; an army formation.

waʻa kaukahi

single canoe, as contrasted with the kaulua. lit., single-placed canoe.

waʻa kaulua

double canoe. lit., double-placed canoe.

waʻa kea₁

unpainted canoe set to sea after the taboos were lifted during the makahiki harvest festivals. lit., white canoe.

waʻa kome

vessel of papyrus (RSV), bullrush (KJV).

waʻa kūpāhoa

a long, thin canoe.

waʻa lau kī

toy canoe made of ti leaves.

waʻa lolo niu

toy canoe made of coconut sheath.

waʻa paulua

said to be a large or double canoe with three ʻiako.

waʻa puhi

a small, slim canoe used for surfing.

waʻa ʻauhau

tribute canoe; a basket filled with food and set adrift during the makahiki ceremonies, said to represent the canoe in which Lono returned to Tahiti.

waʻa ʻula

a chief's canoe with red sails.

waʻa ʻākea

starboard hull of a double canoe.

waʻakau

head fisherman's canoe.

waʻapā

skiff, rowboat; ferryboat. lit., board canoe.

waʻawaʻa₁

full of gulches, gullies, grooves; gullied, furrowed, grooved.

waʻawaʻa₂

muscular, one whose back bulges with muscles.

waʻawaʻa₃

stupid, ignorant; ignoramus, simpleton, fool.

waʻawaʻa₄

upper end of a lobster's leg.

waʻawaʻa₅

hollow at meeting of bones below the Adam's apple.

waʻawaʻa₆

desolate, uninhabited.

waʻa₂

trench, furrow, receptacle. fig., a woman.

waʻa₃

moving masses of liquid lava, so called because of similarity to a moving canoe.

waʻewaʻe₁

cloven hoof, as of cattle, goats, and deer. Kauaʻi.

waʻewaʻe₂

head fisherman in charge of kūʻula, stone gods.

waʻi

Kauaʻi.

waʻu

to grate, scrape, scratch, rasp, claw, wear away by friction; grater, scraper, as of cowry or other shell.

waʻu niu

coconut grater; to grate coconut.

Wehelauniu

wind name associated with Māla, Maui.

Wehewehe₃

name of a star (no data).

Wekaminika

Westminister.

Wekeka

Wessex.

Wekuwia

Vesuvius.

Wela Kaluka

Vera Cruz.

Welehu₂

ancient Hawaiian month, corresponding approximately to November. see month.

Welo ʻUla

a star name, perhaps same as Welo₅.

Welo₄

name of a month in the lunar calendar. see month.

Welo₅

name of a star used by navigators.

Wenuka

Venus.

wehe hala

to remove a personal transgression by prayer, with or without offering; remission of sins; name for sugar cane used in such ceremonies.

wehe ʻana

opening, untying, etc.; prelude (EH)

wehena₁

• opening, unfastening, taking off;   • solution, as of a problem.

wehena₂

difference (with ʻaʻohe).

wehewehe ʻano

analysis; to define, analyze.

wehewehe₂

redup. of wehe, to open, untie, undo...   • to unsaddle or unharness, as a horse;   • to pull growing taro stalks slightly apart so as to strengthen the corm.

wehe₂

to go away.

wehiwa₁

a variety of taro.

wehiwa₂

dark.

wehiwa₃

choice, prized; a choice object.

wehiwa₄

a variety of sweet potato.

wehiwa₅

a secret play language used on Hawaiʻi to prevent others from understanding; u was substituted for vowels: U hulu unu ūkua ūhua for E hele ana ʻoukou i hea? Where are you going?.

wehiwehi₁

festive.

wehiwehi₂

type of pāʻū, woman's skirt...

wehi₁

decoration, adornment, ornament; to decorate.

wehi₂

a song composed as an adornment, a song honoring someone.

wehi₃

dark.

wekaweka₂

a foul stomach.

wekaweka₃

hardhearted; stingy.

weka₁

ink discharged by squid or octopus.

weka₂

dark organs of an ʻopihi, a limpet.

weka₃

first dark excreta of an infant, meconium.

weka₄

mucus in the eyes.

weka₅

weight.

weke keʻokeʻo

lit., white weke.

weke nono

name given for a red weke identified as Upeneus. lit., red weke.

weke pahulu

a weke (Upeneus arge) named for a god on Lanaʻi. lit., nightmare weke. Also called weke ahulu and weke pueo.

weke pueo

a weke, probably the same as weke pahulu. lit., owl weke, probably so called because of similarity of stripes on the tail and the bars of the Hawaiian owl's feathers.

weke ʻula

a species of weke (Mulloidichthys vanicolensis). The color effect of a school of weke ʻula is not red but yellow. They show themselves red when taken out of the water. lit., red weke.

weke ʻā

a fish (Mulloidichthys samoensis). lit., staring weke.

wekea₂

midday; zenith.

wekekē

whisky.

wekewekea

pried open, loosened.

wekeweke₁

to open, as a crack.

weke₁

crack, narrow opening; to open a crack, as a door; to separate, loosen, free.

weke₂

certain species of the Mullidae, surmullets or goatfish. All weke have large scales and are usually found in reefs, sometimes in deep water. Both red and light-colored weke were popular as offerings to the gods to turn away curses: see weke₁. For the connection of weke with nightmares, see pahulu₁. Unidentified varieties of weke are qualified by the terms koaʻe, lāʻō, moelua. see also weke ʻā or weke keʻokeʻo, weke ahulu or weke pahulu or weke pueo, weke nono, weke ʻula.

wela ahi

scald, burned.

wela₃

a new field, as of sweet potatoes; a piece of land cleared for planting by burning.

welehu₁

a deep sea fish resembling the hāuliuli.

welelau

to touch the tip, as of a spear.

weleweka₁

velvet.

weleweka₂

the coleus (Coleus blumei), an ornamental perennial herb or small shrub, from Java. The leaves are ovate, toothed, variegated with red, yellow, green, purple. Small blue flowers are borne in spikes.

welewele iwi

to strip the bones of flesh, as for burial. fig., to criticize or slander one's kin.

welewelelau

very end of the tip.

weleʻā

a lizard fish (Trachinocephalus myops).

wele₂

suspended, hanging; fine, thin, as thread.

welina

a greeting of affection, similar to aloha; a salutation in a letter, in longer form as follows:

weliweli₁

• violent, dreadful, horrible, fearful, ferocious;   • revered;   • respectful, as of the word of a chief;   • full of awe.

weliweli₂

a small weli, holothurian.

weliweli₃

numerous, immense, prolific.

weli₁

fear, terror, dread; fearful, afraid.

weli₂

a holothurian.

weli₃

scion, sucker, shoot, as from a root; spreading root.

weli₄

phosphorescent light on water, believed caused by a ghost that was interfering with fishing.

welokike

velocity.

welokā

thrashing, smiting, as a fishtail.

welowelo

flying streak, as of the tail of a comet or of a firebrand.

welo₁

to flutter, float, or stream, as in the wind.

welo₂

to set, of the sun.

welo₃

• progeny,   • ancestry,   • breed,   • family trait or strain,   • group custom,   • heritage,   • characteristic.

welo₆

a strong purge made of the juice of the bitter gourd or seeds of kāʻeʻe.

welu ahi

ball of tapa cord used to carry fire.

welu ʻula

red rag; tapa made of pieces of red tapa beaten up with other tapa.

weluwelu₁

redup. of welu₁, rag, ragged fragment; ragged, frayed, tattered...; shredded to bits.

welu₁

rag, ragged fragment; ragged, frayed, tattered.

welu₂

straggling clump, as of trees.

wena₁

glow, as of sunrise or fire, red.

wena₂

a close relationship, blood relative.

weoweo₃

a type of tapa.

weo₁

• red, redness;   • to blush.

weo₂

dried banana bark, perhaps so called because of a reddish color.

weo₃

a variety of taro.

wepele

vesper.

weuweu

• herbage, grass, greenery;   • bushy or fuzzy, as a beard;   • fluffy.

weweke

prayer for luakini dedication.

weweli₁

somewhat afraid (less strong than weliweli).

weʻaweʻa₁

to help, abet, or tempt, especially in love affairs; accomplice; accessory in crime; one who aids or incites but does not share; procurer, pimp; to procure.

weʻa₂

a red dye; to print or color red.

Wikapuka

Vicksburg.

Wikiwiki₂

star name (no data).

Wikolia₂

Victoria.

Wilemikona

Wilmington.

Wilikine

Virgin.

Wilikinia Komohana

West Virginia.

wikeke

whiskey.

wiki

to hurry, hasten; quick, fast, swift.

wikilia

vigil.

wikiliola

vitriol.

wikiwama

wigwam.

wiko

veto; to veto.

wikolia₁

a fine lawn used in dresses; victoria lawn.

wilelaiki

the Christmas-berry tree (Schinus terebinthifolius), a rather small tree, from Brazil, the leaves compound, each leaf having about seven leaflets, the flowers whitish, small, in large bunches, the small red fruits of the female tree abundant, resembling those of the pūkiawe. Named for Willie Rice [William Hyde Rice?], who during political campaigns wore a hat lei of the red berries.

wili kope

coffee mill, coffee grinder.

wili kāhei

bit for boring, drilling. lit., circling drill.

wili kō

sugar mill, sugar grinder, to grind sugar cane.

wili lauoho

locks of hair (Mele 5.2) ; false human hair twisted to fall down from the back, like a hair switch, described by Samwell of the Cook expedition (Beaglehole 1179), (Buck 562–3).

wili makani

windmill.

wili nui

auger.

wili ohi ʻili kope

mill for peeling coffee beans.

wili oho

coil or strand of hair, as in a lei palaoa necklace.

wili papa

planing mill.

wili peahi

fan, as for cleaning seeds.

wili wehe ʻumoki

corkscrew.

wili ʻāʻī

to twist the neck; bulldog.

wiliau

• to stir,   • circulate,   • move in eddies;   • mixed currents and eddies;   • turbulent.

wilikina

sister, nun (Catholic).

wilikāʻekā

snarled, tangled, as hair.

wilikī kīwila

civil engineer.

wilikōī

dust or trash blown by the wind.

wilimoʻo

to turn, twist, writhe, as a reptile.

wilinau

to writhe, twist, wriggle.

wilipuaʻa

corkscrew, hand drill, gimlet, screw auger (a euphemism for ulepuaʻa).

wiliwai

eddy, whirlpool.

wiliwili haole

the tiger's-claw (Erythrina variegata var. orientalis, synonym E. indica), distributed from India to southern Polynesia, resembling the native wiliwili in many ways but larger and commonly grown ornamentally in Hawaiʻi for its large, bright-red flowers.

wiliwiliwai

lawn sprinkler. see song, koʻiawe.

wiliwili₂

a Hawaiian leguminous tree (Erythrina sandwicensis, formerly called E. monosperma), found on dry coral plains and on lava flows, somewhat spiny, with short thick trunk. Each leaf has three ovate leaflets; flowers are clustered near branch ends and range in color from red to orange, yellow, white; pods contain red, oblong seeds, used for leis. The wood is very light and formerly was used for surfboards, canoe outriggers, net floats.

wiliʻōhiki kulina

corn sheller or husker.

wiliʻōkaʻi₁

chrysalis of night moth (ʻōkaʻi), cocoon.

wiliʻōkaʻi₂

to whirl, bluster, as wind.

wili₂

mill, drill, wrench, bit; various implements or machines used for turning are listed below.

wili₃

spirals of several colors in composite leis, as of the cigar flower (kīkā).

wili₄

a bird (no data).

winihapa

brick, named for Captain Winship, said to have brought the first bricks to Hawaiʻi.

winiwini

redup. of wini₁, sharp, as a point. fig., impudent, nervy...; tapering, ridged.

wini₁

• sharp, as a point.   • fig., impudent, nervy.

wini₂

wind.

wiola

viol.

wiola ʻumi

instrument of ten strings (Hal. 92.3) , psaltery (Hal. 81.2) . lit., ten viol.

wiwo ʻole

fearless, brave, bold, courageous, dauntless, intrepid.

wiwo₁

fearful, bashful, modest, afraid, timid, shy.

wiwo₂

obedient; to mind, obey.

wiʻu₁

to smart with pain.

wiʻu₂

dirty, filthy.

wiʻu₃

entangled, as a kite.

Wolekeka

Worcestershire.

Word

Definition

woa

calm.

wohi₁

one whose parent was of piʻo, naha, or nīʻaupiʻo rank, and the other parent of second degree collaterality. A wohi chief was exempt from the prostration taboo (kapu moe); he preceded the king on public occasions to see that others prostrated themselves; he was generally a near relative. rare: ohi, as in the spelling ʻAiohikupua . see saying kū kahi.

wolu₁

Kaʻū and Puna, Hawaiʻi.

wolu₂

walrus.

Wulekake

Vulgate.

wulekula

vulture.

Wākea

the mythical ancestor of all Hawaiians. (Kep. 61–7)... according to Hawaiian tradition, a man rather than a god (HM 294). see Haumea, Hoʻohokukalani, Papa, Waka. Probably lit., expanse.

Wāle

Wales. Prince of Wales, Keiki aliʻi o Wāle.

wā e hiki mai ana

future tense or time.

wā hala

past tense.

wā heu ʻole

time of beardless youth, preadolescence. lit., time without whiskers.

wā heʻe

time when heʻe (octopus) abound.

wā hiamoe

time to sleep, bedtime.

wā kahiko

ancient times, antiquity.

wā kamaliʻi

childhood.

wā keiki

childhood.

wā keiki kāne

boyhood.

wā ma hope

the future

wā mamua

formerly, old times.

wā oʻo

maturity.

wā ua

rainy season.

wā uʻi

youth, time of physical perfection.

wā ʻuʻuku

childhood. lit., small time.

wā ʻānō

present tense.

wāhi

• to cleave, split, burst through, break through;   • to change, as money;   • to have sex relations with a virgin, deflower.

wāhi pūniu

"skull cracking", difficult

wāikāhuli₁

a calliopsis (Coreopsis tinctoria), an annual ornamental herb, in the daisy family, from central United States, the ray flowers yellow with dark-red at the base. lit., change [of] color.

wāikāhuli₂

see

wāiʻa

season in which fish are numerous.

wākiuma

to vacuum.

wālua₁

to carry on a pole on the shoulders, of two.

wālua₂

middle, interior.

wāluna

prophecy.

wānana

prophecy; to prophesy, predict, prognosticate, foresee, foretell.

wāpine

the lemon verbena (Aloysia triphylla), a South American shrub, with rough lemonscented, narrow leaves, and small white or lavender flowers in spikes. Formerly the plant was a favorite in Hawaiian gardens, and was used in leis.

wāwae huki

cramps in foot or leg, charley horse.

wāwae pehu

gout, swollen legs or feet.

wāwaeʻiole

a cosmopolitan tropical club moss (Lycopodium cernuum), a far-creeping mosslike plant, growing .3 to 1.5 m high. Its stems and many branches are covered with short, narrow-pointed leaves, and are made into Christmas wreaths. Eight other species of club mosses also bear this name. (Neal 2–3) Other analysts call wāwaeʻiole, Codium edule, and list ʻaʻala- ʻula and ʻalaʻula as variant names. Some equate huluhulua-ʻiole and huluʻiole with wāwaeʻiole.

wāwae₂

hula step (general name).

wāwahi

to tear down, shatter, wreck, dash to pieces, break into, demolish; to break, as a law or a twenty-dollar bill; to cause disorder.

wāwahi hale

burglary, housebreaking; to break and enter.

wāwahi panakō

to break the bank, as in chee-fah or other games.

wāwahiwaʻa₁

borer that bores into canoe hulls, a teredo. lit., canoe breaker

wāwau

name recorded as an insulting term similar to dumb brute.

wāwena

heat; hot.

wāʻōpio

youth (time of).

wā₂

tense, in grammar.

wā₃

• to make a noise, roar, din; noisy, loud;   • to talk much, as of gossip: to talk loudly back and forth;   • to reason.

wā₄

space, interval, as between objects or time; in music, one of the four spaces of the staff; channel.

wā₅

fret of an ukulele, guitar, or similar instrument.

Wēlau Hema

South Pole.

Wēlau ʻĀkau

North Pole.

wēkenanā

a pest, frequently followed by mauʻu Hilo

wēkiu

tip, top, topmost, summit, peak; of the highest rank or station.

wēlau

• tip, extremity, end,   • top,   • pole (not necessarily high or lofty, as wēkiu);   • extremes, as in fractions.

wēlau alelo

tip of tongue.

wē₁

to sift.

wē₂

the letter "w."

wīkani

strong, hard, rigid, inflexible.

wīkaʻo

dry.

wīlou

willow.

wīlou lohaloha

weeping willow. lit., drooping willow.

wīneka

vinegar.

wī₁

famine; to suffer a famine.

wī₂

• to squeal (For. 4:457), squeak,   • tinkle;   • the sound of wind, of gnashing teeth;   • any high shrill sound.

wī₃

the wī tree (Spondias dulcis), a smooth, gray-barked tree in the mango family, from islands of the South Pacific. The round or ovoid orange fruits, called wī apples, are 2.5 or more cm in diameter, have apple-flavored, yellow pulp surrounding a core with a few seeds.

wī₄

the tamarind (Tomarindus indica), a large leguminous tree from tropical Africa and possibly Asia, grown for shade and ornament, and for the wood and fruit. The brown pod contains a few seeds embedded in sticky, brown, acid pulp, which is eaten or made into a drink. sometimes called wīʻawaʻawa.

wī₆

a female kīkī, a bird.

wōwō

to bellow, roar.

ā me

and (sometimes written ame).

āelo

rotten, of eggs that do not hatch due to infertility. fig., spoiled, worthless.

āewa₁

• thin, tall spindly;   • to weave to and fro, as seaweed;   • to sway, as a branch or sea eddy.

āewa₂

possessing a family or lineage.

āhole

an endemic fish (Kuhlia sandvicensis) found in both fresh and salt water. The mature stage is āhole, the young stage āholehole. Because of the meaning of hole, to strip away, this fish was used for magic, as to chase away evil spirits and for love magic. It was also called a "sea pig" (puaʻa kai) and used ceremonially as a substitute for pig. Foreigners were sometimes called āhole because of the light skin of the fish.

āholehole

young stage of the āhole, Hawaiian flagtail.

āhua

var. spelling of ʻāhua₁   • to swell, as a wave;   • heap, mound, hillock, knoll, pile;   • heaped, humped;   • tremendous.

āhunihuni

name given for a fish of the ʻōpakapaka type.

āhā

aha (exclamation of surprise).

āhē

to exclaim, to oh and ah; yes, so that's it, so, oh.

āio

same as ioio, grooves.

āiwaiwa

• inexplicable, mysterious, strange, fathomless, incomprehensible,   • wonderful because of divinity; marvelous, amazing, fantastic,   • wonderfully proficient or skilled;   • weirdly bad, notorious.

ākeakea₂

a kind of gray tapa.

ākea₁

• broad, wide,   • spacious, open, unobstructed,   • public,   • at large;   • full, as a skirt;   • breadth, width.   • fig., liberal.

ākēkē₂

name given for the ʻoʻopu hue, puffer fish, and listed by Malo.

ālaina

obstacle, obstruction.

ālai₁

obstruction, hindrance, block, bar, screen; to obstruct, hinder, block, defend, stand in the way, oppose, hamper.

ālai₂

two sticks carried with the akua loa in the makahiki festival; they were used to mark the boundry of the taboo area.

ālaulau

clothes, tapa, mats; to envelop, clothe.

ālealea₁

a shellfish (Turbo sandwicensis); its shell.

ālia₁

salt bed, salt-encrusted area; salty, brackish.

ālia₂

name of two kauila or māmane sticks carried by priests before the makahiki god; also the two crossed spears with upright spear in the center, used as insignia for the present-day Māmakakaua society; small flag or streamer.

ālohaloha

(less used than hoʻālohaloha).

āloʻi

mud puddle, pool.

ālula

an endemic member of the lobelia family (Brighamia spp.), presently known only on Molokaʻi and Kauaʻi, believed extinct on Maui and Niʻihau, an unbranched, succulent, thick-stemmed perennial about 1.5 m high, topped with a rosette of large oval leaves and racemes of long, white, fragrant flowers. also hāhā.

ālulu

quickly, hastily (used after hele, hana, holo, holoholo, hopuhopu).

ālālā

sweet potatoes that bear front branch (lālā) vines.

āmio

• narrow channel, as to a sea pool;   • to move through such a channel;   • to blow in a current;   • to pass in and out;   • gusty.   • fig., to die.

āmuka

reported as a var. name for the kāhala fish

āmū

to trim, shear, shave; shaving, shearing.

ānai₂

attraction.

ānea₁

insipid, tasteless.

ānea₂

vibration caused by heat.

ānea₃

• pas/imp of ane₁, moth-eaten   • fig., a battered tramp.

ānea₄

bare, leafless

ānehe

• to come upon quietly,   • move stealthily,   • poise.

āneho

transgression of the law, wrong, fault; to transgress.

āneo

a game; the stone called hiu was said to have been used in this game.

ānewa

dizzy, unsteady, as one ill or intoxicated.

āneʻoneʻo

to itch.

āniania

smooth, calm.

ānini

Eurya sandwicensis, a native tree or shrub in the tea family.

ānoni

var. spelling of ʻānoni   • to mix, interweave, intertwine, mixed.   • fig., confused, doubtful.

ānuenue₁

rainbow.

ānuenue₂

scallop-like design on tapa and tapa beater.

āpau

[old spelling, replaced by a pau]. all, entirely.

āukauka

inland; fishing grounds, identified by lining up with landmarks ashore.

āulu₁

rough, raging, as sea or wind; to injure, harm, rage.

āulu₂

to grow.

āulu₃

a tall endemic tree (Pisonia sandwicensis), with large, oblong, dark-green leaves; small, rounded flower heads, narrow, sticky fruits, and very soft wood.

āwā

noisy, loud; to talk loudly.

āēī eia

chant ending.

āēīē

chant refrain.

ā₁

• jaw, cheekbone.   • fig., to talk a lot, jabber, jibber jabber.

ā₂

an instrument made of smooth bone, formerly used for abortion, lancing, or bleeding. also āʻōʻō, piercing ā.

ā₃

mold found in souring foods, especially poi, generally known as Oidium lactis or Oospora lactis, but now called Geotrichum candidum.

ēhē

syllables repeated in chants at ends of verses, affording pleasure by repetition or sameness of sound harmonizing with repetition of sameness of drum beat; similar in function to English tra-la-la but different in mood, tending to be more serious.

ēkoa

same as koa haole, false koa (Leucaena leucocephala), a plant.

ēulu₁

top of tree or plant; trimmed hedge top; cutting; to top, cut or crop off, as top branches.

ēulu₂

a kind of taro, qualified by the terms keʻokeʻo and kohu uauahi.

ēwe kapu

sacred or taboo lineage.

ēwe lani

chiefs of divine descent.

ēweewe

kinsmen, lineage; pertaining to the family, having a family.

ēwe₁

• sprout, rootlet; to sprout.   • lineage, kin;   • birthplace;   • family trait;

ēwe₂

• navel string;   • abdominal aorta,   • mature birth.

ēwe₄

white of an egg.

ē₁

a second ē often follows the head word for emphasis. Ē is shortened to e before third-person pronouns: see e ia nei, e lākou ala.

ē₂

as in the common exclamation below.

ē₃

Alas!

īheʻe

to spread out, prevail, as of calm, peace.

īheʻeheʻe

to flow.

īheʻekai

turmeric or ocher with salt water, used as a daub by guardians of shark gods and other priests.

īkā₁

• to drift upon,   • strike against;   • to turn aside from a straight course;   • flotsam and jetsam.

īkā₂

sides of taro patch or garden.

ōhāhā₁

flourishing, fully developed, plump, healthy.

ōhāhā₂

distinct, clear sound or voice.

ōkea₁

white sand or gravel (contraction of one, sand, and kea, white). cf. Ke-ōkea, a place name.

ōkea₂

hot, as stone heated to whiteness.

ōkea₃

a bird.

ōkelekele

muddy.

ōlaʻa

a weedy raspberry (Rubus rosaefolius) native to southeastern Asia.

ōlaʻi₁

earthquake, tremor.

ōlaʻi₂

light porous stone or pumice, as used for polishing canoes or for scraping off hair of pig or dog to be roasted.

ōleoleo

to quarrel or speak noisily, raise a din.

ōnahanahaiaua

fertile spot in a lava bed.

ōpuhe

three species of endemic trees (Urera), related to the olonā, the bark of which was also formerly used for fishing nets.

ōpū ao

cluster of clouds.

ōpū hale

hut, as in a forest.

ōpū malumalu

shady clump; a humble way to refer to one's house.

ōpū nāhelehele

cluster or clump of any growth; thicket.

ōpū weuweu

• clump of grass,   • a polite depreciatory way to refer to one's home, however magnificent it may be.

ōpūhea

quiet, tranquil, calm, disinclined to work, lazy; tranquillity.

ōpūhue

round, low calabash. lit., calabash clump.

ōpū₁

• clump, as of sugar cane, bananas, kava;   • cluster.

ōpū₂

• to open, as a flower;   • to rise, as water;   • to swell, as waves;   • to grow, as a foetus;   • to sit with knees gathered up.

ōpū₃

to rest, hover, live idly or lazily, exist; existence, rest.

ōpū₄

a tower in a heiau. see drawing, (Ii 57).

ōwī₁

a weedy kind of verbena (Verbena litoralis), from tropical America, with square stems 30 cm to 2 m high, toothed oblong leaves, and narrow flower spikes bearing tiny blue flowers. Hawaiians use it for cuts and bruises, applying the juice externally and later sprinkling the affected area with powdered pia root.

ōwī₂

the Jamaica vervain (Stachytarpheta jamaicensis), another kind of weedy verbena also from tropical America, similar to the above, but with oval toothed leaves, and tiny blue flowers borne on longer, narrower spikes. It is not used medicinally by Hawaiians.

ōwī₃

cry of the bird ʻōʻū; to cry, of the ʻōʻū.

ōūʻole

fearless, courageous.

ōʻukuʻuku₁

a small oʻu, a fish.

ōʻukuʻuku₂

small, petite.

ō₁

• to answer, reply yes, agree, say, talk;   • halloo, yes (in reply);   • tinkling, tolling, or chime of a bell;   • resonance, as generated by the thumping of a gourd drum on a pad;   • sound of whistling (Kauaʻi);   • sound of peacocks;   • to make such sounds.

ō₂

• to remain, endure,   • survive,   • continue, go on, continuing.   • exist;

ō₃

food provisions for a journey, especially at sea; sea rations.

ō₄

sprit of a sail or spar.

ō₅

short for one, sand, in place names, as Keōkea, the white sand.

ō₆

imperative marker, perhaps less emphatic than the more common e.

ō₇

short for the part. iō, as after prepositions.

ū wai

water-soaked, soggy.

ū-

(probably length of ū- was due to assimilation of the long vowel in the base.)

ūi

halloo.

ūkākā

female of ʻōʻō and ʻōʻū, birds.

ūkō

fulfilled. fig., pregnant.

ūkūkua

besieged, pressed with work, crowded.

ūpē

• crushed, flattened;   • humble, bashful;   • dry and juiceless, as sugar cane.

ū₁

breast, teat, udder.

ū₂

moist, soaked; to drip, drizzle, ooze; impregnated, as with salt.

ʻAeʻaeahiwa

name of a star (no data).

ʻAha Hoʻokolokolo Kiʻekiʻe

Supreme Court.

ʻAha Kiʻekiʻe

Supreme Court.

ʻAha Koʻikoʻi

lit., powerful court.

ʻAhahui Hōʻikaika Kalikiano

Christian Endeavor Society.

ʻAhahui Kanu Kō Hawaiʻi

Hawaiian Sugar Planters' Association.

ʻAhahui Moʻolelo Hawaiʻi

Hawaiian Historical Society.

ʻAhahui Māmakakaua

Sons and Daughters of Hawaiian Warriors. Lit., warriors' society.

ʻAhahui Wāhine Kalikiano Hōʻole Wai ʻOna

Women's Christian Temperance Union.

ʻAhahui ʻEuanelio Pae ʻĀina

a term used in 1911 for evangelical conference of all the islands.

ʻAhahuina₂

congregational.

ʻAhaʻaina Kauhalelewa

Feast of Tabernacles. (Bib.)

ʻAhaʻaina Mōliaola

Feast of the Passover. (Bib.)

ʻAhaʻaina Pelena

Holy Communion. lit., feast of bread.

ʻAhaʻaina a ka Haku

Holy Communion, Lord's Supper; feast of the Lord.

ʻAhuʻula₂

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the feather cloak.

ʻAikanaka₁

name of a star.

ʻAikanaka₂

lit., man-eating.(HM 241-242). an older cousin of Kawelo; on becoming chief of Kauaʻi he banished Kawelo's parents, thus provoking an invasion. see Kawelo.

ʻAikanaka₃

an Oʻahu chief who sent men to fetch the beautiful wife of Halemano, causing the couple to flee the island.

ʻAikanaka₄

a Maui chief who married Hinahānaiakamalama. Hina wearied of disposing of her children's excrement and lept into the moon. Her husband, trying to stop her, caught her leg. She hangs in the moon today.

ʻAikikauelono

name of a star, possibly Sirius. Also called Hikikauelono (Hiki-kau-e-lono).

ʻAikiopa

Ethiopia; Ethiopian.

ʻAikoʻo

name of a wind at Nuʻalolo, Kauaʻi.

ʻAikupika

Egypt; Egyptian.

ʻAiliki

Irish.

ʻAilimaiki

a method of lua fighting; to grab little finger of an adversary and twist it.

ʻAiloli

name of a wind at Kaupō, Maui. lit., sea cucumber food.

ʻAimaunu

name of a wind at Hāna, Maui. lit., bait eating.

ʻAiwohikupua

the Kauaʻi hero who vainly wooed Lāʻieikawai at the legendary land of Paliuli on Hawaiʻi.(Laie) lit., semidivine chiefly ruler.

ʻAkakia

Arcadia.

ʻAkama

Assam.

ʻAkamu

Adam.

ʻAkanaka

Arkansas, Arkansan.

ʻAkapakeka

Athabasca.

ʻAkelanika

Atlantic.

ʻAkelona

Akron.

ʻAkenai

Athens.

ʻAkiliakika

Adriatic.

ʻAkilonakaka

Adirondack.

ʻAkipohe₃

name of a wind of Waiheʻe, Maui.

ʻAkole

Azores.

ʻAkulia

Assyria.

ʻAlahonua

name of a light Hilo breeze. lit., land fragrance. Also ʻAʻalahonua.

ʻAlakena

Arden.

ʻAlakona

Aragon.

ʻAlalaka

Ararat.

ʻAlapani

Albany.

ʻAlapia₁

Arabia, Arabian.

ʻAlekanekalia

Alexandria.

ʻAlekaneko

Arkansas.

ʻAlemamaka

Alma Mater.

ʻAlemenia

Armenia; Armenian.

ʻAlepukaka

Albuquerque.

ʻAmehaka

Amherst.

ʻAmekekama

Amsterdam.

ʻAmelika

America; American.

ʻAmelika Hema

South America, South American.

ʻAmelika Hui

United States of America.

ʻAmelika Huipū

United States of America, American.

ʻAmelika Waena

Central America, Central American.

ʻAmelika ʻĀkau

North America, North American.

ʻAnealika

Antarctic.

ʻAneke

Andes.

ʻAnekowela

Andover.

ʻAoa Laenihi

a rainy wind at Niʻihau, said to be so-called because it creeps (nihi).

ʻAoa₅

name of a sea breeze associated with Honolulu and elsewhere. Also ʻAoʻaoa or Ulumano.

ʻAoʻao Komohana

Western Hemisphere.

ʻApa₃

Abba.

ʻApelika

Africa; African.

ʻApipa

Abib, a Hebrew month.

ʻApokelupo

Apocrypha.

ʻAua₃

name recorded for the star Betelgeuse.

ʻAuhuhupaʻina

var. name for the month of Makaliʻi, a time so dry that the ʻauhuhu plant became brittle (paʻina). See month.

ʻAukekulalia

Australia; Australian.

ʻAukekulia

Austria; Austrian.

ʻAukelana

Auckland.

ʻAuwaelewa

a lua fighting stroke. lit., the floating chin

ʻAʻala Honua

name of a wind accompanied by rain associated with Hilo. lit., earth fragrance.

ʻAʻala Loloa

wind name.

ʻAʻala₂

winds.

ʻAʻā₃

Sirius, a zenith star that passes over Tahiti and Raʻiātea, formerly believed used by navigators; one of the brightest stars in the heavens. see Sirius for var. names.

ʻa-₁

prefix to numbers from one through nine, especially for counting in series.

ʻae kai

place where sea and land meet; water's edge.

ʻae o hope

train of a dress (origin uncertain).

ʻae one

sandy beach.

ʻaea

cord, as used in joining two or more nets into a larger one.

ʻaekai mokiha

ancient type of tapa (no data).

ʻaekelona

falcon, vulture.

ʻaeko kula

golden eagle.

ʻaeko₁

eagle.

ʻaeko₂

alto.

ʻaelike

agreement, contract, truce, accord, deal; to come to an agreement; contracted.

ʻaeokahaloa

a kind of fine tapa, used in kuni and other ceremonies, as for divining with pebbles.

ʻaeʻa

• wandering, to wander,   • shiftless,   • unstable;   • stray;   • tramp.

ʻaeʻa haukaʻe₂

a variety of wild sweet potato, good only as pig food.

ʻaeʻae₂

a small native shrub (Lycium sandwicense) growing near salt marshes and among rocks near the sea. It has light-colored bark; succulent, narrow pale-green leaves about 2.6 cm long; small white to blue-tinted flowers; and small red berries.

ʻaeʻae₃

water hyssop, a succulent herb (Bacopa monnieria). Niʻihau cf. (Neal 759).

ʻaeʻoia

to be well supplied with comforts and necessities.

ʻae₂

• sap wrung from seaweed or leaves of plants such as taro;   • liquid remaining after dregs have settled, as of pia, arrowroot starch;   • saliva, drooling of the mouth.

ʻae₃

• fine, mashed, comminuted, as dust or powder;   • silky soft, as down;   • smooth, as well-mixed poi or bread dough.

ʻae₄

to rise, of the tide.

ʻae₅

a native fern (Polypodium pellucidum) commonly seen at Kīlauea Volcano. It has oblong fronds 15 to 40 cm long, once divided into about fifteen or more pairs of oblong segments, each of which bears many round fruit dots.

ʻae₇

shoots from main root portion of the wauke plant.

ʻaha hele honua

ceremonial measuring of the dimensions of a mana house within a place of worship; a priest carried a line to the four corner posts of the mana, and the chief sacrificed a pig; name of the line.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo

general name for court assembly. Names of several types of courts are listed below.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo hoʻomalu

police court.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo kaʻapuni

circuit court.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo koa

military court, court martial.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo koʻikoʻi

superior court.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo kākau

old name for ʻaha kākau, court of records.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo malalo iho

lower court.

ʻaha hoʻokolokolo ʻāpana

district court.

ʻaha hoʻokō

executive council.

ʻaha hoʻokō kauoha

probate court.

ʻaha hoʻomalu

administrative body, assembly.

ʻaha hoʻoponopono i ka nohona

court of domestic relations.

ʻaha hoʻoponopono waiwai hoʻoilina

probate court. Lit., court settling inheritance property.

ʻaha hulahula₁

assembly for ballroom dancing; a ball.

ʻaha hulahula₂

ancient assembly for the hulahula religious ceremony.

ʻaha hāwele

cord support for gourd water bottles.

ʻaha hīmeni

song festival, concert.

ʻaha hōʻike makahiki

annual meeting of Sunday Schools, as of Congregationalists.

ʻaha iki

small gathering for private conversation; small or secret council, as called in an emergency.

ʻaha inu

drinking party, as:

ʻaha kapu₁

a sacred assembly.

ʻaha kapu₂

sacred sennit cord belonging to a high chief and kept on a high place before his house; trespassers entering the house were killed if the cord remained in place, but if it fell down and the stranger stepped over it, this was a token of the stranger's high rank or kinship with the owner of the cord. Some chiefs had several such cords, each given a name, and some were used after the owner's death in making the kāʻai, container for his bones.

ʻaha kau kānāwai

session of the legislature.

ʻaha kaulike

an 1854 name for the highest court.

ʻaha kauoha

probate court.

ʻaha kaʻapuni

Circuit court.

ʻaha kenekoa

senate.

ʻaha kiule kiʻekiʻe

grand jury.

ʻaha kuhina

cabinet, assembly of ministers.

ʻaha kākau

court of records.

ʻaha kūkā

council meeting, discussion meeting, advisory council, conference.

ʻaha kūkā malū

privy council, secret deliberative meeting.

ʻaha lunakahiko

Presbytery, meeting of elders.

ʻaha lunakānāwai

judiciary session, meeting of judges.

ʻaha maha

place or assembly for practice of athletic games, as sham fights. lit., assembly for relaxation.

ʻaha mele

concert, song concert, song festival.

ʻaha mokupuni

island conference, with representative from a single island, especially of Congregationalists.

ʻaha ninaninau

court of inquiry.

ʻaha nīele

inquisition, inquest.

ʻaha o nā lunakānāwai ʻāpana

District court.

ʻaha paeʻāina

convention of delegates from all the islands, especially as held by the Hawaiian Evangelical Association of Congregational Christian Churches.

ʻaha pule

congregation, prayer assembly.

ʻaha ʻelele

convention of delegates; name for American presidential conventions.

ʻaha ʻuao

board of arbitration.

ʻaha ʻula

council of chiefs. lit., regal meeting.

ʻaha ʻāpana

district court.

ʻahaana

design said to resemble duck tracks, carved on tapa beaters.

ʻahahui

society, club, association, organization, company, convention. Various types are listed below.

ʻahahui hoʻole wai ʻona

Temperance union. Lit., society forbidding intoxicating liquor.

ʻahahui kula Kāpaki

Sunday School association.

ʻahahui malū

secret society.

ʻahahui ʻimi naʻauao

academy, learned society.

ʻahahuina₁

corporation, association.

ʻahahuluhulu

bristle worm, a hairy sea creature (Eurythoe complanata).

ʻahakea lau liʻi

a small-leafed ʻahakea (Bobea elatior var. brevipes).

ʻahakea lau nui

a large-leafted ʻahakea (Bobea elatior).

ʻahakea₁

native trees (species of Bobea) with small to medium-sized, oblong leaves; small greenish or white flowers; and small, purple-to-black juicy fruits. The wood is yellow and formerly was used for poi boards and canoe rims.

ʻahakū

cord used for measuring, as in laying out a garden or house.

ʻahalualike

rectangle. lit., two equal sides.

ʻahamaka₁

hammock, as of tapa, fastened to the manuea, center support of a house; hammock in general. lit., sennit meshes.

ʻahamaka₂

cord with which edges of cracks in gourd bowls were sewn together in crisscross patterns suggestive of net mesh; the technique for such repair.

ʻahamaka₃

strangling in lua fighting, as with green vines.

ʻahamaka₄

secret meeting of priests to pray for a chief.

ʻahamele

a yellow-spotted needlefish.

ʻahamoa₁

an assembly watching a lua contest of the kind called hakakāamoa.

ʻahamoa₂

a cord made from the entrails of an enemy killed in a lua fight of the hakakāamoa type.

ʻahaniu

a native sedge (Machaerina mariscoides subsp. meyenii) with pointed, leathery leaves about 90 by 1.6 cm, mostly basal around a more or less zigzag spike, which bears light-brown scattered flower clusters. see also ʻuki, all species of Cladium and Machaerina.

ʻahapiʻi

a kind of tapa dyed with kukui bark and decorated with fine lines, for chiefs.

ʻahawa

waterhead, beginning of a water-course; to overflow.

ʻahaʻaha₁

cordage.

ʻahaʻaha₂

to sit with back stiff and upright, arms akimbo, head up, as with haughty air of superiority; to sit cross-legged; to stand with hands on hips (considered rude and overbearing).

ʻahaʻaha₃

young of the ʻaha, a fish.

ʻahaʻaina hepekoma

Feast of weeks.

ʻahaʻaina hoʻolaʻa

feast of consecration or dedication, as of a house, church, canoe, or fish net.

ʻahaʻaina hoʻolilo

feast of dedication.

ʻahaʻaina hoʻomanaʻo

commemorative or anniversary feast.

ʻahaʻaina kahe

feast given at the time of a boy's subincision. Called in Christian times ʻahaʻaina ʻoki poepoe.

ʻahaʻaina kahukahu

feast given at the completion of a student's first work (as mat, quilt, tapa, net), or of a child's first fish catch; one purpose was to ask the gods to grant greater knowledge and skill to the craftsman. lit., feast to care for.

ʻahaʻaina kala hala

feast given to ask pardon of the gods. lit., feast to forgive sins.

ʻahaʻaina komo

initiation feast.

ʻahaʻaina laulima

feast held after completion of a joint project or cooperative undertaking, especially harvest.

ʻahaʻaina maka luhi

feast given to honor those who prepared the feast and served, the workers being served by those who had celebrated before; also a feast to celebrate completion of a particularly laborious project. lit., feast for tired persons.

ʻahaʻaina make

funeral feast, intended to comfort the mourners.

ʻahaʻaina male

wedding feast or reception.

ʻahaʻaina māwaewae

feast given shortly after the birth of the first child, intended to clear the way (māwaewae) of misfortune for that child and for all others to follow.

ʻahaʻaina piha makahiki

feast on the first birthday of a child, or to celebrate any anniversary. lit., feast for completion of the year.

ʻahaʻaina pī wai

feast given principally to break the monotony of country life; those instigating the feast would sprinkle (pī wai) their friends with a little water; those sprinkled brought food to the feast or, later, gifts of coins.

ʻahaʻaina waimaka

feast of tears, held on the first anniversary of a death, a happy occasion, as the death by this time has been accepted by the family.

ʻahaʻaina ʻūniki

graduation feast, as for hula dancing or lua fighting.

ʻahaʻōlelo

legislature, assembly, council meeting, congress; to hold such meetings; to serve in the legislature.

ʻahaʻōlelo kau kānāwai

Legislature, lawmaking body.

ʻahaʻōlelo lunakahiko

conference of elders.

ʻahaʻōlelo lāhui

Congress of the United States; national assembly.

ʻahaʻōlelo nui

Congress.

ʻaha₁

meeting, assembly, gathering, convention, court, party. Many types of ʻaha are listed below.

ʻaha₂

• sennit;   • cord braided of coconut husk, human hair, intestines of animals;   • string for a musical instrument;   • to stretch the ʻaha cord for the outline of a house so that the posts may be properly placed;   • measurement of an edge or border.

ʻaha₃

a prayer or service whose efficacy depended on recitation under taboo and without interruption. The priest was said to carry a cord (ʻaha).

ʻaha₄

millepede, so called because it coils itself up like a string.

ʻaha₅

any of the needlefishes of the family Belonidae. The young are called ʻahaʻaha. Varieties are qualified by the terms holowī, mele, and uliuli.

ʻaha₆

design supposed to resemble the continuing track of a duck, carved on tapa beaters.

ʻahele

snare; to snare.

ʻahi

Hawaiian tuna fishes, especially the yellow-fin tuna (Thunnus albacares), an important fish in the Honolulu market. The name ʻahimay be qualified by the terms hiʻu wīwī (thin tail) or kaʻakaʻalāʻau (dark stripe), kaha uli, kananā (young stage, lit., the defiant one; cf. he aha sananā), kihikihi or ʻōpū hemo (loose belly), lepalepa, maha ʻōʻō (piercing brow), mālailena, maoli, pālaha, and poʻo nui (large head).

ʻahi pālaha

albacore, Thunnus alalunga (family Scombridae). lit., flat ʻahi.

ʻahia₂

how many?

ʻahiku

seven (especially in counting in a series); seven times.

ʻahiʻahi

to defame, slander, tattle against; false report, defamation, slander.

ʻaho

thatch purlin. Also ʻaʻaho.

ʻaho kopekope

name given for roof thatching on top of the ridgepole.

ʻaho kā

small lashing on the pueo main purlin.

ʻaho piʻo kuahui

thatch purlin support.

ʻaho pueo

main purlin in a house.

ʻahohui

thatch purlin support.

ʻahokele

horizontal thatch purlin.

ʻaholo

sliding rock, landslide, avalanche.

ʻahu

• garment or covering for the upper part of the body and shoulders, as a cape, shirt, coat;   • to put on or wear such;   • fine soft mat, formerly often used as a cloak;   • mat used as a canoe cover;   • short for ʻahu ʻula.

ʻahu hīnano

soft, fine mat garment plaited from fine strands of dried bracts of male pandanus fruit.

ʻahu moena

fine patterned mat, plaited with materials of different colors.

ʻahu poʻo nui

cloth bound about the head of warriors.

ʻahu ua

old type of raincoat made of dried ti leaves fastened to an olonā net, or consisting of a small mat about 1.2 by 1.8 m, made of makaloa sedge, and so supple that it could be rolled up; to wear this garment. Today, raincoat is kukaweke and kuka ua.

ʻahu uhi waʻa

mat canoe covering that protected paddlers in storms.

ʻahu ʻao

choice mat of fine strands of soft white young pandanus leaves, about 3 cm mesh.

ʻahu ʻoʻeno

matting with twilled pattern, associated with Kauaʻi.

ʻahu ʻula₁

feather cloak or cape made of the feathers of the ʻōʻō, ʻiʻiwi and other birds, usually red or yellow trimmed with black or green, formerly worn by high chiefs and kings. Today [ca.1957] about 160 have been located in museums and collections of the world, the largest being in the Bishop Museum, Honolulu. Imitation cloaks of plush, felt, paper, or dyed feathers (rare) are worn today in pageants and by members of Hawaiian societies. lit., royal cloak.

ʻahulu

discolored, foamy, feathery, choppy, uneven, mussed.

ʻahuna

coat, garment, ti-leaf raincoat.

ʻahunāliʻi₁

a tapa for chiefs, colored with candlenut and noni and striped red.

ʻahunāliʻi₂

issue of a union of a male chief and a commoner.

ʻahuʻawa haole

the umbrella plant, a leafless ornamental sedge (Cyperus alternifolius), 30 to 180 cm high, the umbrella-shaped flowering head with about 20 grasslike rays at the top of a slender stalk.

ʻahuʻawa₁

a sedge (Cyperus javanicus) about .3 to 1.3 m high, with a basal tuft of long narrow leaves and a radiating inflorescence borne at the tip of a long slender stem.

ʻahuʻawa₂

another coarse sedge (Cyperus hypochlorus) similar to the preceding one, but with green instead of brown flowers.

ʻahā

four (usually in counting in series): four times.

ʻahē

a hacking cough; to cough. Also ʻehē.

ʻai aliʻi

to rule (or eat) as a chief.

ʻai haʻa₁

hula step danced with bended knees; the chanting for this dance is usually bombastic and emphatic (UL 266); to dance thus. lit., low style.

ʻai haʻa₂

allegro.

ʻai hele

lit., to eat walking.

ʻai hoʻokano

to eat proudly of high-priced food, as a rich person; fig., to have many women.

ʻai kalo paʻa

unpounded taro. fig., difficult problem that must be chewed, as whole taro.

ʻai kanaka₅

cannibal, man-eater; to eat human flesh.

ʻai kapu

to eat under taboo; to observe eating taboos.

ʻai kepa

to cut or tear obliquely, as with teeth or edged instrument; to seize or tear with the teeth; to fit by rabbeting, rabbet.

ʻai kū

to eat freely; to do as one wishes; to break taboos or transgress.

ʻai kūpele

medicinal juices mixed with poi or mashed sweet potato, used to build up strength. lit., kneaded poi.

ʻai lau₁

to eat a great deal.

ʻai lau₂

a bundle of cooked taro wrapped in ti leaves.

ʻai lepo

to eat filth (insulting).

ʻai lā

scorched or sunburned.

ʻai moku

ruler of a moku, district or island; to rule a moku.

ʻai māmā

light meal, snack; to eat such.

ʻai noa

to eat freely, without observance of taboos.

ʻai nui

principle or staple food; to eat a lot.

ʻai pala maunu

to eat a dab of bait. fig., to take the leavings of others, to steal another's mate, one who does so; a beggar.

ʻai pala niho

lit., to eat tooth tartar.

ʻai paʻa

cooked taro pounded into a hard mass not mixed with water, sometimes preserved in ti-leaf bundles. fig., a difficult problem. lit., hard poi.

ʻai pilau

eater of filth, scavenger; to eat rotten food; rotten food; and insulting epithet for a sorcerer who prays others to death.

ʻai puʻupuʻu

lumpy poi.

ʻai pōʻala

to gulp, choke, suffocate.

ʻai pū

to eat together (both sexes), formerly tabu.

ʻai waiū

nursing, suckling, as an infant; to nurse, suckle; a nursing child, unweaned animal. lit., to eat milk.

ʻai ā manō

to eat like a shark. fig., to have a ravenous appetite.

ʻai ā puaʻa

to eat like a pig; to eat greedily; to wolf food.

ʻai ʻokoʻa

cooked unpounded taro. lit., whole taro. Kauaʻi.

ʻai ʻuhaʻuha

to eat wastefully; a wasteful or riotous eater.

ʻai ʻāina

to rule or own land.

ʻaiakahonu

lit., food of the turtle.

ʻaiakanēnē

a native trailing, woody plant (Coprosma ernodeoides), with narrow, tiny leaves and black, berry-like fruits. lit., food of the nēnē goose.

ʻaialo

attendant of the chief's household, intimate of a chief. lit., eating [in the] presence.

ʻaiana

clothes iron; to iron, press, as clothes.

ʻaiau₁

to look about with covetous or jealous eyes; to practice sorcery or poisoning.

ʻaiau₂

weary, discouraged by long continued work.

ʻaiea₁

all species of the endemic Hawaiian genus Nothocestrum, soft-wooded shrubs and trees with ovate or oblong leaves, yellowish flowers, and whitish to reddish berries. One slender species was used for thatching sticks (ʻaho) and fire-making.

ʻaiea₃

exhaustion.

ʻaihue kanaka

to kidnap; kidnapper.

ʻaihumuhumu

to eat in order to destroy; to destroy wantonly or by violence or sorcery.

ʻaihē

center of a taro corm.

ʻaika

hard and poor tasting, as thin or inferior fish.

ʻaikapa

a privileged friend who shares the profits of a friend's land, sometimes sharing in the work; one who shares a friend's spouse; to share land or spouse; to pay part of a debt but withhold the remainder. lit., eat [on the] border.

ʻaikena

sick and tired of a person or situation, surfeited, exhausted, discouraged, fatigued.

ʻaikepakepa

to snap the jaws; to speak rapidly, as with overlapping words; to talk too much or too fast; to jabber.

ʻaikola

interj. of scorn or derision, especially rejoicing over others' misfortunes, with meaning "serves you right" or "I told you so"; as a verb, to use this term.

ʻaila

any oil, grease, lard; to oil, grease, lubricate. Many kinds of oil and grease are listed below.

ʻaila hoʻomaloʻo pena

turpentine. lit., oil for drying paint.

ʻaila hoʻonahā

castor oil. lit., purge oil.

ʻaila koka

cod-liver oil.

ʻaila kolī

castor oil. lit., castor-bean oil.

ʻaila kēpama

sperm oil.

ʻaila māhu

kerosene. lit., steam oil.

ʻaila palai

frying oil.

ʻaila paʻa

thick grease.

ʻaila puaʻa

lard, pork grease.

ʻailahonua

kerosene. lit., earth oil.

ʻailana₁

in love.

ʻailana₂

island.

ʻailea

gasoline (contraction of ʻaila, oil, and ea, air).

ʻailolo₁

ceremony usually marking the end of training, so called because the student ate (ʻai) a portion of the head, and especially the brains (lolo), of a fish, dog, or hog offered to the gods; to partake of the ceremony.

ʻailolo₂

skilled, adept, expert, trained, proficient.

ʻaimīkana

linnet, California house finch, papaya bird (Carpodacus mexicanus frontalis), an early introduction to Hawaiʻi, now well established throughout the Hawaiian Islands. lit., papaya eater.

ʻaina kea

a good-looking variety of sugar cane, of medium height, striped red and green or yellow, pith white and brown, leaves and leaf sheaths with white markings; used in medicine.

ʻaina kea melemele

a variety of sugar cane, the yellow mutant of ʻaina kea.

ʻaina kō

cane trash, bagasse.

ʻaina ʻole

not eaten or consumed; without vegetable foods.

ʻainakini

navy blue cotton cloth.

ʻaina₂

eaten, consumed devoured.

ʻaina₃

rejected, as refuse, especially of sugar cane.

ʻainea

exhausted by strain and trouble, tired, weary.

ʻainemanema

to criticize severely, hunt for flaws, split hairs.

ʻainiha

bad temper; bad tempered, cross.

ʻainā

sore aching; stiffness, as from overexercise.

ʻaipoʻolā

feast to celebrate the completion of a hard task or project. lit., food [for] workers [in the] sun.

ʻaipuni

to encircle, go around, encompass, environ.

ʻaiwa

nine (usually in counting in a series); nine times.

ʻaiā

• ungodly,   • godless,   • irreligious, unbelieving, careless of observance of taboos;   • wicked, wickedness.

ʻaiō₁

a wave that rises and falls without breaking; a swell.

ʻaiō₂

heigh-ho.

ʻaiʻaiele

swinging, unsteady motion.

ʻaiʻaiohua

name given for persons sacrificed for not observing taboos during the offering of prayers by the priest (pronunciation not certain).

ʻaiʻai₂

dependent, one living on the resources of another.

ʻaiʻami

type of hula with little foot movement, but with hip revolving throughout the dance; to dance thus.

ʻaiʻili loko

to have the use of fish ponds (loko); to control the interior (loko) land division known as ʻili.

ʻaiʻē

debt; to owe.

ʻai₂

score, points in a game, stake, wager.

ʻai₃

dancing style or type.

ʻai₄

• stroke or hold in lua fighting;   • spear thrust.

ʻai₅

stone used in the kimo game other than the stone that is tossed and caught, which is the pōhaku kimo.

ʻaka

to laugh; laughter.

ʻaka hene

to laugh at teasingly, jeer.

ʻaka iki

to laugh a little, snicker.

ʻakahakanaʻi

name of a kind of white tapa.

ʻakahi akahi

inexperienced, trying out for the first time; novice, beginner.

ʻakahi₁

one (especially in counting in a series).

ʻakahi₂

for the first time, never before (usually followed by nō).

ʻakahi₃

to have just.

ʻakakane

Hawaiʻi ʻākepa (honey creeper), Loxops coccinea coccinea, endangered.

ʻakaka₁

a rent, split, chink, separation; to crack, split, scale

ʻakaka₂

agate.

ʻakake

agate.

ʻakaki

agate.

ʻakakē

spry, quick, nimble, especially about getting into people's way or into trouble.

ʻakalio

farthing.

ʻakama

adamant.

ʻakaʻakai kulapepeiao

big, yellowish onion. lit., earring onion.

ʻakaʻakai kīkānia

a common variety of onion.

ʻakaʻakai kūmakahiki

a purplish annual onion.

ʻakaʻakai lau

green onion (Allium fistulosum); its leaves are eaten with salt salmon. lit., leaf onion.

ʻakaʻakai mahina

a wild onion, used for sore throat. lit., moon onion, so called because the curve of the section of the bulb suggests a crescent moon.

ʻakaʻakai naku

bulrush.

ʻakaʻakai pilau

garlic (Allium sativum).

ʻakaʻakai pūpū

garlic. lit., bunched onion.

ʻakaʻakai₁

the great bulrush (Scirpus validus, formerly called S. lacustris) that grows on the edge of fresh or brackish water marshes in Hawaiʻi. The plants have unbranched, slender, green stems, 1 to 3 m high, looking like giant onion plants. Formerly Hawaiians used them for house thatch or plaited them into mats for the lower layers of beds or for some temporary purposes, as the material is not durable. S. californicus on Niʻihau.

ʻakaʻakai₂

the common onion (Allium cepa); the tops look like those of the great bulrush.

ʻakekeke₁

ruddy turnstone (Arenaria interpres), a winter migrant to Hawaiʻi, occurring in small flocks which rise and wheel together.

ʻakekeke₂

to talk loquaciously in a friendly, hospitable manner, bidding a guest to feel at home, make himself comfortable, eat plenty.

ʻakekeʻe

a honey creeper (Loxops coccinea caeruleirostris). Usually called ʻākepa in Eng.

ʻakele

acre.

ʻakepeuʻie

Oʻahu ʻākepa (honey eater), Loxops coccinea rufa, presumed extinct; Maui ʻākepa, L. c. ochracea, endangered.

ʻakeu

active, lively, quick; pleasant, sociable.

ʻaki lou

to take with a lou or fruit-plucking stick.

ʻakiahala

an endemic, small, hairy, pink-flowered shrub (Hibiscus youngianus), usually found in marshy places.

ʻakialoa

a group of Hawaiian honey creepers with long, curved bill, olive or yellow-green above, lighter below (Hemignathus obscurus), with subspecies on Hawaiʻi (H.o.o.), Lānaʻi (H.o. lanaiesis), and Kauaʻi (H. procerus). The latter is endangered; it has the longest curved beak, for sipping honey at the base of ʻieʻie and hala pepe leaves. cf. ʻiwi, ʻiʻiwi.

ʻakihi

birds. see below.

ʻakihi keʻehi ʻale

a small black sea bird, probably a stormy petrel (Oceanodroma), of which two dark, sooty species are known about the Hawaiian Islands, especially those to the northwest. lit., billow-treading ʻakihi.

ʻakihi poʻo lāʻau

the nuku puʻu honey creeper of Hawaiʻi (Hemignathus wilsoni).

ʻakihi pōlena

a bird listed by Malo.

ʻakihoʻolana

drydock, lit., floating canoe-rest.

ʻakika

acid.

ʻakika kapolika

carbolic acid.

ʻakikiki

the endemic Kauaʻi creeper (Loxops maculata bairdi, formerly Paroreomyza bairdi).

ʻakiki₁

dwarfed; dwarf.

ʻakilolo ʻulaʻula

a variety of sugar cane, with purplish leaves.

ʻakilolo₁

a wrasse fish of the hīnālea type (Gomphosus varius). Also hīnālea ʻakilolo. This fish was used by priests as the pani or closing medicine for head diseases. The taro or sugar cane of the same name might substitute. lit., brain biting.

ʻakilolo₂

a variety of sugar cane, striped with green and deep purplish-red when young, with yellow and red when older; named for the fish.

ʻakilolo₃

a variety of taro.

ʻakima

feast of unleavened bread.

ʻakimalala

admiral.

ʻakina

biting; bite.

ʻakiohala

an endemic, small, hairy, pink-flowered shrub (Hibiscus youngianus), usually found in marshy places.

ʻakioma

axiom.

ʻakipohe₁

to nip.

ʻakipohe₂

round, as a leaf; compact, concise.

ʻakipohe₄

to center or concentrate in one place, as wind, rain.

ʻakipīhopa

archbishop.

ʻakiu

to search, seek, probe, penetrate, spy.

ʻakiʻaki haole

buffalo grass (Stenotaphrum secundatum), an American grass used for lawns. Some people believed that buffalo grass could be used to exorcise spirits because it had been given the same name (ʻakiʻaki) as the seashore rush grass, which was used for this purpose.

ʻakiʻaki₁

redup. of ʻaki₁, to take a nip and let go, snap; to nibble, as fish...   • to nibble, as a fish;   • constant snapping at,   • attacking.

ʻakiʻaki₂

seashore rush grass (Sporobolus virginicus), a coarse grass growing on sandy beaches; used to exorcise spirits.

ʻakiʻaki₃

a kind of coarse red seaweed (Ahnfeltia concinna) which because of its toughness must be eaten in little bites; a good source of carrageenin, a colloid. Called ʻeleau on Maui.

ʻakiʻikiʻi

dip net, as used in fishing uhu.

ʻaki₁

• to take a nip and let go, snap; to nibble, as fish;   • to bite off the bark of sugar cane;   • to heal, as a wound;   • to scar over;   • sharp recurring pain, as in head or stomach.   • fig., to attack, taunt, malign, snap at;   • slander (Hal. 50.20) ;   • backbiter (Roma 1.30) .

ʻaki₂

height, tip, top (preceded by ke).

ʻaki₃

pillow.

ʻaki₄

block on which a canoe is placed on the shore.

ʻaki₅

filled, as a canoe with waves.

ʻakoa

a small tree resembling koa; dye was made from its bark, and to color tapa. (And) But cf. kūʻoulena.

ʻakohi

a variety or taro.

ʻakoka

a nut.

ʻakoki

a variety of sugar cane, deep-red and green when young, changing to purple and brown-yellow; pith dark-brown; larger and stronger than ʻakilolo, especially in wet districts.

ʻakoko

endemic shrubs and trees (Euphorbia spp.) with jointed stems, opposite leaves, and milky sap. Buds and leaves of one species (E. multiformis) were chewed for debility.

ʻakoleana

accordion.

ʻakole₁

poor, destitute, shiftless.

ʻakole₂

a large endemic fern (Dryopteris unidentata), 1 m or more high, with triangular-oblong fronds much subdivided.

ʻakolika

ostrich.

ʻakolo

to creep, attempt to creep; to put out small roots, as potatoes.

ʻakolu

three (as in counting in a series); three times.

ʻakomika

atomic.

ʻakopie

adobe.

ʻakoʻako₃

crest of a wave; to break or swell, as waves.

ʻako₂

• itch,   • throat irritation,   • venereal disease.   • fig., lust.

ʻakukana

adjutant.

ʻakukana kenelala

adjutant general.

ʻakuku

to beat, as tapa.

ʻakulekele

adultery.

ʻakulikuli kai₁

a tropical American, low succulent (Batis maritima), commonly forming a continuous green cover by salt marshes. Locally called pickleweed.

ʻakumu

broken or cut off, as a pencil point; blunt, stumpy.

ʻakupa₂

a small endemic tree (Bobea mannii).

ʻakēʻakē

Hawaiian storm petrel (Oceanodroma castro cryptoleucura).

ʻakū

an endemic lobelia (Cyanea tritomantha), a small tree 2 to 3 m high, with clustered leaves (up to 78 by 20 cm), somewhat downy beneath. The leaves were cooked and eaten like cabbage.

ʻakūkū

tossing about, agitated; jolting, as a vehicle on a rough road.

ʻakūʻakū₁

swaying, as a canoe in rough sea; not steady; bumpy, as a road.

ʻakūʻakū₂

hasty, poorly done, rash.

ʻakūʻakū₃

an endemic lobelia (Cyanea rollandioides) 1 to 1.4 m high, with rough leaves to 50 by 15 cm. The leaves were cooked like cabbage or taro tops or sweet potato leaves, with pork or salt beef.

ʻalaaumoe

a West Indian shrub, night cestrum (Cestrum nocturnum), Chinese inkberry, with narrow leaves and narrow, tubular, green-to-creamy white flowers, which are most fragrant at night.

ʻalae awī

the introduced Australian gallinule Porphyrio poliocephalus, P. p. melanotus. Also applied to a form of ʻalae kea, with brownish frontal knob.

ʻalae kea

Hawaiian coot (Fulica americana alai), a marsh and pond bird, distinguished from ʻalae ʻula by its ivory-white frontal knob; endangered.

ʻalae nū kea

lit., white-beaked ʻalae.

ʻalae ʻula

Hawaiian gallinule or mudhen (Gallinula chloropus sandvicensis), distinguished from ʻalae kea by its reddish bill and frontal plate; endangered.

ʻalaea kāne

dark-red ʻalaea. lit., male ʻalaea₃.

ʻalaea wahine

light-red ʻalaea. lit., female ʻalaea₃.

ʻalaea₁

• water-soluble colloidal ocherous earth, used for coloring salt, for medicine, for dye, and formaly in the purification ceremony called hiʻuwai;   • any red colloring matter;   • according to Dr. Frank Tabrah, brick-red soil containing hematite.

ʻalaea₂

flesh like redness, especially the dark red meat close to the spine of some fish, as of the aku.

ʻalaea₃

annatto dye plant (Bixa orellana), a tropical American shrub or small tree, bearing fruit with scarlet seeds, used for dyeing. Sometimes called ʻalaea lāʻau to distinguish from the earth; locally also called lipstick plant.

ʻalaea₄

• tribe or clan;   • people in a district who have intermarried.

ʻalaea₅

bad breath, halitosis.

ʻalaea₆

fore part of thigh; long narrow thigh muscle.

ʻalae₁

mudhen or Hawaiian gallinule (Gallinula chloropus sandvicensis), a black wading bird with red frontal plate; cry of this bird is believed a bad omen; some considered the ʻalae an ʻaumakua; endangered. For the coot, see ʻalae kea. see saying, keʻu.

ʻalaiaha

an upland bird, gray, about rite size of the ʻelepaio, reported in 1863.

ʻalakai

potbellied, bloated.

ʻalakapaika

allspice.

ʻalakenika

arsenic.

ʻalakuma

a large crab (Carpilius maculatus), with 11 dark red spots on its back, usually found concealed in rocks or under stones.

ʻalakē

to jump, hurry from place to place.

ʻalalala

to dry or wither leaves over a fire, as of tobacco.

ʻalalauā

young of the red ʻāweoweo fish. Appearance of schools of this fish near shore was an omen that royalty would die.

ʻalalehe

sickly, weak, fretful, as a child; fretfulness.

ʻalalāna

bleating, wailing.

ʻalalā₁

to bawl, bleat, squeal, cry, caw, yelp, wail, scream; such noises.

ʻalalā₂

Hawaiian crow (Corvus tropicus), named for its caw; endangered [extinct in the wild].

ʻalalā₃

a style of chanting with open mouth vibration and tremor of the voice, and prolonged vowels; to chant thus

ʻalalā₄

to gargle.

ʻalalī

sharp shrill yelp, sudden screech; to yelp, screech.

ʻalama

protection, defense.

ʻalamea₁

ripe

ʻalamea₂

precious, as a child

ʻalamea₃

a bird (no data)

ʻalamihi

a common black crab (Metopograpsus thukuhar).

ʻalamoʻo

an endemic fresh-water ʻoʻopu fish (Len tipes concolor). Hilo. Also hiʻu ʻula, hiʻu kole.

ʻalaneo₁

• clear, unclouded,clearness,   • calm, serene, stillness;   • free from impediment;   • emptiness, nothing; desolate.

ʻalaneo₂

of a single color or texture, especially of a feather cloak without design and made of feathers of a single kind and color.

ʻalaneo₃

swelling disease, dropsy, generalized edema, kidney disease.

ʻalaneo₄

name of a class of 12 male supernatural beings called papa pae māhū, said to be hermaphrodite healers from Kahiki. One at least was according to legend turned to stone and has been moved to Kuhiō Park, Waīkīkī, Oʻahu. see Paemāhū (in Pukui, Elbert and Mookini, 1974).

ʻalani Pākē

tangerine, mandarin (Citrus reticulata cv. ‘deliciosa’), a small tree with small leaves and small, loose-skinned, orange, flattened globose, sweet fruits. lit., Chinese orange. On Niʻihau, identified as C. grandis; cf. (Neal 481).

ʻalani ʻawaʻawa

calamondin (Citris mitis), a small tree with flattened-globose fruits to 2.6 cm in diameter, orange-colored, few-seeded, sour.

ʻalaopuna

a variety of taro, growing wild, also cultivated dry in Puna, Hawaiʻi; fragrant when cooked, like kāī.

ʻalapahi

slander, falsehood, deceit; slanderer; to slander, defame, deceive, lie.

ʻalapaka₁

alpaca.

ʻalapaka₂

alabaster, ointment vase of alabaster.

ʻalapapa

alfalfa.

ʻalapia₂

a heavy cloth resembling serge.

ʻalapuʻu

small, young, of creatures.

ʻalauahio

endemic Hawaiian honey creepers (Loxops maculata),   • Oʻahu creeper (L. m. maculata), endangered;   • Lānaʻi creeper (L. m. montana), presumed extinct;   • Maui creeper (L. m. newtoni);   • Hawaiʻi creeper (L. m. mana), endangered.

ʻalawa₁

to glance, look quickly; glance.

ʻalawa₂

a bird (no data).

ʻalaʻala wai nui₁

all species of Peperomia, small native succulent forest herbs, related to ʻawa. The name is qualified by the terms kāne (on Oʻahu) or kupa liʻi (on Hawaiʻi), pehu, pōhina.

ʻalaʻala wai nui₂

a small weedy herb (Plectranthus parviflorus), in the mint family. This name may be qualified by the terms pua kī, wahine.

ʻalaʻala₁

• ink sac in octopus or squid;   • after salting, drying, and broiling on the fire, it is mixed with ʻinamona or chili peppers and eaten;   • mixed with ʻauhuhu juice it is used as bait.   • fig., useless.

ʻalaʻala₂

scar of a scrofulous sore; to be so scarred; perhaps tuberculosis adenitis.

ʻalaʻala₃

aerial tubers of bitter yam, hoi (Dioscorea bulbifera).

ʻalaʻalā

small ʻalā stones.

ʻalaʻeke

an edible crab of the Portunus sp., sandcolored, and found in shallow water.

ʻalaʻi

gentle, as a breeze.

ʻalaʻihi₁

various species of squirrelfishes of the family Holocentridae, including Flammeo sammara (spotfin squirrelfish, 185 mm), Adioryx lacteoguttatus (whitespotted, 117 mm), A. diadema, (crown, 109 mm), A. xanterythrus (Hawaiian, 132 mm), A. tiers (Tahitian, 259 mm). The young are called ʻaʻalaʻihi. Unidentified kinds are qualified by the terms ākoʻakoʻa, kala loa or kanaloa, lā kea, māhū, maoli, and pilikoʻa.

ʻalaʻihi₂

pale pink tapa; any faded color

ʻalaʻihi₃

a variety of sugar cane named for the fish, either a deep-red mutant of ʻāwela or related to it; internodes barrel-shaped, leaves purple.

ʻalaʻuka

• homely, homeliness,   • vile, vileness,   • slovenly,   • worthless;   • dregs of society.

ʻala₂

a variety of taro, said to be pungent-smelling when cooked. Varieties are qualified by the terms ʻeleʻele, keʻokeʻo, ʻōpelu; cf. also ʻalaopuna.

ʻale kua loloa

long-backed billow.

ʻale kuakea

whitecaps, white spray.

ʻale kūpīpī

dashing billow.

ʻale olowalu

billows that follow one after the other.

ʻalea

area.

ʻalehe

snare, noose; to snare.

ʻaleka

large tree of the pine family, cedar, fir. (Bib.)

ʻalekanika

arsenic.

ʻalekea

heron.

ʻaleko

alto.

ʻalekohola

alcohol.

ʻalekuma

algum tree. (Bib.)

ʻalelele

to skip, jump, fly.

ʻalemanaka

almanac, calendar.

ʻalemone

almond (Prunus dulcis), hazel tree (KJV), almond (RSV) (Kin. 30.37) .

ʻalepa

alpha.

ʻalepapeka

alphabet.

ʻaleʻa

sweet-voiced.

ʻaleʻaki

a swamping wave, as one striking a canoe broadside from prow to stern.

ʻaleʻale

redup. of ʻale₁, wave, crest of a wave, billow; to ripple, form waves, stir...;   • stirring, moving, undulating, tossing, rippling,   • full to the brim.

ʻaleʻo

tower, high lookout, gazebo; towering.

ʻale₁

• wave, crest of a wave, billow;   • to ripple, form waves, stir; rippling, stirring.   • to well, as tears in the eyes;

ʻale₂

gust.

ʻale₃

are, a unit of measure.

ʻalihi kēpau

lower cord in a net to which lead sinkers were attached.

ʻalihi pāʻū

line for lashing down the pāʻū mat covering of a canoe.

ʻalihi pīkoi

upper cord in a net to which floats were attached.

ʻalihi pōhaku

lower cord in a net to which stone sinkers were attached.

ʻalihikaua

general, commander in battle, strategist.

ʻalihikaua nui

commander in chief.

ʻalihilele

dragnet, mullet net.

ʻalihi₁

cords or fine ropes threaded through marginal meshes of upper and lower edges of nets, to which were attached floats and sinkers; loops at the top of a kōkō net holding a calabash. see below and ʻupena ʻalihi.

ʻalihi₂

horizon (sometimes qualified by lani or moana). cf. lihi, edge.

ʻalihi₃

deceit, trickery; to deceive, cheat.

ʻalikekoa

alligator.

ʻalima

five (especially in counting in a series); five times.

ʻalimakika

arithmetic.

ʻali₁

scar, depression, groove, imbedded mark. Also ʻeli.

ʻaloe

aloe, any plant of the genus Aloe; also the pānini ʻawaʻawa.

ʻalohi

to shine, glitter, sparkle; bright, brilliant; splendor, brilliancy.

ʻalohi lani

brightness of heaven, a term applied to the heavenly courts of the goddesses Uli and Kapo.

ʻalokio

alodial title, alodium, fee simple.

ʻaloma

aroma.

ʻalopalopā

shiftless, dependent on others for a livelihood.

ʻalopeke

fox.

ʻaloʻalo₁

• to dodge rapidly or continuously;   • to look about slyly;   • evasive.

ʻaloʻalo₃

lumpy, as poi.

ʻaloʻalo₄

a kind of small inshore fish (no data).

ʻalo₂

• to be with, share an experience,   • come near,   • go with, attend, escort, accompany,   • endure,   • resist.

ʻalu

• depression, gutter, ravine;   • lines of the hand,   • loose skin over the eyeball;   • tuck in a garment, shirring, ruffling; to ruff, as a mat.   • descent, as of trail or road;   • of low rank (Kep. 125);   • to bend, duck, stoop;   • hang, sag, slacken,   • to relax;

ʻalua

two, twice. Pōʻalua, Tuesday; lit., second day.

ʻaluheʻe

loose, as a bundle not securely tied; flabby, ill-fitting, loose-jointed.

ʻaluʻalu

• loose, flabby; misshapen, as a premature baby;   • slack, as a rope;   • to sag;   • wrinkled, uneven, rough, lined;   • foetus;   • skin, rind, peel.

ʻalā

dense waterworn volcanic stone, as used for poi pounders, adzes, hula stones; hard lava, basalt. Kinds of ʻalā rock, as used for adzes, are qualified by the phrases pia maka hinu, shiny-faced arrowroot; māhinu, shiny; and maka hinu, shiny face. also (Kam. 76:122) ʻalā haumeku ʻolokele, ʻalā lelekepue.

ʻalā mea

hard volcanic stone, used for adzes

ʻalā poʻo malu

name of a dark basalt.

ʻalē

marshy; marsh, swamp.

ʻalīlea

the common turbo shell (Turbo sandwicensis).

ʻamakihi

a group of small endemic Hawaiian honey creepers, Loxops virens; abundant on Hawaiʻi (L. v. v.), Maui (L. v. wilsoni), and Kauaʻi, uncommon on Oʻahu (L. v. chloris) and Molokaʻi, rare on Lānaʻi. The feathers are yellow and greenish, and were formerly used in feather capes. The Kauaʻi form was also called alawī kihi.

ʻamaʻama₁

mullet (Mugil cephalus), a very choice indigenous fish. Stages are (finger length) pua ʻama, pua ʻamaʻama, pua poʻolā, ʻoʻolā; (hand length) kahaha (or pahaha); (20 cm) ʻamaʻama; (30 cm or more) ʻanae. fig., an easy mark (modern slang).

ʻamaʻumaʻu

young ʻamaʻu ferns; many ʻamaʻu ferns, ferny, abounding in ʻamaʻu ferns; a covering of ʻamaʻu ferns (preceded by ke).

ʻamaʻu₁

all species of an endemic genus of ferns (Sadleria), with trunk more or less evident. The fronds are narrower, smaller, and less divided than those of the hāpuʻu. At least one species has at the top of the trunk a mass of soft scales (pulu) used as pillow stuffing. Formerly, in times of famine, the tasteless pith of the trunk was cooked and eaten. The fronds were used to mulch dry-land taro, the stems for plaiting and as sizing for tapa. The ʻamaʻu was one of the forms that Kamapuaʻa, the pig god, could take at will. Also maʻumaʻu, maʻu.

ʻamaʻu₂

place where ʻamaʻu₁ ferns are found.

ʻama₁

talkative, prattling, tattling.

ʻama₂

light, bright.

ʻama₃

young ʻamaʻama fish, usually called pua ʻama.

ʻameki

amethyst.

ʻamekukeke

amethyst. (Puk. 28.19)

ʻamene

amen; to say amen.

ʻamepela

amber.

ʻami honua

exaggerated and rapid revolving of the hips in the hula; to do so.

ʻami hoʻokuʻi

joint. lit., connecting joint.

ʻami hoʻokuʻina lewa

ball-and-socket joint. lit., swinging connecting joint.

ʻami kai

an amphipod (Caprellid amphipods) that clings to seaweeds or hydroids; it has a long slender body and is the color of the seaweed or hydroid on which it feeds.

ʻami kuʻupau

very rapid revolution of the hips in the hula; an uninhibited (kuʻupau) ʻami; to do so.

ʻami kāhela

hula step; hip rotations with weight on the right hip as the left heel lifts very slightly, then reversing; to do this ʻami.

ʻami kūkū

a hula step with ʻami; like the ʻami kāhela except that the revolutions are smaller and faster and in groups of three; sometimes two slower kāhela revolutions are followed by three faster kūkū revolutions; to perform this step.

ʻami poepoe

same as ʻami kāhela but a new term. lit., round ʻami.

ʻami puka

hinge of door or gate.

ʻami ʻōpū

an ʻami hula step with abdomen thrust forward, considered in poor taste; to do this step. lit. stomach ʻami.

ʻamiʻami

• elastic, pendulous, springy;   • jerking of the hips back and forth in a crude or vulgar ʻami hula;   • motion of sexual intercourse;   • to move on hinges.

ʻamiʻōniu

the figure-eight hula step; the revolving hips (ʻami) form an eight, with weight shifting; to perform this step. lit., spinning ʻami.

ʻami₁

hinge, joint; to turn on hinges.

ʻami₂

a hula step with hip revolutions; to do this step. Three types are ʻami kāhela, ʻami kūkū, and ʻami ʻōniu.

ʻami₃

measuring worm.

ʻamokiʻi₁

stem of fruits or tubers; small end of sweet potato tuber.

ʻamokiʻi₂

genitals of male.

ʻamomo

amomum, a genus of plants in the ginger family.

ʻamonia

ammonia.

ʻamopuʻu

thin, emaciated, lean. lit., protruding anal opening.

ʻamo₁

wink, sparkle; to wink, sparkle, glimmer, twinkle.

ʻamo₂

contraction of the anal muscles, anal opening, vagina. cf. pī ka ʻamo under pī₂.

ʻamumū

dull, blunt; dullness, bluntness.

ʻana ʻalaea

red pumice.

ʻana ʻōlaʻi

white pumice with fine pores.

ʻanae

full-sized ʻamaʻama mullet fish.

ʻanahua

deformed, disfigured, stoop-shouldered, lopsided; such a person.

ʻanaka

gekko (RSV); polecat, ferret (KJV).

ʻanakeʻe

bent, crooked, misshapen.

ʻanakia

anarchy, anarchist.

ʻanakoe

nothing remains to be done.

ʻanakomia

anatomy.

ʻanakoʻi

inflammatory swelling of a lymph gland, venereal tumor, bubo.

ʻanakā

anchor.

ʻanaliʻi₁

wee, stunted.

ʻanaliʻi₂

a native fern (Asplenium lobulatum) with narrow fronds to 45 cm long, having many narrow lobes along two opposite sides of the axis.

ʻananalu

a variety of hīnālea fish.

ʻananuʻu

to collapse or deflate, as a balloon.

ʻanapa

to shine, gleam, glitter, flash, sparkle; brightness, gleam.

ʻanapau

to leap, frisk, frolic; frisky. [Now heard only in the song: He aha ka hana a ʻAnapau (mele maʻi for Queen Liliʻuokalani)? What does Frisky do?]

ʻanapuʻu₁

bumpy, lumpy, jagged, uneven; bump, hump; to hump along, buck; to project, as the bones of a thin animal.

ʻanau

• to move with a jerky motion;   • to go gadding from place to place.

ʻanau hele

to go here and there, gad.

ʻanaʻana₁

pellet-shaped, as goat dung.

ʻanaʻana₂

to shiver, tremble.

ʻana₁

pumice, used as a rubber.

ʻana₂

siliceous sponge (Leiodermatium), used as medicine and as sandpaper.

ʻanekelo

angle.

ʻanekelopa

antelope; gazelle (RSV), roebuck (KJV)

ʻaneko

dill (RSV), anise (KJV).

ʻanemoku

peninsula. lit., near island (perhaps a translation of French presqu'île).

ʻaneʻane

nearly, almost, scarcely, hardly, not quite, fairly; near.

ʻaneʻi₂

doubtful (used idiomatically).

ʻane₁

to draw near.

ʻanianiau

a small, bright olive or yellowish-green Hawaiian honey creeper (Loxops [formerly Chlorodrepanis] parva), endemic to Kauaʻi, and related to the ʻamakihi. The young birds which are confused with young ʻamakihi, were reported to have been called alawī. The greater ʻamakihi (L. satittirostris) is presumed extinct.

ʻanikelikeko

antichrist. Also shortened to ʻanekaliko.

ʻanini₁

dwarfish, stunded, tiny.

ʻanini₂

to vary, as great and small waves.

ʻanini₃

awning.

ʻano akua

godlike, divine; godly form.

ʻano hana

method, case, technique, as in solving problems.

ʻano hou

new variety, fashion, or kind; new, unusual.

ʻano hui

compound, as of fractions.

ʻano huikau

complex, as of fractions.

ʻano lani

of heavenly or royal character, celestial, noble, royal, pure.

ʻano like

resembling, of similar nature or type; resemblance, similarity.

ʻano pili

property, as of a number; fraction.

ʻano ʻole

insignificant, trivial, of no consequence, unattractive; nonsense.

ʻanoʻai₁

greeting, salutation, news; to greet.

ʻanoʻai₂

unexpected.

ʻanoʻai₃

perhaps.

ʻanoʻi

desire, longing, love, desired one, lover; to desire, yearn; loved, beloved.

ʻanuhe

caterpillar.

ʻanuiki

annuity.

ʻanuʻa

heap, mass, pile.

ʻanuʻu hapa

half-step in music.

ʻanuʻu hapa a me nā ʻanuʻu maoli

an augmented second in music.

ʻanuʻu maoli

full step in music.

ʻanuʻu₁

stairs, jogs, steps, terrace, dais, ledge

ʻanuʻu₂

tower in ancient heiau, about 7 m high and 5.5 m square, as enclosed with white ʻōloa tapa.

ʻanuʻu₃

• sprain, strain, disjointed vertebra;   • to stumble, trip, sprain;   • to land heavily or jar, as when one steps down but there is no step; jarred.   • fig., error, slip; to err.

ʻanuʻu₄

a step between two notes on a musical staff.

ʻanuʻu₅

noun indicating comparison of adjectives.

ʻanāʻanā

black magic, evil sorcery by means of prayer and incantation; to practice this.

ʻao kahi

one remaining leaf (ʻao) on an old taro stalk, said of an old taro about to die.

ʻao lūʻau

unexpanded leaf blade of taro; to offer as a sacrifice.

ʻaoa₂

a small shellfish (Melampus castaneus), strung in leis.

ʻaoa₄

name for sacrificial places near fishponds where semiannual offerings were made, as of taro, bananas, mullet, kohekohe sedge, and black pigs.

ʻaoa₆

hour.

ʻaono

six, especially in counting in a series; six times.

ʻaoʻao hoʻomaʻemaʻe

reform party.

ʻaoʻao kālaiʻāina

political party.

ʻaoʻao kūpale

defense, as in a trial.

ʻaoʻao kūpono

perpendicular, of a triangle.

ʻaoʻao kūʻē

opposition, opponent, as in a trial; minority party.

ʻaoʻao leo nui

a variety of taro (no data).

ʻaoʻao loa

hypotenuse.

ʻaoʻao makani

windward side.

ʻaoʻao mau o ka honua

death, afterlife. lit., everlasting side of the earth.

ʻaoʻao moe

base, as of a triangle.

ʻaoʻao nui

young of the kūpīpī fish, or alternate name.

ʻaoʻao ʻaiʻē

debit side (in bookkeeping).

ʻaoʻao ʻakau

right or leeward side of air island.

ʻaoʻaowela

a green fish.

ʻaoʻao₂

group, team, denomination; party (political).

ʻaoʻao₄

way (Sol. 6.6) , habit, mode of living, education.

ʻaoʻao₅

family gods, ʻaumākua.

ʻao₁

a new shoot, leaf, or bud, especially of taro.

ʻao₂

dried baked taro or sweet potato; in Kaʻū this food was hung in baskets in the wind so that it dehydrated; it was used on sea journeys and is perhaps related to ō, sea rations.

ʻao₃

ship biscuit, pilot bread, hardtack.

ʻapakau

• to seize, lay hold of,   • disarrange, displace;   • to spread, as sunlight.

ʻapakeʻe

deceit, dishonesty: deceitful, corrupt, inaccurate.

ʻapapane

a Hawaiian honey creeper (Himatione sanguinea), with crimson body and black wings and tail, found on all the main Hawaiian Islands. Its feathers occasionally were used for featherwork.

ʻapaʻapa₁

to procrastinate, deliberate, slow.

ʻapaʻapa₂

guile, deceit; to practice such. (Roma 1.25) .

ʻapa₁

to delay, waste time, tarry, linger, keep others waiting.

ʻapa₂

ephah. (Bib.)

ʻape

large taro-like plants (Alocasia macrorrhiza, Xanthosoma robustum). A number of beliefs concerning ʻape have been recorded. ʻape was planted by a gate or fence because the irritating sap of the leaves was thought to ward off evil spirits; leaves were placed under tapas or mats on which the sick lay for the same reason. ʻape was not planted near the house for fear the residents might become sick. Varieties are qualified by the colors kea or keʻokeʻo (white), or hiwa or ʻeleʻele (dark).

ʻapelekoka

apricot (Prunus armeniaca).

ʻapeʻape₁

all endemic species of Gunnera, huge leafed forest perennial herbs, with thick, prostrate stems rising at the tip to about 120 cm. Called hāhā on Kauaʻi.

ʻapeʻape₂

elastic, flexible, limber.

ʻapeʻula

kind of tapa, wrapped about images.

ʻapiʻapi₁

elastic, springy; short of breath.

ʻapiʻapi₃

filled, as a basket; abundant, as a feast.

ʻapi₁

soft spot in the temples; soft part of the human body between the pelvic cone and the lowest rib; under part of an animal's body (sometimes preceded by ke).

ʻapi₂

a surgeonfish (Acanthurus guttatus), 20 cm long.

ʻapi₃

fish gills; to breathe through gills.

ʻapi₄

to palpitate, throb, tremble, shake, quiver; to beat, as the pulse; to stir, as waves; palpitation, quivering.

ʻapi₅

a decoy stick basket with a wide opening; it was baited, and after the fish were accustomed to coming for food, a trap was substituted.

ʻapi₆

to gather together, as people or things.

ʻapo leo₁

to record a voice.

ʻapo leo₂

magical voice snatching (a sorcerer was believed able to snatch a victim's voice so that he could not chant or sing); to snatch a voice thus.

ʻapokaka

apostate.

ʻapokekolo

apostle.

ʻapokolo

apostle.

ʻapowai₁

type of Hawaiian dog with solid grayish-brown body and nose tip and eyes of the same color, believed to love water and consequently offered as a sacrifice to moʻo water spirits.

ʻapowai₂

to be a grayish-brown color, as a horse, perhaps bay.

ʻapowale

a native variety of wet-land taro grown chiefly for poi.

ʻapoʻapo₁

• catching, grasping;   • attack, fit, heart palpitation, agitation; to have an attack, fit.

ʻapoʻapo₂

half-grown stage of the āhole, a fish.

ʻapo₁

• to catch, grasp, seize and retain,   • grab,   • hug,   • acceptance, admission.   • fig., to perceive, understand. cf:     ʻaʻapo, to learn quickly, to catch the meaning quickly, apt...     ʻapoa, pas/imp, to catch, grasp, grab...     ʻapoʻapo, catching, grasping...     ʻāpō (var) to rebound, in basketball

ʻapo₂

a variety of sweet potato (no data).

ʻapo₃

a variety of taro (no data).

ʻapu kōheoheo

deadly poison, as given to prisoners.

ʻapu ʻauhuhu

cup containing ʻauhuhu plant concoction used for stupefying fish; poison cup.

ʻapuhi

to deceive, lie, cheat.

ʻapuki

short.

ʻapuwai

a variety of taro: its corm is used for poi and table taro, its leaves for lūʻau. Varieties are white (kea) and red (ʻula).

ʻapuʻapu₁

cup-shaped.

ʻapuʻapu₂

type of agricultural land, as for sweet potatoes, mentioned in 1848 land claims, perhaps a pocket-like area.

ʻapuʻu₁

an endemic fern (Sadleria squarrosa), 30 to 60 cm high, with short trunk, narrow oblong leaves; related to ʻamaʻu.

ʻapuʻu₂

hill, mound.

ʻapu₁

• coconut shell cup;   • to drink. [kava]

ʻapu₂

general name for medical potions, as made of taro, yam, or herbs.

ʻapu₃

a taro cultivar, perhaps related to the ʻapuwai.

ʻau hau

• stalk of a hau tree,   • spear made of hau wood.

ʻau hulaʻana

to swim around a hulaʻana, or precipice facing the sea; course or route for swimming here.

ʻau kolo

crawl (swimming); to swim thus.

ʻau koʻi

axe handle.

ʻau kī

stem of a ti plant.

ʻau kū

to tread water.

ʻau like

to swim evenly or abreast.

ʻau lima₁

bone of arm below elbow.

ʻau lima₂

stick held in the hand and rubbed in the fire-plow to produce fire by friction.

ʻau moku

fleet of ships.

ʻau umauma

breast stroke (swimming); to swim thus.

ʻau waʻa

canoe fleet.

ʻau wāwae

leg bone.

ʻauamo

pole or stick used for carrying burdens across the shoulders; yoke, palanquin, burden; to carry on the ʻauamo. lit., carrying handle. Also ʻaumaka and māmaka.

ʻauana

to wander, drift, ramble, go from place to place; to stray morally or mentally.

ʻaua₁

lean, as fish.

ʻaua₂

cawing, as of the ʻalalā, crow.

ʻauhaka

spindle-legged; spindleshanks; an animal with slender legs.

ʻauhau Pōʻalua

Tuesday tax, a term used in 1852, probably an educational tax.

ʻauhau maʻule

misplaced or concealed noʻa stone in the game of pūhenehene.

ʻauhaupuka

beggar; to go from door to door asking for charity.

ʻauhau₁

tax, assessment, levy, charge, tariff, toll, tribute, price; to levy a tax, pay tribute, tax.

ʻauhau₂

femur and humerus bones of the human skeleton.

ʻauhau₃

stems of plants whose bark can be stripped, such as wauke and olonā, but not maile.

ʻauhea hoʻi

Where indeed (with implication of neglect or indifference)? Where's the interest? Where's the care?

ʻauhea₂

listen (in commands, common in songs).

ʻauhea₃

Sir [formal beginning of a letter].

ʻauheʻe

• to flee from danger;   • routed, dispersed, defeated.

ʻauhuhu

a slender, shrubby legume (Tephrosia purpurea syn. T. piscatoria), 30 to 60 cm high, with small, compound leaves, small white or purplish flowers, and narrow pods, used for poisoning fish. The plant is known from tropical Asia eastward into Polynesia. Also ʻauhola, hola.

ʻauialo

accusative case. lit.., front case.

ʻauihea

vocative case. lit.., calling case.

ʻauihele

case denoting separation, as shown by mai, from, ablative.

ʻauihui

case denoting association. lit.., joined case; ablative (PHG).

ʻauiiki

genitive or possessive case.

ʻauikumu

nominative case.

ʻauikōhaʻi

possessive case. lit.., case belonging to someone else.

ʻauimoe

locative case.

ʻauina

bending, sloping; descent, slope.

ʻauinapō

midnight, late night.

ʻauipaʻewa

dative case.

ʻauipili

possessive case; genitive (PHG).

ʻauiʻia

agentive case.

ʻaui₁

• to turn aside, digress, deviate,   • pass by,   • decline,   • bend down.

ʻaui₂

to swell and roll, as the sea; to pitch; billow, roller.

ʻaui₃

declension, case; to name declensions or conjugations (term devised by Andrews based on Latin declinare, to turn aside); never used extensively and not entered in (Hitchcock).

ʻaui₄

a hula step: the dancer turns to the side and points out one foot once or several times, drawing the foot well back between each pointing; at the same time the body is tipped, with a lowered hand pointing to the outpointing toes, and the other hand raised in the opposite direction; to dance thus.

ʻauka

out (in games).

ʻaukai

to travel or swim by sea; seafaring; sailor, seafarer.

ʻaukoʻi₁

coffee senna (Cassia occidentalis), a tropical American shrubby legume, each leaf with eight to ten leaflets, and with yellow flowers and narrow, many-seeded pods. Used medicinally for ringworm.

ʻaukuku

tapa beater.

ʻaukuʻu kāhili

a variety of ʻaukuʻu heron.

ʻaukuʻu pili ʻāina

name given by Kepelino for a bird resembling the kioea, and not an ʻaukuʻu.

ʻaukuʻu₁

black-crowned night heron (Nycticorax nycticorax hoactli), a non-migratory land bird, which feeds on small fish and the larvae of insects in water. See sayings, heron.

ʻaukuʻu₂

kind of fishhook with a long slender shaft, perhaps named for its resemblance to the heron's neck.

ʻaukuʻu₃

a long bamboo pole with two maile stalks across the top that were gummed with lime to catch birds.

ʻaukuʻu₄

to vomit, retch.

ʻaukuʻu₅

cords held by the fishermen (hoʻāu) who managed the net in kuʻu fishing.

ʻaukā kopa

bar of soap. lit.., bar soap.

ʻaukā₁

• bar, as of soap or gold,   • nugget;   • ridge or strip between the flutes of a column,   • facet,   • fillet,   • capstan bar,   • bar across a roadway;   • stump.

ʻaukā₂

long stems, as of some species of mangoes.

ʻaukā₃

wood woven through sticks in ʻie kala fish trap.

ʻaukā₄

stools, feces.

ʻaulama

to light with a torch.

ʻaulani

messenger of a chief.

ʻaulau

leaves strung on lines at ends of seines, as ti leaves.

ʻaulena

a variety of native banana.

ʻauliʻi₁

dainty, neat, trim, cute, exquisite, nice, perfect.

ʻauliʻi₂

a small staff.

ʻaumakiki

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻaumakua₂

to offer grace to ʻaumākua before eating; to bless in the name of ʻaumākua.

ʻaumakua₃

to ask someone to hula; the request was not refused without giving the caller a lei or flower.

ʻaumoana₁

to travel on the open sea; sailor.

ʻaumoana₂

name of laws enacted by Queen Kaʻahumanu, so called in commemoration of her attempt to commit suicide by swimming out to sea. She was saved by a child who swam after her and refused to leave her. She returned to shore rather than cause his death.

ʻaumoana₃

nautilus. usually called ʻauwaʻalālua, moamoa, moamoa waʻa.

ʻaunaki₁

stick rubbed in obtaining fire by friction.

ʻaunaki₂

ounce.

ʻaupapa

everything, as of things taken or lost; destitute.

ʻauwaepahāha

mumps. lit., puffed chin.

ʻauwaepaʻa

firmly opposed, set against. lit., firm chin.

ʻauwaepili

close relative.

ʻauwaepuʻu₁

indifference to work, discouraged. lit., chin lump.

ʻauwaepuʻu₂

to squat.

ʻauwaeʻāina

tribute of the best selected (wae) hogs or fruits of the land to the landlord; to inspect land.

ʻauwae₁

chin. fig., indifferent, scornful.

ʻauwae₂

curved notch cut on the outer side of a post below the base of a tenon, also called maʻi wahine.

ʻauwae₃

portion of the point of a pearl-shell lure which overhangs the shank.

ʻauwaha₁

• ditch, furrow, trench, gutter,   • canal, channel;   • groove, as in a tapa beater;   • to notch, as tops of house posts.

ʻauwaha₂

outhouse, as for storing canoes.

ʻauwai

ditch, canal.

ʻauwai papa

flume.

ʻauwai paʻa

conduit, solid ditch.

ʻauwiniwini

sharp end of a leaf; term of raillery applied to men, referring to the male member.

ʻauʻaukī₁

young eel.

ʻauʻaukī₂

a fish said to resemble weke (no data).

ʻauʻauwaha

furrowed.

ʻauʻau₂

• stick, stem (as of ti plant);   • spear made of loulu palm, with shark teeth on its end;   • extra ridgepole.

ʻauʻau₃

trap, snare, as for catching birds.

ʻauʻa₁

• stingy, selfish, stinginess;   • to withhold, grudge, refuse to part with;   • to detain,   • sparingly.

ʻauʻa₂

a kind of ʻōpelu fish said to be larger than others in a school and hence more visible. When net fishermen see an ʻauʻa they know a school is present; the ʻauʻa then can not be caught [he refuses].

ʻau₂

to jut out into the sea, as a land point; to project.

ʻau₃

• handle,   • staff, shaft;   • stem, stalk,   • bone of lower arm or leg.

ʻau₄

group (followed by a qualifier, as moku, waʻa.)

ʻawa hiwa

a variety of kava with long internodes.

ʻawa keʻokeʻo

probably same as ʻawa papa kea.

ʻawa lau

a young kava plant (root, stem, and leaves) used as an offering to the gods.

ʻawa maha kea

name for ʻawa ākea, ʻawa mākea at Kaʻū, Hawaiʻi.

ʻawa mamaka

a variety of kava with short internodes and light-green stalk, reported at Wainiha, Kauaʻi.

ʻawa mokihana

a variety of kava with short yellowish-green internodes and hairlike roots, named for the mokihana plant because of its fragrance, and yielding a strong brew; famous on Kauaʻi.

ʻawa mākea

a variety of kava.

ʻawa mānienie

a variety of kava with smooth, white stalk.

ʻawa mōʻī

a variety of kava with short, dark-green internodes and whitish nodes, called ʻawa papa mōʻī at Kaʻū, Hawaiʻi.

ʻawa nēnē

a variety of kava with long, spotted internodes.

ʻawa papa

a variety of kava with short internodes and spotted stalk. This name may be qualified by the terms ʻeleʻele, mōʻī, and kea (or keʻokeʻo), the last being the commonest variety, and whitish in general appearance.

ʻawa ākea

a variety of kava with long, light-green internodes and reddish nodes.

ʻawa ʻapu

a variety of kava.

ʻawaakāne

it is said that the god Kāne brought the first ʻawa to Hawaiʻi.

ʻawahua

ingratitude, meanness; to be mean, ungrateful, embittered, resentful.

ʻawaikū

kava root dug ceremonially by a priest and held up (kū) towards heaven while chanting a prayer of consecration and eulogy, after which the root was termed ʻawailani.

ʻawaiāhiki

swelling in the groin, bubo; to have such a swelling.

ʻawakupoi

avoirdupois.

ʻawakūmakua

a variety of kava with green internodes of medium length.

ʻawaliʻi

type of hard stone from which adzes were made.

ʻawalu

eight (usually in counting in a series).

ʻawapuhi Pākē

ginger (Zingiber officinale), yielding a valuable commercial root spice. The plant looks much like ʻawapuhi kuahiwi and probably comes from southeast Asia. lit., Chinese ginger.

ʻawapuhi keʻokeʻo

the white ginger (Hedychium coronarium), a large herb from India, both wild and cultivated in Hawaiʻi. White fragrant flowers, popular for leis and perfume, are borne in heads at tips of leafy stems.

ʻawapuhi koʻokoʻo

torch ginger (Phaeomeria speciosa), a large herb, from the East Indies, grown in Hawaiʻi for its ornamental pink or red cone-shaped flower heads. These are borne on long stems separate from the longer leafy stems. lit., walking-stick ginger.

ʻawapuhi kuahiwi

wild ginger

ʻawapuhi luheluhe

the shell ginger (Catimbium speciosum), a large ornamental herb from East Indies. Clusters of irregularly bell-shaped flowers that are white and marked with red and yellow bend downward from the top of leafy, arching stems, which are 1.5 to 3.5 m high. lit., drooping ginger.

ʻawapuhi melemele

the yellow ginger (Hedychium flavescens), similar to ʻawapuhi keʻokeʻo and similarly used, but the flowers are yellow.

ʻawapuhi ʻai

lit., edible ginger.

ʻawapuhi ʻulaʻula

the red ginger (Alpinia purpurata), an ornamental plant having a long flower spike with many red bracts. It is a native of some islands of the western Pacific.

ʻawapuhiakanaloa

Liparis hawaiensis, a small, endemic orchid with two large ovate leaves and small flowers.

ʻawapuhi₂

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻawapuhi₃

a type of taro (no data).

ʻawawaiakamanu

a variety of kava, an offshoot of ʻawa hiwa, with joints green on one side and dark on the other. lit., watery kava of the bird.

ʻawaʻawahua

bitter, sour. fig., crabbed in nature, bitter, ungrateful.

ʻawaʻawaina

bitterness.

ʻawaʻawa₁

• bitter, sour, tart, acid, fermented, brackish; bitterness, sourness.   • fig., unpleasant, disagreeable, harsh, bad-tempered;   • unpleasant or tragic experience,   • anguish.

ʻawa₁

the kava (Piper methysticum), a shrub 1.2 to 3.5 m tall with green jointed stems and heart-shaped leaves, native to Pacific islands, the root being the source of a narcotic drink of the same name used in ceremonies (Neal 291), prepared formerly by chewing, later by pounding. The comminuted particles were mixed with water and strained, When drunk to excess it caused drowsiness and, rarely, scaliness of the skin and bloodshot eyes. Kava was also used medicinally.

ʻawa₂

sour, bitter, poisonous.

ʻawa₃

cold mountain rain, fog, mist; to rain or mist. fig., tragic misfortune or ordeal; in (PH) this word is preceded by ke and may refer to volcanic eruption:

ʻawa₄

a premature infant, believed caused by a "sour" condition of the mother.

ʻawa₅

a kind of bitter seaweed.

ʻawe puhi

eel tentacle, but referring to the octopus, a euphemism for ʻaweule.

ʻaweka

to hide rather than share wealth (perhaps related to weka, squid ink).

ʻawelika

average, pro rata. divided equally.

ʻaweule

lone octopus tentacle, said to wave in order to entice and ensnare a victim. lit., penis tentacle.

ʻaweʻawe

• pack, knapsack; [NB: 1986 editions omit comma after "pack" where earlier editions include it.]   • straps for a bundle;   • strips, as of wauke; runners, as on a vine;   • tentacles.

ʻawe₁

pack, knapsack carried on the back; to carry on the back.

ʻawe₂

tentacle.

ʻaʻa lole

clothlike sheath at base of coconut frond; European cloth.

ʻaʻa manu

coconut-leaf or pandanus-leaf bag used for carrying birds.

ʻaʻa moni

purse. (Bib.)

ʻaʻa niu

clothlike sheath at base of coconut frond.

ʻaʻa pua

arrow case, quiver.

ʻaʻaahi

bag for carrying fire-making equipment (ʻaʻa, bag, and ahi, fire).

ʻaʻae

second or third crop, as of taro; taro patch where the taro has been pulled up.

ʻaʻaea

the sound ay that infants make in calling for attention; to make this sound.

ʻaʻaha

netted carrier for a calabash, made of sennit or olonā cord. More commonly called kōkō.

ʻaʻaho₁

thatch purlin; rails, as in a fence.

ʻaʻaho₂

container, as for pia, arrowroot starch; to put pia in small packages so that it may keep sweet.

ʻaʻahu

• clothing in general, garment, array, attire, costume, mantle, gown;   • to put on or wear clothing, especially shirt, suit, or coat;   • to cover or wrap, as the body with a blanket.

ʻaʻahu a poʻo

head shield; protection for the head in war, as helmet, shield.

ʻaʻahu aliʻi

regal attire, a royal robe, a type of colored tapa worn by people of rank.

ʻaʻahu kaua

armor, war garment.

ʻaʻahu makaloa

a long malo or ornamented band made of the soft makaloa rush; to put on or wear this garment.

ʻaʻahu pāwehe

garment made of pāwehe, patterned mat; mat made of soft material and woven in the pāwehe pattern; to put on and wear this garment.

ʻaʻahu ʻoihana piha

full regalia, dress uniform. Lit., full professional garment.

ʻaʻahuki

tendon. lit., pulled vein.

ʻaʻahuā

to speak reproachfully, contemptuously, deride, jeer; jealous challenge.

ʻaʻaia

demented.

ʻaʻaiole

inferior, weak, said of breadfruit or fruit with a weak stem that may fall before maturity; weak object. (Kep. 93) fig., of persons dying before their time.

ʻaʻaiʻanuheakāne

legendary bird. Lit., caterpillar eater of Kāne.

ʻaʻai₁

• eating, spreading, festering, increasing, as a sore;   • ulcerous, cancerous, malignant;   • to eat away, corrode;   • to take bait readily, as fish;   • erosion.

ʻaʻai₂

bright, vivid, as of contrasting colors.

ʻaʻaka₁

• surly, cranky, roiled, complaining, irritable, peevish, bad tempered, cantankerous, cross;   • severe, as labor.

ʻaʻaka₂

• dry, as coral of the reef at low tide;   • parched,   • wrinkled,   • dry and thirsty;   • peeling off, as the tough skin of such fish as the humuhumu after it has been in the fire;   • to crackle,   • burst, as a ripe melon.

ʻaʻaka₃

rocky undersea cavern. (PH 219), (Malo 26).

ʻaʻaka₄

wood of the naio, bastard sandalwood.

ʻaʻaki

redup. of ʻaki₁, to take a nip and let go, snap...   • to nip repeatedly; a bite, nibble.   • to take a nip and hold on (cf. nahu, to bite with the whole mouth, and nau, to chew);   • fig., thick, obscure, dark, penetrating;   • to feel pangs, as of love or childbirth.

ʻaʻaki makau

a hook nibbler, said of small fish that nibble away the bait; to nibble at a hook.

ʻaʻako₁

repeated plucking.

ʻaʻako₂

insatiable lust.

ʻaʻako₃

to get into action.

ʻaʻakū

name of a combination of diseases: liver complication resulting in hardening of the veins, bloody dysentery accompanied by fever.

ʻaʻalaihau

a fish (no data; perhaps a local name for one of the chaetodons).

ʻaʻalaioa

wild, demented person; uncivilized.

ʻaʻalakai₁

insipid, unsavory, tasteless.

ʻaʻalakai₂

large, plump.

ʻaʻalaʻihi

young of the ʻalaʻihi fishes.

ʻaʻalaʻula

velvety-green, succulent-appearing seaweeds, one of several species of Codium. It yields a red liquid when placed in a container overnight with brine, after chopping or pounding. Both the liquid and the seaweed are well liked, being eaten plain or with other food. (KL. line 47) ʻaʻalaʻula is the common name on Kauaʻi and Maui, wāwaeʻiole elsewhere.

ʻaʻali

redup. of ʻali₁; scarred, marked, grooved; depression, groove; wattles of a fowl; slight depression under the gills of a fish.

ʻaʻalina₁

scarred.

ʻaʻalina₂

large, fat, weak, as a fat person.

ʻaʻaliʻi

native hardwood shrubs or trees (Dodonaea, all species), 30 cm to 10 m [1-33 ft] high, more or less sticky at branch tips; leaves narrow, 2 to 10 cm [¾"-4"] long; flowers small; fruit a yellow, red, or brown papery capsule about 1 cm long and with two to four wings. Fruit clusters are made into leis with their own leaves or ferns and worn in the hair. (Neal 536–7), (FS 57). symbol of independent people of Kaʻū. (Wight)

ʻaʻalu

ravine, small stream, valley, depression.

ʻaʻama₁

a large, black, edible crab (Grapsus grapsus tenuicrustatus) that runs over shore rocks.

ʻaʻama₂

to spread and relax, as the fingers. [The ʻaʻama crab was offered in sacrifices so that the gods would loosen (aʻama) and grant the request.]

ʻaʻamoʻo₁

young clothlike sheath at base of coconut frond; gauze, as of a veil; diaphanous cloth. lit., ʻaʻa portion.

ʻaʻamoʻo₂

snakeskin; slime, as on fresh water. lit., lizard ʻaʻa.

ʻaʻana

to use abusive language, revile, malign.

ʻaʻanema

to criticize maliciously; malign.

ʻaʻano₁

overbearing, arrogant, bold, defiant, daring; bully.

ʻaʻao₁

greedy, voracious.

ʻaʻao₂

uncultivated bananas.

ʻaʻapi

warped, curved.

ʻaʻapo

to learn quickly, to catch the meaning quickly, apt.

ʻaʻapu₁

coconut-shell cup; cuplike.

ʻaʻapu₂

to warp, bend, ruffle.

ʻaʻau₁

to move here and there, wander, rove; to ripple, as the sea.

ʻaʻawa hua kukui

a native tree (Pittosporum hosmeri and its varieties), about 6 m high, with leaves 10 to 25 cm by 1.5 to 6 cm, shiny and wrinkled above, brown-wooly beneath; small, clustered, cream-colored flowers; ovoid fruits about 5 cm long, each with two to four thick valves containing orange pulp and black oily seeds.

ʻaʻawa₁

wrasse fishes, Hawaiian hogfish (Bodianus bilunulatus), considered ʻaumākua by some. The name ʻaʻawa may be qualified by the terms ʻeʻa, hai ʻeʻa, lelo, ule holu (pliable penis).

ʻaʻawa₃

name given for an insect that destroys potatoes.

ʻaʻaʻa

clothlike sheath at base of coconut frond; vascular bundles in taro corm, chaff, tissue; fibrous, stringy.

ʻaʻa₁

• to brave, dare, challenge, defy (1-Sam. 17.10) , check, venture; to accept a challenge;   • bold, venturesome, valiant, intrepid.   • to volunteer, involving a difficulty;   • to act wickedly or presumptuously (Kanl. 1.43) ;

ʻaʻa₂

belt, girdle, waist; to gird, tie on.

ʻaʻa₃

• bag,   • pocket,   • caul, envelope for a foetus,   • scrip [archaic: bag or wallet carried by wayfarers] (1-Sam. 17.40) ;   • fiber from coconut husk;   • clothlike sheath at base of coconut frond;   • cloth;   • chaff, hull (Ier. 23.28) ;   • skin covering eyeballs.

ʻaʻe

• to step over, get on top of, tread upon,   • trespass;   • to get into by stepping up, as into a car; step.   • to raise;   • to massage the back with the feet;   • to break a taboo or violate a law;   • counter sorcery; to inflict sorcery on a sorcerer;   • fig., oppressed.

ʻaʻe kaʻa

a step, as on a carriage; running board of an automobile.

ʻaʻei

fine net, as used for ʻōpelu and maomao fish; it was held open at the mouth by kuku, stretching poles.

ʻaʻina

crackling, snapping; an explosive sound, sharp report, bang (rare), loud prolonged sound, peal (less common than ʻuʻina).

ʻaʻo

Newell's puffin or shearwater (Puffinus puffinis newelli), said to be the only sea bird endemic to Hawaiʻi, and to breed only in Hawaiʻi; glossy black above, white beneath; endangered.

ʻaʻoe

same as ʻaʻole, not. See chant, wāhia.

ʻaʻā maka

to stare or glare with wide-open eyes, as in desire, fear, or intent to frighten; one who does so.

ʻaʻā pele

ʻaʻā lava or flow, volcanic.

ʻaʻā puʻupuʻu

sharp or waterworn, coarse gravel or rock.

ʻaʻā₁

• to burn, blaze, glow; fire;   • staring, as eyes.   • fig., angry; fury.

ʻaʻā₂

ʻaʻā lava; stony, abounding with ʻaʻā lava.

ʻaʻā₄

young stage of damselfish (ʻāloʻiloʻi).

ʻEhukai

name of a wind of Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

ʻEka₂

name of a wind at Kona, Hawaiʻi.

ʻEkekemō

Eskimo.

ʻEkeloa

wind name.

ʻEkeʻeke₄

name of a wind of the island of Kaʻula.

ʻEkinapolo

Edinburgh.

ʻEkuakola

Ecuador; Ecuadorian.

ʻEleʻū₁

a dark-skinned people said to be descended from a chief of this name.

ʻElie

Erie.

ʻEnekelea

incarnation.

ʻEpekopala

Episcopal; Episcopalian. Less common than Hoʻomana Pīhopa.

ʻEpipania

Epiphany.

ʻEukalikia₁

Eucharist.

ʻEulopa₁

Europe; European.

ʻEwa₂

place name west of Honolulu, used as a direction term.

ʻEwa₃

Eve. fig., woman.

ʻEʻelokoa

name of a storm from the northeast of Waimea, Hawaiʻi.

ʻe-

prefix to numerals, inanimate, as ʻekahi, ʻelua, ʻekolu.

ʻea hanu paʻa

condition of frequent colds. lit., ʻea with hardened breath.

ʻea huna

dizzy spells, dizziness; latent ʻea disease.

ʻea kai wawaka

impaired vision, perhaps labyrinthitis.

ʻea kua neneke

a variety of ʻea, a land tortoise. lit., tortoise with back fitted into sections.

ʻea kākua

a disease, perhaps secondary lues; lumbago (EH).

ʻea kāmolowā

condition of listlessness.

ʻea kū manawa

severe headaches, perhaps due to high blood pressure. lit., ʻea at fontanel.

ʻea kūkaʻa

disease with swelling symptoms.

ʻea māhani

a type of ʻea [illness] described as evanescent [vanishing, fading way, fleeting].

ʻea mālani

light-brown in color.

ʻea pōniu

dizziness, vertigo.

ʻea wawaka

acute childhood ʻea disease.

ʻea wāhi paʻa

osteomalacia, gradual softening of the bones.

ʻea ʻula

wine-colored, such a color.

ʻea ʻōlena

jaundice, hepatitis.

ʻeahoupo lewalewa

great hunger, perhaps due to diabetes. lit., loose-hanging diaphragm ʻea.

ʻeaʻea₁

spray; encrusted with spray (sometimes confused with eaea and ʻeʻaʻeʻa).

ʻeaʻea₂

dignified, honorable.

ʻeaʻea₃

a bird (no data).

ʻea₁

• hawksbill turtle (Chelone imbricata), both land and sea species;   • the shell of this turtle.

ʻea₂

reddish-brown, as the color of the ʻea shell.

ʻea₃

a general term for infections and infectious diseases; coated tongue, sometimes accompanied by sore throat, the thrush disease of children. Many diseases of miscellaneous nature begin with ʻea and are listed below.

ʻea₄

spray.

ʻea₅

vocative interj. usually at the beginning or end of utterances. (1 Sam. 9.5) , (Lunk. 7.3) .

ʻea₇

noisy; to yell, whoop; whoop.

ʻeha wale

easily hurt, sensitive, having feelings easily hurt; to hurt for no reason.

ʻehakō

the Chinese lace-necked, or ring-necked dove (Streptopelia chinensis), an early introduction to Hawaiʻi, said to be named for its call ʻeha kō, prolonged pain.

ʻehaʻeha

great pain, agony, tribulation, many small pains; painful.

ʻeheheu

wings.

ʻehipa

somewhat crooked, warped; not in sound mind. (Similar to but perhaps less strong than hipa and hepa.)

ʻeho₁

stone pile (FS 107), especially as used to mark land boundaries; stone image; heap of stones under water (at times fishermen block one end with a net and drive the fish in from the other end), also umu, imu; pillar (Kin. 35.20) ; red-hot stones put inside dressed animals in cooking (also pōhaku ʻeho).

ʻeho₂

swelling or ulcerous sore, as caused by friction under the arm, tumor.

ʻehu ahiahi

the dust of evening. fig., twilight, old age.

ʻehu hīnano

hīnano-blossom pollen.

ʻehu kai

sea spray, foam.

ʻehu kakahiaka

the dust of morning. fig., dawn, youth, a shower that clears quickly.

ʻehu kumu uli

hair black at the roots that shades out to reddish at the tips, said to be characteristic of some ʻehu people.

ʻehu lepo

dust; dusty.

ʻehu pua

flower pollen.

ʻehu wai

spray from water.

ʻehuehu

(this form was perhaps once ehuehu and is sometimes pronounced thus still).

ʻehuʻawa

same as ʻahuʻawa (Cyperus javanicus).

ʻehu₁

spray, foam, mist. (Many older people say ehu for ʻehu₁,₂,₃,₄, which is probably the older form; note lack of glottal stops in such forms as ehuehu, ʻehuehu, kaiehu, kēhu, kuehu, luehu, puehu.)

ʻehu₂

dust; dusty.

ʻehu₃

pollen.

ʻehu₄

faint, difficult to see; wisp.

ʻehu₅

reddish tinge in hair, of Polynesians and not of Caucasians; one with ʻehu hair; reddish-brown complexion said to be characteristic of some ʻehu people; ruddy. (This ʻehu is invariably pronounced with an initial glottal stop.)

ʻehē

a hard, dry cough; to cough.

ʻeiʻa

emphatic variation of eia: here! here it is!

ʻekalekia

church (the organization, not the building; usually pronounced ʻekalesia).

ʻekaʻeka₂

Hawaiian name for a Japanese variety of taro (adado) grown in Hawaiʻi.

ʻeka₁

dirty, foul, fecal (Kam. 64:109); filth, dirt, soil.

ʻeka₃

a variety of bananas.

ʻeka₄

acre.

ʻeke hau

icecap [i.e. ice bag].

ʻeke hoʻopaʻa laho

male supporter, jockstrap. lit., basket supporting scrotum.

ʻeke huluhulu

gunny sack. lit., hairy sack.

ʻeke kūkaenalo

flour sack or sack of unbleached muslin (kūkaenalo), as formerly used for poi.

ʻeke leka

mail pouch, mailbag.

ʻeke paʻa lima

handbag, hand basket, briefcase.

ʻeke wai wela

hot-water bag.

ʻekekeu

wings.

ʻekekeʻi

short, as a dress or fishline (probably a redup. of ʻeke₂ + -ʻi, transitivizer).

ʻekeliuma

ethereum.

ʻekemauʻu

gunny sack, burlap. lit., grass sack.

ʻekemo

akimbo.

ʻekemu

to answer briefly, speak but little; taciturn.

ʻekepue

to bend over, crouch, as to hide oneself or an object. fig., secretive, as in love affairs; to keep a secret.

ʻekepuʻu

a bird (no data).

ʻekeʻeke kālā

billfold, wallet, small purse.

ʻekeʻeke maʻa

holder for stone in the sling (maʻa), sometimes a kind of woven basket, but in smaller slings merely a kind of noose.

ʻekeʻeke₁

small bag or sack, pocket, purse, scrotum

ʻekeʻeke₂

fussy, overexacting, cranky, particular.

ʻekeʻeke₃

a herringbone design, as in mat plaiting or in the pāpale ʻie.

ʻekeʻula

a type of banana.

ʻeke₂

to cringe, shrink from, draw away from, flinch, wince; to become smaller, shrink.

ʻeki

ace.

ʻekiʻeki

Hawaiian tern (Anous sp.).

ʻekoko

same as ʻakoko and koko, shrubs and trees.

ʻeku

to root, as a pig. paw up dirt, as a dog (NKE12). fig., prow of a canoe.

ʻekulēkū

digging place.

ʻekuʻeku

• to soften the earth, as for planting.   • redup. of ʻeku, to root, as a pig.   • fig., prow of a canoe.

ʻekī₁

bayonet. cf. kī, to shoot, and ʻēlau waikī.

ʻekī₂

place where ti plants grow.

ʻela

ale.

ʻela kinika

ginger ale.

ʻele hiwa

coal-black, jet-black, all black. See chant, ʻelemoe.

ʻele-₁

old. see:     ʻelehine, old woman. see luahine...     ʻelekule, old fellow, old chap...     ʻelemakule, old man...     ʻelemākule, plural of ʻelemakule, old man...     lāʻele, old leaf,... (a contraction of lau ʻelemakule); fig., aged; old age...

ʻele-₂

prefix to names of directions used by priests; see:     ʻelehonua, priests' name for west...     ʻeleiāhonua, same as ʻelehonua, priests' name for west...     ʻeleiālani, same as ʻelelani, priests' name for east...     ʻelekū₄, priests' name for north...     ʻelelani, priests' name for east...     ʻelemoe₂, priests' name for south...

ʻeleao₁

plant louse, aphid; germ, blight; blighted, as by ʻeleao. fig., troublemaker.

ʻeleao₂

a native fungus (Gnomania iliau), parasitic on leaf sheaths of sugar cane.

ʻeleao₃

time of light, daylight, a term used in kuwā prayers, as to indicate that a new house is free from taboo and may be occupied.

ʻeleao₄

door at the leeward end of a house.

ʻeleau₁

period of darkness.

ʻeleau₂

perhaps same as ʻakiʻaki, a seaweed. Maui.

ʻeleheʻu₁

mutilated, deprived of some essential part; mayhem.

ʻeleheʻu₂

angry.

ʻelehine

old woman.

ʻelehonua

priests' name for west.

ʻeleiki

to bear a grudge.

ʻelekule

old fellow, old chap. cf. the common ʻelemakule.

ʻelekuma

small crabs (Xanthidae spp.).

ʻelekū₁

coarse vesicular basalt.

ʻelekū₂

stone polisher or rubber made of this rock.

ʻelekū₃

entirely black, coal-black, said jokingly of dark people, including Negroes. See chant, ʻelemoe.

ʻelekū₄

priests' name for north.

ʻelelani

priests' name for east.

ʻelele

messenger, delegate, ambassador, envoy, any diplomatic representative.

ʻelele waha ʻole

letter, written message. lit., messenger without mouth.

ʻelelū

cockroaches (Blattidae).

ʻelelū kea

a cockroach that has shed its skin and is light (kea) in color; a term of ridicule for an unclean white person.

ʻelelū kīkēkē

a large American cockroach (Periplaneta americana). lit., knocking cockroach.

ʻelelū laʻa loa

a cockroach, kitchen roach.

ʻelelū lepo

burrowing cockroach (Pycnoscelus indicus) lit., earth cockroach.

ʻelelū papa

a cockroach.

ʻelelū ʻulaʻula

large, brown cockroaches, such as the American cockroach (Periplaneta americana), and the somewhat smaller Australasian cockroach (P. australasiae).

ʻelemakaiāuli

an expert taro farmer (no data). (For. 5:681).

ʻelemihi

same as ʻalamihi and ʻelepī, a small black crab.

ʻelemika

hermit.

ʻelemio₁

tapering.

ʻelemio₂

to snatch without being seen, as by a thief.

ʻelemoe₁

dark, still, as sea or forest.

ʻelemoe₂

priests' name for south.

ʻelepaio₁

a species of flycatcher with subspecies on Hawaiʻi (Chasiempis sandwichensis sandwichensis), Kauaʻi (C. sandwichensis sclateri), and Oʻahu (C. sandwichensis gayi). The Kauaʻi subspecies is also called ʻāpekepeke. This bird was believed to be the goddess of canoe makers, hence the saying ua ʻelepaio ʻia ka waʻa, the canoe is [marked] by the ʻelepaio [an ʻelepaio bird pecking slowly on a tree trunk for insects signified that the trunk was insect-ridden and not suitable for a canoe (see kani₁); the saying may be applied to any failure]. The name also refers to one who craves fish but does not go fishing, as the cry of the bird was thought to suggest ʻono ka iʻa, ʻono ka iʻa, fish is delicious, fish is delicious.

ʻelepaio₂

a native variety of taro; the leaves are mottled with white.

ʻelepani

elephant.

ʻelepani kai

sea elephant.

ʻelepī

same as ʻalamihi, ʻeleʻelepī, and ʻelemihi, a small black crab.

ʻeleua₁

darkness of rain or rain clouds.

ʻeleua₂

a new house before it has beem made noa, or free from taboo.

ʻeleua₃

door on the weather end of a house.

ʻeleua₄

ancestor or aged male of a family.

ʻeleua₅

a major illness (no data).

ʻeleuli₁

grayish black.

ʻeleuli₂

a rare type of dark-gray or perfumed tapa.

ʻelewawā

dark and tumultuous, as sea or forest. See chant, ʻelemoe.

ʻeleī

blue-black, shiny black. fig., select, choice.

ʻeleʻele kanikau

black crepe worn for mourning.

ʻeleʻele mākoko

a taro cultivar.

ʻeleʻele paʻa

coal-black.

ʻeleʻelekū

unattractively dark and ugly, coal-black.

ʻeleʻelepī₁

agitated, turbulent, tumultuous.

ʻeleʻeleu

vivacious, energetic, lively.

ʻeleʻele₂

variety of tapa said to have originated at Kaumakani, Maui; it was dyed with candlenut, pāʻihi, and black mud.

ʻeleʻele₃

long, filamentous, green, edible seaweeds (Enteromorpha prolifera). Some kinds are among the most popular in Hawaiʻi, being eaten raw as condiments at feasts. Called pīpīlani on Maui.

ʻeleʻele₄

a cooking banana (a form of Musa xparadisiaca), valued for shiny black skin of trunk, used for designs worked into pandanus mats and hats.

ʻeleʻele₅

same as hinupuaʻa and naioea, varieties of taro.

ʻeleʻele₇

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻeleʻio

to go after secretly and speedily; agile, spry; the name of a famous runner of Maui.

ʻeleʻū₂

a hard stone, sometimes used as a fish god.

ʻele₁

black (less used than ʻeleʻele). cf. also ʻeʻele, pāʻele.

ʻele₂

embryo.

ʻele₄

water hole, dark spring covered with growth.

ʻeli ua

to dig a trench so that rain water will run off.

ʻeliʻeli

Redup. of ʻeli;   • to dig often.   • fig., firmly rooted, profound,   • deep, as a taboo, or its removal;   • reverence.

ʻelo

wet, soggy.

ʻemelala

emerald.

ʻemepaea

empire.

ʻemepake

embassy.

ʻemepakekoa

ambassador.

ʻemepela

emperor.

ʻemila

emir.

ʻemo

a waiting, delay; to wait, delay (often used with a negative).

ʻemo ʻole

without delay, immediately, suddenly, in no time at all, quickly.

ʻemoloa

a native grass (Eragrostis variabilis) 30 to 90 cm high, with long narrow flowering panicles, growing on open slopes and ridges.

ʻena makani₁

stormy wind.

ʻena makani₂

windmill.

ʻenakōī

to break wind foully; such action. Probably lit., flowing abundance.

ʻenamela

enamel.

ʻenaʻena₂

all species of cudweeds (Gnaphalium), members of the daisy family, small herbs having small inconspicuous flowers and more or less white woolly stems and leaves. Formerly Hawaiians stored feather standards, kāhili, with native species (G. sandwicensium and G. hawaiiense) to repel insects. called pūheu on Niʻihau.

ʻena₁

• red-hot, glowing.   • fig., raging, angry; anger.

ʻena₂

shy; to shy.

ʻena₃

abundance, plenty.

ʻena₄

opening in the clouds said to be like the jaw of the aʻu swordfish and a sign of rain.

ʻenekini

engine.

ʻenekinia kīwila

civil engineer.

ʻenemi

enemy; to feel enmity; to be an enemy. (Note that the Hawaiian stress is on the second syllable, contrasting with Eng. stress on the first syllable.)

ʻeno

wild, untamed, fearful of people, shy.

ʻenoʻeno

very wild, etc.

ʻenuhe

caterpillar, as of hawk or sphinx moths (Sphingidae). fig., a rapacious person.

ʻenuhe kilika

the introduced silkworm (Bombyx mori).

ʻeo₁

full of food, as a calabash (but not as full as pihaʻū).

ʻeo₂

to agree.

ʻepaka

ephphatha; let it be opened.

ʻepane

apron.

ʻepa₁

• tricky, mischievous,   • dishonest; deceit; to deceive.

ʻepa₂

ephah.

ʻepe

stanza.

ʻepikekole

epistle.

ʻepukane

spouse. (Possibly French époux, husband, + kāne, male.)

ʻeuanelika

Evangelist; evangelistic.

ʻeuanelio

Evangelical; gospel.

ʻeukalikia₂

eucalyptus tree.

ʻeunuha

eunuch. (Bib.)

ʻeuʻeu

exciting, rousing, alert, lively, animated, aroused.

ʻeu₁

• mischievous, naughty, playful, as a child; rogue, rascal, scamp; mischief;   • hoot of an owl ʻaumakua warning of imminent danger (also same as hōʻeu).

ʻeu₂

• to crawl along;   • to rise, rising.

ʻewai

perhaps a var. of ʻauwai, ditch (noted in 1848 land claim, Hāmākua, Hawaiʻi).

ʻewaʻewa₁

irregular, biased, unequal, unjust.

ʻewaʻewa₂

sooty tern (Sterna fuscata oahuensis); forehead and sides of head white, rest of head black; upper parts black, white beneath. Also ʻewaʻewa iki.

ʻewa₁

• crooked, out of shape,   • imperfect,   • ill-fitting.   • fig., incorrect, unjust.

ʻeweʻewe

cry of ʻEweʻeweiki, a legendary woman who died in childbirth and who is said to return at night as a ghost and make this cry, which is followed by a nā cry like that of an infant, an omen that a birth is imminent.

ʻeāʻeā

at end of verses in some chants that maintains rhythm and affords pleasure in repetition, something like English tra-la-la.

ʻeā₁

Isn't that so? That's it!

ʻeā₂

song refrain. see (EM 81).

ʻeʻaʻeʻa

dust; dusty; obscure, darkened, cloudy, shady; to cloud, overshadow (sometimes confused with eaea and ʻeaʻea).

ʻeʻa₁

dust, dirt, dust cloud, spray (ʻeʻa and ʻea₄ are probably interchanged at times).

ʻeʻa₂

mountain banana patch.

ʻeʻa₃

a fish similar to ʻaʻawa, but with dark flesh.

ʻeʻe

hard, stiff, dry.

ʻeʻea₁

quick ready, expert.

ʻeʻea₂

a bird, said to be an adult ʻalaiaha.

ʻeʻehia

• overcome with fearful reverence, terror-stricken, awe-stricken;   • awe-inspiring, solemn;   • reverence, awe,   • fear, terror;   • weird.

ʻeʻehu

reddish; a number of ʻehu persons.

ʻeʻei

offensive, filthy, fly-ridden.

ʻeʻekeloi

to tap a drum slowly, as to accompany a chant.

ʻeʻeke₂

name given for a hard-shelled crab (no data).

ʻeʻelekoa

stormy.

ʻeʻelekū

blackened or darkened, as leaves or fruit due to maturity or to pelting by storms; dark, gloomy, as clouds.

ʻeʻelo₁

drenched, soaked.

ʻeʻelo₂

loitering; to dilly-dally.

ʻeʻena₁

• shy, timid, wary, afraid, to shy away.   • wild, fearsome, untamed;

ʻeʻena₂

extraordinary.

ʻeʻepa

extraordinary, incomprehensible, abnormal, deceitful, peculiar, as persons with miraculous powers; such persons. Many ʻeʻepa characters in mythology were born in strange forms, as a plant, an animal, or a piece of rope. cf. ʻepa₁, ʻepaʻepa, kino ʻeʻepa. The Menehune, Nāwā, and Nāmū of Waolani in Nuʻuanu Valley were ʻeʻepa. Trickery or deceit that passes comprehension is also ʻeʻepa.

ʻeʻeu₁

to crawl, creep, as an insect.

ʻeʻeu₂

shuddering sensation of revulsion (less strong than mania); to rise in horror, flinch (sometimes interpreted as a portent).

ʻeʻewa

to make a wry face, pout, as in derision; to protrude the lips mockingly.

ʻeʻeʻe

to keep climbing over everything, as an active child; mischievous.

ʻeʻeʻina

to creak, crackle.

ʻeʻole

if not for … would not have.

ʻeʻole … inā

if not … would have.

ʻIao₂

• name of Jupiter appearing as the morning star;   • fig., dawn.

ʻIao₃

valley and peak, West Maui.

ʻIkelaʻela

Israel. (For the Hawaiian glottal stop, cf. (Gram. 2.9.3))

ʻIkuā₂

month of the Hawaiian year, named, according to Kepelino, for the roar of surf, thunder, and cloudbursts of this month. Pohākōʻeleʻele is a var. name: see month.

ʻIlelani

Ireland; Irish.

ʻIlikini₁

Indian (of America).

ʻIliʻula

name of a star.

ʻIlokuoa

Iroquois.

ʻImihau

name of a stormy wind at Lahaina, Maui. lit., dew seeker.

ʻInia

East Indian.

ʻInia Hikina

East Indies.

ʻIniana

Indian, as Indian Ocean.

ʻIolani

name of the Palace and of a school in Honolulu; also the names of Kamehameha II and IV: see (PN). lit., royal hawk (the high flight of the hawk symbolized royalty).

ʻIowa

Iowa.

ʻIo₈

probably the name of a stroke in lua fighting; also a low stroke in club fighting

ʻiako₁

outrigger boom. arched crossbeams which fasten the floater (ama) to the hull of an outrigger canoe

ʻiako₂

forty, as in counting tapas, canoes, or feathers.

ʻiamo

to jump into water from a height, feet first, without causing a splash.

ʻiao₁

silversides (Pranesus insularum), a fish 5 to 8 cm long, in shallow pools, used as bait for such fish as aku.

ʻiao₄

a bird said to resemble the moho (no data).

ʻie lawe

fish-trap basket made of ʻie vine. lit., portable ʻie.

ʻie palaoa

breadbasket.

ʻie ʻōpala

wastebasket.

ʻiele

person of distinction, chief.

ʻiewe₁

afterbirth, placenta.

ʻiewe₂

infant.

ʻiewe₃

relatives of a common ancestry.

ʻieʻiea

barbed, as a hook; barb.

ʻieʻie₁

an endemic woody, branching climber (Freycinetia arborea) growing luxuriantly in forests at altitudes of about 300 to 600 m. The ringed stems end in tufts of long, narrow, spiny leaves, in the center of which flowers are borne on cylindrical spikes surrounded by leafy bracts, which are orange or green with orange bases. (Neal 54) ʻIeʻie was one of five plants used on the hula altar (see palai).

ʻieʻie₂

a native variety of taro with leaf blades and flowers suggesting ʻieʻie₁; the leaves are dark and glossy, the petioles reddish with yellow-green stripes.

ʻieʻie₃

high, conceited.

ʻie₁

aerial root of the ʻieʻie vine; the vine itself.

ʻie₂

a woven basket.

ʻie₃

a flat, plaited braid as used in hats; braided.

ʻie₄

wicker.

ʻie₅

name for fish traps, combined with the name of the fish, as ʻie kala, ʻie palani.

ʻie₇

canvas, cotton, linen.

ʻie₈

corduroy.

ʻihaʻiha

• feeling of discomfort of one needing to relieve himself;   • tight, taut, tense.

ʻihi kū ma kua

a weedy sorrel. (Oxalis sp.).

ʻihi kūkae hipa

same as kūkaehipa, spiny bur (Acanthospermum australe).

ʻihi lani

heavenly splendor; sacredness of a chief; reverence due a chief.

ʻihi lāʻau

Marsilea villosa. lit., medicinal sorrel. Niʻihau.

ʻihi mākole

a creeping variety of ʻihi with red stems (differing in this from ʻihi ʻawa), yellow flowers, and no bulbs; used medicinally. lit., red-eyed ʻihi.

ʻihi pehu

a kind of sorrel (Oxalis martiana) with large leaves, pink flowers, bulbous scaly root, used medicinally.

ʻihi pua kea

shamrock. lit., white-flowering Oxalis.

ʻihi ʻai

a kind of ʻihi (Oxalis corniculata). lit., edible ʻihi.

ʻihiʻawaʻawa

storm accompanied by much thunder and lightning, and an epithet for the gods of thunder and lightning. lit., stormy sacred ones.

ʻihiʻihiione

a mustard plant, Coronopus didymus. Niʻihau.

ʻihiʻihi₁

revered.

ʻihiʻihi₂

an unknown plant formerly growing at ʻIhiʻihilauākea [ʻIhiʻihi-lau-ākea], the western side of Hanauma Bay, Oʻahu.

ʻihi₁

sacred, holy, majestic, dignified; treated with reverence or respect.

ʻihi₂

wood sorrels (Oxalis, all species), perennial weedy herbs, creeping or not, and bearing cloverlike leaves and yellow, white, red, or pink bell-shaped flowers. The plants have a pleasant sour taste due to oxalic acid. (Neal 473–4) Known to some as Portulaca spp.

ʻike hana lima

skilled craftsman, craftsmanship; deft.

ʻike hānau

instinct. lit., birth knowledge.

ʻike kaʻa kaua

strategy, knowledge pertaining to war; to know the strategy of war.

ʻike kumu

basic or fundamental knowledge.

ʻike kūhohonu

deep knowledge or insight.

ʻike lihi

to glimpse.

ʻike loa

to know very well indeed, knowledgeable, versed, wise.

ʻike mahuʻi

to glimpse; inkling.

ʻike maka

eyewitness, witness as to a will, eyesight, visual knowledge; visible; to see or witness personally.

ʻike pono

to see clearly; to know definitely; certain knowledge.

ʻike pāpālua

to see double; to have the gift of second sight and commune with the spirits; supernatural knowledge, extrasensory perception.

ʻikena

view, seeing, knowing, association, scenery, knowledge.

ʻikeoma

idiom; idiomatic.

ʻike₂

of scorn in the phrase: I ka ʻike! What does [he, she] know!

ʻikuā₁

noisy, clamorous, loud-voiced; to make a din; din, clamor; voices of the gods in the elements.

ʻikuʻiku

stench; foul-smelling.

ʻikāmū

gathering together, as of fish about a hook.

ʻilau

to do together.

ʻili ahi

a fiery surface.

ʻili eʻe

contagious skin disease.

ʻili hau

bark of the hau tree, as used for rope and for modern grass skirts.

ʻili hinuhinu

patent leather. lit., shiny leather.

ʻili holoholona

leather; fur, as about the neck.

ʻili honua

surface of the earth.

ʻili kala

skin of kala, a fish, sometimes stretched over a coconut shell to form the top of the small pūniu, knee drum.

ʻili kani₁

a skin that sounds, as used in drums.

ʻili kani₂

tough skin.

ʻili kapu

taboo against contact with clothing or bedding of others; one with such a taboo.

ʻili kauō

reins. lit., pulling strap.

ʻili kea₁

fair skin, of Hawaiians less dark than ʻilikou.

ʻili kea₂

white kōnane pebble.

ʻili keʻehi

stirrup.

ʻili kou

dark-skinned, as dark Hawaiians. lit., kou-wood skin.

ʻili kuapo

belt.

ʻili kūpono

a nearly independent ʻili land division within an ahupuaʻa, paying tribute to the ruling chief and not to the chief of the ahupuaʻa. Transfer of the ahupuaʻa from one chief to another did not include the ʻili kūpono located within its boundaries.

ʻili lele

portion of an ʻili land division separated from the main part of the ʻili but considered a part of it.

ʻili lua

new skin, as over a sore; new bark.

ʻili luna

epidermis; outer bark.

ʻili lāʻau

tree bark.

ʻili mākuʻakuʻa

dark-red bark, especially of koa trees.

ʻili mākuʻe

dark-skinned.

ʻili mānoanoa

callus, calloused skin, thick leather; calloused.

ʻili omo wai

suction tube.

ʻili pakalua

thick, coarse, or wrinkled skin or bark.

ʻili pala uli

dark-complexioned.

ʻili palapala

parchment.

ʻili pale o kāmaʻa

sole of shoes.

ʻili paʻa

an ʻili land division complete in one section, as distinguished from an ʻili lele.

ʻili pilo

smelly skin, said approvingly of industrious farmers.

ʻili pipi

leather, cowhide.

ʻili poʻo

scalp.

ʻili poʻopoʻo

concave surface; hollow.

ʻili pāpaʻa

sunburned or tanned skin.

ʻili wahī

scabbard, sheath.

ʻili ʻawa

skin not easily bruised or infected; one with such a skin is said to emit an acrid (ʻawa) odor; a strong-smelling fish caught by him (as pualu or palani) is said to become more offensive in odor.

ʻili ʻaʻai

a skin or complexion prone to infection. lit., corrosive skin.

ʻili ʻeleʻele

black kōnane stone.

ʻili ʻāina₁

land area.

ʻili ʻāina₂

an ʻili land division whose chief pays tribute to the chief of the ahupuaʻa of which it is a part, rather than directly to the king.

ʻili ʻōmaka

foreskin.

ʻiliahialoʻe

a small shrubby form of Hawaiian sandalwood (Santalum ellipticum), found rarely and near the beach.

ʻiliahi₁

all Hawaiian kinds of sandalwood (Santalum spp.), shrubs and trees, with fragrant heart wood, small pale-green or gray-green leaves, small, dull-red or greenish flowers, and small purple fruits. From about 1790 to 1830 sandalwood trees were cut and exported to China.

ʻiliahi₂

one whose clothes wear out fast, as due to carelessness.

ʻilieʻe

wild plumbago (Plumbago zeylanica), a native of tropics of the Eastern Hemisphere to Hawaiʻi, a shrub with white tubular flowers and thin, oval leaves that were used medicinally; the sap was used to blacken tattoo marks. lauhihi on Niʻihau.

ʻilihelo

unsystematic or unskilled in farming, working spasmodically.

ʻilihia

a kind of haʻiwale (Cyrtandra begoniaefolia), on East Maui, having unequal heart-shaped leaves.

ʻilikai₁

surface of the sea.

ʻilikai₂

horizontal.

ʻilikalakala

a bird (no data).

ʻilikana

corm immediately under the skirt, as of taro.

ʻilikaʻa

harness.

ʻilikini₂

naked, nude.

ʻilikiuma

iridium.

ʻiliki₁

• to strike suddenly; onset, striking,   • pour down, as rain; downpour.

ʻiliki₂

a varnish, as made of candlenut bark, ti root, banana stump, and other plants.

ʻilikole₁

poverty-stricken, very poor, destitute; pauper (stronger than ʻilihune). lit., bare skin.

ʻilikole₂

flesh of half-ripe coconut.

ʻilikona

wart. lit., hard skin.

ʻilima koli kukui

a rare ʻilima with bronze-red flowers, domesticated on Oʻahu. lit., kukui candle ʻilima.

ʻilima kuahiwi

a kind of ʻilima.

ʻilima kū kahakai

a kind of ʻilima creeping on sand on which beach dodder (kaunaʻoa) grows. lit., ʻilima standing on beach.

ʻilima kū kula

a wild form of ʻilima, not so often used for leis as ʻilima lei, the cultivated form. lit., ʻilima standing on plains.

ʻilima lei

domesticated form of ʻilima.

ʻilima makanaʻā

a wild ʻilima growing on old lava beds in Kaʻū, with small flowers; of medium height.

ʻilima mamo

a kind of ʻilima, probably same as ʻilima lei.

ʻilima ōkea

a domesticated ʻilima, light yellow in color.

ʻilima₁

small to large native shrubs (all species of Sida, especially S. fallax), bearing yellow, orange, greenish, or dull-red flowers; some kinds strung for leis. The flowers last only a day and are so delicate that about 500 are needed for one lei. Fruits of maʻo (Abutilon grandifolium), when green and soft, are used with ʻilima leis, one fruit at each end of the lei ; or the pale-green, cap-like calyx of the ʻilima flower is used. A mild laxative for babies is made by squeezing out the juice of flowers; this is called kanakamaikaʻi. The ʻilima was designated in 1923 by the Territorial Legislature as the flower of Oʻahu. It is related to the hibiscus. see songs, nōweo, pue₁.

ʻilima₂

area where ʻilima plants may grow.

ʻilipuakea

white person. lit., white flower skin. Poetic.

ʻiliuaua

a variety of taro with large, thick, firm leaf blades. The corms are very large, with white flesh tinged with pink; good as table taro but not for poi; leaves good for lūʻau. lit., tough hide.

ʻiliwai₁

surface, as of water; level, horizontal, flat.

ʻiliwai₂

carpenter's or surveyor's level.

ʻiliwai₃

water hose.

ʻiliʻili hānau

the birth pebbles of Kōloa (a small section of the beach at Puna-luʻu, Kaʻū), which were believed to reproduce themselves, the smooth nonporous ones being male, the porous ones female. These stones were best liked for the pebble hula.

ʻiliʻili kea

white kōnane pebble.

ʻiliʻili makaliʻi

gravel, small stones.

ʻiliʻiliʻeleʻele

black kōnane pebble.

ʻiliʻili₂

to pile, overlap.

ʻiliʻohu

lit., mist skin.

ʻiliʻā

a variety of taro.

ʻiliʻōpua

a variety of sugar cane like the kea but dwarfed.

ʻili₂

leather.

ʻili₃

surface, area.

ʻili₄

binding, cover.

ʻili₅

land section, next in importance to ahupuaʻa and usually a subdivision of an ahupuaʻa.

ʻili₆

strap of any kind, as reins, harness, fan belt, machine belt; hose.

ʻili₇

pebble (less used than ʻiliʻili); kōnane pebble.

ʻili₈

square, as in measurements.

ʻimepeliala

imperial.

ʻimi hakakā

to look for a fight; one doing so, antagonistic.

ʻimi haku

to seek a chief, as of a lesser chief or priest wishing a new master; one who seeks a chief; a chief who marries one of higher rank than himself, or a sister or half sister so that their child will be of still higher rank.

ʻimi hala

to find fault with, blame, seek condemnation.

ʻimi hale₁

to establish, as a dynasty; to acquire authority, power, property; one who does so; to look for a house.

ʻimi hale₂

to form a friendship so close that one feels welcome in the house of the other. Rare today.

ʻimi hana₁

to seek work.

ʻimi hana₂

to stir up trouble.

ʻimi kālā

to seek money, to earn a livelihood; commercial.

ʻimi loa

to seek far, explore; distant traveler, explorer. fig., one with great knowledge or avaricious for knowledge.

ʻimi loaʻa

money-earner, as for a family; breadwinner.

ʻimi naʻauao

to seek knowledge or education; ambitious to learn; one seeking education or learning, research, learning.

ʻimi pono

to seek or strive for righteousness; endeavor.

ʻimi ā loaʻa

discoverer; to discover; to seek until found.

ʻimi ʻike

to seek knowledge; a seeker of knowledge.

ʻimi ʻōlelo

to lie, slander, stir up trouble by gossip.

ʻimina

looking, seeking; search.

ʻimiʻepa

deceit, troublemaker.

ʻimo

to wink, twinkle; winking, twinkling. cf. ʻiʻimo, (Hal. 35.19) .

ʻimona

twinkling.

ʻina uli

black ʻina, perhaps young of Echinometra oblonga, or one of several other sea urchins.

ʻina ʻula

a red ʻina, perhaps young of Heterocentrotus mammillatus.

ʻinaleo

prep. (part of speech).

ʻinalua₂

another name for huehue₂, native plant, stems used for fish traps...

ʻinamona

relish made of the cooked kernel of candlenut (kukui) mashed with salt (perhaps a contraction of ʻīnaʻi momona, sweet garnish).

ʻinawaena

preposition (part of speech).

ʻinaʻina₁

reddish discharge preceding labor in childbirth, amniotic fluid.

ʻinaʻina₂

tiny ʻina.

ʻina₁

small sea urchin (wana), as Echinometra spp. Qualifying terms are ʻeleʻele or uli, kea or keʻokeʻo, and ʻula or ʻulaʻula. Some of these are listed below.

ʻina₂

kind of stone, used to make octopus, sinkers.

ʻina₃

contraction of ʻia ana in the idiom e aha ʻia ana? What is being done?

ʻinekuikikio

inquisition.

ʻiniki

to pinch, nip; sharp and piercing, as wind or pangs of love. (probably ʻini- + -ki, transitivizer.)

ʻinikua

insurance.

ʻinikua home

home insurance.

ʻinikua kaʻa

automobile insurance.

ʻinikua ola

life insurance.

ʻinikua pau ahi

fire insurance.

ʻinikua ulia

accident insurance.

ʻinikō

indigo (Indigofera suffruticosa), a West Indian legume with compound leaves, small reddish flowers, and small, clumped, curved seed pods, introduced to Hawaiʻi about 1850 for commercial purposes. It was not a financial success.

ʻinipākeke

in the pocket (used in the phrase: komo ma ka ʻinipākeke, put in the pocket [pocketed]).

ʻiniʻini

to pinch. [possibly an error - cited text example shows 'ini'iniki on p. 17 (in facsimile in new edition and Ke Alakai o Hawaii 7/17/1932)]

ʻiniʻiniki₁

to pinch or nip repeatedly; tingling, as with cold.

ʻiniʻiniki₂

a way of catching small eels by holding bait on the palm of the hand and clenching the fist when the eels come.

ʻinoʻino₁

spoiled, contaminated, rotten, foul, broken, damaged; wretched.

ʻinoʻino₂

stormy; storm.

ʻinoʻino₃

wicked, sinful; sin.

ʻinoʻino₄

angry.

ʻino₂

spoiled, contaminated, bad-smelling, of poor quality, ugly; spoiled object, pollution.

ʻino₃

to injure, hurt, harm, break.

ʻino₅

a commoner.

ʻino₆

very, very much, intensely. (Sometimes pejorative)

ʻināʻinau

• to make love;   • pleasant, agreeable,   • sprightly.

ʻio mea

a variety of ʻio hawk without dark markings.

ʻio paʻakai

container for salt, as made of pandanus leaves.

ʻio poʻi moa

chicken-stealing hawk. fig., a clever thief, especially of another's sweetheart.

ʻio uli

a dark ʻio, hawk.

ʻiokoʻo

young pandanus leaves, white at the base and light green at the apex, as used in fine mats.

ʻiolana

to soar, poise, as a hawk; soaring hawk.

ʻiole liʻiliʻi

small rat, mouse.

ʻiole lāpaki

rabbit.

ʻiole manakuke

mongoose.

ʻiole nui

introduced large rat.

ʻiole poʻo wai

introduced large rat, probably Norway rat. lit., water-source rat.

ʻiole puaʻa

Guinea pig.

ʻiolea

unsocial.

ʻioleholokula

extinct variety of small, sweet gourd with long stem, formerly used as medicine. lit., rat running on plains.

ʻioleniho

octopus lure. lit., rat tooth.

ʻiole₂

classifier for rodents. see below.

ʻiole₃

name for a sinker of an octopus lure and the lure.

ʻiolo

to vibrate, whiffle, sough.

ʻioʻiole

mousy, like a rat.

ʻioʻiolepo

tattletale; to gossip or tattle maliciously.

ʻioʻio₁

cheeping, peeping.

ʻioʻio₂

to project, taper.

ʻio₁

Hawaiian hawk (Buteo solitarius), an endemic and endangered hawk with dark and light color phases, confined to forests on the island of Hawaiʻi, where it is regarded by some as an ʻaumakua. The ʻio signified royalty because of its lofty flight, and hence occurs in such names as ʻIo-lani, royal hawk.

ʻio₂

to twitter, chirp, peep; peeping.

ʻio₃

to flee.

ʻio₄

a round, light-colored bitter gourd (Lagenaria siceraria), about 30 cm in diameter.

ʻio₅

tag; a Hawaiian game similar to tag; to play these games.

ʻio₆

bundle or food package; loaded with such bundles.

ʻio₇

one who announces the presence of a chief; herald.

ʻipeka

ibex.

ʻiui

ceremonial feeding by the high chief of the messenger carrying the image Lono about the island during the makahiki festivals.

ʻiuʻiu

intensification of ʻiu₁, lofty, sacred, revered, consecrated...;   • majestic,   • lofty, very high;   • distant, far away;   • long absent and out of sight;   • a distant realm of the gods.

ʻiu₁

lofty, sacred, revered, consecrated; such a place.

ʻiu₂

taboo isolating menstruating women in a special hut.

ʻiwa puakea

same as mānā₂, a fern. Maui.

ʻiwaʻiwa hāuli

the fan maidenhair fern (Adiantum tenerum), with each of the last fan-shaped subdivisions split into five to ten segments.

ʻiwaʻiwa hāwai

the Venus-hair, a kind of maidenhair fern (Adiantum capillus-veneris), known in many warm countries, both wild and cultivated in Hawaiʻi. The fronds are subdivided into many small, bright-green, fan-shaped divisions, borne on slender, black stems.

ʻiwaʻiwa kahakaha

lit., striped ʻiwaʻiwa.

ʻiwaʻiwa lau liʻi

a native fern (Asplenium macraei) with narrow, feather-shaped fronds 30 to 60 cm long, with subdivisions of each frond lobed or scalloped. lit., small-leafed ʻiwaʻiwa.

ʻiwaʻiwa lau nui

an endemic fern (Tectaria gaudichaudii) with thin, triangular fronds 30 cm to 1.2 m long, much divided into rather broad lobes. lit., large-leafed ʻiwaʻiwa.

ʻiwaʻiwa ʻAukekulalia

lit., Australian maidenhair.

ʻiwaʻiwa ʻāpiʻipiʻi

the curly-leaved maidenhair (Adiantum tenerum f. farleyense), an ornamental fern much like the ʻiwaʻiwa hāuli, but the leaf subdivisions much larger, more deeply cut, fringed and overlapping. lit., curly maidenhair.

ʻiwaʻiwaakāne

an endemic fern (Asplenium rhipidoneuron) with narrow, feather-shaped fronds, which are stiff, 10 to 30 cm long, dark-green, the divisions pointed and obliquely cut, their stems bearing many dark scales.

ʻiwaʻiwa₁

all maidenhair ferns (Adiantum spp.), from warm regions of the world, many grown ornamentally. The stems are dark, commonly shiny, slender, wiry; the fronds' subdivisions are four-sided, oblong, or wedge-shaped.

ʻiwaʻiwa₂

a small, high-mountain fern (Asplenium adiantum-nigrum), with shiny, brown stems and triangular or ovate, subdivided, stiff fronds, the spores numerous, often found covering the under side of the fronds. Known in many countries.

ʻiwaʻiwa₃

var. name for manawahua₂, ferns (Doryopteris spp), listed by (Rock) and (Hillebrand).

ʻiwa₁

frigate or man-of-war bird (Fregata minor palmerstoni); it has a wing span of 2.1 m. fig., thief, so called because it steals food by forcing other birds to disgorge; also used figuratively for a handsome person, as follows.

ʻiwa₂

a native fern (Asplenium horridum) with narrow, feather-shaped fronds 45 to 95 cm long, their dark stems bearing dark-brown hairs and scales. The stems were formerly used for making hats.

ʻiwi₁

var. of ʻiʻiwi, a bird; considered by some an ʻaumakua.

ʻiwi₂

reddish.

ʻiwi₃

twitching of the eye, sometimes accompanied by contraction of the mouth.

ʻiʻiaao

cooked and partly dried taro or sweet potato that becomes sour or ferments.

ʻiʻika

• contracted, drawn, as facial features;   • wincing, as in pain;   • to contract, wince, shrivel, as octopus that writhes or turns while being broiled.

ʻiʻike

to see well; observant; to recognize and accost in a friendly way.

ʻiʻimi

to seek again and again; one seeking everywhere, as for knowledge.

ʻiʻimo

to blink.

ʻiʻini

to desire, crave, yearn for, wish; desire, liking.

ʻiʻiwi haole

cape honeysuckle (Tecomaria capensis), a climbing shrub bearing narrow, curved, tubular, scarlet flowers and fernlike leaves (Neal 765), introduced to Kaʻū by George Jones.

ʻiʻiwi pōpolo

immature, greenish-yellow, blackspotted stage of the ʻiʻiwi bird, lit., pōpolo berry honey creeper.

ʻiʻiwi₁

scarlet Hawaiian honey creeper (Vestiaria coccinea), found on all the main islands; its feathers were used extensively in feather work. Also ʻiwi, ʻiʻiwi pōlena, olokele. cf. also ʻiʻiwi pōpolo and kikiwi.

ʻiʻiwi₂

same as the honey creeper called ʻakialoa on Oʻahu (Hemignathus obscurus ellisianus).

ʻiʻiʻi₁

intensification of ʻiʻi₁, small, tiny.

ʻiʻiʻi₂

small hāpuʻu ʻiʻi and ʻamaʻu ʻiʻi ferns.

ʻiʻiʻī

to restrain, choke back; to groan, as with exertion.

ʻiʻi₁

small, stunted, undersized, dwarf.

ʻiʻi₂

admired deep, rasping sound in chanting; tremor; guttural quality of some sounds, as back vowels or strongly aspirated "h".

ʻiʻi₄

to gather, collect.

ʻiʻi₆

reddish-brown, as a dog's hair.

ʻiʻo hala

small white seeds in a hala key, eaten by children and used as medicine.

ʻiʻo hipa

mutton, flesh of sheep.

ʻiʻo holoholona

meat.

ʻiʻo huki

muscle.

ʻiʻo kupu

disease of the nose, gumboil; growth on the roof of a horse's mouth.

ʻiʻo lau maiʻa

yellowish grain in wood, especially koa, named for its resemblance to the yellow color of a banana leaf (lau maiʻa).

ʻiʻo lāʻau

grain of wood; heart of wood.

ʻiʻo lūʻau

greenish meat of turtles, considered the best, so named because its color resembled cooked taro tops (lūʻau).

ʻiʻo maha

temple muscle.

ʻiʻo niu

flesh of coconut.

ʻiʻo nui₁

meaty, fleshy, as of some fish, or as the soft part of pandanus keys that are strung for leis.

ʻiʻo nui₂

a fern known in many countries (Dryopteris parallelogramma syn. D. paleacea), up to 80 cm high, with feather-shaped fronds clustered on a short trunk, the frond stems clothed with long brown to black scales.

ʻiʻo nīoi

condiment of boiled pulp of chili peppers (nīoi), often mixed with relish such as ʻinamona.

ʻiʻo pale niho

gums. lit., tooth-protecting flesh.

ʻiʻo pipi

beef.

ʻiʻo pipi i wili ʻia

hamburger, ground round steak. lit., ground beef flesh.

ʻiʻo pipi keiki

veal.

ʻiʻo pono

blood relative.

ʻiʻo ponoī

one's own relative.

ʻiʻo puaʻa uahi

bacon. lit., smoked pork flesh.

ʻiʻo ulu

growth, tumor.

ʻiʻo ʻalaea

blood kin (but not children or siblings).

ʻiʻo ʻōhiʻa

ʻōhiʻa wood grain; reddish grain of koa wood.

ʻiʻoaweawe

a variety of taro.

ʻiʻoliu

tenderloin.

ʻiʻoʻiʻo

clitoris.

ʻiʻo₂

true, genuine, significant, real; really, truly, surely, actually; true worth.

ʻiʻo₃

grain of wood.

ʻiʻī₁

tight, difficult to extract, as a plug; stiff.

ʻiʻī₂

to frown, scowl.

ʻiʻī₃

to move swiftly. Kauaʻi.

ʻiʻī₄

lost, as old knowledge.

ʻOhaio

Ohio.

ʻOhiʻikau

a hold in lua fighting.

ʻOihana Kahuna₂

Book of Leviticus in the Old Testament.

ʻOkaka

a particular company of soldiers belonging to Kamehameha.

ʻOkalahoma

Oklahoma.

ʻOkalana

Oakland.

ʻOkapoka

Oxford.

ʻOkeka

Odessa.

ʻOkia₂

wind name, Hālawa, Molokaʻi.

ʻOkoikua

stroke in lua fighting.

ʻOle Kū Kahi

seventh and twenty-first nights of the month.

ʻOle Kū Kolu

ninth night of the month.

ʻOle Kū Lua

eighth and twenty-second nights of the month.

ʻOle Kū Pau

tenth night of the month.

ʻOlekona

Oregon.

ʻOliona

Orion.

ʻOlolū₂

Name of a star (no data).

ʻOlopana₁

an Oahu chief, and uncle of Kamapuaʻa. When Kama stole his chickens, ʻOlopana repeatedly sent hundreds of men to catch him; but each time Kama's grandmother, Kamaunuaniho, sang Kama's name songs, and Kama's teeth cut down and killed the men carrying him on a stretcher. (FS 196-205).

ʻOlopana₂

a famous chief at Waipiʻo, Hawaii, the brother of Haʻinakolo and father of Luʻukia and Kāwelu.

ʻOlumepia

Olympia.

ʻOluʻekeloahoʻokaʻamoena

guardian of the sleeping place of the high chief or chiefess (said to be an expert lua fighter and of the same sex as the chief or chiefess). lit., ʻEkeloa breeze coolness that rolls mats.

ʻOnekalio

Ontario.

ʻOpikana

short for ʻOpikanalani or ʻOpikananuʻu.

ʻOpikanalani

name of a mythical faraway place, higher than ʻOpikananuʻu.

ʻOpikananuʻu

name of a mythical, faraway place.

ʻOākiʻiala

a stroke in lua fighting.

ʻOʻopuola

a stroke in lua fighting; fish was said to be taboo to those learning the stroke. lit., alive ʻoʻopu.

ʻOʻopu₂

name of a wind associated with Waiheʻe, Maui.

ʻo … ia

indicating recent action. Just, just now.

ʻo-

same as ʻō- (cf. ʻolalau); pronounced ʻow- before e (ʻoehuehu); the -w- need not be written unless the following vowel is the initial sound of a recognizable base, as ʻowala, to turn over (cf. wala, to tilt).

ʻoaikū

gasping for breath, as during an attack of asthma; shortness of breath accompanied by a churning, heaving motion as by one attempting to breath.

ʻoai₁

to entwine, twine; to stir round and round, as a liquid; to go round and round.

ʻoai₂

bubo, swelling

ʻoai₃

porous stone, as used for polishing canoes and calabashes.

ʻoaka₂

to sprout, as sweet potatoes.

ʻoala₁

• to gambol, buck, rear, bucking, rearing,   • turn over, somersault;

ʻoala₂

to brandish a club with a twirling motion; brandishing...

ʻoama

young of the weke, goatfish.

ʻoau₁

Oʻahu and Maui name for a freshwater ʻoʻopu fish (Eleotris sandwicensis) called ʻōkuhe elsewhere. see ʻōkuhe for other names. The name ʻoau is said to be so called because of a tale: a fisherman caught a lot of these fish, but they disappeared; the fisherman called for them and a voice answered "ʻo au, ʻo au" (it's me, it's me) and the fish turned into lizards and scampered off.

ʻoau₂

a cat, so called because of its cry: to mew.

ʻoau₃

a variety of taro.

ʻoau₄

a moss.

ʻoawa

var. spelling of ʻōawaawa, ʻowāwa, valley.

ʻoehaʻa

• crooked, distorted, deformed;   • to walk in an ungainly manner, swaying the shoulders;   • to waddle.   • fig., deceitful; trick.

ʻoehu

• to romp, gambol, prance, leap;   • blustery, gusty, as a storm or angry person;   • to head straight for, as a canoe.

ʻoehuehu

redup. of ʻoehu:   • to romp, gambol, prance, leap;   • blustery, gusty, as a storm or angry person;   • to head straight for, as a canoe.   cf ehuehu: animation varying from fury and storm to power and majesty...

ʻoene₁

mesh size between one and two fingers.

ʻoene₂

last taro taken from a crop; small-sized taro.

ʻoeowewe

fluttering.

ʻoeʻoe

young stage of the kawakawa bonito.

ʻoe₁

resembling, like.

ʻoe₃

much, indeed (sometimes following nō or connecting enumerations).

ʻohai aliʻi

the pride of Barbados (Caesalpinia pulcherrima), an ornamental leguminous shrub with red and orange flowers. One variety has yellow flowers. lit., royal ʻohai.

ʻohai keʻokeʻo

the sesban (Sesbania grandiflora), a leguminous tree from tropical Asia with pea-shaped flowers about 7.5 cm long and pods to 60 by 1.3 cm. lit., white ʻohai.

ʻohai ʻula

the royal poinciana (Delonix regia), a legume from Madagascar, one of the showiest ornamental trees in Hawaiʻi because of its bright-red canopy of flowers, which are common and prolific in early summer. One form has yellow flowers.

ʻohai ʻulaʻula

the red-flowered variety of ʻohai keʻokeʻo (Sesbania grandiflora var. coccinea). lit., red ʻohai.

ʻohai₁

monkeypod or rain tree (Samanea saman), a large leguminous tree from tropical America, grown in Hawaiʻi for shade and street planting; flowers pink, tufted.

ʻohai₂

a native legume (Sesbania tomentosa), a low to prostrate shrub with hairy, pale leaves and red or orange flowers about 2.5 cm long. (Neal 450) White monkeypod (Albizia lebbeck) on Niʻihau. cf. (Neal 403).

ʻohana₂

to gather for family prayers (short for pule ʻohana).

ʻohaohala₁

a half-truth, exaggeration; to enlarge on certain points; to exaggerate the arguments on one side, but overlook conflicting evidence; dichotomized thinking.

ʻohaohala₂

rank, of lush growth.

ʻohaohala₃

soft, sweet, of melody.

ʻohe Kahiki

bamboo with short, green joints and large leaves; wood hard, used for knives, fishing poles, house construction; introduced from Tahiti.

ʻohe hoʻonui ʻike

microscope. lit., tube magnifying vision.

ʻohe kani

flute. lit., playing bamboo.

ʻohe kikoʻolā

a native tree (Tetraplasandra waimeae), found only in forests of Kauaʻi above Waimea; about 9 m tall, with few branches, the leaves about 30 cm long, each leaf with five to thirteen large, oblong leaflets, and like some other araliads, with many flowers in umbels. lit., straggly bamboo.

ʻohe kāpala

piece of bamboo carved for printing tapa; bamboo stamp. lit., printing bamboo.

ʻohe lau liʻiliʻi

small-leafed bamboo.

ʻohe liʻiliʻi

dwarf bamboo.

ʻohe mauka

a small native tree (Tetraplasandra oahuensis), found only on Oʻahu; much like its relative, the ʻoheokai, but having oblong, entire leaflets. lit., upland ʻohe.

ʻohe naupaka

a native naupaka (Scaevola glabra and S. kauaiensis), a shrub or small tree of the mountains, with yellow, curved, tubular flowers, about 2.5 cm long.

ʻohe nānā

spyglass, telescope, microscope.. lit., tube for looking.

ʻohe piʻo

siphon. lit., bent bamboo.

ʻohe puhi ahi

bamboo fire-blowing tube.

ʻohe puluka

flute. lit., flute (Eng.) bamboo.

ʻohe wai

water pipe, hose; bamboo water container.

ʻohe ʻala

sweet cane.

ʻohelo huki manu

flexible gummed rod used for extracting ʻuaʻu fledglings from their holes. lit., rod for pulling birds.

ʻohene

same as ʻOluʻekeloahoʻokaʻamoena, but a guardian of the opposite sex of the high chief or chiefess whose sleeping place was guarded.

ʻoheʻohe₁

tall native trees (Tetraplasandra kavaiensis and varieties), closely related to the ʻohe mauka, and found on all Hawaiian Islands. Also Reynoldsia sandwicensis (Niʻihau).

ʻoheʻohe₃

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻohe₁

• all kinds of bamboo;   • reed (Mat. 27.48) ;   • flute;   • pipe, hose, tube, catheter;   • bamboo tube for preserving fish.

ʻohe₂

a coarse, jointed, native grass (Isachne distichophylla), to 190 cm high, with stiff, pointed leaves and open flowering panicle.

ʻohe₃

a native bamboo-like plant (Joinvillea ascendens), with stem about 3 m high, 2.5 cm or less in diameter, unbranched; leaf blades 60 to 90 cm by 8 to 13 cm, pointed and plaited; flowering panicle about 30 cm long.

ʻohe₄

a native tree (Reynoldsia sandwicesis), an araliad, with leaves about 30 cm long, each leaf with seven to eleven broad leaflets with scalloped edges. (Neal 652) The wood of this kind of tree growing at Mauna Loa, Molokaʻi, was reputed to be poisonous, was used for making poison images, and is the tree form of Kapo, a goddess. see kālaipāhoa, kauila. This tree growing elsewhere was not considered poisonous and was used for making stilts, hence it was also called ʻohe kukuluaeʻo or ʻoheokai or ʻohemakai.

ʻohe₅

a native variety of taro, thriving at altitudes above 450 m; leaf stem light-green, tinged with reddish-brown (perhaps like some variety of bamboo); the corm pink-tinted, making excellent poi. (Whitney 58). The term may be qualified by the colors ʻeleʻele, kea or keʻokeʻo, ʻulaʻula.

ʻohe₆

variety of fish (no data).

ʻohi loaʻa

to collect revenue; revenue collection.

ʻohi wauke

bundle of wauke bark.

ʻohikau

• to listen in order to gossip;   • to gossip;   • a gossip.

ʻohikui

to talk ramblingly.

ʻohina

• gathering, collecting;   • selection.

ʻohi₂

to gush, chatter aimlessly and ramblingly, gabble.

ʻohona manu

brood.

ʻohuʻohu₂

white tapa with black dots and figures.

ʻohuʻohu₃

redup. of ʻohu₂, adorned as with leis...

ʻohu₁

mist, fog, vapor, light cloud on a mountain;

ʻohu₂

adorned as with leis

ʻohā

• taro corm growing from the older root, especially from the stalk called kalo;   • tender plant (Isa. 53.3) ,   • shoot, sucker, branch (Isa. 11.2) .   • fig., offspring, youngsters ((FS 235);   cf. ʻohana). also muʻu. see kalo for names of generations.

ʻohākia

(perhaps a pas/imp., (Gram. 6.6.3))

ʻoi lua

two-edged, as a dagger.

ʻoia ana

Let me see! Show me! I dare you! (sarcastically) (Usually shortened to ʻoiana or ʻoliana.)

ʻoia ana nō

it's the same result; regardless.

ʻoia hoʻi hā

all right, then; so that's it after all. (About the same as ʻoia hoʻi: see ʻoia₁.)

ʻoia ʻaneʻi

Is that so! So that's it!

ʻoiai₁

while, meanwhile, during.

ʻoiai₂

although.

ʻoiana

usu. shortened form of ʻoia ana, Let me see! Show me! I dare you! ...

ʻoihana aliʻi₁

duty or office of chief or king.

ʻoihana aliʻi₂

Book of Chronicles (Old Testament).

ʻoihana hana kālā

mint. lit., moneymaking department.

ʻoihana hana lima

trade.

ʻoihana hemolele

clergy. lit., pure profession.

ʻoihana hoʻonaʻauao₁

educational system, profession.

ʻoihana hoʻonaʻauao₂

department of Instruction, Dept. of Education

ʻoihana hui malū

Society of Masons.

ʻoihana kahuna₁

priesthood, office and duties of a priest, minister, or sorcerer.

ʻoihana kinai ahi

fire department; job of putting out fires. lit., fire-extinguishing job or department.

ʻoihana kiu

secret service, department of secret police.

ʻoihana koa

military service.

ʻoihana kākau kope

registration office. lit., copyrighting office.

ʻoihana kālaiʻāina

department of Interior, in the days of the monarchy.

ʻoihana kālepa

commerce, mercantile profession.

ʻoihana kālā

finance.

ʻoihana kānāwai

judicial department.

ʻoihana kūʻai ʻāina

real estate business.

ʻoihana leka

postal department.

ʻoihana mikiʻala

manufacturing.

ʻoihana mokulele

aviation.

ʻoihana wai₁

water works.

ʻoihana wai₂

department (or Board) of Water Supply.

ʻoihana ʻimi kālā

finance.

ʻoihana₂

tools, utensils.

ʻoiʻo

procession of ghosts of a departed chief and his company. More commonly called huakaʻi pō.

ʻoiʻoina

point, peak, cape, promontory, headland.

ʻoiʻoi₁

superior; a superior person.

ʻoiʻoi₂

• full of sharp points,   • pointed,   • sharp;   • thorn;   • to protrude, stick or jut out.

ʻoka kilika

the silky or silver oak (Grevillea robusta), a large tree from Australia, used for reforesting in Hawaiʻi. The leaves are subdivided like some ferns; the orange flowers are abundant in early summer. lit., silk oak. also haʻikū keʻokeʻo and on Niʻihau, ʻoka.

ʻoka pua ʻulaʻula

Niʻihau.

ʻokakalika ʻakika

oxalic acid.

ʻokanaki

organdy.

ʻokana₁

• district or subdistrict, usually comprising several ahupuaʻa;   • portion, as of food.

ʻokana₂

organ.

ʻokanika

organic (said of the Organic Act).

ʻokawa

octave.

ʻokaʻoka

a bad odor, as of garbage.

ʻokaʻokai

insipid, tasteless, especially of freshly pounded poi.

ʻoka₁

oak.

ʻoka₂

oats.

ʻoke

rotten, as wood, cloth.

ʻokekelika

ostrich. ʻakolika is more common.

ʻokele

ocher.

ʻokelekelika

ostrich.

ʻokepela

osprey.

ʻokepelaka

vulture (RSV), ossifrage (KJV).

ʻoki huelo

to cut only the ends of the hair. lit., cut tail.

ʻoki kūmākena

to cut the hair on one side of the head, formerly a sign of mourning.

ʻoki mahiole

to cut the hair leaving a strip down the middle. lit., helmet cut.

ʻoki male

divorce; to divorce. lit., cut marriage.

ʻoki mauʻu

to mow the grass.

ʻoki pahu

to bob the hair. lit., smooth cut.

ʻoki poe

to bob the hair. lit., round cut.

ʻoki poepoe

subincision, to subincise; circumcision, to circumcise (a Biblical euphemism, (Kin. 17.10) ; the Hawaiian terms were kahe ule and kaha ule). lit., cut roundness.

ʻoki poʻo

to behead.

ʻoki puʻu

to cut the throat; cutthroat.

ʻoki ʻino

to mutilate.

ʻokika

orchid.

ʻokika honohono

an orchid (Dendrobium anosmum).

ʻokikene

oxygen.

ʻokilipi

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻokina₁

cutting off, ending, severance, separation.

ʻokipuʻu

forest clearing (term noted in Oʻahu land records).

ʻokiʻoki

• to cut into pieces, chop,   • prune,   • slash,   • carve.

ʻokokomo

filled, as a canoe.

ʻokolekē

a play language something like pig Latin. Example: e hesele ana ʻoutou sele ihesele, for e hele ana ʻoukou i hea? Where are you going? [sele is added at random.]. see language.

ʻokomopila

automobile.

ʻokoʻa₂

to be early or continuing, of time of day.

ʻokūʻokū

to pitch, as a canoe tossed by waves; to rear and pitch, as a horse.

ʻolalahina

frail, delicate.

ʻolalau

somewhat lalau; wrong, incorrect; mistakenly.

ʻole loa

not at all, void, not in the least, none whatsoever; of no value, worthless.

ʻole wale

Not at all! Of no interest, value, use.

ʻolelehu

drowsy, sleepy.

ʻolepū

to discard.

ʻole₂

for nights of the moon beginning with ʻOle see also (Malo 31, 32, 35).     ʻOle Kū Kahi, Olekūkahi n. 7th and 21st nights of the month...     ʻOle Kū Lua n. 8th and 22nd nights of the month...     ʻOle Kū Kolu n. 9th night of the month...     ʻOle Kū Pau n. 10th night of the month... Collectively these nights were called nā ʻOle; they were considered unlucky for fishing, planting, or beginning any important activity because ʻole also means nothing.

ʻoli

joy, happiness, pleasure; happy, joyful, gay.

ʻoliana₁

a common ornamental shrub (Nerium oleander and var. indicum), native from south Europe to Japan. Its flowers may be single or double, white, pink, or red.

ʻoliana₂

a variety of sugar cane, like lahaina in type of growth and color, but the pith dark-brown and the leaf sheath covered with red-brown hairs.

ʻoliana₃

Let me see! Show me!

ʻoliko

shiny, sparkling, bright.

ʻolili

shiny, sparkling, shimmering, as moonlight.

ʻoliliko₁

shimmering.

ʻolina

to make merry; joyous, rejoicing, merrymaking.

ʻoliwa kū kahakai

air plant (Kalanchoe pinnata, also Bryophyllum pinnatum), a succulent growing wild and cultivated in Hawaiʻi and other tropical countries. New plants develop along the edges of the thick scalloped leaves. The tubular green and red flowers hang lantern-like. The Hawaiian name was given because the first plants seen in Hawaiʻi grew near the beach. lit., beach-standing olive.

ʻoliwa₁

the olive tree (Olea europaea), from the Mediterranean region, a small tree grown only, ornamentally in Hawaiʻi, where it rarely flowers or yields fruit. Called ʻoliwa haole on Niʻihau.

ʻoliʻoli

delight, enjoyment.

ʻolo wae

calf of the leg. also ʻoloʻolo wāwae.

ʻolo wai

gourd water container.

ʻolo ʻawa

coconut shell cut lengthwise as a cup for kava.

ʻoloa₂

fine white tapa, said to have been placed over an image during prayers (Laie 467); perhaps a verb to make ʻoloa tapa.

ʻoloa₃

gift to a child at birth.

ʻolohaka

• empty, emptiness,   • sunken,   • hollow, as eyes or cheeks;   • deficiency, deficit.

ʻolohani

to strike, quit work; mutiny, riot.

ʻolohewa

demented, deranged; delirious, incoherent.

ʻolokaʻa₁

• to roll along, as a wheel;   • to remove;   • to transfer, as a debt.

ʻolokaʻa₂

stake to which a live rat was tied as a decoy in an owl-catching trap.

ʻolokele

bog, swamp.

ʻolokeʻa₁

• cross, gibbet, gallows (Eset. 5.14) ,   • scaffolding;   • ladder made of sticks tied horizontally;   • crisscross, crossed;   • bones of a corpse buried with knees tied to breast.   • fig., contrary, antagonistic.

ʻolokā

to shake or quiver, as flesh of a fat person.

ʻololaiki

all right.

ʻololā₁

broad.

ʻololā₂

a small flying fish resembling the puhikiʻi.

ʻololī

narrow.

ʻololū₁

dejected, downcast.

ʻolomana

old man.

ʻolomeka

old maid.

ʻolomene

old man.

ʻolomua

foreskin. (changed to ʻōmaka in later editions of the Bible).

ʻolopala

old fellow.

ʻolopū₁

inflated, billowed out, as a sail in the wind; puffed out, as cheeks of one eating; blistered, as hands from work; mouthful of food or water.

ʻolopū₂

a native shrubby violet (Viola chamissoniana).

ʻolopū₃

adze for cutting ʻōhiʻa logs for images.

ʻolouha

overstuffed with food, an insulting epithet. lit., sagging intestine.

ʻoloʻio

to move swiftly.

ʻoloʻolo wāwae

calf of the leg.

ʻoloʻolo₁

to hang too low, as a petticoat; to hang loose and long; to hang (as coconuts).

ʻoloʻolo₂

to overflow, flood, as streams.

ʻoloʻolo₃

to loiter, lag.

ʻoloʻolōna

sagging under a weight, overladen, loaded down; a burden.

ʻoloʻā

splashing on rocks, as a rough sea.

ʻolo₁

long gourd container used as a receptacle, as for kava or water; long body of a gourd used as a hula drum cf. heke, ipu.

ʻolo₂

• double chin, sagging skin, jowls,   • calf of leg;   • scrotum;   • wattles of a turkey;   • fat part under the jaws of an eel;   • pendant;   • pendulous;   • to roll with fat;   • to sag, hang down.

ʻolu

• cool, refreshing; coolness;   • soft, supple, flexible, pliant, elastic, slack, springy; softness, slackness;   • pleasant, comfortable, at ease; comfort, amenities;   • polite, kind, courteous; grace, courtesy, kindness.

ʻoluea

to slacken, ease. fig., mental relaxation.

ʻolā

gurgling; to gurgle.

ʻolēhala

cheerful singing, as of birds in treetops.

ʻolēʻolē₁

a small conch shell.

ʻolēʻolē₂

to rant.

ʻolēʻolē₃

wide-mouthed grin, as of an idol; to grin thus.

ʻolē₁

• conch shell (Charonia tritonis);   • trumpet;   • crochet pattern with a design suggestive of a trumpet.

ʻolē₂

to talk indistinctly or garrulously.

ʻolē₃

tapa beater.

ʻoma Pukikī

dome-shaped cement or stone outdoor oven, as used by the Portuguese (Pukikī) for bread.

ʻomaliō

broad, extended, extensive, flat, as land; a wide athletic field of ancient times.

ʻoma₂

to open the mouth, as though to speak, or as a child about to nurse at the breast; to ask indirectly.

ʻoma₃

female mahimahi fish; but cf. oma₃.

ʻoma₅

small adze.

ʻoma₆

space between opposing armies where sacrifices were offered; preparations for war; first men killed in war.

ʻomeka

omega.

ʻomela

omer.

ʻomimo

naked, nude.

ʻomo

lid, cover, plug, cork, as of a calabash; lamp chimney.

ʻomo ipukukui

lamp chimney.

ʻomoʻomo

• loaf;   • any long, oval body, as balls of arrowroot;   • a mold or molded thing, as adobe bricks.

ʻomoʻomo palaoa

loaf of bread.

ʻomua

whiplash used to throw a keʻa, dart, as of olonā fiber.

ʻomī

to wither, droop; to burn weakly, as a candle.

ʻona lama

drunk on rum or any alcoholic liquor; drunkenness; alcoholic.

ʻona mau

constantly drunk, alcoholic.

ʻona miliona

millionaire. lit., owner [of a] million.

ʻona waiwai

rich person.

ʻonana

weak, awkward, unskilled.

ʻonaulu loa

a wave of great length and endurance.

ʻonaʻona₁

faint, dizzy, punch-drunk.

ʻonaʻona₂

bad-smelling, as stagnant water; unpalatable.

ʻona₁

drunk, dizzy and unsteady; intoxicating; intoxication.

ʻona₂

owner, possessor, proprietor; to own.

ʻoneki

deck.

ʻoneʻi

• here,   • local.

ʻonika

onyx.

ʻonina

moving, etc.

ʻoninini

to pick at food with no appetite, as would a sickly child.

ʻonipaʻa

• fixed, immovable,   • motionless,   • established,   • steadfast, firm, resolute, determined (this was the motto of Kamehameha V and of Liliʻuokalani.   lit., fixed movement.

ʻoniʻoni₁

redup of ʻoni₁, to move, stir, shift, fidget...; to wag.

ʻoniʻoni₂

striped.

ʻoni₁

• to move, stir, shift, fidget, squirm, wiggle; movement, motion.   • to take to court, as land matters;

ʻoni₂

spirals of several colors in composite leis.

ʻono wai

thirsty; to crave water.

ʻonohinohi₂

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻonou

• to shove, push,   • force into,   • thrust on;   • to persuade;   • to give secretly or underhandedly; to offer in secret.

ʻonou poʻo

to shove or push into something headlong, regardless of consequence. lit., shove head.

ʻopakuma

opossum.

ʻope

bundle, package; to tie in a bundle (sometimes preceded by ke).

ʻopeha

a native fern (Elaphoglossum aemulum variety), a small variety of ʻēkaha ʻula.

ʻopekama

opossum.

ʻopeni

offense.

ʻopeʻalu

baggy and ill-fitting, as clothes; loose, sagging. lit., slack bundle.

ʻopeʻope kau

bundle that is hung, as bones of a relative.

ʻopeʻope₁

• bundles, packages,   • baggage;   • to fold, as clothes (Ioane 20.7) ;   • pillow (Kauaʻi).

ʻopeʻope₂

same as ʻōpeʻa₁   • to twist, bind, or cross the hands, as behind the back;   • to throw over the shoulder, as a shawl;   • to overturn, overthrow;   • to evict, as a tenant;   • to trip, as with a spear thrust between the legs.   • fig., to deceive, trick, treat treacherously; treachery.

ʻopi

• fold, crease; to fold, crease.   • wrinkled;   • bend of a wave;   • sunken, as the jaw of a toothless person;

ʻopi wai

stream embankment.

ʻopihi kapuaʻi lio

limpet, umbrella shell (Siphoneria sp.). lit., horseshoe ʻopihi [this name post-dated arrival of horses in Hawaiʻi]. Called naka kua poʻi in some areas.

ʻopihi mākuʻekuʻe

Molokaʻi.

ʻopihi ʻawa

small bitter ʻopihi, perhaps Cellana sandwicensis, nonedible, used in sorcery, perhaps hoofshells. lit., bitter ʻopihi.

ʻopihi ʻālinalina

yellow-meated ʻopihi. lit., scarred ʻopihi.

ʻopihi₂

salted and dried abalone from the mainland. also ʻopihi malihini.

ʻopihi₃

design for tapa and mats consisting of small triangles, probably named for the limpet.

ʻopina

fold, bend, crease.

ʻopiuma₁

opium.

ʻopiuma₂

the Manila tamarind (Pithecellobium dulce), from tropical America, both cultivated and wild in Hawaiʻi. It is a medium-sized tree, a legume, with long slender branches, four-parted leaves, whitish flowers in small round heads, and red, twisted pods. Round, flat, black seeds embedded in white, edible pulp were thought to resemble commercial opium, hence the name.

ʻopiʻopi₁

to fold; folding.

ʻopiʻopi₂

a seaweed.

ʻopo

to lay a foundation, as of stones; to dam up, as water.

ʻopuʻopu₁

to belch; filled, as a calabash.

ʻopu₁

to dive into the water, feet first, without making a splash, an ancient sport (used only with lele or lele a); one so skilled.

ʻoulanakana

orangutan.

ʻoulu

growth.

ʻoumuamua

leader, as in battle or other activity; scout.

ʻouo

young animal, plant or person; young woman, pullet, cock, youth; youthful, sprightly; immature, as a coconut.

ʻoupē₁

beaten down, as by storm (UL 79); to cast down (2-Oihn. 25.8) .

ʻoupē₂

extreme lower end of a canoe paddle.

ʻouʻou₂

a sharp sound, as of a tapa mallet or of a tapping knee drum; to sound thus.

ʻou₁

• sharp, protruding; to protrude, project, jut out,   • piercing; pierce, puncture;   • to reach out for;   • to stretch out;   • to sound sharply;   • pinnacle, high peak;   • royal;   • sharp sound as of knee drum or of tapa anvil.

ʻou₂

Bulwer's petrel (Bulweria bulwerii), a small sea bird; for some people, an ʻaumakua.

ʻowala

• to gambol, buck, rear, bucking, rearing,   • turn over, somersault;   • to brandish a club with a twirling motion; brandishing.

ʻowali₁

weak, sickly, puny.

ʻowāʻowaka₁

a bivalve, perhaps one of the Isognomonidae.

ʻowā₁

split, cracked, burst, grooved; to split, crack...

ʻowā₂

to talk loudly back and forth, roar.

ʻowā₃

cry of the ʻaukuʻu, heron, which suggests ʻowā; to cry thus.

ʻowā₄

to retch, gag.

ʻowā₅

a measurement equal to half the width of a finger, of fishing nets.

ʻowā₅

in music, one of the five lines of the staff.

ʻowē

murmuring, rustling, soughing, whining, as of surf, leaves, water, wind, a bullet; to pitter patter, as rain; to sound thus; sound of tearing, as of cloth; buzzing of insects.

ʻoālaala

• rising of the wind; to rise, as wind;   • to occur, as a thought.

ʻoāliʻi

maidenhair spleenwort, a fern (Asplenium trichomanes) found on high mountains of Hawaiʻi and also present in many temperate regions of the world. Wiry-stemmed, narrow fronds grow in dense tufts 10 to 30 cm high, the fronds consisting of numerous small, round divisions on two sides of the stem.

ʻoāliʻi makaliʻi

a native fern (Schizaea robusta). Called haili-o-Pua on Hawaiʻi.

ʻoāuluniu

a variety of taro (no data).

ʻoāʻoā₂

a variety of taro.

ʻoā₁

• split, cracked, burst, grooved; to split, crack.   • gap, intervening space (Hopita)   • fig., bereaved, forsaken.

ʻoā₂

to talk loudly back and forth, roar.

ʻoā₃

cry of the ʻaukuʻu, heron, which suggests ʻoā; to cry thus.

ʻoā₄

to retch, gag.

ʻoā₅

a measurement equal to half the width of a finger, of fishing nets.

ʻoā₆

in music, one of the five lines of the staff.

ʻoē

variant spelling of ʻowē,   • murmuring, rustling, soughing, whining, as of surf, leaves, water, wind, a bullet;   • to pitter patter, as rain; to sound thus;   • sound of tearing, as of cloth;   • buzzing of insects.

ʻoʻeno

twill plaiting, as in hats, mats.

ʻoʻe₁

• to probe upward, prod, pry, prick,   • jab, poke,   • gore;   • sharp darting pain;   • jagged, spiked.

ʻoʻi

to limp.

ʻoʻohu

stoop-shouldered, bent, as with age.

ʻoʻoi₁

• redup. of ʻoi sharp, acute; sharpness...   • prickly;   • sting, as of scorpions (Hoik. 9.10) ;   • to protrude, as eyelashes.

ʻoʻoi₂

an inedible seaweed. Also called popohe makaliʻi.

ʻoʻoki₂

to take effect, as intoxication.

ʻoʻoleʻa

hard, stiff, strong, inflexible, rigid, harsh, rough; rigor, strength, hardness. fig., strenuous, severe, strict, stubborn, obstinate; obstinacy.

ʻoʻolokū

• boisterous, blustering,   • stormy,   • disturbed;   • upset, as stomach;   • fury, rage.

ʻoʻololā

young of fish.

ʻoʻolomaʻo

variety of bird, perhaps the maʻo, thrush.

ʻoʻolopū

to change, as appearance.

ʻoʻolu₁

two edible, fragile, red seaweeds (Champia sp. and Chondria tenuissima). They melt in fresh water, hence must be cleaned in sea water.

ʻoʻolu₂

thin, feeble.

ʻoʻolu₄

a variety of taro.

ʻoʻoma

• concave; concavity,   • spout,   • gouge, oval-shaped chisel;   • flare of a bonnet;   • large sharp nose.

ʻoʻoma noho

leather covering of stirrups.

ʻoʻopa

lame, crippled; a cripple, lame person; to limp, be lame.

ʻoʻopu haole

name for black bass, introduced in 1901. lit., foreign ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu hiʻu kole

a variety of fresh-water ʻoʻopu. lit., red-tailed ʻoʻopu. It is believed that this fish drives other fish away, and hence must be thrown out of a net with an exclamation of disgust.

ʻoʻopu hue

swellfishes, puffers, balloon fishes, globefishes (Arothron meleagris and Chilomycterus affinus); not related to ʻoʻopu; these fish contain poison which is sometimes removed by those who like the flesh, especially the Japanese; the poison is sometimes fatal; considered by some an ʻaumakua. lit., gourd ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu hāpuʻu

a variety of large deep-sea fish said to be related to the ʻoʻopu. lit., ʻoʻopu of the hāpuʻupuʻu [family].

ʻoʻopu kui

lit., spiked ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu kukū

an introduced fresh-water black fish with sharp spines near the gills, said to have been introduced from China. lit., spiny ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu kumu iki

female nākea variety of the fish ʻoʻopu. lit., small source ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu kāniʻo

a brackish-water ʻoʻopu. lit., striped ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu lehe

large male of the nākea variety of ʻoʻopu, so called because its lip (lehe) is said to show when it hides in the mud.

ʻoʻopu maoli

lit., indigenous.

ʻoʻopu moana

lit., ocean.

ʻoʻopu moʻala

a variety of ʻoʻopu smaller than the kāniʻo, perhaps named for the moʻala, a crab.

ʻoʻopu mākole

lit., red-eyed ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu nōpili

Kauaʻi.

ʻoʻopu poʻopaʻa

lit., hardheaded.

ʻoʻopu puhi

lit., eel.

ʻoʻopu ʻumiʻumi

lit., bearded ʻoʻopu.

ʻoʻopu ʻōkala

spiny puffer fish, Diodon holocanthus.

ʻoʻopuhue

strong concoction made of green gourd and kukui nut, used as an enema.

ʻoʻopukai

a native variety of taro, so named as the leaf stem is similar in coloring to the salt-water ʻoʻopu (the fish), being yellow-green with dark-purple markings. The corms are used mainly as table taro, the leaves often for lūʻau. Grown chiefly in uplands of Kona, Hawaiʻi. The name may be qualified by the colors keʻokeʻo and ʻulaʻula.

ʻoʻopu₁

general name for fishes included in the families Eleotridae, Gobiidae, and Blennidae. Some are in salt water near the shore, others in fresh water, and some said to be in either fresh or salt water. Varieties include bluespotted goby (Quisquilius eugenius) and indigo hover goby (Ptereleotris heteropterus).

ʻoʻō

to crow, as a rooster; cock-a-doodle-doo.

ʻUhane Hemolele

Holy Ghost, Holy Spirit.

ʻUlakamakaiākuikuipahu

a stroke in lua fighting.

ʻUlalena

a reddish-hued rain associated with Haʻikū, Maui, and Mt. Kaʻala, Oʻahu. Also a wind at Piʻiholo, Maui (Nak. 68).

ʻUmi₃

probably the most famous of early chiefs, dated by Fornander (For. 6:324) as thirteen generations before Kalākaua. Allowing twenty-five years to a generation, this would place ʻUmi's time at about A.D. 1550. Beckwith (HM 391) calls the ʻUmi legend 'one of the most popular of all Hawaiian prose sagas of heroes, embellished as it is with many stock episodes but still preserving the thread of historical accuracy. ʻUmi is still famed as a farmer and fisherman.. .. He kept up the worship of the gods and magnified the practice of human sacrifice.' ʻUmi was conceived by Līloa on his travels. He left recognition tokens, which ʻUmi later took to Līloa. The hostile, oppressive older brother, Hākau, with the conniving of a kahuna, was stoned to death, and ʻUmi left his incognito poverty to become ruling chief.

ʻUnuloa₂

a wind, Puna, Hawaiʻi.

ʻuala hoʻomalamala

mashed sweet potato, slightly fermented and eaten as poi.

ʻuala hēʻī

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻuala hūpē

Madeira vine (Boussingaultia gracilis.) lit., mucus sweet potato.

ʻuala kahiki

the white or Irish potato (Solanum tuberosum), a weak-stemmed herb about .9 m high, with lobed leaves. The white, starchy, underground tuber is a valuable food in many countries. A native of the Andes, it was introduced to Hawaiʻi in the early 1800s.

ʻuala lehu₂

a variety of sweet potato.

ʻuala nika

a variety of introduced sweet potato.

ʻuala pilau

turnip (Brassica rapa). lit., smelly potato.

ʻuala ʻawaʻawa

sweet-potato beer.

ʻuala ʻula kīnaʻu

a variety of red sweet potato.

ʻualalehu

a name later applied to yellow bamboo.

ʻuala₂

a variety of sugar cane, a yellow mutant of ʻakoki with large stalks; often called pilimai and similar to it but stronger.

ʻuala₃

see uhi ʻuala, a variety of yam (Dioscorea alata).

ʻuala₄

large muscles of the upper arm, biceps, brachii.

ʻuala₅

a kind of cowry shell (no data).

ʻuao

• to intercede, arbitrate, reconcile, mediate;   • referee, umpire, conciliator, arbitrator, peacemaker.

ʻuaʻu

dark-rumped petrel (Pterodroma phaeopygia sandwichensis), an endangered sea bird, considered by some an ʻaumakua.

ʻuaʻu kani

wedge-tailed shearwater or moaning bird (Puffinus pacificus chlororhynchus). lit., calling ʻuaʻu.

ʻuaʻu kēwai

(Malo text, chapter 13, section 23)

ʻuaʻuala

sour odor, as of fermenting or decaying sweet potatoes; to smell thus.

ʻueʻuele

wet (used with kēhau, dew).

ʻuha

wasteful, extravagant; waste, extravagance; to waste.

ʻuha ʻai

to waste food or anything; to squander; extravagant; extravagance. (The old Hawaiians did not waste food.)

ʻuhaloa

a small, downy, American weed (Waltheria indica var. americana), with ovate leaves and small, clustered yellow flowers. Leaves and inner bark of root are very bitter and are used for tea or chewed to relieve sore throat. (Neal 575–6) One of the plant forms of the pig demigod Kamapuaʻa (FS 215).

ʻuhane

soul, spirit, ghost; dirge or song of lamentation (rare); spiritual.

ʻuhane haukaʻe

wandering, friendless spirits.

ʻuhane hele

a traveling spirit, usually of a living person.

ʻuhane kiaʻi

guardian spirit.

ʻuhane kīhei pua

a spirit partially controlling a person and giving him strength, animation, or talents. lit., flower-mantle spirit.

ʻuhane noho

a spirit possessing a person completely and talking through him.